
<book-part book-part-type="chapter" id="chap14">
<book-part-meta>
<book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.22233/.14</book-part-id>

<subj-group subj-group-type="topic-type">
<subject>Clinical pathology and cytology</subject>
</subj-group>

<subj-group subj-group-type="animal-type">
<subject>Dog</subject>
<subject>Cat</subject>
</subj-group>

<subj-group subj-group-type="product-type">
<subject>Manual</subject>
</subj-group>

<subj-group subj-group-type="animal-type">
<subject>Dog</subject>
<subject>Cat</subject>
</subj-group>

<title-group>
<label>14</label>
<title><xref ref-type="page" id="page_"/>The thoracic boundaries</title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<given-names initials="F">Francisco</given-names>
<surname initials="L">Llabr&#x00E9;s-D&#x00ED;az</surname>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<given-names initials="A">Audrey</given-names>
<surname initials="P">Petite</surname>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<given-names initials="J">Jimmy</given-names>
<surname initials="S">Saunders</surname>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name name-style="western">
<given-names initials="T">Tobias</given-names>
<surname initials="S">Schwarz</surname>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
</book-part-meta>
<body>

<sec1 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiographic anatomy</title>
<p>The boundaries of the canine and feline thoracic cavity consist of the thoracic skeleton, the cranial and caudal thoracic apertures and the covering soft tissue structures. The rib cage is covered by thoracic, pectoral, spinal and other musculature, subcutaneous fat and skin, and serves as an attachment for the thoracic extremities.</p>

<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Cranial thoracic aperture</title>
<p>The cranial thoracic aperture (also known as the thoracic inlet) is a small passage for the trachea, oesophagus, vessels and nerves. It is enclosed by the deep fascia as well as the pectoral, scalenius and longus colli muscles. Radiographically, it is synonymous with the area between the first pair of ribs.</p>
<p>The right pleural cupula normally extends to the level of the first rib in the dog (both cupula extend to this level in cats; see Figure 12.1, p. 242). The left pleural cupula extends slightly further cranially in full inspiration in the dog (see Figures 12.1c, p. 242 and 12.2, p. 243).</p>
<p>The thoracic inlet serves as a reference for radiographic tracheal diameter measurements (see Figure 10.3, p. 214) and a tangential radiographic view into the inlet can be used for assessment of tracheal collapse (see Figure 10.13, p. 218). Occasionally, it is used as an ultrasonographic approach for the cranial mediastinum.</p>
</sec2>

<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Thoracic skeleton</title>
<p>The thoracic skeleton consists of the ribs, sternum and thoracic spine.</p>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Ribs</title>
<p>Dogs and cats normally have 13 pairs of ribs, which have the following characteristics:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Flat surface in dogs, cylindrical in cats</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Contour:

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Evenly curved (barrel-chested dog breeds, cylindrical-shaped feline thorax)</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Angled (wedge- or flat-chested dog breeds)</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>S-shaped (&#x2018;cottage loaf&#x2019; chest in Basset Hounds and Dachshunds).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Consist of a large bony dorsal and small cartilaginous ventral portion (costal cartilage)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The dorsal extremity of the rib consists of a head, neck and tubercle</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Two synovial joints between the rib and the spine:

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Costovertebral joint between the rib head and the costal vertebral facet (hinge joint)</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Costotransverse joint between the tubercle and the transverse process of the vertebra (sliding joint).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Costochondral junction between the osseous and cartilaginous part of the rib</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Synovial sternocostal joints for the first eight to nine ribs (sternal ribs), remaining ribs fused by connective tissue to each other and the last sternal rib to form the costal arch (asternal or false ribs)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Last one (dogs) or two (cats) pair(s) of ribs not connected to the costal arch (floating ribs).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec3>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Sternum</title>
<p>The sternum consists of a series of eight bones that form the floor of the thorax. The most cranial sternebra is called the manubrium, and the most caudal sternebra is the xiphoid process. The xiphoid cartilage prolongs the xiphoid process caudally. The individual sternebrae are joined by intersternebral cartilage. The first nine ribs articulate with the sternum through the costal cartilages.</p>
<p>Dogs have a curved sternum, which is square in cross section; cats have a cylindrical straight sternum with a flat xiphoid process. The sternum rotates outward in inspiration with the anchor point at the manubrium. The respiratory excursion is higher in cats (3&#x2013;5 degrees) than in dogs (1 degree in the German Shepherd Dog).</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Thoracic spine</title>
<p>Dogs and cats usually have 13 thoracic vertebrae, which articulate cranially with a corresponding rib pair. The cranial nine thoracic vertebrae share the following features:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Short bodies with flattened extremities</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Flat articular facets</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Closely fitting vertebral arches</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Long spinous processes with converging orientation. Eleventh, or occasionally tenth, thoracic vertebra is closest to dorsoventral orientation (anticlinal vertebra)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Small transverse process bearing the costal facets for articulation with the ribs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>At the caudal thoracic spine, the mamillary and accessory processes emerge from the transverse process and diverge in opposite directions (Figure 14.1)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Species and breed differences:

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Vertebral body shape in cats is more cylindrical than in dogs</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Spinal arrangement is physiologically more flexible in cats (curving)</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Brachycephalic dog breeds have very short vertebral bodies.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<fig14.1/>

</sec3>
</sec2>

<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Caudal thoracic aperture and diaphragm</title>
<p>The diaphragm is a dome-shaped musculotendinous organ that attaches to the costal arch and covers the caudal thoracic aperture. It develops from six embryogenic segments into two muscular masses, the crura diaphragmatica, and a central collagenous tendon. The normal adult diaphragm has three openings:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Dorsal aortic hiatus (for aorta, azygos vein and thoracic duct)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Central oesophageal hiatus</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Dextroventral caval foramen (for caudal vena cava, CdVC).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<p>The diaphragm is normally only radiographically visible as an interface between the air-filled lungs and the combined soft tissue opacity of the diaphragm and liver. In obese dogs and most cats, the ventral diaphragm is visible in lateral radiographs as a narrow, soft tissue band between the falciform and retrosternal fat (or caudoventral lung margins) (Figure 14.2). The dorsal portion of the crura diaphragmatica attaches to the ventral surfaces of the third and fourth lumbar vertebrae. At this junction the diaphragm forms the lumbodiaphragmatic recess.</p>
<p>The diaphragmatic silhouette has a variable appearance on the different radiographic views (see Figures 1.27, p. 17 and 1.29, p. 18):
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>On the lateral view, the tendinous dome is projected cranioventrally and the two crura are projected caudodorsally</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>On the ventrodorsal (VD) view, the tendinous dome is projected most cranially with the peak of the dome slightly to the right of midline. Both crura are positioned laterally</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>On the dorsoventral (DV) view, only the dome is radiographically visible</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The right crus is positioned cranially to the left crus in right lateral recumbency, and <italic>vice versa</italic> in left lateral recumbency. This is due to the weight of the abdominal organs pushing more on the dependent crus</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The right crus can be easily identified radiographically because the CdVC enters the thoracic cavity via the caval foramen through the right crus</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The left crus is often underlined by the gas-filled fundus of the stomach</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In right lateral recumbency, the two diaphragmatic crura tend to run parallel; whereas they are usually converging ventrally in left lateral recumbency.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<fig14.2/>
<p>The diaphragm forms several recesses where it attaches to the thoracic wall: the dorsal, ventral, right and left costodiaphragmatic recesses. The right and left costodiaphragmatic recesses are located at the same level on both sides (see Figure 1.27, p. 17). On DV/VD views, the point where the projection of the caudal mediastinum joins the shadow of the diaphragm also forms an angle, referred to as the cardiodiaphragmatic angle (see Figure 1.29, p. 18).</p>
<p>Conventional radiography displays the diaphragmatic position only at the precise moment of the exposure. Fluoroscopy allows dynamic assessment of the diaphragm during inspiration and expiration.</p>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Functional aspects of the thoracic boundaries</title>
<p>The thoracic boundaries are constructed to protect the thoracic viscera, yet allow the respiratory expansion of the lungs. During inspiration the diaphragm contracts, resulting in a flattening of its contour. There is opening of the lumbodiaphragmatic and costodiaphragmatic recesses. The diaphragm is the main contributor to inspiratory chest expansion. Contraction of the inspiratory muscles contributes to chest expansion via:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Outward rotation of the ribs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Slight ventral angulation of the sternum</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>First rib pair is fixated by scalenius muscles and thereby acts as an anchor point for rib cage movement.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>During expiration there is passive relaxation of diaphragm, resulting in its dome-shaped cranial contour, and relaxation of the inspiratory muscles. Expiration can be enhanced by contraction of the expiratory thoracic and abdominal musculature. There are slight differences in the functional anatomy of the rib cage in dogs and cats, which are outlined in Figure 14.3.</p>
</sec2>
</sec1>

<sec1 id="ch-ss">
<title>Interpretive principles</title>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Thoracic skeleton</title>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Ribs</title>
<p>The ribs are often overlooked or not carefully scrutinized during thoracic radiographic assessment. Their small individual size and abundant number, combined with low-contrast chest radiographic technique, makes them blend in with other thoracic structures. To avoid distraction from other thoracic organs, it is useful to evaluate the ribs with the radiograph in a non-standard orientation (see Figure 1.21, p. 14). Assessment of the ribs should be based on the classic R&#x00F6;ntgen signs.</p>
<fig14.3/>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Number, location and symmetry:</title>
<p>It is important to count the ribs when assessing them. If there are rib abnormalities, it is important to know which particular rib is affected:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Monostotic rib lesions are suggestive of primary rib neoplasia, osteomyelitis or focal trauma</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Polyostotic rib lesions are suggestive of trauma, osteochondromatosis, osteomyelitis (bite wounds, migrating foreign body), or underlying metastatic or metabolic disease.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Asymmetry of rib spacing can be an indicator of:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Thoracic and spinal deformities</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Local trauma or previous surgery</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Unilateral pneumothorax</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Unilateral hyper- or hypoinflation</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Oblique radiographic technique (artefactual).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Shape and opacity:</title>

<list list-type="bullet">

<list-item><p>Osteolysis (Figure 14.4):

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Irreversible destruction of bone by aggressive disease</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Active destruction of the rib cortex and/or medulla</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Punctate lucencies in bone marrow tumour (multiple myeloma or lymphoma)</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>May lead to pathological fracture</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Tangential radiographs helpful in subtle lesions.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>

<list-item><p>Osteopenia (see Figures 14.5 and 14.43):

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Benign, reversible process</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Predominant mineral resorption due to: local disuse (Wolff&#x2019;s law), leading to detached rib fragments; or generalized disturbance of calcium homeostasis, commonly seen with hyperparathyroidism and hyperadrenocorticism</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>May lead to pathological fractures.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>

<list-item><p>Periosteal reaction (Figure 14.6):

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>A reparative or proliferative process of bone</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Active and/or proliferative processes have more irregular margins</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Inactive and/or benign processes have smoother margins</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>The nature of the periosteal reaction plus other features (e.g. osteolysis) will indicate whether the process is aggressive or benign.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>

<list-item><p>Sclerosis and osteopetrosis (Figure 14.7):

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Increased radiopacity without alteration in shape due to internally laid down bone</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Sclerosis is a local phenomenon in response to applied stress (Wolff&#x2019;s law) and is rarely seen in ribs</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Osteopetrosis (myelosclerosis) is a generalized condition with defective bone resorption (bone dysplasia). It can be associated with diseases affecting the bone marrow (feline leukaemia virus, pyruvate kinase deficiency or other genetic defects). It affects the entire skeleton but ribs are among the most evidently affected bones. Affected ribs have a marbled opaque appearance.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig14.4/>
<fig14.5/>
<fig14.6/>
<fig14.7/>

<p>Other indicators of rib pathology include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Adjacent soft tissue swelling</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Extrapleural sign (see Figures 14.4 and 14.35c). This sign is characterized by a locally concave peripheral lung margin and signifies the presence of a mass originating from the pleura, chest wall or ventral mediastinum (sternal lymphadenopathy).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec4>
</sec3>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Soft tissues of the thoracic wall</title>
<p>The soft tissue mantle of the rib cage should be thin and even. Skin folds are common in many dog breeds, and are particularly prominent in Shar Peis (Figure 14.8). They can cast a disturbing pattern of lucencies and opacities over the entire thorax. Skin folds should be differentiated from intrathoracic pathology; skin folds extend beyond the thoracic margins. They can give rise to a false appearance of pneumothorax (pseudopneumothorax) (see Chapter 13).</p>
<p>Subcutaneous emphysema is a common sequel to neck and chest wall injuries (Figure 14.9) and displays a pattern of dispersed lucencies over the thorax, which could be misinterpreted as lung pathology. Two views and careful examination of the soft tissues with an intense light source will aid in differentiation:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Usually extends beyond the chest wall margin</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Can be localized to skin via an orthogonal view.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>A wet haircoat and subcutaneous oedema create a mottled or streaky (hair) opacity superimposed on the thorax. Ultrasound coupling gel can also give rise to confusing patterns and should be thoroughly wiped off before radiography.</p>

<fig14.8/>
<fig14.9/>

<p>Lipomas, nipples and other soft tissue masses should be recognized radiographically. If palpable, it can be useful to mark masses with barium or a radiopaque marker, to account for their contributing radiopacity to the radiographic image.</p>
</sec3>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Spine</title>
<p>For proper radiographic assessment of the thoracic spine it is important to:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Position the animal in an extended position, preferably under general anaesthesia</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Ensure straight positioning by use of positioning devices (foam wedges, trough):

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Sternum overlaps spine on a VD radiograph</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Dorsal arches of rib pairs superimpose on a lateral radiograph.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>

<list-item><p>Obtain a VD view rather than a DV radiograph (to avoid magnification).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Assessment of the spine relevant to thoracic diseases should include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Counting the number of vertebrae</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Relative position, size, shape and opacity of thoracic vertebrae and spine as a whole:

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Rule out fractures and aggressive bone lesions</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Relate to rib abnormalities</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Rule out scoliosis, lordosis and kyphosis.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>

<list-item><p>Assessment of the intervertebral disc spaces for size and margination.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec3>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Sternum</title>
<p>The sternum is best evaluated on the lateral view (see Figure 1.23, p. 15) because of superimposition over the spine on straight VD/DV views. Oblique views can be helpful if sternal abnormalities are suspected. Normal degenerative ageing features include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Formation of ventral or dorsal bony spurs, bridging between sternebrae</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mineralization of sternal cartilages and sternal&#x2013;costal junctions.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec3>
</sec2>

<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diaphragmatic silhouette</title>
<p>Several parameters should be taken into consideration when assessing the diaphragm radiographically:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Position</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Shape and symmetry</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Integrity and contour.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Numerous technical and patient-related factors have a great influence on the appearance of the diaphragmatic silhouette. These should be ruled out before diaphragmatic disease is diagnosed, and include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Location of the central ray and beam direction. The diaphragm appears different on radiographs centred over the abdomen</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Visceral distension, obesity, state and depth of respiration</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Recumbency of animal</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Breed-specific chest conformation.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diaphragmatic displacement</title>
<p>Diaphragmatic displacement is usually caused by thoracic or abdominal volume increase or reduction. Intrinsic diaphragmatic diseases, causing phrenic laxity, are rare. The position of the diaphragm can be subjectively assessed evaluating:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>The distance between the diaphragmatic dome and the cardiac silhouette</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The orientation of the CdVC and cardiodiaphragmatic angle</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The caudal extent and angle of the costodiaphragmatic and lumbodiaphragmatic recesses.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<tab14.10/>
<fig14.11/>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Unilateral displacement:</title>
<p>DV or VD radiographs are best to assess alterations from the physiological asymmetry of the diaphragm (Figures 14.10, 14.11 and 14.12):
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>A raised right hemidiaphragm or a depressed left hemidiaphragm will accentuate the asymmetry</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A depressed right hemidiaphragm or a raised left hemidiaphragm will decrease the degree of asymmetry</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The costodiaphragmatic recesses will move cranially or caudally with the raised or depressed hemidiaphragm accordingly, both sides being then at a different level of rib number</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A marked asymmetry of the diaphragm without asymmetry of the costodiaphragmatic angles is usually of no clinical significance.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<fig14.12/>

<p>If a change in asymmetry of the diaphragm is suspected on the DV view, it should be confirmed by obtaining a VD view and <italic>vice versa</italic>. An increased asymmetry on the VD/DV views often corresponds to a marked disparity in the level of the two crura on the lateral view. Inspiratory as well as expiratory radiographs may help in confirming the asymmetry/disparity of level between the two crura.</p>
<p>Associated radiographic signs, such as thoracic wall integrity, pleural effusion or thickening, mediastinal shift and alterations in lung lobe volumes, should be assessed to identify a potential underlying thoracic aetiology.</p>
</sec4>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Bilateral displacement:</title>
<p>Bilateral displacement of the diaphragm is more difficult to diagnose as the normal shape of the diaphragm is maintained (Figures 14.13, 14.14 and 14.15):
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Repeated exposures at various stages of the respiratory cycle or continuous fluoroscopy may be necessary to assess the dynamics of the diaphragm in relation to respiration</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In animals with radiographic signs of increased inspiratory effort yet an incompletely contracted diaphragm, an upper airway obstruction impeding respiratory flow and full lung inflation should be considered.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<tab14.13/>
<fig14.14/>
<fig14.15/>

</sec4>
</sec3>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Interrupted outline and changes in diaphragmatic contour</title>
<p>The diaphragmatic silhouette should be assessed on at least two orthogonal views. Radiographic change or interruption of the diaphragmatic contour (see Figures 14.4 and 14.16) can be due to:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>The presence of soft tissue opacity cranial to the diaphragm (border obliteration)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Interruption of the diaphragm with herniation of abdominal organs into the thorax</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Diaphragmatic masses.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Tenting of the diaphragm refers to small triangular protrusions with their base at the diaphragm and their peaks toward the lungs. This is frequently seen in cats, due to visualization of the diaphragmatic attachments to the costal arch ribs during deep inspiration. It can be a manifestation of pleural adhesion (inspiration and expiration).</p>
<p>If gas opacities outline both sides of the diaphragm, free peritoneal and/or retroperitoneal gas must be present (see Figure 14.49). The following should be considered:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Pneumoretroperitoneum as an extension of pneumomediastinum/pneumothorax</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Recent laparotomy or other gas-introducing procedure</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Abdominal hollow viscus organ rupture</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Gastrointestinal ulceration with rupture</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Body wall laceration</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Gas-producing organisms.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<tab14.16/>


</sec3>
</sec2>
</sec1>

<sec1 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diseases of the thoracic skeleton</title>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Congenital and developmental abnormalities</title>
<p>Congenital abnormalities of the thoracic skeleton are a relatively common phenomenon, particularly in dogs, and are often incidental. Rib, spinal and sternal abnormalities are often combined and should be assessed together. It is important to recognize these changes so as not to mistakenly diagnose pulmonary pathology due to superimposition.</p>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Abnormal number of ribs</title>
<p>This is usually an incidental finding, which is only relevant if the ribs are used as a surgical landmark. Supernumerous or subnumerous ribs are usually associated with transitional vertebrae at the cervicothoracic or thoracolumbar junction. Fusion of the first and second ribs is occasionally seen in chondrodystrophic dog breeds. Rib duplication is rare.</p>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>The abnormal number and shape of ribs are easily recognizable (Figure 14.17).</p>
</sec4>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Metaphyseal developmental disorders of ribs</title>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Metaphyseal osteopathy:</title>
<p>Metaphyseal osteopathy (hypertrophic osteodystrophy) is an osteomalacic disease in young growing dogs of unknown aetiology. It primarily affects metaphyses of the long bones but can also affect the ribs, which may be swollen and painful. The condition is usually self-limiting. Radiographic findings include abnormal radiolucent lines in all rib metaphyses. These are seen better on long bone metaphyses.</p>
<fig14.17/>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Rickets:</title>
<p>This is caused by vitamin D deficiency; it is rare in dogs and cats in the developed world. It can result in a <italic>rickettic rosary</italic>, a chain of palpable swellings along the costochondral junctions. Radiographic findings include widening and radiolucency of the metaphyseal side of the physis. Rickets may result in bony deformity.</p>
</sec4>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Sternal abnormalities</title>
<p>Variation in the size and number of sternebrae, and in the shape of the manubrium and xiphoid process, is common and is usually incidental. Cats commonly have a ventrally deviated xiphoid process, which can be painful.</p>
<p><italic>Sternal dysraphism</italic> is the failure of the left and right cartilaginous sternal precursors to fuse. It leads to a ventral defect that is only closed by thoracic fascia and pleura. In the absence of diaphragmatic defects, sternal dysraphism has no adverse respiratory or circulatory consequences.</p>
<p>The absence, splitting or malformation of the xiphoid cartilage has been associated with peritoneopericardial diaphragmatic hernia, which can be a useful radiographic feature in distinguishing this condition from other pericardial diseases.</p>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Abnormal number and shape of sternebrae (Figure 14.18) is easily recognizable</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Ventrally deviated xiphoid process in cats</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Split sternum or xiphoid process is seen on VD/DV or oblique views with dysraphism.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<fig14.18/>
</sec4>
</sec3>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Spinal abnormalities</title>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Hemivertebrae:</title>
<p>This is a congenital malformation due to hemimetametric displacement or lack of vascularization of somites (Figure 14.19). It can result in spinal curvature. It is very common in screw-tailed dog breeds, where it is usually an incidental finding.</p>
<fig14.19/>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Curved thoracic spine (scoliosis and kyphosis most common) (Figure 14.20)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Associated abnormal number and spacing of ribs (Figure 14.21).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec4>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Other spinal disorders:</title>
<p>Transitional vertebrae (super- or subnumerous thoracic vertebrae) are only clinically relevant if used as surgical landmarks. Spondylosis deformans is very commonly seen in the ventral aspect of the thoracic spine of dogs and cats, and is of no clinical significance. If bone formation over at least four contiguous vertebrae is present, the condition is called disseminated skeletal hyperostosis (DISH), but does not cause thoracic disease. This term is derived from human medicine and its use in animals is controversial.</p>

<fig14.20/>

<p>There is a widespread misconception that intervertebral disc degeneration and prolapse does not occur in the mid-thoracic spine. However, in cats and some dog breeds, such as the German Shepherd Dog, mid-thoracic degenerative disc disease with spinal cord compression is not uncommon.</p>

<fig14.21/>

<p>Radiographic findings are shown in Figures 14.22 and 14.23 (see also Figure 1.23, p. 15):
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Identification of transitional vertebrae requires an entire spinal radiographic series</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Spondylosis deformans is characterized by smooth ventral and lateral bone spurs, bridging adjacent endplates</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>DISH is characterized by abundant smooth or irregular new bone formation, along the ventral and lateral aspects of at least four subsequent vertebral bodies</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Intervertebral disc degeneration is characterized by a narrowed intervertebral disc space, foramen and articular facet space, and mineralized disc material protruding into the vertebral canal (protrusion or extrusion). Detailed description is beyond the scope of this book (see <italic>BSAVA Manual of Canine and Feline Neurology</italic>).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<fig14.22/>
<fig14.23/>

</sec4>
</sec3>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Altered ribcage conformation</title>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Chondrodysplasias:</title>
<p>These are congenital skeletal deformities, resulting from abnormal cartilage development. They cause proportionate (all bones affected) or disproportionate (affecting primarily facial bones and/or appendicular skeleton) dwarfism. They are often inherited and selectively bred for in many breeds of dogs, e.g. disproportionate dwarfism in Dachshunds and Basset Hounds gives rise to the unusual &#x2018;cottage loaf&#x2019; chest conformation.</p>
<p>Congenital hypothyroidism causes disproportionate dwarfism as a result of arrested thyroid activity. Mucopolysaccharidosis is a group of genetic connective tissue disorders in dogs and cats, which result in generalized skeletal deformities.</p>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Chondrodystrophic breed chest conformation on VD/DV view: inward deviation of the ventral rib component and soft tissue opaque chest wall (Figure 14.24)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Congenital hypothyroidism: delayed physeal closure and shortened, often kyphotic vertebrae (Figure 14.25)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mucopolysaccharidosis:

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Oar-shaped ribs</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Endplate sclerosis, widened and fused vertebrae</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Degenerative joint disease and spondylosis</p></list-item>
<list-item><label>&#x2013;</label><p>Often pectus excavatum (see below).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<fig14.24/>
<fig14.25/>

</sec4>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Pectus excavatum:</title>
<p>Pectus excavatum (funnel chest) is a congenital or developmental abnormality, with a variable decrease in the thoracic dorsoventral diameter due to inward deviation of the sternum, especially in its middle portion. It can affect normal respiratory physiology in severe cases. Canine brachycephalic breeds are more commonly affected and concurrent congenital malformations have been reported (hypoplastic trachea, ventricular septal defect, peritoneopericardial diaphragmatic hernia and mucopolysaccharidosis).</p>
<p>Pectus excavatum should be differentiated from physiological respiratory excursion of the sternum, which is relatively high in cats (3&#x2013;5 degrees). With severe inspiratory dyspnoea due to upper airway obstruction, the sternum rotates inward to its maximal range and can mimic mild pectus excavatum. It should also be differentiated from flail sternum (bilateral rib cartilage fractures, see below) by taking radiographs at peak inspiration and expiration.</p>
<p>Radiographic findings (see Figures 14.26 and 12.17, p. 250) include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>S-shaped ventral aspect of the ribs/costal cartilages with the ribs extending ventral to the sternum, which is superimposed on the cardiac silhouette (lateral radiograph)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Static appearance in inspiratory and expiratory views</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lateral displacement of the cardiac silhouette, usually towards the left (VD/DV view).</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<fig14.26/>

<p>Some radiographic indices have been proposed to assess the severity of the condition/need for surgical intervention:

<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>Fronto-sagittal index</italic>: ratio between the width of the chest at the tenth thoracic vertera and the distance between the centre of the ventral surface of the tenth thoracic vertebral body and the nearest point on the sternum. Moderate cases have a ratio of 2&#x2013;3. More than 3 is seen in severe cases</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Vertebral index</italic>: ratio between the distance from the centre of the dorsal surface of the tenth thoracic vertebral body to the nearest point on the sternum, and the dorsoventral diameter of the vertebral body at the same level. Moderate cases have a ratio of 6.00&#x2013;8.99. Less than 6 indicates a severe case</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The vertebral index better differentiates normal from abnormal chest conformation, but there is still some overlap between the groups and diagnosis should not be based solely on indices.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec4>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Flat pup syndrome:</title>
<p>Flat pup syndrome (swimmers, turtle pup) is presumably a congenital condition in dogs, similar to pectus excavatum (decreased dorsoventral thoracic diameter)<italic>,</italic> but without inward rotation of the sternum. &#x2018;Swimmer puppies&#x2019; have flattened chests and move dragging themselves by paddling their limbs laterally and caudally. Being kept on smooth floors and being overweight are believed to be contributing factors. Both chondrodystrophic and non-chondrodystrophic breeds can be affected. Radiographs show that the chest is flattened dorsoventrally, with no inward deviation of the sternum.</p>
</sec4>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Pectus carinatum:</title>
<p>Pectus carinatum (pigeon or keeled chest) is a rare congenital or developmental abnormality, with an increase in the dorsoventral diameter of the thoracic cavity due to the outward deviation of the cranial sternebrae, together with an inward deviation of the most caudal sternebrae. It is usually incidental. There is a possible relationship with congenital cardiac abnormalities. Radiographs show an increased dorsoventral dimension of the rib cage due to caudal displacement of the sternum.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Barrel chest:</title>
<p>This is an acquired condition where a maximally dilated chest is found, with a marked outward position of all ribs and the sternum. An underlying condition should be identified and could include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Marked pleural effusion or pneumothorax</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Large intrathoracic masses</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pulmonary emphysema or hyperpnoea.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Barrel chest is a breed-specific feature in some brachycephalic dog breeds (e.g. Bulldog, Boston Terrier). Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Rounded chest conformation with wide equal rib spacing in inspiration and expiration</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Radiographic features of an underlying condition, causing chest distension.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec4>
</sec3>
</sec2>

<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Fractures of the thoracic skeleton</title>

<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Rib fractures</title>
<p>Most rib fractures are of <italic>traumatic</italic> origin. However, particularly in outdoor cats or stray animals, a traumatic history is not always known. Traumatic fractures are usually transverse, oblique or segmental, and are often multiple and sequential. Displaced fragments can cause penetrating injuries, and open or closed pneumothorax. With a known history of trauma, rib fractures should be taken as an indicator of potential adjacent lung trauma. Radiographic signs of lung contusion may only become visible 6 hours after the injury; serial radiographs are useful to monitor pulmonary disease in such cases.</p>
<p>Rib fractures and thoracic wall bruising can be very painful and impair proper ventilation, leading to hypoxaemia. Non-displaced rib fractures are most commonly treated conservatively (analgesia and rest), whereas internally displaced rib fractures need surgical reduction and stabilization.</p>
<p>Flail chest is associated with the presence of three or more sequential segmental rib fractures or five or more single rib fractures.</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Causes paradoxical movement of the affected portion of the thoracic wall (inward on inspiration, outward on expiration).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Worsens hypoxaemia and contusion to the underlying lung parenchyma.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Requires surgical stabilization.</p></list-item>
</list>

<p>Flail sternum is a specific form of flail chest, which can occur with multiple bilateral rib cartilage fractures and paradoxical respiratory movement of the sternum.</p>
<p><italic>Pathological</italic> or <italic>stress</italic> rib fractures are not uncommon and can be associated with conditions that weaken the bone structure, or as a result of chronic hyperinflation and cough. Features of pathological fractures include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Usually chronic malunion or non-union fracture</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>More common in females and cats</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Often multiple</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Preferential caudal and dorsal location (serratus dorsalis cranialis muscle insertion)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Often coincident with hiatal hernia</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Occasionally occur as a greenstick fracture</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Usually not painful.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Without traumatic history, rib fractures should be considered as an indicator for underlying osteopenic, osteolytic or respiratory conditions. Possible underlying diseases of pathological or stress fractures are:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Chronic feline renal disease or other causes of hyperparathyroidism</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Rib neoplasia (fracture consistent with lesion location)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Feline asthma, chronic canine bronchial disease</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lobar emphysema.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Because of the constant movement of the thoracic bellows, ribs have a poor healing tendency and non-union or malunion fractures are commonly seen. The age of a fracture should be considered when relating it to the history and current complaint of the patient.</p>
<fig14.27/>

<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Interruption of the cortical margins/radiolucent line traversing the rib</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Focal increase in radiopacity at the site where the fracture ends overlap</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Altered direction and spacing of the ribs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Flail chest: inspiratory inward displacement of fracture segments of three or more adjacent ribs (Figure 14.27)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Flail sternum: inspiratory inward displacement of the sternum, expiratory outward rotation (Figure 14.28)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Traumatic fractures, usually ipsilateral to the impact site</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Fractures due to metabolic or respiratory conditions, often serial and caudally and dorsally located</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The fracture margin should be sharp in recent traumatic fractures and remodelled in chronic fractures. Unsharp fracture margins without remodelling suggest a recent pathological fracture due an osteolytic process.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<fig14.28/>
<p>Orthogonal views should always be taken in cases of suspected/known thoracic trauma (Figure 14.29). Multiple views should help to detect:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Non-displaced fractures</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lesions of the costal cartilage or junction, or the very proximal aspect of the rib</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Costosternal luxations.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Findings with chronic fractures may include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Normal callus formation: smooth bony proliferation that diminishes over time, small static residual changes</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Non-union: &#x2018;elephant foot&#x2019;-like, enlarged, sclerotic fracture ends (Figure 14.30)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Malunion: abnormal angulation, often with a large callus.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<fig14.29/>
<fig14.30/>

</sec4>
</sec3>
******************364
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Sternal fractures and dislocation</title>
<p>Malalignment of sternebrae, with or without prior trauma, is frequently observed and is insignificant unless accompanied by intra- and extrathoracic soft tissue swelling or clinical signs.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>There is usually obvious dislocation (Figure 14.31). Malposition of the xiphoid process in cats is usually not traumatic.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Spinal fractures and dislocations</title>
<p>Spinal fractures and dislocations usually occur at junctions between major segments (cervical, thoracic, lumbar, sacral and coccygeal), are often compressive and can be a sequel to underlying osteolysis (pathological fracture). In the context of thoracic trauma, the spine should be carefully examined for evidence of fractures because radiographic features are often subtle; this requires two orthogonal views, and may change prognosis and treatment options.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Epiphyseal slip fracture in young animals with often minimal displacement (Figure 14.32)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Compression fracture: shortening of the vertebral body.</p></list-item>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Computed tomography:</title>
<p>Computed tomography (CT) is a sensitive and specific tool used to assess the instability of spinal fractures (Figure 14.33).</p>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Benign mass lesions</title>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Osteochondroma</title>
<p>This is a skeletal dysplasia (a form of hamartoma) associated with expansile bony lesions, which usually arises from the osteochondral junction of bones. The lesion usually stops growing at the time of skeletal maturity. Aetiological theories include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Herniation of part of a physis</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Proliferative response to stress at the physeal margin</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Biochemical disorder, allowing redirection of physeal growth</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Periosteum regaining its perichondral potential due to an unknown factor.</p></list-item>
<p>It is potentially a hereditary condition. In rare cases malignant transformation may occur. Commonly affected areas are the costochondral rib junctions; less frequently, the metaphyses of the long bones and vertebrae may be involved. Small rib lesions are common in dogs, but rare in cats. The condition can affect multiple sites simultaneously (multiple cartilaginous exostoses).</p>
<p>Clinical signs are usually related to lameness or paresis/paralysis in the case of spinal cord compression.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>There is one or more bone mass of variable opacity and margination (Figure 14.34):
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Often cauliflower or soapy bubble-like</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Active lesion irregular in opacity and poorly marginated</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Inactive lesions are homogenously opaque and smoothly marginated.</p></list-item>
<p>Differentiation of osteochondroma from malignant neoplasia and healed rib fracture is based on the typical location at the costochondral junction of several ribs.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Other imaging techniques:</title>
<p>CT or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) may be used to assess spinal cord compression of vertebral osteochondroma.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Aneurysmal bone cyst</title>
<p>This is a rare benign non-neoplastic condition seen in different bones, including the ribs. The presumed aetiology is that an original insult disrupts, but does not interrupt, bone marrow vasculature. A large arteriovenous fistula then forms, distending the cortex.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Large expansile osteolytic rib lesion with eggshell-like rim</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Monostotic</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Cannot always be differentiated from malignant neoplasia and osteochondroma.</p></list-item>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Neoplasia</title>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Rib and chest wall tumours</title>
<p>Primary rib tumours are relatively rare in dogs and very rare in cats; there is no known sex or breed predisposition, and they are also seen in young animals. Osteosarcoma and chondrosarcoma are the most common; fibrosarcoma, haemangiosarcoma and benign neoplasms (osteoma, chondroma) are seen less frequently. Primary tumours are often located in the distal third of the rib (costochondral junction). They tend to metastasize to the lungs and other organs. Primary rib tumours are rare compared with appendicular primary bone tumours. Clinical signs are associated with the enlargement of the mass:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Fixed firm chest wall mass in some cases</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Can expand predominantly intrathoracically without a visible external mass</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Dyspnoea, cough due to lung compression and/or haemothorax</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Front limb lameness if impeding on shoulder joint or brachial plexus.</p></list-item>
<p>Metastatic, bone marrow and invading soft tissue neoplasia in ribs have certain features:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Metastatic rib tumours are usually small and located in the proximal or middle portion of the rib</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Multiple myeloma frequently affect the ribs along with the vertebrae and other bones, where changes are more easily recognizable</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Primary bone lymphoma or bone involvement in multicentric lymphoma is rare in dogs and cats. Young animals can be affected. Primary bone lymphoma can preferentially affect the metaphyses in growing bones</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The most common soft tissue mass of the chest wall is fibrosarcoma, which is particularly common in cats. Fibrosarcomas can usually be distinguished from diffuse processes, such as cellulitis or haemorrhage, by their focal distribution and their propensity to grow toward the thoracic cavity. They can be difficult to differentiate from primary rib tumours. There is often polyostotic involment in soft tissue tumours</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pleural neoplasia (mesothelioma) can affect multiple ribs and be difficult to differentiate from other types of neoplasia.</p></list-item>
<p>Lipoma and liposarcoma may arise from the thoracic wall. Benign lipomas are extremely common in the subcutaneous layers of the thoracic wall, and are characterized as soft, moveable slow-growing masses. Occasionally, a benign mass arises from the internal thoracic wall and causes a mass effect on internal thoracic organs. Infiltrative lipomas and liposarcomas can also infiltrate the inter- and intramuscular layers of the thoracic wall.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Tangential and opposite lateral radiographs are often helpful. Osteolysis is seen (Figure 14.35) but can be subtle to detect. There may be an irregular to sunburst periosteal reaction and amorphous new bone. Fractures may be present, with unsharp margins (pathological fracture). The extrapleural sign (focal inward deviation of the pleural and pulmonary structures) may be seen. There may be displacement of adjacent ribs.</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Primary rib tumours:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Monostotic</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Preferentially distal third of the rib (costochrondral junction)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Displaced adjacent ribs, which are otherwise normal</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Often very large intrathoracic component.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Metastatic rib tumours:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Often polyostotic, but randomly oriented</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Preferentially middle and proximal third of the rib</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Often small at time of detection.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Soft tissue tumour invading the ribs (Figure 14.36):</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Soft tissue mass with variable external component</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Osteolysis, periosteal reaction, fractures of multiple adjacent ribs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Any part of the rib can be affected</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mesothelioma: abundant pleural effusion, no external chest wall mass, periosteal reaction on several ribs possible.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Multiple myeloma and lymphoma:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Multiple myeloma: multiple punctate lucencies without periosteal reaction or sclerosis; pathological fractures are uncommon</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lymphoma: irregular periosteal reaction and punctate or diffuse lysis in metaphyseal area; pathological fractures are uncommon.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lipoma and liposarcoma:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Fat opacity in lipoma lesions, which distinguishes them from soft tissue masses</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Liposarcoma may have fat and/or soft tissue opacity</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Can be difficult to differentiate from obesity-related fat deposition</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>External masses should marked for radiography to explain opacity changes.</p></list-item>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Other imaging techniques:</title>
<p>Ultrasonography is helpful to differentiate a mass lesion from pleural effusion, lung and other internal thoracic structures, and to characterize the nature and extent of the lesion. Assessment can be made of the mass movement in relation to respiration:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Chest wall mass moves with the rib cage</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lung mass moves with pulmonary excursion</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Smooth convex mass displaces the normal pleura&#x2013;lung interface inwards.</p></list-item>
<p>Most neoplasms have a mixed echogenic appearance (Figure 14.37a), often with central hypoechoic (necrosis, haemorrhage) regions. Hyperechoic foci with shadowing (soft tissue mineralization) may be identified. The margins may or may not be discernible. The echogenicity of the mass should always be compared with the adjacent normal tissue. This can be useful in identifying a lipoma, which is uniformly hyperechoic compared with the surrounding tissue (Figure 14.37b). A liposarcoma is more echogenic and less organized than a lipoma.</p>
<p>Ultrasonography is rarely tissue- or cell-specific but is very useful in guiding a needle into a mass for aspiration or biopsy. CT and MRI can be very helpful to assess:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Tumour extent for surgical resection and radiation treatment planning (see Figures 14.38 and 4.1, p.71)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Involvement of other thoracic organs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Detection of lung metastases.</p></list-item>
<p>Bone scintigraphy may be used for detection of subtle active lesions, or assessment of the number and location of skeletal metastases (Figure 14.39).</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Sternal neoplasia</title>
<p>Primary or secondary neoplasia of the sternum is rare and should be differentiated from osteomyelitis.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>A combination of osteolytic and irregular osteoproductive lesions is seen. Masses may grow into the thorax and reach a large size.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Spinal neoplasia</title>
<p>Primary or secondary neoplasia can occur in the vertebrae, surrounding soft tissues, meninges and spinal cord. The most common vertebral tumours include osteosarcoma, chondrosarcoma, fibrosarcoma and haemangiosarcoma. Paravertebral neoplasms include neuroendocrine tumours and soft tissue sarcomas. Diffuse neoplasms, such as multiple myeloma and lymphoma, also occur. Lymphoma is the most common spinal tumour in the cat. The thoracic spine is a common location for spinal neoplasia.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Vertebral tumours (Figure 14.40):</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Monostotic (primary) or randomly polyostotic (secondary)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Usually very subtle osteolysis with or without periosteal reaction</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Occasionally, osteosclerotic appearance</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pathological compression fracture is common</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Perivertebral soft tissue mass extension into the thorax is possible.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Paravertebral neoplasms:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Large soft tissue mass in the dorsal mediastinum (see Figures 14.41 and 10.31d, p.226)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Periosteal reaction along several vertebrae is possible.</p></list-item>
<p>Detailed discussion of other spinal neoplasms is beyond the scope of this manual.</p>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Osteomyelitis, metabolic and reactive changes</title>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Ribs and chest wall</title>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Osteomyelitis and abscessation:</title>
<p>Infections of the thoracic wall result from foreign bodies, lacerations, bite wounds or surgical wound contamination. Migrating foreign bodies, such as grass awns, penetrating via the skin, or a wooden skewer, penetrating via the gastrointestinal tract, can cause inflammatory disease, an abscess/granuloma, a fistulous tract in the thoracic wall region or even lead to pleural effusion. Inhaled grass awns often migrate towards the epaxial musculature of the cranial lumbar spine, causing local abscessation and spondylitis. Fungal or parasitic (hepatozoonosis) osteomyelitis and cellulitis occur in endemic areas. These lesions are often very painful, more so than neoplasia.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Metabolic diseases:</title>
<p>Nutritional or renal hyperparathyroidism causes marked demineralization and deformities of the entire skeleton, and pathological fractures. Other osteopenic (Cushing&#x2019;s disease) or osteosclerotic conditions are usually not sufficient to cause clinical signs relating to the thoracic skeleton, although pathological rib fractures are possible.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Hypertrophic osteopathy:</title>
<p>In the presence of large chronic masses in the lungs or other thoracic organs, a systemic response can be evoked in the appendicular and, to a lesser extent, in the axial skeleton. It can also be induced by a non-thoracic mass. The distal legs are most commonly affected; the ribs are less commonly affected. Aetiological theories include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Circulating toxins from the mass lesion, promoting periosteal response</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Sympathetic stimulation, promoting peripheral vascularization</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Neural reflex originating from the mass, stimulating increased peripheral vascularization of poorly oxygenated blood (shunting through anastomoses in the mass).</p></list-item>
<p>Hypertrophic osteopathy is reversible if the original mass is removed.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Osteomyelitis and abscessation (Figure 14.42):</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Predominantly, osteoproductive lesion with irregular periosteal reaction on one or multiple ribs and adjacent soft tissue swelling and/or free gas</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Local soft tissue opacity with abscess or granuloma formation</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pleural effusion or lung changes possible with fistulous tract</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Hepatozoonosis; signs seen on the proximal long bones in particular.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Hyperparathyroidism (Figure 14.43):</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Osteopenic skeleton, spinal curvature deformities and pathological fractures, particularly of the ribs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Cushing&#x2019;s disease, osteosclerosis (see Interpretive principles, above).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Hypertrophic osteopathy:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Subtle palisade-like periosteal reaction on multiple ribs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>More marked changes in the appendicular skeleton.</p></list-item>
</sec5>
<sec5 id="ch-ss">
<title>Contrast studies:</title>
<p>Fistulography and sinography may be used to explore the extension of sinuses and connections of fistulous tracts.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Ultrasonography:</title>
<p>This is very useful for the identification of foreign material, abscessation and haematomas in the chest wall (Figure 14.44):
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Foreign body:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Identification of the foreign body (mostly hyperechoic interface): a grass awn is spindle-shaped with two or three echogenic interfaces; a wooden skewer produces a linear hyperechoic interface</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Surrounding poorly echogenic area represents inflammatory fluid/abscess.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Abscess:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Well defined, hypoechoic or anechoic fluid collection, which may contain varying degrees of echogenic debris</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Identification of small gas bubbles</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Hyperechoic surrounding tissue (cellulitis)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>If chronic, often encapsulated with an irregular internal margin.</p></list-item>
<p>An abscess is sometimes indistinguishable from an organized haematoma, necrotic tumour or seroma.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Sternal osteomyelitis</title>
<p>This is uncommon but may be a sequel to trauma (bite, penetrating foreign body) or a complication of midline thoracotomy (sterniotomy). An intermittently discharging sinus may be present.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Periosteal reaction around the affected sternebra (Figure 14.45)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Osteolysis or sclerosis</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Soft tissue swelling ventral to sternum; lucent gas tracts may be seen if there is a discharging sinus.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pleural thickening and effusion.</p></list-item>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Spondylitis and discospondylitis</title>
<p>True vertebral infection is rare. However, discospondylitis is not uncommon in dogs. The thoracic spine is a common location for bacterial discospondylitis; this should be differentiated from intervertebral disc disease. The original nidus of infection is often elsewhere in the body, such as in the prostate.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Collapsed intervertebral disc space with both endplates irregularly outlined (Figure 14.46)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Healed discospondylitis shows smooth new bone formation, endplate sclerosis and vertebral fusion</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Can occur at one or multiple sites.</p></list-item>
</sec1>
<sec1 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diseases of the thoracic inlet</title>
<p>For information on diseases of the thoracic inlet, see Chapter 12.</p>
</sec1>
<sec1 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diseases of the diaphragm</title>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diaphragmatic rupture</title>
<p>Diaphragmatic ruptures are usually traumatic in origin. They are frequently misnamed as <italic>acquired diaphragmatic hernias.</italic> This is an incorrect term, since the prolapsed organs are not contained within a hernial sac.</p>
<p>The diaphragm normally ruptures at its weakest point, following a sudden increase in intra-abdominal pressure while the glottis is open. The site and size of the rupture are variable. Right-sided tears are reported to be more frequent than left-sided. Tears can extend from one side to the other and be radial or circumferential.</p>
<p>The liver is the most frequently prolapsed organ with right-sided ruptures; the stomach is the most frequently prolapsed organ with left-sided ruptures. Prolapse of the small intestines and omentum can be present with any tear. Less commonly prolapsed organs include the spleen, large intestine, omentum, uterus and kidney.</p>
<p>The most frequent clinical sign is dyspnoea; ranging from mild to severe, depending on the volume of the prolapsed organs and fluid accumulation. Other clinical signs can be present, such as regurgitation or vomiting, and are related to the organ prolapsed in the thoracic cavity. Gastric prolapse is a surgical emergency as sudden strangulation and bloating may quickly become life-threatening.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography</title>
<p>A DV view should be taken to avoid further respiratory compromise. Positional radiographs, such as a lateral view using a horizontal beam, should be considered if the respiratory distress worsens in lateral recumbency. It is useful to obtain abdominal radiographs to be able to check for the presence of abdominal organs. One or more of the following radiographic signs can be detected (Figure 14.47):
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Loss or change of contour of the diaphragmatic outline</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Obliteration and/or dorsal displacement of the cardiac shadow</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Increased opacity of the ventral thoracic cavity, with or without elevation of the trachea and/or cardiac silhouette</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mediastinal shift</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Presence of gas-filled tubular structures and/or speckled mineral opacities, suggestive of the ingesta-filled gastrointestinal tract being located within the thoracic cavity</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pleural effusion may be present and mask herniated parenchymal organs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Lung lobe collapse</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Absence of abdominal organs from the abdominal cavity is often associated with cranioventral displacement of the stomach axis. Some organs may be clearly identified within the thoracic cavity</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>In cats, falciform fat may be the only abdominal organ herniated, in which case the fat pad ventral to the liver will appear very small, the liver will be closer to the abdominal wall and the ventral outline of the diaphragm will be lost</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Other radiographic signs of trauma (e.g. rib fractures, lung contusions and appendicular skeleton fractures).</p></list-item>
<p>A diaphragmatic tear without organ prolapse cannot be ruled out based on the absence of radiographic signs.</p>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Contrast studies:</bold></italic> Contrast studies which may aid diagnosis include:</p>
<list-item><p><italic>Barium transit studies</italic> (Figure 14.48) are useful if survey radiography is equivocal. Radiographs should be repeated over a time period long enough to demonstrate the presence of the stomach, small and/or large intestines within the thoracic cavity, or cranioventral displacement of the gastric axis if only liver has herniated. Barium studies are contraindicated when perforation of the gastrointestinal tract is suspected in addition to the diaphragmatic rupture. Water-soluble iodinated agents can be used instead</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Positive-contrast peritoneography</italic>. A positive non-ionic iodine-based contrast medium is injected into, and should remain in, the peritoneal cavity. If positive contrast medium is found in the pleural space, diaphragmatic rupture is confirmed. A negative study does not rule out a diaphragmatic rupture since, in chronic cases, adhesions may obstruct the tear</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>Pneumo</italic>- or <italic>capnoperitoneography</italic> (Figure 14.49). Positive-contrast studies are preferred and easier to interpret. A small quantity of gas is injected into the peritoneal cavity. If a pneumothorax is then radiographically visible, diaphragmatic rupture is confirmed. Carbon dioxide is preferred due to the reduced risk of vascular air emboli (capnoperitoneography). A negative study does not rule out a diaphragmatic rupture.</p></list-item>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Ultrasonography</title>
<p>This is a useful non-invasive method to identify an unclear case of diaphragmatic rupture and organ prolapse. It can be difficult to determine this as the normal diaphragmatic outline is hard to visualize and mirror image artefacts can be confusing. The following should be looked for:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Visualization of abdominal organs in the pleural cavity. Differentiation between normal liver and consolidated/collapsed lung may be difficult</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Interruption of the normal echogenic lung&#x2013;diaphragm interface.</p></list-item>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diaphragmatic hernias</title>
<p>Diaphragmatic hernias are common congenital anomalies in dogs and cats, due to agenesis of a portion of the diaphragm or lack of fusion between the parts of the primitive diaphragm. They include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Ventral diaphragmatic hernias</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Hiatal hernias</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Paraoesophageal intramediastinal hernias</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Peritoneopericardial hernias</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Aortic hiatal diaphragmatic hernias.</p></list-item>
<p>In contrast to diaphragmatic ruptures, the prolapsed abdominal organs are contained within a peritoneal or pericardial hernial sac, i.e. are <italic>herniated.</italic> Diaphragmatic hernias are usually found in young animals with no history of trauma. They appear in predetermined areas of the diaphragm and may be associated with other congenital defects. No granulation or scar tissue will be found during surgery. Hiatal hernias may be acquired. Hernia of the cranial abdominal wall can lead to a <italic>paracostal hernia,</italic> where the hernial sac is contained between the ribs and soft tissue layers of the thorax.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Paracostal abdominal wall hernia</title>
<p>Herniation of viscera occurs via a body wall defect at the costal arch. Abdominal viscera are contained in the subcutaneous layers of the thoracic wall.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>There is a soft tissue swelling along the body wall, which may contain gas-filled viscera (Figure 14.50).</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Ventral diaphragmatic hernia</title>
<p>Ventral (true) diaphragmatic hernias are typically due to a congenital lack of fusion between parts of the primitive diaphragm, which leads to the persistence of an aperture through which abdominal organs herniate into the thoracic cavity. Abdominal organs are contained within a hernial sac, usually the parietal pleura of the diaphragm, which prevents direct communication between the peritoneal and pleural cavities. True ventral diaphragmatic hernias are rare in animals. They are usually small and not associated with clinical signs.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>There is a cranial bulge in the ventral diaphragmatic silhouette with a possible cardiac shift away from the bulge on a lateral radiograph.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Hiatal hernia</title>
<p>A hiatal hernia corresponds to a herniation of any abdominal organ through the oesophageal hiatus. It is most often congenital in origin but can be acquired, following the repair of a chronic diaphragmatic rupture or secondary to a traumatic event, oesophageal/upper respiratory tract pathologies or neuromuscular disorders. Three main types of hiatal hernia are recognized in animals (Figure 14.51):
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Short oesophagus hiatal hernia</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Sliding hiatal hernia</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Paraoesophageal hiatal hernia.</p></list-item>
<p>Sliding and paraoesophageal hiatal hernias can coexist. Chinese Shar Pei dogs are predisposed for hiatal hernias.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Short oesophagus hiatal hernia:</title>
<p>The lower oesophageal sphincter lies in the caudal mediastinum due to a short oesophagus. The cardia is pulled through the oesophageal hiatus. This type of hernia is very rare and has only been described in the dog.</p>
</sec5>
<sec5 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Ovoid soft tissue opacity in the mid-caudal thorax with a locally obliterated diaphragmatic silhouette on a lateral radiograph.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Central, slightly left-sided location of opacity on DV/VD views.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Permanent appearance.</p></list-item>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Sliding intramediastinal hiatal hernia:</title>
<p>The lower oesophageal sphincter moves freely back and forth into the caudal mediastinum, followed by parts of the stomach, through a loose oesophageal hiatus (see Figure 14.51a). Clinical signs include variable degrees of vomiting or regurgitation, hypersalivation and chronic weight loss. If the stomach is incarcerated, severe respiratory distress can be present. Aspiration pneumonia is frequently associated with this condition.</p>
</sec5>
<sec5 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings (Figure 14.52) include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Semicircular soft tissue mass, merging with the liver shadow localized between the CdVC and the aorta on the lateral view and in the caudal mediastinum on the DV view, superimposed over the hepatic shadow</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Gas present in the herniated stomach may allow recognition of rugal folds. If a large portion of the stomach is herniated and incarcerated, a large hyperlucent cyst-like structure surrounded by a thin soft tissue rim may be seen. In this case, lung collapse and mediastinal shift to the contralateral side is also visible</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Radiographic signs of aspiration pneumonia may be an associated finding.</p></list-item>
<p>Radiographic signs might be absent, particularly during expiration, due to the sliding nature of the hernia. Positional radiography is usually unsuccessful in demonstrating a sliding hiatal hernia.</p>
<p>Contrast studies (Figure 14.53) may aid diagnosis:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>A barium oesophagram may confirm suspicion of a sliding hiatal hernia. As the lower oesophageal sphincter moves back and forth, it can be in a normal position at the time of the examination</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Gastric rugae may be visible both in the caudal mediastinum and in the cranial abdomen, separated by a marked narrowing at the level of the oesophageal hiatus</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The lower oesophageal hiatus can be seen cranial to the cardia as a shallow indentation. It also allows assessment of concurrent oesophageal disorders, such as strictures or masses.</p></list-item>
</sec5>
<sec5 id="ch-ss">
<title>Fluoroscopy:</title>
<p>This, together with an oesophagram, allows dynamic assessment of the position of the lower oesophageal sphincter and of the stomach. As the lower oesophageal sphincter function is altered due to its abnormal position, gastro-oesophageal reflux of contrast medium may be seen associated with swallowing.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Paraoesophageal hiatal hernia:</title>
<p>The lower oesophageal sphincter remains in place and is competent, but part of the stomach surrounded by a peritoneal sac herniates through the oesophageal hiatus parallel to an immobile oesophagus. Two subtypes exist:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Abdominal organs may herniate to the left of the oesophagus in which case they come to lie in the pleural cavity (see Figure 14.51b)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Abdominal organs may also slide to the right of the oesophagus and herniate into the potential space between the two mediastinal pleural leaves (Sussdorf&#x2019;s space &#x2013; <italic>cavum mediastini serosum</italic> or <italic>bursa infracardiaca</italic>) (see Figure 14.51c). This space is normally closed by a thin membrane, which may be congenitally weak or ruptured following trauma. The prolapsed organs, usually part of the stomach, liver or small intestines, can move in and out as the space widens during inspiration and shrinks during expiration.</p></list-item>
<p>Clinical signs may range from none to recurrent gastrointestinal signs, including anorexia, retching, vomiting or bloating of the stomach without gastric torsion.</p>
</sec5>
<sec5 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Left-sided paraoesophageal hernia:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Changes in the diaphragmatic contour associated with a mass in the mid-caudal thoracic cavity</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Extrapleural sign with the base of the mass toward the diaphragm and very sharp margins on the lung side</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Presence of gas-filled tubular structures in the caudal thoracic cavity</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Presence of a hyperlucent cyst-like structure surrounded by a thin soft tissue rim filling the left hemithorax, may be seen if the stomach herniates and becomes incarcerated</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Mediastinal shift to the right and pulmonary atelectasis.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Right-sided paraoesophageal hernia:</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Soft tissue mass in the mid-caudal thorax on the lateral view, caudal to the heart</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Widening of the caudal mediastinum on the DV view, associated with displacement of the cardiac silhouette to the left. As the pericardium is intact, the cardiac silhouette remains a normal size</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Gas in the stomach or small intestines may be identified in the caudal mediastinum.</p></list-item>
<p>Barium studies can confirm a suspicion of paraoesophageal hiatal hernia by outlining the abnormal position of the stomach or the small intestines in the caudodorsal thorax.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Peritoneopericardial diaphragmatic hernia</title>
<p>Peritoneopericardial diaphragmatic hernia (PPDH) is the most common diaphragmatic hernia in dogs and cats. It is due to an embryological fusion defect in the ventral diaphragm, leading to a communication between the pericardial and the peritoneal cavities. PPDHs are often associated with sternal or cardiac defects. The liver is the most frequently herniated organ, and may be associated with gallbladder, stomach, small intestine or omental herniation.</p>
<p>Clinical signs depend on the organs herniated and the size of the defect, and include respiratory, cardiovascular and gastrointestinal disorders. Auscultation may reveal muffled heart sounds or borborygmy over the cardiac area. Sudden onset of clinical signs may arise secondary to strangulation of a herniated organ. Most frequently no clinical signs are present and a PPDH is found incidentally.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Moderate to gross enlargement of the cardiac silhouette, merging caudally with the diaphragmatic outline (Figure 14.54) without associated radiographic signs of heart failure</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Dorsal displacement of the trachea</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Dorsal displacement of the CdVC</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Heterogenous opacity of the cardiac shadow due to the presence of falciform or omental fat, and/or gas or mineralized speckled structures contained in the herniated small or large intestines</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Persistence of a dorsal mesothelial remnant between the cardiac silhouette and the diaphragmatic outline, at the level or slightly dorsal to the CdVC, can be seen in cats</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Cranial displacement of the stomach and other abdominal organs</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Sternal abnormalities, including various </p></list-item>
<list-item><p>	deformities, reduction in the number of sternebrae and the absence or split of the xiphoid process</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Umbilical hernia or other abdominal wall defects</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Absence of radiographic signs of cardiac failure.</p></list-item>
</sec5>
<sec5 id="ch-ss">
<title>Contrast studies:</title>
<p>Barium studies may outline the abnormal position of the stomach or the small intestine in the pericardium if they are herniated (Figure 14.55). Positive- or negative-contrast peritoneography may be useful when barium studies are inconclusive.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Fluoroscopy:</title>
<p>The normal cardiac and diaphragmatic motion is not visible due to obliteration by herniated soft tissue structures.</p>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Ultrasonography:</bold></italic> This is an excellent modality to differentiate between cardiomegaly and a PPDH. An abdominal organ, usually part of the liver, is visible next to the heart, within the pericardial sac (Figure 14.56). Ultrasonography allows evaluation of the herniated organs as well as providing an assessment of cardiac function, if cardiovascular impairment was the reason for investigation.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Aortic hilar hernia</title>
<p>The aortic hilus is the only diaphragmatic opening that connects the mediastinum with the retroperitoneal space. Free mediastinal gas can pass through the hilus and enter the retroperitoneal space relatively easily. If defects in this hilus exist, retroperitoneal organs such as the adrenal glands and kidneys can prolapse into the mediastinum. Intramediastinal kidneys are rare in dogs and cats and are usually detected incidentally.</p>
</sec4>
<sec4 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography:</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Caudodorsal mediastinal location of a kidney (Figure 14.57)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Should be differentiated from a dorsal circumferential diaphragmatic tear and renal prolapse.</p></list-item>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diaphragmatic neoplasia</title>
<p>Diaphragmatic neoplasia is extremely rare in dogs and cats. Neoplasms can be primary or metastatic.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography</title>
<p>An extrapleural soft tissue mass is seen, with the base merging with the diaphragmatic outline and a sharp rounded margin towards the thoracic cavity. If the mass extends strictly towards the abdominal cavity, it will not be radiographically visible on plain radiographs. It can be very difficult to differentiate from other mass lesions or diaphragmatic hernias.</p>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diaphragmatic abscess</title>
<p>Diaphragmatic abscesses mainly result from penetrating injuries or migrating foreign bodies penetrating the diaphragm. Less frequently, infection from the abdomen may extend to the peritoneal surface of the diaphragm.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography</title>
<p>An extrapleural soft tissue mass is seen, with the base merging with the diaphragmatic outline and a sharp rounded margin towards the thoracic cavity. If the abscess arises on the peritoneal surface of the diaphragm, it will not be visible on plain radiographs.</p>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Muscular dystrophy</title>
<p>Duchenne muscular dystrophy is a rare inherited disorder in humans, dogs, cats and other animals, leading to a deficiency in the myofibre protein, dystrophin. The deficiency causes excessive intracellular calcium and subsequent myocyte hypertrophy, necrosis and replacement by fibrous tissue. Many skeletal and smooth muscles and the myocardium can be affected, leading to muscular hypertrophy, organomegaly and dystrophic mineralization.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography</title>
<p>Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Convex, scalloped diaphragmatic silhouette (Figure 14.58)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Abdominal organomegaly</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Cardiomegaly</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Soft tissue mineralization.</p></list-item>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diaphragmatic (phrenic nerve) paralysis</title>
<p>The phrenic nerves arise from the fifth to the seventh cervical nerves, and run through the cranial mediastinum and on each side of the dorsal pericardium. Diaphragmatic paralysis can be uni- or bilateral, temporary or permanent. Diaphragmatic paralysis causes paradoxical diaphragmatic movement; a cranial movement of the affected hemidiaphragm at inspiration and a caudal movement at expiration (Kienbock&#x2019;s phenomenon). Associated inward movement of the abdominal wall at inspiration and outward movement at expiration occurs in bilateral paralysis. Unilateral paralysis of the diaphragm rarely causes any clinical signs, whereas bilateral paralysis often causes moderate to severe signs.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Radiography</title>
<p>Inspiratory and expiratory films should be obtained. Radiographic findings include:
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Increased asymmetry of the diaphragmatic outline on DV/VD views in right hemidiaphragmatic paralysis due to the raised right hemidiaphragm (Figure 14.59)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Decreased asymmetry of the diaphragmatic outline on DV/VD views in left hemidiaphragmatic paralysis due to the raised left hemidiaphragm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Right and left costophrenic angles positioned at different levels in the case of unilateral paralysis, with the paralysed side positioned more cranially</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Cranioventral angulation of the ribs on the side of the paralysed hemidiaphragm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Cranial displacement of the diaphragmatic structures during inspiration and caudal displacement during expiration in the case of bilateral paralysis, or absence of diaphragmatic displacement at different stages of the respiratory cycle (Figure 14.60)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Poor pulmonary inflation on the affected side.</p></list-item>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Fluoroscopy</title>
<p>This is the imaging modality of choice to observe respiratory excursion of the diaphragm. There is a reduced range of motion of one crus, or paradoxical movement of both crura, during the respiratory cycle.</p>
</sec2>
<sec2 id="ch-ss">
<title>Diaphragmatic flutter</title>
<p>Flutter of the diaphragm consists of synchronous spastic contractions of one or both hemidiaphragms. It occurs synchronous with the first heart sound. It is thought to be due to a lower threshold of excitability of the phrenic nerves at the level of the pericardium, which allows their stimulation by action currents of the myocardium. It is commonly a self-limiting condition that disappears if the underlying cause is treated, usually an electrolyte imbalance of variable origin. Marked rhythmic movements of the costal arch and the abdominal wall are the only clinical signs of a diaphragmatic flutter. These can last from only a few days to several months.</p>
</sec3>
<sec3 id="ch-ss">
<title>Fluoroscopy</title>
<p>This allows dynamic visualization of the spastic contractions of one or both hemidiaphragms, synchronous with the heartbeat. This is not detectable radiographically.</p>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References and further reading</title>
<p>Baines SJ, Lewis S and White RA (2002) Primary thoracic wall tumours of mesenchymal origin in dogs: a retrospective study of 46 cases. <italic>The Veterinary Record</italic> <bold>150</bold>, 335&#x2013;339</p>
<p>Berry CR, Gaschen FP and Ackerman N (1992) Radiographic and ultrasonographic features of hypertrophic feline muscular dystrophy in two cats. <italic>Veterinary Radiology and Ultrasound</italic> <bold>33</bold>, 357&#x2013;364</p>
<p>Berry CR, Koblik PD and Ticer JW (1990) Dorsal peritoneopericardial mesothelial remnant as an aid to the diagnosis of feline congenital diaphragmatic hernia. <italic>Veterinary Radiology</italic> <bold>31</bold>, 239&#x2013;245</p>
<p>Biller DS, Johnson GC, Birchard SJ and Fingland RB (1987) Aneurysmal bone cyst in a rib of a cat. <italic>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</italic> <bold>190</bold>, 1193&#x2013;1195</p>
<p>Bright RM, Sackman JE, DeNovo C and Toal C (1990) Hiatal hernia in the dog and cat: a retrospective study of 16 cases.<italic> Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>31</bold>, 244&#x2013;250</p>
<p>Burnie AG, Simpson JW and Corcoran BM (1989) Gastro-oesophageal reflux and hiatus hernia associated with laryngeal paralysis in a dog. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>30</bold>, 414&#x2013;416</p>
<p>Caporn TM and Read RR (1996) Osteochondromatosis of the cervical spine causing compressive myelopathy in a dog. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>37</bold>, 133&#x2013;137</p>
<p>Dennis R (1993) Radiographic diagnosis of rib lesions in dogs and cats. <italic>Veterinary Annual</italic> <bold>33</bold>, 173&#x2013;192</p>
<p>Feeney DA, Johnston GR, Grindem CB<italic> et al</italic>. (1982) Malignant neoplasia of canine ribs: clinical, radiographic and pathologic findings. <italic>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</italic> <bold>180</bold>, 927&#x2013;933</p>
<p>Forrest LJ and Thrall DE (1994) Bone scintigraphy for metastasis detection in canine osteosarcoma. <italic>Veterinary Radiology and Ultrasound</italic> <bold>35</bold>, 124&#x2013;130</p>
<p>Fossum TW, Boudrieau RJ and Hobson PH (1989) Pectus excavatum in eight dogs and six cats. <italic>Journal of the American Animal Hospital Association</italic> <bold>25</bold>, 595&#x2013;605</p>
<p>Fowler JD (1998) Thoracic cage defects. In: <italic>BSAVA Manual of Small Animal Cardiorespiratory Medicine and Surgery</italic>, ed. V Luis Fuentes and S Swift, pp. 353&#x2013;358. BSAVA Publications, Gloucester</p>
<p>Grandage J (1974) The radiology of the dog&#x2019;s diaphragm. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>15</bold>, 1&#x2013;17</p>
<p>Hammer AS, Weeren FR, Weisbrode SE and Padgett SL (1995) Prognostic factors in dogs with osteosarcomas of the flat or irregular bones. <italic>Journal of the American Animal Hospital Association</italic> <bold>31</bold>, 321&#x2013;326</p>
<p>Hardie EM, Clary EM, Kornegay JN<italic> et al</italic>. (1998) Abnormalities of the thoracic bellows: stress fractures of the ribs and hiatal hernia. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine</italic> <bold>12</bold>, 279&#x2013;287</p>
<p>Heyman SJ, Diefenderfer DL, Goldschmidt MH and Newton CD (1992) Canine axial skeletal osteosarcoma. A retrospective study of 116 cases (1986&#x2013;1989). <italic>Veterinary Surgery</italic> <bold>21</bold>, 304&#x2013;310</p>
<p>Hornyak L (1999) Malformation of the processus xiphoideus in two breed cats. <italic>Kleintierpraxis</italic> <bold>44</bold>, 373&#x2013;378</p>
<p>Jankowski MK, Steyn PF, Lana SE<italic> et al</italic>. (2003) Nuclear scanning with 99mTc-HDP for the initial evaluation of osseous metastasis in canine osteosarcoma. <italic>Veterinary and Comparative Oncology</italic> <bold>1</bold>, 152&#x2013;158</p>
<p>Kraje BJ, Kraje AC, Rohrbach BW<italic> et al</italic>. (2000) Intrathoracic and concurrent orthopedic injury associated with traumatic rib fracture in cats: 75 cases (1980&#x2013;1998). <italic>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</italic> <bold>216</bold>, 51&#x2013;54</p>
<p>Kramers P, Fl&#x00FC;ckiger MA, Rahn BA and Cordey J (1988) Osteopetrosis in cats. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>29</bold>, 153&#x2013;164</p>
<p>Lamb CR (2004) Radiology corner: loss of the diaphragmatic line as a sign of ruptured diaphragm. <italic>Veterinary Radiology and Ultrasound</italic> <bold>45</bold>, 305&#x2013;306</p>
<p>Langley-Hobbs SJ, Carmichael S, Lamb CR, Bjornson AP and Day MJ (1997) Polyostotic lymphoma in a young dog: a case report and literature review. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>38</bold>, 412&#x2013;416</p>
<p>Morgan JP and Stavenborn M (1991) Disseminated idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) in a dog. <italic>Veterinary Radiology</italic> <bold>32</bold>, 65&#x2013;70</p>
<p>Pirkey-Ehrhart N, Withrow SJ, Straw RC<italic> et al</italic>. (1995) Primary rib tumors in 54 dogs.<italic> Journal of the American Animal Hospital Association</italic> <bold>31</bold>, 65&#x2013;69</p>
<p>Pratschke KM, Hughes JML, Skelly C and Bellenger CR (1998) Hiatal herniation as a complication of chronic diaphragmatic herniation. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>39</bold>, 33&#x2013;38</p>
<p>Spattini G, Rossi F, Vignoli M and Lamb CR (2003) Use of ultrasound to diagnose diaphragmatic rupture in dogs and cats. <italic>Veterinary Radiology and Ultrasound</italic> <bold>44</bold>, 226&#x2013;230</p>
<p>Stickle RL (1984) Positive-contrast celiography (peritoneography) for the diagnosis of diaphragmatic hernia in dogs and cats. <italic>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</italic> <bold>185</bold>, 295&#x2013;298</p>
<p>St&#x00F6;rk CK, Hamaide AJ, Schwedes C<italic> et al</italic>. (2003) Hemiurothorax following diaphragmatic hernia and kidney prolapse in a cat. <italic>Journal of Feline Medicine and Surgery</italic> <bold>5</bold>, 91&#x2013;96</p>
<p>Sullivan M and Lee R (1989) Radiological features of 80 cases of diaphragmatic rupture. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>30</bold>, 561&#x2013;566</p>
<p>Suter PF (1984) Chapter 1 &#x2013; Normal radiographic anatomy and radiographic examination; Chapter 5 &#x2013; Lesions of the thoracic wall, extrapleural diseases; Chapter 6 &#x2013; Abnormalities of the diaphragm. In: <italic>Thoracic Radiography. A Text Atlas of Thoracic Diseases of the Dog and Cat</italic>, ed. PF Suter, pp. 1&#x2013;45; 161&#x2013;177; 179&#x2013;204. Peter F. Suter, Wettswill, Switzerland</p>
<p>The Veterinary Cooperative Oncology Group (1993) Retrospective Study of 26 Primary Tumors of the Osseous Thoracic Wall in Dogs. <italic>Journal of the American Animal Hospital Association</italic> <bold>29</bold>, 68&#x2013;72</p>
<p>Vignoli M, Toniato M, Rossi F<italic> et al</italic>. (2002)Transient post-traumatic hemidiaphragmatic paralysis in two cats. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>39</bold>, 312&#x2013;316</p>
<p>Vincent-Johnson NA (2003) American canine hepatozoonosis. <italic>Veterinary Clinics of North America: Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>33</bold>, 905&#x2013;920</p>
<p>Vollmerhaus B, Roos H, Matis U, Veith G and Tassani-Prell M (1999) The specific anatomy and function of the thorax of the domestic cat. <italic>Tier&#x00E4;rztliche Praxis K</italic> <bold>27</bold>, 365&#x2013;370</p>
<p>Appendix 1</p>
<p><CHT>M-mode echocardiography reference values for cats</CHT></p>
<p><CA><bold>Joanna Dukes-McEwan</bold></CA></p>
<p>References and further reading</p>
<p>Allen DG (1982) Echocardiographic study of the anaesthetised cat. <italic>Canadian Journal of Comparative Medicine<bold></italic> 46<italic></bold></italic>, 115&#x2013;122</p>
<p>Allen DG and Downey RS (1985) Echocardiographic assessment of cats anaesthetized with xylazine &#x2013; sodium pentobarbital. <italic>Canadian Journal of Comparative Medicine</italic> <bold>47</bold>, 281&#x2013;283</p>
<p>Boon JA (1998) Appendix IV. In: <italic>Manual of Veterinary Echocardiography</italic>, ed. JA Boon, pp. 456&#x2013;457. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, Philadelphia</p>
<p>Drourr L, Lefbom BK, Rosenthal SL and Tyrrell WD (2005) Measurement of M-mode echocardiographic parameters in healthy adult Maine coon cats. <italic>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</italic> <bold>226</bold>, 734&#x2013;737</p>
<p>Fox PR, Bond BR and Peterson ME (1985) Echocardiographic reference values in healthy cats sedated with ketamine hydrochloride. <italic>American Journal of Veterinary Research</italic> <bold>46, </bold>1479&#x2013;1484</p>
<p>Jacobs G and Knight DH (1985) M-mode echocardiographic measurements in non-anaesthetised healthy cats: Effects of body weight, heart rate and other variables. <italic>American Journal of Veterinary Research</italic> <bold>46</bold>, 1705&#x2013;1711</p>
<p>Moise NS, Dietz AE, Mezza LE <italic>et al.</italic> (1986) Echocardiography, electrocardiography and radiography of cats with dilation cardiomyopathy, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy and hyperthyroidism. <italic>American Journal of Veterinary Research</italic> <bold>47</bold>, 1476&#x2013;1486</p>
<p>Pipers FS, Reef V and Hamlin RL (1979) Echocardiography in the domestic cat. <italic>American Journal of Veterinary Research</italic> <bold>40, </bold>882&#x2013;886</p>
<p>Sisson DD, Knight DH, Helinski C <italic>et al.</italic> (1991) Plasma taurine concentrations and M-mode echocardiographic measures in healthy cats and cats with dilated cardiomyopathy. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine</italic> <bold>5,</bold> 232&#x2013;238</p>
<p>Appendix 2</p>
<p><CHT>M-mode echocardiography reference values for dogs</CHT></p>
<p><CA><bold>Joanna Dukes-McEwan</bold></CA></p>
<p>References and further reading</p>
<p>Atkins CE and Snyder PS (1992) Systolic time intervals and their derivatives for evaluation of cardiac function. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine</italic> <bold>6</bold>, 55&#x2013;63</p>
<p>Bavegems V, Duchateau L, Sys SU and De Rick A (2007) Echocardiographic reference values in whippets. <italic>Veterinary Radiology and Ultrasound</italic> <bold>48</bold>, 230&#x2013;238</p>
<p>Bodey AR (1998) A study of the relationship between blood pressure and echocardiographic measurements of the left ventricular dimensions in Scottish Deerhounds. <italic>Congress Proceedings of the British Small Animal Association</italic>, p. 248</p>
<p>Bonagura JD, O&#x2019;Grady MR and Herring DS (1985) Echocardiography: principles of interpretation. <italic>Veterinary Clinics of North America: Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>15,</bold> 1177&#x2013;1194</p>
<p>Boon J, Wingfield WE and Miller CW (1983) Echocardiographic indices in the normal dog. <italic>Veterinary Radiology</italic> <bold>24</bold>, 214&#x2013;221</p>
<p>Borgarelli M, Tarducci A, Bussadori C and Ru G (1996) Echocardiographic and Echo-Doppler parameters in normal Great Danes. <italic>European Society of Veterinary Cardiology Newsletter</italic> <bold>10</bold>, 27&#x2013;28</p>
<p>Calvert CA (1995) Diagnosis and management of ventricular tachyarrhythmias in Dobermann Pinschers with cardiomyopathy. In: <italic>Kirk&#x2019;s Current Veterinary Therapy. Small Animal Practice XII,</italic> ed. JD Bonagura, pp. 799&#x2013;806. WB Saunders, Philadelphia</p>
<p>Calvert CA and Brown J (1986) Use of M-mode echocardiography in the diagnosis of congestive cardiomyopathy in Dobermann Pinschers. <italic>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</italic> <bold>189,</bold> 293&#x2013;297</p>
<p>Calvert CA, Chapman WL and Toal RL (1982) Congestive cardiomyopathy in Dobermann Pinscher dogs. <italic>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</italic> <bold>181</bold>, 598&#x2013;602</p>
<p>Calvert CA, Hall G, Jacobs G and Pickus C (1997) Clinical and pathologic findings in Dobermann Pinschers with occult cardiomyopathy that died suddenly or developed congestive heart failure: 54 cases (1984&#x2013;1991). <italic>Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association</italic> <bold>210</bold>, 505&#x2013;511</p>
<p>Crippa L, Ferro E, Melloni E, Brambilla P and Cavalletti E (1992) Echocardiographic parameters and indices in the normal Beagle dog. <italic>Laboratory Animals</italic> <bold>26</bold>, 190&#x2013;195</p>
<p>Della Torre PK, Kirby AC, Church DB and Malik R (2000) Echocardiographic measurements in Greyhounds, Whippets and Italian Greyhounds &#x2013; dogs with similar conformation but different size. <italic>Australian Veterinary Journal</italic> <bold>78(1),</bold> 49&#x2013;55</p>
<p>de Madron E (1996) M-mode echocardiographic values in the dog. A review of the recent literature. <italic>European Society of Veterinary Cardiology Newsletter: June 1996</italic> <bold>9, </bold>10&#x2013;16</p>
<p>Dukes-McEwan J (1999) Echocardiographic criteria of normality, the findings in cardiac disease and the genetics of familial dilated cardiomyopathy in Newfoundland dogs. University of Edinburgh, pp. 108&#x2013;122. PhD thesis</p>
<p>Gooding JP, Robinson WF and Mews GC (1986) Echocardiographic characterization of a dilatation cardiomyopathy in the English Cocker Spaniel. <italic>American Journal of Veterinary Research</italic> <bold>47(9), </bold>1978&#x2013;1983</p>
<p>Gooding JP, Robinson WF, Wyburn RS and Cullen LK (1982) A cardiomyopathy in the English Cocker Spaniel: a clinico-pathological investigation. <italic>Journal of Small Animal Practice</italic> <bold>23</bold>, 133&#x2013;149</p>
<p>H&#x00E4;ggstr&#x00F6;m J, Hansson KM, Kvart C, Pedersen HD, Vuolteenaho O and Olsson K (2000) Relationship between different natriuretic peptides and severity of naturally acquired mitral regurgitation in dogs with chronic myxomatous valve disease. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Cardiology<bold></italic> 2,<italic></bold></italic> 7&#x2013;16</p>
<p>Herrtage ME (1994) Echocardiographic measurements in the normal Boxer. <italic>Proceedings of the European Society of Veterinary Internal Medicine 4th Annual Congress, Brussels, Belgium</italic> pp. 172&#x2013;173</p>
<p>Jacobs G and Mahjoob K (1988) Multiple regression analysis, using body size and cardiac cycle length, in predicting echocardiographic variables in dogs. <italic>American Journal of Veterinary Research</italic> <bold>49</bold>, 1290&#x2013;1294</p>
<p>Kayar A, Gonul R, Or ME and Uysal A (2006) M-mode echocardiographic parameters and indices in the normal German Shepherd Dog. <italic>Veterinary Radiology and Ultrasound</italic> <bold>47</bold>, 482&#x2013;486</p>
<p>Kayar A and Uysal A (2004) Determination of cardiac reference parameters using M-mode and 2-D echocardiographic techniques in adult Karabash dogs. <italic>Turkish Journal of Veterinary Animal Science</italic> <bold>28</bold>, 39&#x2013;46</p>
<p>Koch J, Pedersen HD, Jensen AL and Flagstad A (1996) M-mode echocardiographic diagnosis of dilated cardiomyopathy in giant breed dogs. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Medicine</italic> <bold>43,</bold> 297&#x2013;304</p>
<p>Lobo L, Canada N, Bussadori C, Gomes JL and Carvalheira J (2007) Transthoracic echocardiography in Estrela Mountain Dogs: reference values for the breed. <italic>The Veterinary Journal</italic> doi:10.1016/j.tvjl.2007.03.024</p>
<p>Lombard CW (1984) Normal values of the canine M-mode echocardiogram. <italic>American Journal of Veterinary Research</italic> <bold>45</bold>, 2015&#x2013;2018</p>
<p>Lusk RH and Ettinger SJ (1990) Echocardiographic techniques in the dog and cat. <italic>Journal of the American Animal Hospital Association</italic> <bold>26</bold>, 473&#x2013;488</p>
<p>Mashiro I, Nelson RR, Cohn JN and Franciosa JA (1976) Ventricular dimensions measured non-invasively by echocardiography in the awake dog. <italic>Journal of Applied Physiology</italic> <bold>41</bold>, 953&#x2013;959</p>
<p>Miller et al (1989) &#x2013; au: please provide full reference</p>
<p>Morrison SA, Moise NS, Scarlett J, Mohammed H and Yaeger AE (1992) Effect of breed and body weight on echocardiographic values in four breeds of dogs of differing somatotype. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine</italic> <bold>6,</bold> 220&#x2013;224</p>
<p>Muzzi RAL, Muzzi LAL, De Ara&#x00FA;jo RB and Cherem M (2006) Echocardiographic indices in normal German Shepherd Dogs. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Science</italic> <bold>7(2),</bold> 193&#x2013;198</p>
<p>O&#x2019;Grady (2006) ranges for LVIDd and LVIDs in Dobermanns. <italic>Protocol for Investigators on PROTECT study</italic>, p. 22. Boehringer Ingelheim Vetmedica</p>
<p>O&#x2019;Grady MR and Horne R (1995) Occult dilated cardiomyopathy in the Dobermann Pinscher. <italic>Proceedings of the 13th ACVIM Forum</italic>, pp. 298&#x2013;299</p>
<p>O&#x2019;Leary CA, Mackay BM and Atwell RB (2003) Echocardiographic parameters in 14 healthy English Bull Terriers. <italic>Australian Veterinary Journal</italic> <bold>81(9),</bold> 535&#x2013;542</p>
<p>Page A, Edmunds G and Atwell RB (1993) Echocardiographic values in the greyhound. <italic>Australian Veterinary Journal<bold></italic> 70,<italic></bold></italic> 361&#x2013;364</p>
<p>Pietra M, Guglielmini C and Cipone M (1998) Normal M-mode and Doppler echocardiographic values in English setter. <italic>European Society of Veterinary Cardiology Newsletter</italic> <bold>16,</bold> 8&#x2013;14</p>
<p>Pipers FS, Andrysco RM and Hamlin RL (1978) A totally non-invasive method for obtaining systolic time intervals in the dog. <italic>American Journal of Veterinary Research</italic> <bold>39,</bold> 1822&#x2013;1826</p>
<p>Schober KE and Luis Fuentes V (2002) Doppler echocardiographic assessment of left ventricular diastolic function in 74 Boxer dogs with aortic stenosis. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Cardiology</italic> <bold>4, </bold>7&#x2013;16</p>
<p>Snyder PS, Sato T and Atkins CE (1995) A comparison of echocardiographic indices of the non-racing healthy greyhound to reference values from other breeds. <italic>Veterinary Radiology and Ultrasound</italic> <bold>36,</bold> 387&#x2013;392</p>
<p>Sottiaux J and Amberger C (1997) Normal echocardiographic values in the Dobermann Pinscher (French breeding). <italic>European Society of Veterinary Cardiology Newsletter,</italic> <bold>12,</bold> 8</p>
<p>Tarducci A, Borgarelli M, Bussadori C, D&#x2019;Angelo A, Ru G and Dotta U (1997) Valori echocardiografica negli alani normali. <italic>ATTI della societa italiana delle scienze veterinarie.</italic> LI, Bologna. <bold>17(20),</bold> 593&#x2013;594</p>
<p>Tidholm A and J&#x00F6;nsson L (1996) Dilated cardiomyopathy in the Newfoundland: a study of 37 cases (1983&#x2013;1994). <italic>Journal of the American Animal Hospital Association</italic> <bold>32,</bold> 465&#x2013;470</p>
<p>Vollmar A (1996) Kardiologische Untersuchungen beim Irischen Wolfshund unter besonderer Ber&#x00FC;cksichtigung des Vorhofflimmerns und der Echokardiographie. <italic>Kleintierpraxis</italic> <bold>41</bold>, 397&#x2013;408</p>
<p>Vollmar A (1998) Kardiologische Untersuchungen beim Deerhound, Referenzwerte f&#x00FC;r die Echodiagnostik. <italic>Kleintierpraxis</italic> <bold>43</bold>, 497&#x2013;508</p>
<p>Appendix 3</p>
<p><CHT>Conversion tables</CHT></p>
<p>Appendix 4</p>
<p><CHT>Differential diagnoses for thoracic mineralization</CHT></p>
<p><CA><bold>Tobias Schwarz</bold></CA></p>
<p>