<p><bold>thisissue</bold></p>
<p><bold>Advertise </bold>Open Box, 0121 200 7820, sales&#x0040;ob-mc.co.uk <bold>Subscribe </bold>www.rcseng.ac.uk/publications/subscriptions <bold>Submit </bold>www.rcseng.ac.uk/publications/submissions <bold>Contact </bold>bulletin&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk, 020 7869 6164</p>
<p>This issue looks at the fallout from the general election and the Paterson verdict, and what Brexit means for medical devices.</p>
<p><italic><bold>At the front</bold></italic></p>
<p>240	<bold>Editorial: </bold>June almost marks the end of May</p>
<p><italic>David Sanders</italic></p>
<p>241	<bold>From the President: </bold>Facing a challenging future</p>
<p><italic>Clare Marx, RCS President</italic></p>
<p>242	<bold>Bites: </bold>Nuggets of surgical news</p>
<p>244	<bold>From Westminster:</bold></p>
<p>Making the NHS a priority out of a hung parliament <italic>Will Culliford</italic></p>
<p>245	What could the DUP alliance mean for health?</p>
<p><italic>Susan Kelly </italic>248 Letters to the Editor</p>
<p><italic><bold>Features</bold></italic></p>
<p>250 Medical device use post Brexit:</p>
<p>should we be concerned?</p>
<p><italic>K Keogh and G McConaghie </italic>252 Implications of the Ian Paterson</p>
<p>case for the private hospital sector</p>
<p><italic>Colin Leys </italic>255 Medical Women: Perspectives from</p>
<p>the Victorian medical profession</p>
<p><italic>Alison Moulds </italic>258 RCS Current Awareness Updates</p>
<p><italic>Amy McEwan </italic>260 Improving communication in</p>
<p>recruitment consultations for</p>
<p>randomised controlled trials</p>
<p><italic>Joshua R Burke, James Glasbey,</italic></p>
<p><italic>Dmitri Nepogodiev et al </italic>264 Te extended surgical team</p>
<p><italic>Johnny Matthews</italic></p>
<p><italic><bold>Research</bold></italic></p>
<p>268 Te study of art and its infuence on the education of surgeons <italic>AV Sterpetti and M Ventura</italic></p>
<p>276 Re-evaluation of three-session theatre efciency <italic>AS Nadig, ID Kamaly-Asl</italic></p>
<p>278 Emergency laparotomy, the ELC and quality improvement <italic>G Aggarwal and N Quiney</italic></p>
<p><italic><bold>At the back</bold></italic></p>
<p>281	<bold>Cross-examination: </bold>Consent for a cannula <italic>Robert Wheeler</italic></p>
<p>282	<bold>Crossword </bold><italic>Escort</italic></p>
<p>283	<bold>Mr Slop </bold>and decrepitude</p>
<p>284	</p>
<p><bold>Article key</bold></p>
<p><bold>t*	</bold>Articles that carry the</p>
<p><bold>tEKCa </bold>RCS logo at the top of the</p>
<p>page are written in &#x2018;the voice of the College&#x2019; and articulate the views and policy of the RCS.</p>
<p><bold>PeerRev </bold>Articles that carry the</p>
<p>&#x2018;PeerRev&#x2019; logo have been peer</p>
<p>reviewed by our panel of surgeons.</p>
<p>/X	MIX</p>
<p>\f 1 <italic>fj	</italic>Paper from</p>
<p>^	responsible sources</p>
<p>J&#x00DC;&#x00DC;s&#x00FC;&#x00DC;	FSC&#x201D; C013436</p>
<p><bold>Editor-in-Chief </bold>Professor Neil Mortensen <bold>Editor </bold>David Sanders <bold>Associate Editor </bold>Matthew Whitaker <bold>Technology Editor </bold>Greg McConaghie</p>
<p><bold>Political Editor </bold>Patrick Leahy <bold>Contributing Editor </bold>Jyoti Shah <bold>Trainees&#x2019; Forum Editor </bold>Kenneth Keogh</p>
<p><bold>Production Manager </bold>Kim Lewry <bold>Production Editor </bold>Vivienne Button <BOLD>ISSN </BOLD>1473-6357</p>
<p><bold>Published by </bold>The Royal College of Surgeons of England. Registered charity 212808. <bold>Printed by </bold>Latimer Trend, Plymouth, UK. Printed on FSC Accredited paper.</p>
<p><bold>239</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>EDITORIAL</BOLD></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.240</p>
<p><italic>June almost marks the end of May</italic></p>
<p>How healthcare stands to fare following the results of the surprise general election and the Paterson trial.</p>
<p><bold>David Sanders, Editor</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>F</BOLD></p>
<p>rench elections, FBI sackings, a general election and another month of political turmoil. For the third time in three years a UK national vote delivered a verdict that almost no one predicted, and we find ourselves scurrying to adapt to yet another new political landscape. At the time of going to press, even Tim Shipman&#x2019;s modern political truism that all UK general elections end with Nigel Farage resigning or being appointed leader of UKIP &#x2013; and sometimes both &#x2013; has yet to be reconfirmed.</p>
<p>Who do you vote for when there is no one worth voting for? Like many, I voted for what I believed was the lesser of two evils rather than for a party that I actually liked. Public service cuts and austerity measures were on the minds of voters fed up of underfunding, fudged statistics and the status quo. The Conservative government ran a presidential-style campaign that didn&#x2019;t address these concerns sufficiently. Labour&#x2019;s manifesto proposed increased funding to the health service as well as renationalisation of rail and utilities, which appears to have appealed to voters prepared to overlook claims of fiscal irresponsibility, radical socialism and the economic turmoil predicted by increased taxation on businesses and those with assets. The result: an election in which there seemed to be no real winners.</p>
<p>Although Labour&#x2019;s performance exceeded expectations, one could make the case that the biggest losers are the members of the Parliamentary Labour Party, who are now left with a leader who is effectively unsackable but in whom many of them have little confidence. The Prime Minister&#x2019;s political career is hanging by a thread after</p>
<p><bold>240</bold></p>
<p>she promised to offer certainty for Britain but instead delivered even more uncertainty when her election gamble backfired. In all this chaos, it is difficult to see there being any room for an adult debate on the proper funding of healthcare in the coming months.</p>
<p>The horrendous attacks in Manchester and London highlighted the exceptional work of the police and emergency response teams. NHS staff, in particular, won widespread praise for their dedication. After both the London Bridge and Manchester concert attacks, hospitals ended up turning away doctors, nurses and other staff who were volunteering to come in. Many of these staff have been subject to a 1&#x0025; pay freeze since 2012 &#x2013; a subject that barely gained any traction in the campaign but that continues to rankle with health workers. Once the turmoil of the election has calmed down, we must hope that addressing the issue of morale in the NHS is on the to-do list for the government, alongside the more tangible issues such as tackling bed-blocking caused by lack of social care provision.</p>
<p>Outside our domestic bubble the tides of history continue to rise and fall, indifferent to our problems. We are now left with a hung parliament and only a couple of weeks before the Brexit negotiations start. And the EU2 7, having accepted Britain is leaving, is now holding the door open and glancing politely at its watch. With only 19 months remaining to prepare for a post-EU future, UK industries are facing a race against time to establish new regulatory frameworks and trading arrangements. On page 214 we place the microscope over just one of these industries</p>
<p>to examine exactly what the implications of leaving the single market are likely to be for medical device regulation.</p>
<p>The conviction of Ian Paterson has put the issue of patient safety in private hospitals back on the agenda &#x2013; see our analysis on page 252. We will be discussing this issue further in future issues. Following our guide to building a randomised control trial in the June 2017 issue, Josh Burke and his colleagues from STARSurg provide some more in-depth advice about the difficult art of recruiting patients to trials on page 260. And for the first time, we are running a prize crossword. Turn to page 272 to see if you can fathom the workings of our setter Escor t &#x2018;s mind .</p>
<p><bold>Happy birthday to the <italic>Annals</italic></bold></p>
<p>July 2017 marks 70 years since the publication of first issue of the <italic>Annals</italic>. To celebrate the occasion we are republishing the whole of that first issue in full (http:// publishing.rcseng.ac.uk/ toc/ann/1/1), and you can read commentaries on some of those articles &#x2013; as well as an editorial from Tim Lane &#x2013; in the current issue: http://publish-ing.rcseng.ac.uk/toc/ann/current.</p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.241</p>
<p>ttRCS <BOLD>FROM THE PRESIDEN T</BOLD></p>
<p><italic>Facing a challenging future</italic></p>
<p>Our outgoing President&#x2019;s final thoughts on unprecedented national events.</p>
<p><bold>Clare Marx, RCS President</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>O</BOLD></p>
<p>ur thoughts are with everyone affected by the awful incidents in Manchester and London; particularly with the families of those people, including children, who have tragically died or had their lives changed forever. I am enormously proud and grateful for the fantastic work of the emergency services and our NHS. I have heard of countless accounts of surgeons who pulled out all the stops to help, rescue and care for those in their immense need.</p>
<p><BOLD>IAN PATERSON</BOLD></p>
<p>We responded to the judgement and sentencing of Ian Paterson with sadness and revulsion. His wilful abuse of the trust put in him by patients and his appalling actions and behaviours have no doubt had an impact on the profession. We must do everything in our power to prevent such a violation being repeated. I had the opportunity to talk to the leader of the Paterson Patients&#x2019; Action Group about their experiences and perspective. They are justifiably angry and aggrieved. The impact on that group of individuals has in some cases been life-changing. We will be working with the next government and other surgical colleges to consider what can be learnt, and what may need to change in the NHS. We have also called for the incoming government to review how safety standards and data transparency in the private sector can be improved in line with similar patient safety initiatives that have concentrated in the NHS.</p>
<p>Can I remind everyone of the RCS&#x2019; good practice guidance on consent, duty of candour, and morbidity and mortality meetings. All are freely available on the RCS website at: https://www.rcseng.ac.uk/stand-ards-and-research/standards-and-guidance/ good-practice-guides/</p>
<p><BOLD>GENERAL ELECTION</BOLD></p>
<p>At the time of writing, we are in the midst of the election campaign, with polls predicting an uncertain outcome.</p>
<p>During the campaign, the RCS has continued to raise the profile of our priority issues and strengthen our position as a respected commentator on the NHS more widely. We have focused on access to surgery, NHS and social care funding, the impact of Brexit and professional regulation. Since the election was called in April, we have spoken of our new analysis showing increasing six- and nine-month waiting times, and have made statements on record bed occupancy rates and delayed discharges.</p>
<p>We have also provided members with regular updates during the election period through our political update each Friday. In addition, we published articles on the election in recent editions of the <italic>Bulletin</italic>.</p>
<p>We will now act quickly to influence the new government to highlight our priority issues. Making the voice of the surgical community heard is going to be particularly important in the funding-restricted environment that is likely whatever the nature of the next government.</p>
<p><bold>LINCOLN&#x2019;S INN FIELDS BUILDINGS</bold></p>
<p>With the final pieces of the puzzle falling into place for the redevelopment of our buildings at Lincoln&#x2019;s Inn Fields, I have been delighted to begin the fundraising for the project.</p>
<p>I have met with a number of longstanding donors to the RCS and have been pleased by their support and enthusiasm for transforming our headquarters to have a building fit for purpose and sustainable for many years to come. It is with pleasure that I am able to share with you the news that we have had</p>
<p>formal pledges of support to date of more than &#x00A3;1.5 million.</p>
<p>I will be approaching you all on behalf of the incoming President Derek Alderson to enlist your help in raising funds towards this ambitious project and to ask you for financial and practical support. If you would like to be involved or have contacts or ideas then please do get in touch at president&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk</p>
<p>As always, the latest information on the project and our services during the building programme is available on the website at: https://www.rcseng.ac.uk/about-the-rcs/ future-of-lincolns-inn-fields-buildings/</p>
<p><BOLD>HANDOVER</BOLD></p>
<p>As I recounted in my first newsletter in September 2014, my first day as President started on the <italic>To d a y </italic>programme talking about waiting lists, gallbladders and the pivotal role surgeons want to play in the challenges facing surgical services. As I step down, I can report that the RCS remains in the headlines and continues to influence decision-makers. As I write, I have just completed another <italic>To d a y </italic>programme interview in which I highlighted the increasing number of patients waiting longer to access surgical care in a timely manner.</p>
<p>It has been a privilege and an honour to be able to lead the RCS and the profession for the past three years. The task would be impossible without the support of the officers, members of Council and the RCS staff. The feedback I have received from you through events, meetings, emails and phone calls has been invaluable and helped shape the way we have responded and reflected your concerns. I am pleased to be leaving the RCS in the more than capable hands of Derek Alderson to take forward our mission to &#x2018;advance surgical care&#x2019;.</p>
<p><bold>241</bold></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.242</p>
<p><bold>Equality and diversity considerations in surgical curriculum revision</bold></p>
<p>In August 2015 the General Medical Council (GMC) announced new regulations that made it obligatory to address equality and diversity considerations before any curriculum revisions are made. Curriculum revisions must now include evidence that people who share protected characteristics (Age, Disability, Gender Reassignment/Variance, Marriage and Civil Partnership, Pregnancy and Maternity, Race and Ethnicity, Religion and Belief, Sex, and Sexual Orientation) will not suffer any discrimination as a result of the change unless</p>
<p>patient safety requirements dictate that the change must be made.</p>
<p>It became apparent that assistance for this would need to be given to all Specialty Advisory Committee (SAC) Chairs and Editors, as well as anyone else involved in surgical curriculum revision. The full article reports on the development of that assistance process. In particular, the article reports on the steps involved in the collection of opinion and advice from leaders of bodies representing those who share protected characteristics. Some unexpected findings became apparent. Recommendations to all curriculum writers were then given as part of the assistance process and are included in the full article.</p>
<p><bold>New: Postgraduate Certifcate in Surgery</bold></p>
<p>The PGCert in Surgery is our new, flexible and interactive way to build up invaluable surgical knowledge and skills. As our first completely online course, the PGCert in Surgery will allow you to demonstrate your commitment to surgery and will support your career development.</p>
<p>If you are a foundation level or core trainee, looking to tailor a programme to your interests and study at your own pace, then the PGCert in Surgery is ideal. The PGCert in Surgery is great preparation for the MRCS exam, and will enhance your application for specialty selection.</p>
<p>Once enrolled, you will have up to 2 years to accrue the 60 credits needed to complete the PGCert in Surgery. Completing other RCS courses may also count towards your credits. Are you an RCS member? You will receive &#x00A3;40 off your enrolment fee.</p>
<p>Enhance your surgical career, by enrolling online today: https://goo.gl/aKEJEH</p>
<p><bold>Council noted with regret the deaths of the following fellows and members of the College</bold></p>
<p>BAHL, Baldev Raj, of Eastbourne. FRCS 1960</p>
<p>BREWER, Arthur Clifford, of Fareham. FRCS 1938</p>
<p>BUCHOLZ, Robert, of Irving Texas, United States of America. FRCS (Honorary) 2004</p>
<p>HAMILTON, John William, of Kloof, South Africa. FRCS 1967</p>
<p>LEVITT, Solomon, of WA, Australia. FRCS 1957</p>
<p>MARTIN, James Herbert Stephens, of VIC, Australia. FRCS 1961</p>
<p><italic>Plarr&#x2019;s Lives of the Fellows</italic></p>
<p>is a biographical register of the fellows of The Royal College of</p>
<p>Surgeons of England. It can be accessed online at:</p>
<p>http://livesonline.rcseng.ac.uk/.</p>
<p>If you are interested in writing a fellow&#x2019;s obituary, please email lives&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk.</p>
<p>To report a death, please email membership&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk.</p>
<p><bold>242</bold></p>
<p><bold>Join the conversation</bold></p>
<p>Follow &#x0040;RCSNews on Twitter to get</p>
<p>up-to-date NHS, medical, surgical and</p>
<p>professional news from The Royal</p>
<p>College of Surgeons of England -</p>
<p>setting standards for the highest quality</p>
<p>of surgical care for patients.</p>
<p><BOLD>POLITICS</BOLD></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.244</p>
<p><italic>Jrom </italic>Westminster</p>
<p>Making the NHS a priority out of a hung parliament</p>
<p>Will Culliford RCS Policy and Public Affairs Manager</p>
<p><BOLD>D</BOLD></p>
<p>espite polls and pundits predicting a comfortable majority, in the end the Conservatives lost 13 seats and ended on 318 MPs &#x2013; 8 short of an overall majority. This has left Theresa May under intense pressure from the media, her own party colleagues, and an emboldened Labour opposition. Under Jeremy Corbyn, Labour finished the night with an additional 30 MPs, with post-election polls even putting them ahead for the first time since Corbyn became leader. So what are the implications for the NHS?</p>
<p>Theresa May&#x2019;s failure to secure a majority has left her seeking an alliance with the Democratic Unionist Party, while attempting to maintain the status quo as far as possible. This has resulted in Jeremy Hunt being re-appointed, leaving him on track to overtake Norman Fowler&#x2019;s record of 5 years and 272 days as the longest-serving Health Secretary. Although Hunt&#x2019;s reappointment will be met with continued opposition from many in the health service and beyond, he does offer a sense of stability during uncertain political times. We know about his priorities and at least his return to Richmond House will provide NHS England with the opportunity to resume normal service.</p>
<p>The current state of our Parliament will of course have far-reaching consequences for the NHS though. The election has already caused unhelpful delays and distractions for</p>
<p><bold>244</bold></p>
<p>the health service. A clear majority would have made it much easier to pass legislation too. The Conservatives rightly pledged in their manifesto to legislate to reform and rationalise the &#x2018;current outdated system&#x2019; of professional regulation and ensure there is effective registration and regulation of those performing cosmetic interventions. This would be an important step forward for surgery. The RCS has been calling for regulation for physician associates and other members of the extended surgical team &#x2013; and until the election was called, we were expecting the government to consult on reforming the regulators. Although still likely to proceed, this will now be more difficult without a majority in Parliament, particularly given the tight timescales for introducing a comprehensive health bill.</p>
<p>The lack of a working majority is also likely to affect Conservative manifesto plans for social care. The controversial pledge captured the headlines during the campaign as Theresa May was forced to clarify that there would be a cap on total care costs to protect at-risk homeowners. Without a majority, the Prime Minister is unlikely to risk putting such a controversial policy forward, which is potentially bad news for the NHS. As the RCS and many other organisations across health and social care have been highlighting, social care needs addressing and there is a concern now that it will not receive</p>
<p>the attention it so desperately needs. The Conservatives were right to focus on social care in their manifesto and we must ensure it remains on the agenda.</p>
<p>On NHS spending more broadly, the Conservatives have pledged a minimum of &#x00A3;8 billion in real terms during the next 5 years, delivering an increase in real funding per head of the population for every year of the Parliament. This effectively extends the principle provided for in the 2015 spending review, to fund the Five Year Forward View, for an extra two years until 2022. How current spending is increased year by year is not stated, other than to promise real-terms growth per capita in NHS England budgets. However, the Nuffield Trust and Institute for Fiscal Studies have warned that the Conservative funding pledges &#x2013; like those made by Labour and the Liberal Democrats &#x2013; will not be enough. NHS Clinical Commissioners have already said this could result in access to routine care &#x2018;slowing down&#x2019; in a bid to contain costs. There were nearly 12 million operations done in 2016 &#x2013; more than ever before &#x2013; and the Conservatives have overseen a dramatic fall in the number of people waiting more than a year for treatment. However, new funding is still needed to improve access to elective care and the election result might actually help. The Prime Minister has reportedly already told colleagues &#x2018;austerity is over&#x2019; and her new Chief of Staff, the former</p>
<p><BOLD>POLITIC S</BOLD></p>
<p>Croydon Central MP Gavin Barwell, has admitted that Labour &#x2018;tapped into&#x2019; concerns about the public sector pay freeze. This could lead to a shift in direction.</p>
<p>One of the Conservative Party&#x2019;s biggest announcements for the NHS, which managed to slip under the media&#x2019;s radar, was the commitment to the &#x2018;biggest ever extension&#x2019; of capital funding in the NHS&#x2019; history. In an interview with the BBC&#x2019;s Andrew Neil, the Prime Minister confirmed that &#x00A3;10 billion would be made available. Capital investment in the NHS estate is something the RCS has long been calling for. Responsibility for the NHS estate was devolved as part of the measures introduced by the Lansley reforms, and spending on capital projects has continued to decrease since the 2015 spending review &#x2013; with funding redirected to minimise frontline service shortfalls. Sir Robert Naylor&#x2019;s review of NHS property and estates, published in March, raised the profile of this important issue. The Conservatives must now act on their promise and deliver the transformation needed. We will await further details of this in the autumn budget.</p>
<p>The fact the Conservatives have returned to government is also good news for</p>
<p>Sustainability and Transformation Plans (STPs), which faced an uncertain future under Labour. In the previous budget in early March &#x2013; which already seems like a political lifetime ago &#x2013; the government pledged &#x00A3;325 million in capital funding for the most advanced STPs, so this will move ahead as planned. The Conservatives will almost certainly proceed with the plans set out in the Five Year Forward View, which again provides continuity and is likely to mean Simon Stevens keeps his job at the top of NHS England. Further change would surely be considered too risky.</p>
<p>The future of EU staff working in the NHS was another contentious issue during the election campaign. Currently 20&#x0025; of surgeons working in the NHS trained in EU countries (excluding the UK) and there are more than 22,000 EU nurses and more than 27,000 other staff from the EU working in the NHS. The Conservatives have so far resisted calls to guarantee the rights of NHS workers after the UK leaves the EU, although they have now said they will &#x201C;make it a priority&#x201D; in negotiations with the EU. The pro-EU Damian Green has now been promoted to First Secretary of State as May&#x2019;s Deputy in all</p>
<p>but name. Yet it remains to be seen whether the Conservatives will shift their approach to Brexit and what this will mean for the thousands of EU nationals working in the health service.</p>
<p>Public concern about the NHS has risen sharply to its highest level in 15 years, with 61&#x0025; of Britons now considering the NHS to be one of the biggest issues facing Britain. Remarkably, this is the highest level of concern recorded since April 2002. Another poll in the days after the general election indicated that health was the single most important issue in deciding which way people voted. So although the focus may be on forming an alliance with the DUP and negotiating an exit from the EU, public scrutiny of the NHS will continue. The NHS is treating more patients than ever before, with activity increasing across the board, while key performance measures for hospital services are being missed on a regular basis.</p>
<p>The Prime Minister&#x2019;s next big challenge will be to enact her election mantra and strengthen and stabilise a health system buckling under financial pressures, record waiting times and declining staff morale.</p>
<p>What could the DUP alliance mean for health?</p>
<p>Susan Kelly RCS Policy and Public Affairs for Northern Ireland</p>
<p><BOLD>T</BOLD></p>
<p>hose of us who call Northern Ireland home may have been disappointed, but not shocked, to see a return to so-called &#x2018;tribal voting&#x2019; in the devolved nation after a rollercoaster year. But those responsible for maintaining the Democratic Unionist Party (DUP) website almost certainly had the biggest surprise of all: a website meltdown brought about by the highest volume of traffic ever witnessed, as a direct result of the hung parliament. So, who are the DUP, what have they said about health and social care and what can we expect from their negotiations with the Conservatives?</p>
<p>At Castle Buildings, Stormont, home to the Northern Ireland Assembly, the DUP have had a difficult year so far. Their leader and First Minister, Arlene Foster, has been mired in the Renewable Heat Incentive scandal and their local representatives are out of government owing to the subsequent collapse of the NI Assembly. But Theresa May&#x2019;s snap Westminster election has, like so much else, turned that on its head. Arlene Foster&#x2019;s party saw a resurgence in their popularity in the election and have returned 10 MPs to Westminster. Crucially, the Prime Minister is now reliant on the support of these MPs to</p>
<p>form a majority government, most likely via a &#x2018;supply and confidence&#x2019; arrangement. The full details will emerge in the coming weeks but for now the discussions are underway and no one should underestimate the negotiating skills of the DUP, forged in the crucible of successive power-sharing agreements and mandatory coalition government.</p>
<p>For those unfamiliar with the party, the DUP are highly socially conservative &#x2013; although from an economic perspective, they are pragmatic and populist in their approach. The DUP&#x2019;s likely demands won&#x2019;t be found in their 2017 general election manifes-</p>
<p><BOLD>POLITICS</BOLD></p>
<p>to &#x2013; which was written on the assumption of a Conservative majority &#x2013; but in their Northern Ireland Plan, which was drawn up in 2015 in preparation for a hung parliament. The NI Plan set out demands for an increased budget for Stormont, including a real-terms increase in health spending and a yearly commitment to &#x00A3;80 million additional funds to tackle waiting times, which are much higher than elsewhere in the UK.</p>
<p>Plans are underway to establish &#x2018;accountable care systems&#x2019; in Northern Ireland, similar to the current plan set out by NHS England, so any negotiating list is likely to revisit the 2015 pledges, seeking additional funds to bolster the costs of implementing the reform agenda. New concessions could include the extension of NI welfare reform mitigations, such as dropping the &#x2018;bedroom tax&#x2019;, to the wider UK and retaining the winter fuel allowance and triple lock on pensions. Brexit was not a consideration at the time the NI Plan was written, but it is likely to be the cornerstone of the negotiations.</p>
<p>As staunch advocates of Brexit during the EU referendum and despite Northern Ireland voting to remain in Europe (56&#x0025; voted remain with border areas most heavily in favour), the Party has continued to support the UK-wide result. It does, however, share</p>
<p>the concern that a hard border would be detrimental to the economic fortunes of Northern Ireland, particularly in terms of trade and travel. As a party that champions the union above all else, it is opposed to any internal UK borders, and so the idea of having a &#x2018;soft&#x2019; north/south border but controls at the east/west level (airports and ports) would be seen as anti-union and would therefore be unacceptable. So far, they have objected to calls for &#x2018;special status&#x2019; for Northern Ireland, against the wishes of some of the main NI political parties, the Irish government and EU member states, who are sympathetic to the proposal as they fear it risks the union. A &#x2018;softer Brexit&#x2019; to obtain cross-party consensus may work for both parties in their negotiations, although the long-term implications are hard to define at such an early stage.</p>
<p>With regard to the implications for health, Sinn Fein held this ministerial portfolio in the Northern Ireland Assembly prior to the collapse of power-sharing in January. The previous health minister took over at a critical time, setting out her vision for delivering on much-needed reforms identified in a series of reviews during the past few years. Her DUP predecessor, Simon Hamilton, oversaw part of the previous review and was instrumental in leading the reform agenda</p>
<p>that set the scene for the major policy paper, <italic>Health and Wellbeing 2026 &#x2013; Delivering Tog e t h e r</italic>. He also supported the introduction of much-needed &#x2018;all-island services&#x2019; such as the Paediatric Congenital Cardiac Service, and important cross-border services such as the Radiology Service based in the North West treating patients on both sides of the border. The Brexit implications for such cross-border services, including ENT and urology and for those who staff them, are yet to be determined.</p>
<p>The previous minister managed to achieve agreement on major structural and cultural change with her DUP partners in government, including the need to expand cross-border services. These plans now lie unimplemented, waiting for the conclusion of local talks aimed at restoring devolution, in turn delayed by the DUP&#x2019;s Westminster discussions.</p>
<p>The election delivered surprise results across the UK and catapulted the DUP into the national spotlight &#x2013; there may be many more surprises to come.</p>
<p><bold>Note: </bold>These articles were correct at time of going to press (14/06/2017).</p>
<p><bold>RCS Accreditation &#x2013; part 1</bold></p>
<p><italic>The providers listed below have been recognised by the RCS as conforming to their standards of surgical education and training. </italic>FORTHCOMING ACCREDITED CPD EVENTS	RECENTLY ACCREDITED UNIVERSITY PROGRAMMES RECENTLY ACCREDITED COURSES</p>
<p>&#x00BB; 19th Spinal Research Network Meeting International Spinal Research Trust <italic>1&#x2013;2 September 2017 London</italic></p>
<p>&#x00BB; PRESSURE Thoracic Trauma Course <italic>4&#x2013;5 December 2017 University Hospital Southampton</italic></p>
<p>&#x00BB; Master of Orthopaedic Surgery (MCh Orth) Programme and MSc in Orthopaedic Science (distance programme) <italic>University of Dundee</italic></p>
<p>RECENTLY ACCREDITED SURGICAL PROGRAMME PROVIDER</p>
<p>&#x00BB; The Egyptian Military Medical Academy (EMMA) programme <italic>Cairo, Egypt</italic></p>
<p>&#x00BB; UCLH Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy for Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma course &#x2013; part of the Headstart training programme <italic>University College London Hospital</italic></p>
<p>RCS Quality Assurance and Accreditation Department | The Royal College of Surgeons of England | 35&#x2013;43 Lincoln&#x2019;s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3PE t: 020 7869 6236 | e: qa&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk | For further information: www.rcseng.ac.uk/surgeons/training/accreditation</p>
<p><bold>246</bold></p>
<p>References: 1. In Use Surgical Gove Failure Rate Comparison. Study G009-005.2009. Data on fle. 2. MKT004. Why Choose Biogel. 2009. Data on fle</p>
<p>M&#x00F6;lnlycke Health Care Ltd, Unity House, Medlock Street,Oldam, OL1 3HS UK. Tel. 0800 731 1876 Email: info.uk&#x0040;molnlycke.com</p>
<p>The M&#x00F6;lnlycke Health Care and Biogel trademarks, names and logo types are registered globally to one</p>
<p>or more of the M&#x00F6;lnlycke Health Care Group of Companies. &#x00A9; 2017 M&#x00F6;lnlycke Health Care AB. All rights reserved. UKSU0069</p>
<p><BOLD>LETTERS</BOLD></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.248</p>
<p>Letters to the Editor</p>
<p><BOLD>THIS HOUSE BELIEVES THAT EMERGENCY SURGERY SHOULD BE A SPECIALTY IN ITS OWN RIGHT</BOLD></p>
<p>Sir,</p>
<p>Having recently attended the ASGBI meeting in Glasgow, I read this article with interest <italic>(This house believes that emergency surgery should be a specialty in its own right, </italic>May 2017 <italic>Bulletin).</italic></p>
<p>The Editor-in-Chief is sticking to his guns and his belief that we do not require an additional subspecialty of &#x2018;emergency general surgery&#x2019; and, on this occasion, I agree with him.</p>
<p>I agree because, as we train in the generality of surgery and head towards our CCT, we should all have the depth and breadth of knowledge to diagnose and manage acute, non-elective surgical patients. We should be confident and competent enough to operate and get the patient to a stage in their care where the advice of a specialist can be sought. To think that these patients are best served by specialists is incorrect, as these surgeons do not always function best when &#x2018;flying off the seat of their pants&#x2019;. Rather, they do so when numerous investigations and results are available to them and they have had the opportunity to discuss every finer point with their esteemed colleagues at an MDT meeting!</p>
<p>So often we are encouraged to look at the workings and safety procedures of our colleagues in the airline industry. What we usually overlook is that we are comparing our elective surgical practice with scheduled and charter flights. When on deployment, I often don&#x2019;t have this luxury as a severely injured casualty may appear without warning and</p>
<p><bold>248</bold></p>
<p>require rapid decision-making and expedient resuscitative surgery. The same could be seen for the on-call surgeon who has to deal with &#x2018;unprocessed patients&#x2019;. The trauma and emergency surgeon should perhaps therefore be compared with our military pilots who fly fighter jets and have to respond instantly to a crisis or situation without warning.</p>
<p>Like our Editor-in-Chief, I will also stick to my guns and I maintain that on-call surgeons need to be trained in the generality of surgery (Chambers WM, Mortensen NJ, Lambert AW. Specialist or generalist? <italic>Ann R Coll Surg Engl </italic>2004; 86: 308&#x2013;311). I do not believe we need to invent a new specialty or change our title either.</p>
<p>The generalist is dead! Long live the generalist!</p>
<p><bold>Surg Cdr AW Lambert</bold></p>
<p><italic>Consultant General Surgeon</italic></p>
<p>Si r,</p>
<p>It was with great interest that I read the article by James <italic>et al </italic>debating the desirability of emergency surgery being recognised as a distinct specialty (<italic>This house believes that emergency surgery should be a specialty in its own right</italic>, May 2017 <italic>Bulletin</italic>). I congratulate the authors on bringing this pressing issue to the fore. I did feel, however, that they neglected to address a few important angles related to the current challenges in the provision of emergency care.</p>
<p>Emergency surgical care is a technically demanding discipline with inherently sick patients who may require prolonged admission and who generate the vast majority of</p>
<p>complaints and litigation against surgeons. To practise this aspect of surgery day-in and day-out would arguably lead to burnout. Having at least one emergency surgery specialist in a unit, as suggested by the parties for the motion, is therefore unlikely to be sustainable. The load has to be shared.</p>
<p>If the arduousness and challenges faced by a surgeon practising only emergency surgery are the stick, then what is the carrot? Different ways of thinking are required here; maybe exempting the role from out-of-hours work, providing an environment where training or research can flourish, departmental managerial roles or financial compensation?</p>
<p>Staffing of general surgery rotas tends to be driven by the need to maintain a workable on-call rota, as opposed to planning elective work. As most general surgeons have a subspecialist interest, the elective work is then divided among colleagues, which leads to a reduction in the frequency of emergency work (often welcomed!) but there is an associated dilution in the subspecialty experience (most unwelcome!).</p>
<p>The NHS cannot afford an expansion of consultant numbers on the sole basis of an increasing emergency workload. This means that gastrointestinal surgeons will continue to form the backbone of the emergency surgical services for the foreseeable future. The reality of the situation that faces the NHS at present means that new ways of working are required. Pathways will need to optimise early diagnosis with collaboration from our radiology colleagues. Sick patients might need prompt input from critical care teams and intensivists. A</p>
<p><BOLD>LETTER S</BOLD></p>
<p>set of conditions that can be managed by <italic>any </italic>gastrointestinal surgeon can be locally defined with more complex cases funneled to subspecialist teams. Admission prevention can be aided using ambulatory clinics, eg uncomplicated diverticulitis, non-specific abdominal pain.</p>
<p>The challenges facing emergency surgery are not going to go away and there are limited resources available to tackle them. There is no escaping the fact that we also have individual aspirations as generalists and as subspecialists. It is in our patients&#x2019; and our professional interests as surgeons to collaboratively modify the way in which we work together in order to deliver high-quality emergency care.</p>
<p><bold>W Baraza</bold></p>
<p><italic>Consultant Surgeon</italic></p>
<p>Annals_120x175_Surgeon_JAN 02/12/2016 University Hospital of South Manchester</p>
<p><BOLD>STRONGER IN THE BROKEN PLACES</BOLD></p>
<p>Sir,</p>
<p>I was interested to read the article about stress and suicides in the NHS <italic>(Stronger in the broken places, </italic>May 2017 <italic>Bulletin). </italic>This is nothing new and I recall similar episodes when I was a student in the early 1960s, even though the stresses then were fewer than today. There was a difference, though, in that there was some care given to staff. We had a room to retreat to - a doctors&#x2019; mess where you were able to talk to colleagues on an informal basis and gain support. Even so, some colleagues suffered and paid the price. What is astonishing is that the terms and conditions for NHS staff are ignored time and again yet Parliament can spend time and effort harassing private sector employers about their workers&#x2019; terms of work and contracts o<sup>0</sup> f <sup>:</sup> f <sup>0</sup>ere d. It is disappointing that that those</p>
<p>MPs who are doctors appear to take so little interest. Surely the state, through Parliament, should set an example by looking after its own employees and offer conditions of work that are reasonable and fair to give doctors a sense of being appreciated and valued.</p>
<p><bold>G A C Welply</bold></p>
<p><bold>Something to say?</bold></p>
<p>If you have any comments, complaints or compliments about anything you read in the <italic>Bulletin, </italic>please do get in touch at: E: bulletin&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk P: <italic>Bulletin </italic>Office, The Royal College of</p>
<p>Surgeons of England, 35&#x2013;43 Lincoln&#x2019;s</p>
<p>Inn Fields, London WC2A 3PE</p>
<p><bold>that will never let you down</bold></p>
<p><bold>The world&#x2019;s leading surgeons and healthcare professionals can always rely on the consistent quality, precision and performance of surgical blades, handles and scalpels from Swann-Morton.</bold></p>
<p>Our extensive range includes over 70 blade shapes and a selection of 27 handles. Used in various disciplines for both general and specialist surgery, all our products are subject to the strictest quality control procedures and are guaranteed never to let you down.</p>
<p><bold>Where only Swann-Morton will do.</bold></p>
<p><bold>For more information on the complete range of surgical blades, handles, scalpels, disposable, fine and retractable scalpels please go to our website.</bold></p>
<p>Owlerton Green, Sheffield S6 2BJ</p>
<p>Telephone: 0114 2344231, Sales: 0114 2344223,</p>
<p>Fax: 0114 2314966</p>
<p>uksales&#x0040;swann-morton.com,</p>
<p>exportsales&#x0040;swann-morton.com</p>
<p>www.swann-morton.com</p>
<p><bold>Medical device use post Brexit: should we be concerned?</bold></p>
<p>The potential effect of our departure from the EU on regulation and supply.</p>
<p>K Keogh SpR General Surgery, Bristol Royal Infirmary</p>
<p>G McConaghie Orthopaedic SHO, Kettering General Hospital</p>
<p><BOLD>B</BOLD></p>
<p>ritain&#x2019;s departure from the European Union (EU) may lay to rest the straight banana debate, but what other regulatory impacts will we see? With so much of the mainstream media coverage of &#x2018;Brexit&#x2019; focusing on trade deals, tariffs and the movement of people, it is easy to overlook the area of regulation. Just about every medical device from a suture to a replacement hip carries a &#x2018;CE&#x2019; mark and has gone through a rigorous process to ensure it is safe to use for patients. How will regula-</p>
<p><bold>250</bold></p>
<p>tion be affected by Brexit and should we as clinicians be concerned?</p>
<p><BOLD>CURRENT MODEL</BOLD></p>
<p>At present, each EU member state has a competent authority for medical devices; in the UK, this is the MHRA, which oversees regulation of medical devices and the UK Notified Bodies that directly assess products for safety. The MHRA does not test products itself.</p>
<p>Manufacturers apply for their device to be approved within a particular framework,</p>
<p>effectively describing what the device&#x2019;s intended use is. Once the required standard is achieved, the Notified Body informs the MHRA and the manufacturer is allowed to place a CE mark on the product. This demonstrates its safety and allows it to be sold anywhere in the EU. However, following the Prime Minister&#x2019;s announcement that the UK will no longer be a member of the single market after Brexit, that arrangement could change. But what would replace it and how would it work?</p>
<p><BOLD>FEATURE</BOLD></p>
<p><BOLD>WHAT IS THE FUTURE FOR REGULATION AND THE MHRA?</BOLD></p>
<p>The MHRA is a highly respected body in the European regulatory establishment. It is not only involved in the implementation of changes to EU framework at present; it also oversees UK Notified Bodies that regulate a significant proportion of the highest-risk medical devices in the EU. This overlap creates a mutual need between Britain and the EU, as the knowledge and skills within the UK Notified Bodies are not easy to replace. The MHRA contributes significantly to the European Medicines Agency regulatory work; however, discussion of medicines is a separate topic in its own right.</p>
<p>Although we have the equipment and expertise in the UK to undertake a significant proportion of regulatory testing, the prospect of having to repeat the regulatory process on every existing device is not feasible or desirable. Similarly, if the UK&#x2019;s Notified Bodies were removed from the European network &#x2013; and vice versa &#x2013; it would require duplication of the process for every manufacturer, which would be time-consuming and costly.</p>
<p>In addition, there would be capacity issues with regulation should paths diverge completely.</p>
<p><BOLD>COULD WE FACE A SHORTAGE OF MEDICAL DEVICES POST-BREXIT?</BOLD></p>
<p>The big concern for clinicians would be that the timeframe for establishing new regulatory pathways is short, which could mean that on Brexit Day +1 we go to the supply rooms and find the shelves bare. Could this really happen?</p>
<p>In short, this seems highly unlikely, as it would not be in the interests of Britain or the EU. Although Britain imports many medical devices, it also exports in large volumes. Even with regulatory changes it is likely that interim transition agreements will ensure mutual recognition of, and acceptance of, existing regulatory approval. The situation in Britain and in the EU would be untenable if this were not the case.</p>
<p>One greater concern that is less resolved is the supply chain. What happens when a product is manufactured in a number of different countries? Both in terms of taxation and the regulation of import and export of partially constructed devices, the future is less clear. For example, if a device was to have an initial build in Germany, followed by transit to Britain for component addition and then return to France for final assembly and sterilisation then the situation is complex. It is not clear how often regulation &#x2013; or taxation, for that matter &#x2013; will be imposed on that product, especially if a trade deal is not achieved and we fall back on World Trade Organization rules.</p>
<p>Another area that remains unclear is whether products with an animal component (porcine-derived mesh for example) would continue to be classed solely as a medical device or whether any legislation from agriculture, for example, could come into play.</p>
<p>The UK government has said as part of Brexit the country will &#x2018;remain the best place for science and innovation&#x2019; and has set this among its 12 objectives. But how is it going to deliver on this?</p>
<p><BOLD>RESEARCH AND SAFETY</BOLD></p>
<p>One great advantage of the current regulatory framework is Europe-wide databases for the reporting of adverse outcomes. These require large populations to identify problems with less-commonly used devices. At present it would seem that involved parties are keen to keep access to these databases open, so they can continue to benefit from as wide a range of sources of reporting as possible.</p>
<p><BOLD>WHAT DO COUNTRIES OUTSIDE THE EU DO?</BOLD></p>
<p>Although Britain will become a sovereign nation it does not have to be a sovereign regulator for medical devices &#x2013; as such, it can accept standards at its own discretion. As the MHRA works with European colleagues to meet the new incoming European framework, there is nothing to suggest that standards in the UK need to diverge in the future. It is unlikely that regulatory pathways could be shortened and there is little will to do so as</p>
<p>the MHRA was intimately involved in the formation of the current and new EU pathways. Safety must retain priority over trade. Sadly it does seem inevitable that the MHRA&#x2019;s influence in future EU regulatory decisions will be diminished, meaning we may adopt or work to standards we cannot influence.</p>
<p>Other countries such as Norway, Switzerland and Turkey are not in the EU but have trade and regulatory arrangements regarding medical devices. Australia has a different arrangement. Its regulatory body, the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA), largely accepts overseas standards such as the CE mark, but for higher-risk devices it may require additional documentation or testing prior to issuing approval. The downside is that the Australian system works by accepting individual overseas Notified Bodies rather than the overall regulators&#x2019; approval, and this could be difficult to implement. In the shared opinion of these authors, it would seem likely that the UK would lie somewhere between these systems in the future.</p>
<p><BOLD>WHAT LIES AHEAD?</BOLD></p>
<p>No doubt the devil will be in the detail, but there is a vast amount of work going on to ensure we can still have the equipment available to ensure the NHS provides world-class care. In addition to regulating devices, the MHRA regulates pharmaceuticals, which pose a different but equally monumental challenge in the years ahead. It is essential that the UK does not slide down the priority chain to the extent that US Food and Drug Administration and EMA approval is sought by manufacturers prior to applying for UK regulatory approval. Many countries face delays of six months to three years for device or medicine approval after the FDA and EMA are approached.</p>
<p>Although it is obvious that a great many people are working hard to make the transition as smooth as possible, it still remains possible that some devices could see an interruption to their supply chain during the transition. As clinicians this is something we must prepare for.</p>
<p><bold>251</bold></p>
<p><bold>Implications of the Ian Paterson case for the private hospital sector</bold></p>
<p>After the breast surgeon was sentenced to 15 years for performing unnecessary operations on cancer patients, Colin Leys considers what the inevitable inquiry could mean for private hospitals.</p>
<p><bold>252</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>FEATURE</BOLD></p>
<p><BOLD>T</BOLD></p>
<p>he conviction of Ian Paterson has put the issue of patient safety in private hospitals back on the agenda. The efficacy of a regulatory regime that allowed a surgeon to continue operating on patients in private hospitals despite there being known concerns about his professional competence and conduct has once again been brought into question, prompting the Secretary of State to propose that a public inquiry should be held by the next government. What should such an inquiry focus on?</p>
<p><BOLD>ACCOUNTABILITY</BOLD></p>
<p>The starting point should be the need for private hospitals to be held accountable for the care that takes place in them, and the mechanisms they have in place for ensuring that patient safety is prioritised. There are no doubt issues about the failings of the NHS in relation to Paterson&#x2019;s patients; but although significant measures have been put in place to improve patient safety in NHS hospitals following the events at Mid Staffs and Morecambe Bay, successive governments have left the private hospital sector&#x2019;s model of operation and system of clinical governance essentially untouched for more than half a century.</p>
<p>Unlike NHS hospitals, which are liable for the actions of their surgeons and physicians, private hospitals do not employ the consultants who work in them. The contract for undertaking an operation is between the patient and the surgeon, with a separate contract between the patient and the hospital for the use of the hospital&#x2019;s facilities and services. So whereas the NHS Litigation Authority &#x2013; which covers the liabilities of NHS hospitals &#x2013; is paying out significant sums to compensate Paterson&#x2019;s victims, the private hospitals involved have in most cases refused to do so and Paterson&#x2019;s victims are being forced to take legal action to seek redress from him personally. If private hospitals are not legally liable when things go wrong in clinical settings they will always lack the most important incentive to prevent this happening.</p>
<p>Leading on from this, any inquiry should also examine the role played in private hospitals by Medical Advisory Committees (MACs), which advise hospital managements on the granting of privileges to consultants to practise there. The independent inquiry into the way the Paterson case was handled by the private hospitals found significant shortcomings in the oversight role played by the MACs.<sup>1</sup> The MACs at both hospitals failed to notice his malpractice, unlike in the NHS where it was detected and &#x2013; belatedly &#x2013; stopped. Patients&#x2019; complaints were dismissed on the basis of Paterson&#x2019;s assurances, and he was even allowed to continue to practise in the private hospitals for three weeks after he had been excluded by his NHS trust.</p>
<p><italic>He was even allowed to continue</italic></p>
<p><italic>to practise in the private hospitals for three weeks after he had been excluded</italic></p>
<p><italic>by his NHS trust</italic></p>
<p><BOLD>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST AND PERVERSE INCENTIVES</BOLD></p>
<p>The key problem here is that MACs have a built-in conflict of interest and no legal duties. They are supposed to represent the interests of patients but, as they are composed of and elected by the clinicians who have practising privileges at the hospital, there is no clear incentive for them to put patient safety first and to highlight areas of poor practice or possible malpractice among their colleagues. MACs have no statutory role, and although private hospital managers are supposed to accept their advice on clinical issues they are not legally required to do so.</p>
<p>In addition, because hospitals rely on the consultants to bring in business they too have a conflict of interest when it comes to prioritising patient safety concerns. As the independent investigation mentioned above noted, for the hospital &#x2018;patients are the ultimate customer, [however] consultants are promoted corporately as [the] primary customer&#x2019;. In other words, they rely on consultants to bring in patients, and because they are not legally liable for the work the consultants do, there is an inherent disincentive to audit and monitor their work. There is also the practical difficulty faced by small private hospitals of monitoring the work and competence of (in some cases) hundreds of consultants with practising privileges, as a 2014 report by the Centre for Health and the Public Interest showed.<sup>2</sup> A future government inquiry should examine these conflicts of interest and the overall efficacy of the clinical governance arrangements in private hospitals.</p>
<p><BOLD>TRANSPARENCY</BOLD></p>
<p>The Royal College of Surgeons has called for a review to improve safety standards and data transparency in the private sector, and for private hospitals to be required to report safety incidents and unexpected deaths on the same basis as the NHS, and to take part in clinical audits as a condition of registration by the Care Quality Commission. We should strongly endorse this call. Systematic reporting of safety incidents and unexpected deaths to the National Reporting and Learning System, and participation in clinical audits, are key means whereby patterns of unsafe practice are identified by independent experts and acted on. There is no good reason for exempting private hospitals from these requirements.</p>
<p>Some may consider that the recent attempt by the private hospital sector to improve transparency has addressed this concern. But the purpose of the data transparency called for by the RCS is quite different from the publication of performance data that the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) has ordered from providers of private treatment.</p>
<p><bold>253</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>FEATURE</BOLD></p>
<p>That information is intended to help private patients to compare different providers and, although it includes some data relevant to patient safety, it notably fails to include some information that is critical for safety &#x2013; such as, for instance, whether a hospital has a rota of on-call anaesthetists, or on-site specialist physicians, or level-3 intensive care beds.</p>
<p>Moreover, the provision of data about hospital performance should meet the test set down by Sir Robert Francis in his report into Mid Staffs &#x2013; namely, that if it is to be trusted it should be published by organisations that are &#x2018;unimpeachably independent&#x2019;.<sup>3</sup> But the Private Hospitals Information Network (PHIN), which is charged with publishing the data ordered by the CMA, is not independent from the private hospital sector. On the contrary, it is funded by the sector and represents it heavily in its governance structure, as the CMA intended. The quality of the data published by PHIN thus does not meet the standard set for the NHS.</p>
<p>No system is fool-proof or knave-proof, as the scandal at the Morecambe Bay maternity unit also tragically showed. But the history o f t w a r r o s a</p>
<p><BOLD>R</BOLD></p>
<p>1.</p>
<p>Parkway-and-Little-Aston-hospitals-Spire-Healthcare-March-2014.pdf [last accessed 31 May 2017].</p>
<p>2. Centre for Health and the Public Interest. <italic>Patient</italic></p>
<p><italic>safety in private hospitals: the known and the unknown risks. </italic>https://chpi.org.uk/wp-content/ uploads/2014/08/CHPI-PatientSafety-Aug2014.pdf [last accessed 31 May 2017].</p>
<p>S Foundation Trust Inquiry.</p>
<p><italic>care provided by Mid ation Trust January 2005 aired by Robert Francis</italic></p>
<p>chive.nationalarchives. ttp:/www.dh.gov.uk/ /dh_digitalassets/&#x0040;dh/&#x0040; alasset/dh_113447.pdf [last</p>
<p>hor of <italic>Market-Driven emocracy and the </italic>shed by Verso in art Player, <italic>The Plot </italic>lished by Merlin n Honorary Professor sity and a member of</p>
<p>the management team at the Centre for</p>
<p>Health and the Public Interest.</p>
<p><bold>33RD ANNUAL SCIENTIFIC MEETING 2017</bold></p>
<p><bold>t</bold></p>
<p><bold> Perspectives from the Victorian medical profession</bold></p>
<p>As the first female President of the RCS finishes her term, we take a look at how the role of women in medicine was represented in the Victorian press. How far have we come?</p>
<p>Alison Moulds DPhil Candidate, University of Oxford</p>
<p>t is more than 150 years since the first women joined the Medical Register in Britain. The achievements of early pioneers like Elizabeth Blackwell and Elizabeth Garrett Anderson are often celebrated as milestones in the history of women in medicine. It is less well-known perhaps that the Victorian period also saw the movement for medical women develop into a concerted campaign. By 1892, there were 135 female</p>
<p>practitioners on the register. Unsurprisingly, their inroads into the profession were met with hostility and resentment.</p>
<p>The RCS Library has an extensive collection of medical journals from the 19th century and these provide a fascinating insight into contemporary debates about whether women could or should study and practise medicine. The subject was covered in familiar titles such as the <italic>Lancet </italic>and</p>
<p><italic>British Medical Journal (BMJ), </italic>as well as lesser-known journals including the <italic>Medical Press and Circular (MPC) </italic>and <italic>Medical Mirror. </italic>It featured in their editorials and news articles, correspondence columns, and transcripts of debates at professional societies. The topic was so ubiquitous that by 1877 the <italic>Lancet </italic>complained that &#x2018;[t]he medical-women question is perennial. It knows no limits; we encounter it at every turn&#x2019;.1</p>
<p><BOLD>FEATURE</BOLD></p>
<p>for female practitioners.<sup>5</sup> Two months later, however, it refused to cede even this territory, suggesting there would be no demand for medical women among female patients. In a particularly vitriolic aside, it asserted that &#x2018;women hate one another, often at first sight, with a rancour of which men can form only a</p>
<p>faint conception&#x2019;.<sup>6</sup></p>
<p>With more women entering the profession, however, hostility gradually began to wane. The perceived necessity of female practitioners for work in the British Empire was crucial to tempering opposition. In 1885, the National Association for Supplying Female Medical Aid to the Women of India</p>
<p>When Blackwell and Garrett Anderson joined the register in 1859 and 1864 respectively, it was through loopholes in the system that were subsequently closed to prevent other women following suit. In 1869, Sophia Jex-Blake and several female peers successfully lobbied for their admission to a recognised medical degree at the University of Edinburgh. With the prospect of medical women becoming more plausible, professional journals began debating the subject with increasing urgency and zeal.</p>
<p>Many were initially vociferous in their opinions. In 1870, the <ITALIC>BMJ </ITALIC>featured a leading article in which it suggested that women entering professional life would be detrimental to the interests of their gender and society. In sensationalist language, it branded the &#x2018;lady-doctor&#x2019; a &#x2018;traitress to her sex&#x2019; and insisted that, in a civilised society, women should not follow their own &#x2018;eccentric long-ing[s] for the will-o&#x2019;-the-wisp pleasures of independence&#x2019;.<sup>2</sup> Meanwhile, the rather more progressive <italic>Medical Mirror </italic>defined its position against the views of its contemporaries, deriding the <ITALIC>BMJ </ITALIC>for its &#x2018;medieval notions concerning woman&#x2019;.<sup>3</sup> The <ITALIC>MPC </ITALIC>adopted a moderate stance, arguing that &#x2013; in the spirit of &#x2018;toleration&#x2019; &#x2013; women should be allowed to pursue medical education, though it doubted whether they would ever succeed.<sup>4</sup></p>
<p>A particular bone of contention was the prospect of mixed or co-educational medical classes, which were seen as a threat to Victorian ideas of propriety and delicacy. In the face of opposition, Jex-Blake and her peers were denied the right to graduate and had to obtain their degrees abroad. Despite this setback, there were significant developments in following decades. Schools designed exclusively for female students opened in London (1874) and Edinburgh (1886). There were also wider reforms to the professional and educational landscape. In 1876, legislation formally authorised universities to award degrees to women (although it did not compel them to do so). A year later, the King&#x2019;s and Queen&#x2019;s College of Physicians of Ireland &#x2013; one of Britain&#x2019;s 19 medical licens-</p>
<p><bold>256</bold></p>
<p>ing bodies &#x2013; opened its final examinations to women.</p>
<p>From the early days of the movement, commentators debated where and how this new cohort of medical women would practise. Aspiring women doctors and surgeons claimed that there was an appetite or demand for their services among female patients, drawing on emerging ideas of patient preference or choice. They alleged that women were reluctant or unwilling to consult medical men, particularly when it came to their intimate health. In March 1870, the <italic>Lancet </italic>suggested that women and children&#x2019;s medicine was &#x2018;the most appropriate field&#x2019;</p>
<p><italic>Resistance to female</italic></p>
<p><italic>practitioners was</italic></p>
<p><italic>linked to ideas</italic></p>
<p><italic>about women&#x2019;s</italic></p>
<p><italic>physical or mental</italic></p>
<p><italic>weakness and their</italic></p>
<p><italic>perceived roles as</italic></p>
<p><italic>wives and mothers</italic></p>
<p>was established, with the backing of Queen Victoria. It provided support for medical women of British and Indian descent and catered for female patients who observed practices of veiling or segregation. In colonial journals such as the <italic>Indian Medical Gazette </italic>and <italic>Indian Medical Record</italic>, medical women were not only tolerated but celebrated. They were seen as extending the reach of Western medicine and thus incorporated into wider ideas about the imperialist project.</p>
<p>Significantly, historical medical journals grant access to the voices of early medical women themselves. They wrote in to participate in debates and share their own experiences. In the <italic>Lancet</italic>, Jex-Blake criticised suggestions that women should be given poorly remunerated midwifery cases, while Marion Ritchie (from the Clapham Maternity Hospital) tried to deflect allegations that medical women were undercutting men by working for lower fees. Their voices did not appear purely in the context of debates about the medical-woman movement; they also contributed clinical material. Even before the British Gynaecological Society admitted women in 1901, it published contributions from them. In the 1890s, it featured observations from Mary Ann Scharlieb (Senior Surgeon at the New Hospital for Women) on hysterectomy cases and an article from American doctor Mary Dixon Jones on diseases of the ovary.</p>
<p>Women&#x2019;s engagement with the medical press was sporadic &#x2013; unsurprising, perhaps, given its initial hostility towards them. Aspiring female practitioners often turned to other types of writing to make their case. In 1869, Jex-Blake produced a polemical essay entitled <italic>Medicine as a Profession for Women</italic>, while novels such as Margaret Todd&#x2019;s <italic>Mona Maclean, Medical Student </italic>(1892) and Arabella Kenealy&#x2019;s <italic>Dr Janet of Harley Street </italic>(1893) aimed to influence popular audiences.</p>
<p>Resistance among the profession continued until the century&#x2019;s close, however. During the 1890s, the BMA, RCS and RCP all debated whether to admit women to their ranks. Although the BMA voted in</p>
<p><BOLD>FEATURE</BOLD></p>
<p>1. &#x2018;Medical Women&#x2019;. <italic>Lancet. </italic>3 November 1877, p. 659.</p>
<p>2. &#x2018;Lady Surgeons&#x2019;. <ITALIC>BMJ</ITALIC>. 2 April 1870, pp. 338&#x2013;339.</p>
<p>3. &#x2018;Notes and Comments: Female Physicians&#x2019;. <italic>Medical Mirror. </italic>1 December 1869, p. 173.</p>
<p>favour, both royal colleges voted against. (Decisions that were only overturned in 1908.) The <italic>Lancet </italic>and <ITALIC>BMJ </ITALIC>published transcripts of these debates, which show arguments advanced on either side. Some questioned whether women&#x2019;s participation might weaken the reputation or authority of the professional bodies. At the RCS, general practitioner FH Alderson said he did &#x2018;not think it would give strength to the College to admit women to the best surgical diploma in the world&#x2019;.<sup>7</sup> In a letter to the <italic>Lancet</italic>, however, physician John Walter Carr countered that many women &#x2018;would grace the profession even more than the domestic circle&#x2019;.<sup>8</sup> He implied that femininity could elevate medicine. The <ITALIC>MPC </ITALIC>criticised the arguments put forward against female practitioners during the royal college debates. Although uncertain about women&#x2019;s physical and mental fitness for medical practice, it suggested that arguments against them were cynically based on &#x2018;sordid, commercial ground&#x2019;.<sup>9</sup></p>
<p>The mixed coverage of medical women reveals not only Victorian attitudes towards</p>
<p>gender, but also the anxieties and aspirations of the medical profession. In part, resistance to female practitioners was linked to ideas about women&#x2019;s physical or mental weakness and their perceived roles as wives and mothers. However, opposition also stemmed from insecurities about professional status. Medicine was seen as overcrowded and often unremunerative;<sup>10</sup> women therefore presented unwanted competition. Although physic had long been held in high esteem, surgery and general practice were still in the process of establishing themselves, shedding their old associations with trade and consolidating their respectability. The profession was divided about whether women&#x2019;s participation would improve or undermine its public image and medical journals were a key site for contestation and debate.</p>
<p><bold>References</bold></p>
<p>4. &#x2018;Lady Doctors&#x2019;. <ITALIC>MPC. </ITALIC>16 February 1870, pp. 127&#x2013;128. &#x2018;Lady Doctors&#x2019;. <ITALIC>MPC</ITALIC>. 23 February 1870, pp. 146&#x2013;147.</p>
<p>5. &#x2018;Notes, Short Comments, and Answers to Correspondents: Lady Doctors&#x2019;. <italic>Lancet. </italic>12 March 1870, p. 400.</p>
<p>6. &#x2018;The Medical Education of Women&#x2019;. <italic>Lancet. </italic>7 May 1870, pp. 672&#x2013;673 (p. 673).</p>
<p>7. &#x2018;Royal College of Surgeons of England: Admission of Women&#x2019;. <italic>Lancet. </italic>9 November 1895, pp. 1,199&#x2013;1,200.</p>
<p>8. Carr JW. <italic>&#x2018;Correspondence: The Admission of Women to the Royal Colleges of Physicians of London and Surgeons of England&#x2019;. Lancet</italic>. 30 November 1895, pp. 1,390&#x2013;1,391 (p. 1,391).</p>
<p>9. &#x2018;Notes on Current Topics: Admission of Women to the Profession&#x2019;. <ITALIC>MPC. </ITALIC>20 November 1895, pp. 532&#x2013;533.</p>
<p>10. Anne Digby. <italic>The Evolution of British General Practice 1850&#x2013;1948. </italic>Oxford: Oxford University Press; 1999, pp. 23-24 .</p>
<p>Alison is in the final year of her DPhil English Literature at the University of Oxford, where she is researching the formation of professional identities in Victorian medical writing. She is part of the Constructing Scientific Communities project, which works in partnership with the RCS.</p>
<p><bold>257</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>RCS MEMBER BENEFITS</BOLD></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.258</p>
<p><bold>RCS Current Awareness Updates</bold></p>
<p>RCS members will receive email summaries of relevant papers in their specialty every other month. Here&#x2019;s what fellows and members can expect from the service, and how to contribute.</p>
<p>Amy McEwan RCS Senior Information Specialist</p>
<p><BOLD>RCS MEMBER BENEFITS</BOLD></p>
<p><BOLD>T</BOLD></p>
<p>he Current Awareness Service was launched by the RCS Library in 2012 as a response to indications from fellows and members that they wanted more support in keeping up to date with the latest scientific advancements. After its inception, the service expanded quickly and was delivering specialty bulletins to eight specialties by the end of its pilot in 2016.</p>
<p>Following further feedback, we have been working hard behind the scenes and are now ready to relaunch with some exciting changes. The bulletins have been rebranded as <italic>Updates </italic>and will cover all ten surgical specialties by summer 2018, meaning that this valued membership benefit will be available to all current fellows and members within the next year. Patient safety content, which had been sent in a separate bulletin, will now be embedded into each <italic>Update</italic>, ensuring that surgeons only receive the information most relevant to them.</p>
<p>Sent directly to your inbox every two months, the <italic>Updates </italic>are concise email summaries of the latest evidence compiled by qualified Information Specialists with support from a panel of specialist advisors. Information is selected from a variety of sources, with a strong focus on the highest levels of evidence, guidelines, policy and new technology. Presented in an easy-to-use format sorted by topic, the <italic>Updates </italic>allow highly specialised consultants to easily</p>
<p>focus on their chosen subspecialty. Citations include a brief summary and link directly to the full text of the article, where possible, which will make reading for continuing professional development (CPD) easier and less time-consuming.</p>
<p><BOLD>WHEN WILL I START TO RECEIVE UPDATES?</BOLD></p>
<p>Cardiothoracic &#x2013; May 2017 Plastic and Reconstructive &#x2013; May 2017 Trauma and Orthopaedics &#x2013; May 2017 Emergency General Surgery &#x2013; July 2017 Urology &#x2013; July 2017</p>
<p>Further details on launch dates for the following specialties will be available soon:</p>
<p>Colorectal</p>
<p>Va s cu la r</p>
<p>Paediatric Surgery</p>
<p>Neurosurgery</p>
<p>Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</p>
<p>Otolaryngology.</p>
<p><BOLD>BECOME A SPECIALIST ADVISOR</BOLD></p>
<p>We are currently looking to recruit fellows and members to be specialist advisors for the <italic>Updates</italic>. The role is suitable for certification as a formal professional development activity and certificates will be awarded to those panel members that actively work to fulfil the responsibilities and functions of the post.</p>
<p>The specialist advisor&#x2019;s main role will be to:</p>
<p>&#x2022;	provide clarity about the suitability of content for specific specialties and subspecialties</p>
<p>&#x2022;	review the <italic>Updates </italic>before they are distributed more widely</p>
<p>&#x2022;	highlight important content to the Information Specialists.</p>
<p>This work will require a time commitment of beween one and two hours every two months.</p>
<p>&#x2018;I have thoroughly enjoyed contributing to the plastic [and reconstructive] current awareness bulletin since its inception. It keeps me up to date with my reading across the specialty. This makes me a better surgeon and academic&#x2019; &#x2013; Matthew Gardiner, Honorary Clinical Lecturer in Plastic Surgery and specialty trainee.</p>
<p>If you would like to get involved please visit the Current Awareness page (www.rcseng.ac.uk/library-and-publica-tions/library/guide-to-services/cas/) on the RCS website to see which specialties we are currently recruiting for. The page contains more information, including a full role description and expression of interest forms that can be downloaded and sent to updates&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk.</p>
<p><bold>Five easy steps to make sure you receive the <italic>Update </italic>for your specialty:</bold></p>
<p><bold>Step 1 </bold>&#x2013; Log into the RCS website</p>
<p><bold>Step 2 </bold>&#x2013; Click on your name in the top right-hand corner to access your profile <bold>Step 3 </bold>&#x2013; From the My Account section on the right, select Account Preferences <bold>Step 4 </bold>&#x2013; Choose your surgical specialty and other areas of interest and click &#x2018;Update interests&#x2019;</p>
<p><bold>Step 5 </bold>&#x2013; Scroll further down the page to Communications and the Journals option, select Current Awareness Service and click &#x2018;Update email preferences&#x2019;.</p>
<p>Once you have updated this information you will receive the relevant Updates when the service is re-launched. It is also easy to change your preferences again at any time.</p>
<p>If you have any questions or comments please email updates&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk.</p>
<p><bold>259</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>SURGICAL TRIALS SERIES</BOLD></p>
<p><bold>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull. 2017.260</bold></p>
<p><italic><bold>y </italic>Improving ^<italic></bold></italic></p>
<p><bold>communication in 1 recruitment consultations <SUB>L</SUB> for randomised <sub><italic>&#x00C0; </italic></sub>&#x25BA;^ controlled trials <ITALIC>A</ITALIC></bold></p>
<p>Six key recommendations for <bold>^ ^^^&#x00C9; </bold>increasing recruitment to clinical trials.</p>
<p>Joshua R Burke Academic Foundation Year 21</p>
<p>James Glasbey NIHR Academic Clinical</p>
<p>Fellow in General Surgery<sup>1</sup></p>
<p>Dmitri Nepogodiev NIHR Academic</p>
<p>Clinical Fellow in General Surgery<sup>1</sup></p>
<p>Thomas Drake Academic Foundation Year 11</p>
<p>Natalie Blencowe Clinical Lecturer in Surgery<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>Leila Rooshenas Lecturer in Qualitative Health Sciences<sup>23</sup></p>
<p>J Edward Fitzgerald Visiting Lecturer Centre</p>
<p>of Global Health, Kings College London<sup>1</sup></p>
<p>Nicola S Fearnhead Consultant Colorectal Surgeon<sup>45</sup></p>
<p>Jane M Blazeby Professor of Surgery<sup>23 </sup>Simon Bach Senior Lecturer in Surgery<sup>56 </sup>Aneel Bhangu Clinical Lecturer in Surgery<sup>17 </sup>1STARSurg Collaborative, Nationwide <sup>2</sup>MRC ConDuCT-II Hub, Bristol <sup>3</sup>QuinteT research group, University of Bristol <sup>4</sup>Addenbrooke&#x2019;s Hospital, Cambridge 5Bowel Disease Research Foundation <sup>6</sup>Diagnostics, Drugs, Devices and Biomarkers</p>
<p>(D3 B) Clinical Trials, Birmingham 7Birmingham Surgical Trials Consortium, Birmingham</p>
<p><BOLD>SURGICAL TRIALS SERIES</BOLD></p>
<p><BOLD>T</BOLD></p>
<p>he Student Audit and Research in Surgery collaborative (STARSurg, www. starsurg.org) was founded in 2013 to empower students to participate in high-quality academic projects, gain an understanding of audit and research methodology and develop communication, teamwork and leadership</p>
<p><bold>1 -11 </bold>1,2,3	2017<bold>	</bold></p>
<p>skills. As of March , more than 2,400 UK medical students from across the UK and Ireland have participated in STARSurg&#x2019;s observational studies. STARSurg shares the National Institute of Health Research (NIHR) vision of ensuring that all doctors acquire research skills that enable them to effectively contribute to high-impact multicentre studies that have the potential to change clinical practice and improve patient care.</p>
<p><BOLD>TRIAL RECRUITMENT IN SURGERY</BOLD></p>
<p>Despite patients being increasingly willing</p>
<p>participate in research, up to 80&#x0025; of randomised controlled trials (RCTs) fail to reach their recruitment target and are either discontinued, or published but underpowered to address the original research</p>
<p>&#x201E;	4-- &#x201E; 6,7,8,9 <italic>\ </italic>1,1	.1 - &#x201E;-	l ,	&#x201E;</p>
<p>question. Although junior doctors are ideally placed to identify and recruit patients to clinical trials across emergency, inpatient and outpatient settings, few are confident in discussing participation in clinical trials with patients. Most medical students graduate having received limited clinical research training and no structured training on how to recruit patients into research studies. Given the particular challenges associated with balancing the risks and benefits of par-</p>
<p><bold>		</bold>9,10</p>
<p>ticipating in complex surgical trials, there is an opportunity for junior surgeons and medical students to be trained to undertake recruitment. A dedicated course aimed at empowering these groups to participate in clinical trial recruitment has the potential to benefit patients by enhancing recruitment to the UK surgical research portfolio.</p>
<p><BOLD>GENERATING STUDENT RECRUITERS FOR RANDOMISED TRIALS (GRANULE) COURSE</BOLD></p>
<p>STARSurg has collaborated with the Birmingham Surgical Trials Consortium, the</p>
<p>Bristol Surgical Trials Centre and members of the Medical Research Council Hub for Trials Methodology Research (ConDuCT-II) and QuinteT research group to design and deliver a one-day course to train medical students to effectively communicate equipoise to patients, and recruit to clinical trials. Twenty senior medical students attended the first Generating Student Recruiters for Randomised Trials (GRANULE) course, held at The Royal College of Surgeons of England in May 2016.</p>
<p>The course highlighted six key recommendations for improving recruitment to clinical trials and communication in recruitment consultations (Table 1):</p>
<p><bold>1.	KNOW YOUR PATIENT POPULATION</bold></p>
<p>It is important to have a clear understanding of the trial&#x2019;s inclusion and exclusion criteria. This will enable you to readily identify patients, and approach them within the clinical environment. Consider all potential recruitment pathways, including outpatient and pre-assessment clinics, telephone contact and ward review. The multidisciplinary team (for example, surgeons, radiologists, ward nurses and clinical nurse specialists) should be made aware of ongoing trials and incentivised to flag up potential patients for recruitment. Flexible communication platforms such as WhatsApp<sup>11</sup> and Slack<sup>12 </sup>can enhance communication within a site&#x2019;s research team. Following these steps will maximise the number of patients who can be approached for a recruitment consultation; this is particularly important for trials in emergency surgery.</p>
<p><bold>2.	PROVIDE CLEAR SUMMARIES OF THE TRIAL, SUPPORTED WITH A PUBLISHED PATIENT INFORMATION LEAFLET (PIL)</bold></p>
<p>During the recruitment consultation, it is important to provide a clear, succinct summary of the research study to potential patient participants. The patient will want to be told why they are eligible to participate, what aspect of their care or procedure the intervention will change, and what the</p>
<p>expectations of involvement are (eg frequency and nature of follow-up). In particular, <italic>Good Clinical Practice </italic>guidelines stipulate that the following key points should be explained to patients:<sup>13</sup></p>
<p>&#x00BB; Purpose of the trial</p>
<p>&#x00BB; Standard treatment</p>
<p>&#x00BB; Uncertainty about experimental treatment arms, their features and potential risks and benefits</p>
<p>&#x00BB; Randomisation procedure</p>
<p>&#x00BB; Right to withdraw from the research.</p>
<p>The volume, rate and delivery of information must be flexible and targeted to a patient&#x2019;s needs, which vary greatly.<sup>14</sup></p>
<p><bold>3.	EQUIPOISE</bold></p>
<p>Be mindful of your personal sense of equipoise, and think about whether there is community equipoise (ie within the scientific community there is uncertainty as to what the superior treatment is).<sup>15</sup> If you lack personal equipoise, or are unable to communicate community equipoise, this can be reflected in your recruitment consultation and potentially bias the patient towards a particular treatment.<sup>16,17</sup> This problem is particularly common if the trial includes both surgical and non-operative treatment arms. In this type of challenging surgical trial, support to improve communication and informed consent is recommended.<sup>18</sup> Interventions have been developed to optimise recruitment to these challenging RCTs. For example, the QuinteT Recruitment Intervention<sup>6</sup> aims to rapidly understand recruitment challenges in an RCT, with a view to delivering tailored strategies to overcome recruitment obstacles as the trial is underway. This can be particularly helpful in feasibility studies, which provide an opportunity to fine tune recruitment strategies for a main RCT.<sup>19</sup></p>
<p><bold>4.	ELICIT PATIENT PREFERENCES AND EXPLORE REASONING</bold></p>
<p>During recruitment consultations it is important to explore and address patients&#x2019; ideas,</p>
<p><bold>261</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>SURGICAL TRIALS SERIES</BOLD></p>
<p><bold>Recommendation</bold>	<bold>Summary</bold></p>
<p>1	Know your patient population</p>
<p>2	Provide clear summaries of the trial, supported with a published patient information leaflet (PIL)</p>
<p>3 4	Equipoise</p>
<p>Elicit patient preferences and explore reasoning</p>
<p>5	Understand and explain the randomisation process</p>
<p>6	Seek recruitment training</p>
<p><bold>Table 1 </bold>Summary of six key recommendations for improving recruitment to clinical trials and communication in recruitment consultations</p>
<p>concerns and expectations, in the context of the evidence for each trial arm. Trial participation can improve when patients feel supported and reassured about the management of potential adverse effects.<sup>18</sup> Avoid coercion at all costs. Recruiters sometimes inadvertently use &#x2018;loaded&#x2019; vocabulary such as &#x2018;gold standard&#x2019; and &#x2018;experimental&#x2019;, which can lead to an unbalanced presentation of</p>
<p>the facts.<sup>17,20,21</sup></p>
<p><bold>5.	UNDERSTAND AND EXPLAIN THE RANDOMISATION PROCESS</bold></p>
<p>Randomisation is a key aspect of RCT participation that needs to be clearly communicated to patients to safeguard informed consent. One approach to discussing this concept is to explain the &#x2018;process&#x2019; and &#x2018;purpose&#x2019; of randomisation. Randomisation may be described as a process of creating two or more groups of patients that are as similar as possible. These groups are determined by chance. Neither doctors nor the patient can choose which group the patient goes in, as this could result in the groups being unequal. In terms of purpose, randomisation is done to achieve as fair a comparison as possible, in that any differences observed in the groups at the end of the study can be attributed to the treatments received, rather than differences in group characteristics (the &#x2018;purpose&#x2019;).<sup>6</sup></p>
<p><bold>6.	SEEK RECRUITMENT TRAINING</bold></p>
<p>Several studies have assessed variation in training of trial recruiters and how this can influence recruitment.<sup>22-25</sup> A recent review describing interventions to improve</p>
<p><bold>262</bold></p>
<p>recruitment identified training site staff as a priority,<sup>26</sup> with an emergent need to develop recruiter training programmes.<sup>10</sup> A number of UK-registered Clinical Trials Units and universities provide trial recruitment courses for clinicians of all stages of training.<sup>27 </sup>Bespoke training can also be provided through interventions such as the QuinteT Recruitment Intervention,<sup>6</sup> which works with the trial management group, clinicians, and nurses to optimise recruitment during a n RC T.</p>
<p><italic>Randomisation</italic></p>
<p><italic>may be described</italic></p>
<p><italic>as a process of</italic></p>
<p><italic>creating two or</italic></p>
<p><italic>more groups of</italic></p>
<p><italic>patients that are as</italic></p>
<p><italic>similar as possible</italic></p>
<p><BOLD>PLANS FOR THE FUTURE</BOLD></p>
<p>STARSurg are connecting GRANULE participants with trainee-led research collaboratives and RCT chief investigators, to develop pathways for delegates to gain practical experience. The group will work with the Surgical Specialty Leads and the Royal College of Surgeons Surgical Trials Units to build a database of current oppor-</p>
<p>tunities to participate in trial recruitment across surgery.</p>
<p>GRANULE demonstrated that medical students and junior doctors have an appetite for developing the necessary skills to effectively recruit patients to RCTs. The course has created a geographically dispersed cohort of trainees who will champion surgical RCTs across the UK. The next GRANULE course will take place in June 2017, continuing STARSurg&#x2019;s work to integrate clinical research into undergraduate training with direct benefits for patients.</p>
<p>For further information, please visit the STARSurg webpage at www.starsurg.org and follow STARSurg on Twitter at &#x0040;STARSurgUK.</p>
<p><BOLD>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</BOLD></p>
<p>This course was supported by a research grant from the Bowel Disease Research Foundation. We are also grateful to The Royal College of Surgeons of England, the Birmingham Surgical Trials Consortium, the Bristol Surgical Trials Centre, the MRC ConDuCT-II Hub (Collaboration and innovation for Difficult and Complex randomized controlled Trials in Invasive procedures &#x2013; MR/ K025643/1), and the Association of Surgeons in Training &#x2013; without whose support, the GRANULE course would not have been possible. STARSurg is part of the SURG Foundation collaborative research charity, registered charity number 1159898.</p>
<p><bold>References</bold></p>
<p>1. STARSurg Collaborative. Impact of postoperative non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs on adverse events after gastrointestinal surgery. <italic>Br J Surg </italic>2014; 101(11): 1,413&#x2013;1,423.</p>
<p>2. STARSurg Collaborative. Multicentre prospective cohort study of body mass index and postoperative complications following gastrointestinal surgery: Body mass index and postoperative complications following</p>
<p><BOLD>SURGICAL TRIALS SERIES</BOLD></p>
<p>gastrointestinal surgery. <italic>Br J Surg </italic>2016; 103(9): 1,157&#x2013;1,172.</p>
<p>3. Chapman SJ, Glasbey JCD, Khatri C <italic>et al</italic>. Promoting research and audit at medical school: evaluating the educational impact of participation in a student-led national collaborative study. <italic>BMC Med Educ </italic>2015; 15: 47.</p>
<p>4. London: Department of Health. <italic>Department of Health: Best Research for Best Health &#x2013; A New National Health Research Strategy. </italic>2006. https://www.gov.uk/ government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_ data/file/568772/dh_4127152_v2.pdf [last accessed 31 March 2017].</p>
<p>5. Medical Research Council. <italic>The use of personal health information in medical research. General public consultation. 2007</italic>. https://www.mrc.ac.uk/documents/ pdf/the-use-of-personal-health-information-in-medical-research-june-2007/ [last accessed 18 January 2017].</p>
<p>6. Donovan JL, Rooshenas L, Jepson M <italic>et al</italic>. Optimising recruitment and informed consent in randomised controlled trials: the development and implementation of the Quintet Recruitment Intervention (QRI). <italic>Trials </italic>2016; 17: 1. http://trialsjournal.biomedcentral.com/ articles/10.1186/s13063-016-1391-4 [last accessed 18 January 2017].</p>
<p>7. Sully BGO, Julious SA, Nicholl J. A reinvestigation of recruitment to randomised, controlled, multicenter trials: a review of trials funded by two UK funding agencies. <italic>Trials </italic>2013; 14(1): 166.</p>
<p>8. Carlisle B, Kimmelman J, Ramsay T, MacKinnon N. Unsuccessful trial accrual and human subjects protections: An empirical analysis of recently closed trials. <italic>Clin Trials </italic>2015; 12(1): 77&#x2013;83.</p>
<p>9. Chapman SJ, Shelton B, Mahmood H <italic>et al</italic>.</p>
<p>Discontinuation and non-publication of surgical randomised controlled trials: observational study. <ITALIC>BMJ </ITALIC>2014; 349: g6870&#x2013;g6870.</p>
<p>10. Townsend D, Mills N, Savovi&#x0107; J, Donovan JL. A systematic review of training programmes for recruiters to randomised controlled trials. <italic>Trials </italic>2015; 16: 1. http:// trialsjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13063-015-0908-6 [last accessed 18 January 2017].</p>
<p>11. Whatsapp Messenger [Internet]. www.whatsapp.com/ [last accessed 19 January 2017].</p>
<p>12. Slack Messaging [Internet]. <italic>https://slack.com/ is?</italic>cvosrc=ppc.google.slack&#x0026;cvo_campaign=&#x0026;cvo_ crid=102683539275&#x0026;Matchtype=b&#x0026;utm_ source=google&#x0026;utm_medium=ppc&#x0026;utm_campai gn=generalbrand&#x0026;c3api=5542,32949068115,kwd-16140880&#x0026;gclid=CNL8vveyz9ECFccV0wodFR4A5Q [last accessed 19 January 2017].</p>
<p>13. International Conference on Harmonisation. <italic>Guideline for good clinical practice E6. </italic>1996. https://www. ich.org/fileadmin/Public_Web_Site/ICH_Products/ Guidelines/Efficacy/E6/E6_R1_Guideline.pdf [last accessed 19 January 2017].</p>
<p>14. McDonald AM, Treweek S, Shakur H <italic>et al</italic>. Using a business model approach and marketing techniques for recruitment to clinical trials. <italic>Trials </italic>2011; 12: 1. http://trialsjournal. biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1745-6215-12-74 [last accessed 19 January 2017].</p>
<p>15. Kukla R. Resituating the principle of equipoise: justice and access to care in non-ideal conditions. <italic>Kennedy Inst Ethics J </italic>2007; 17(3): 171&#x2013;202.</p>
<p>16. Cook C, Sheets C. Clinical equipoise and personal</p>
<p>equipoise: two necessary ingredients for reducing bias in manual therapy trials. <italic>J Man Manip Ther </italic>2011; 19(1): 55&#x2013;57.</p>
<p>17. Rooshenas L, Elliott D, Wade J <italic>et al</italic>. Conveying equipoise during recruitment for clinical trials: qualitative synthesis of clinicians&#x2019; practices across six randomised controlled trials. <italic>PLOS Med </italic>2016; 13 (10): e1002147.</p>
<p>18. Paramasivan S, Huddart R, Hall E <italic>et al</italic>. Key issues in recruitment to randomised controlled trials with very different interventions: a qualitative investigation of recruitment to the SPARE trial (CRUK/07/011). <italic>Trials </italic>2011; 12: 1. http://trialsjournal.biomedcentral.com/ articles/10.1186/1745-6215-12-78 [last accessed 18 January 2017].</p>
<p>19. O&#x2019;Cathain A, Hoddinott P, Lewin S <italic>et al</italic>. Maximising the impact of qualitative research in feasibility studies for randomised controlled trials: guidance</p>
<p>for researchers. <italic>Pilot Feasibility Stud </italic>2015; 1: 1. http://pilotfeasibilitystudies.biomedcentral.com/ articles/10.1186/s40814-015-0026-y [last accessed 18 January 2017].</p>
<p>20. Albrecht TL, Eggly SS, Gleason MEJ <italic>et al</italic>. Influence of clinical communication on patients&#x2019; decision making on participation in clinical trials. <italic>J Clin Oncol </italic>2008; 26 (16): 2,666&#x2013;2,673.</p>
<p>21. Donovan J. Quality improvement report: Improving design and conduct of randomised trials by embedding them in qualitative research: ProtecT (prostate testing for cancer and treatment) study. Commentary: presenting unbiased information to patients can be difficult. <ITALIC>BMJ </ITALIC>2002; 325: 7 6 6 &#x2013;7 7 0 .</p>
<p>22. Donovan JL, Paramasivan S, de Salis I, Toerien M. Clear obstacles and hidden challenges: understanding recruiter perspectives in six pragmatic randomised controlled trials. <italic>Trials </italic>2014; 15 (1): 5.</p>
<p>23. Larkey LK, Staten LK, Ritenbaugh C <italic>et al</italic>. Recruitment of Hispanic women to the Women&#x2019;s Health Initiative. <italic>Control Clin Trials </italic>2002; 23 (3): 289&#x2013;298.</p>
<p>24. Kimmick GG. Improving accrual of older persons to cancer treatment trials: A randomized trial comparing an educational intervention with standard information: CALGB 360001. <italic>J Clin Oncol </italic>2005; 23 (10): 2,201&#x2013;2,207.</p>
<p>25. Donovan JL, Athene Lane J, Peters TJ <italic>et al</italic>. Development of a complex intervention improved randomization and informed consent in a randomized controlled trial. <italic>J Clin Epidemiol </italic>2009; 62 (1): 29&#x2013;36.</p>
<p>26. Bower P, Brueton V, Gamble C <italic>et al</italic>. Interventions to improve recruitment and retention in clinical trials: a survey and workshop to assess current practice and future priorities. <italic>Trials </italic>2014; 15: 1. http://trialsjournal. biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1745-6215-15-399 [last accessed 18 January 2017].</p>
<p>27. QuinteT Team, School of Social and Community Medicine, The University of Bristol. <italic>Qualitative Research Integrated within Trials (QuinteT). </italic>http:// www.bristol.ac.uk/social-community-medicine/ research/groups/social-sciences-health/quintet/ [last accessed 12 March 2017].</p>
<p><bold>263</bold></p>
<p><bold>The extended surgical team</bold></p>
<p>How hospitals around the UK are using the extended surgical team to improve patient care.</p>
<p>Johnny Mathews Orthopaedic Registrar, National Director&#x2019;s Clinical Fellow.</p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.264</p>
<p><bold>264</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>FEATURE</BOLD></p>
<p><BOLD>T</BOLD></p>
<p>he healthcare environment we work in is continually changing. Accordingly, surgical departments have evolved in terms of their structure, personnel and output. Recent developments have been underpinned by increasing patient needs, and moulded by working time regulations, the new junior doctor contract terms and conditions, and chronic understaffing.</p>
<p>How do we best maintain quantity and quality of the service provided to patients while assuring high-quality training for surgical trainees in the system? It is na&#x00EF;ve to consider &#x2018;service&#x2019; and &#x2018;training&#x2019; to be mutually exclusive, but few would refute that most tasks lie closer to one end of the spectrum drawn between the two.</p>
<p>With steady evaporation of the classical surgical &#x2018;firm&#x2019; structure and increasingly widespread rota gaps, the make-up of most surgical teams has undergone significant reconfiguration. Without useful change, trainees left in the system will likely remain overstretched to deliver &#x2018;service&#x2019;, at the cost of their own surgical &#x2018;training&#x2019; and to the long-term disadvantage of patients. Maintaining the balance is perhaps more tricky than ever. How do we protect continuity?</p>
<p><bold>THE EXTENDED SURGICAL TEAM &#x2013; A PART OF THE SOLUTION?</bold></p>
<p>Surgical departments around the country have responded in various ways. While all have done their best to improvise in the short term, many have sought to find more definitive solutions. Some have tried to make use of the Extended Surgical Team, in various settings. These include: (to name a few) surgical care practitioners, advanced nurse practitioners, extended scope practitioners and physician associates.</p>
<p>When such roles are developed optimally, they can without a doubt enhance the quality of patient care AND the proportion of time that trainees spend doing work with greater educational value. Practitioners in extended roles can greatly enhance continuity of inpatient ward care. They can facilitate new foundation doctors as they settle into a</p>
<p><bold>EST: A surgical care practitioner perspective</bold></p>
<p>As a surgical care practitioner (SCP) and constant member of the team, I provide consistency within the surgical team alongside the consultants. This has the benefit of continuity of care for patients and familiarity with the organisation&#x2019;s workings and the consultant preferences, which I relay to trainee doctors to smooth their transition into the team. As an SCP I provide flexible working to support service needs and enhance junior doctor training by adapting, where possible, my job plan and covering different aspects of the patient pathway. SCPs have different clinical backgrounds. As a nurse with a perioperative background working within a medicalised role, I have insight into the pressures both of nurses and junior doctors in numerous clinical areas and can offer appropriate support. Having different strengths has helped myself and the junior doctors I work with to support each other, build relationships and optimise patient care. I consider that part of my role as an SCP is to support the development and training of the surgeons of the future.</p>
<p><bold>Sara Dalby </bold>Surgical Care Practitioner</p>
<p><bold>EST: The consultant perspective</bold></p>
<p>Most surgeons, at some point in their career, will be fortunate enough to work in a unit where one or more extended surgical team members play a critical role. In the past 20 years in the vascular unit at Cheltenham, where there has been a rapid turnover of surgical trainees, we have found that EST roles provide continuity in patient care. Contrary to the fears of many trainees that the presence of these extended roles will detract from training, we&#x2019;ve seen educational opportunities increase.</p>
<p>The exact role of the EST member will depend on departmental requirements and we suggest that these are identified early. It is clear from our experience that key factors in successful integration include careful candidate selection, a supervising consultant surgeon &#x2018;champion&#x2019; with clinical, educational and line management responsibility, well-defined training and competency requirements, and the opportunity for professional development and career progression.</p>
<p>We believe that adopting this approach will help teams to embrace both surgical training requirements and the dynamics of surgical team management.</p>
<p><bold>Simon M Higgs </bold>Consultant Upper GI and General Surgeon <bold>Keith R Poskitt </bold>Consultant General and Vascular Surgeon</p>
<p>new specialty and &#x2018;iron out&#x2019; learning curves	in the outpatient setting by affording more</p>
<p>between rotations.	predictable clinic staffing. The regularity</p>
<p>The use of appropriately trained prac-	of registrar presence is often attenuated by</p>
<p>titioners can also be greatly advantageous	shift working, on-call commitments and the</p>
<p><bold>265</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>FEATURE</BOLD></p>
<p><bold>Four principles needed for the extended surgical team to work</bold></p>
<p>1.	Roles should be properly planned prior to recruitment</p>
<p>Consider all of the following: responsibilities, scope of practice, training, assessment, progression, accountability and sustainability.</p>
<p>2.	Roles should be initiated specifically in response to local departmental needs</p>
<p>For instance, if a system primarily needs additional support on the wards or in the outpatient setting then hiring purely theatre-based practitioners would accentuate the imbalance rather than help, and vice versa. Roles should complement, not substitute, trainees.</p>
<p>3.	There must be emotionally intelligent consultant leadership</p>
<p>This is necessary to guide the needs and development of non-medical practitioners through mentoring and supervision, while concomitantly ensuring that there is no negative impact on surgical trainees.</p>
<p>4.	Strong departmental training culture</p>
<p>Departments should balance the education of surgical trainees (ie future consultants) with service provision, and the most effective non-medical practitioners subscribe to this ethos.</p>
<p>need to cover rota gaps. After trainees rotate to a new sub-specialty, it takes time to gain familiarity with the presenting pathologies and the best management plans. Practitioners in extended roles present a sustainable solution that reduces the fluctuations in expertise to maintain care standards, and reduces reliance on rotating registrars. These registrars can in turn benefit from a slightly more &#x2018;supernumerary&#x2019; outpatient role alongside a consultant, allowing greater educational value. This has to be better if our system aims to create the best consultants, for patient care, with breadth as well as depth of knowledge.</p>
<p>There can also be benefits in the theatre environment. Owing to the above mentioned factors that impact on trainee availability, many departments can struggle to allocate the necessary number of assistants to run regular theatre lists. The flexibility afforded by having theatre-based practitioners helps fill this void and can also help trainees to fulfill their individual needs. If there are clashing lists, it can help a trainee attend a case where he or she can derive the best marginal training value, rather than assist in an operation he or she may have seen many times before. If the trainee is senior, having an experienced practitioner to assist can give consultants the confidence to supervise unscrubbed, or remotely, which is a key step during the transition towards CCT.</p>
<p><BOLD>WHAT ARE THE CONCERNS AROUND USE OF THE EXTENDED SURGICAL TEAM?</BOLD></p>
<p>Some have justifiable concerns about the potential expansion of extended practitioner roles. Some consultants express concern about quality assurance and standard setting for these practitioners. Others question their clinical governance, regulation and accountability. Practitioners themselves have questions regarding support, training and career progression. Both groups have different views on scope of practice. Exactly what tasks should (or should not) be delegated?</p>
<p>From a trainee perspective, some are concerned at the potential further loss</p>
<p><bold>266</bold></p>
<p>of training opportunities. They highlight worrying anecdotes where they have experienced heavy service workloads that have been compounded rather than attenuated by the involvement of practitioners with extended roles. The training phase for these practitioners requires particular consideration; when properly planned this can be achieved without negatively affecting surgical trainees but otherwise there may be unhealthy competition.</p>
<p>The heterogeneity of the roles and the spectrum of needs within departments across the country, means that one size does not fit all. This needs to be recognised when recruiting extended surgical team members. Having seen the potential benefits, and shortfalls, of the roles during the case studies conducted for the Extended Surgical Team report,<sup>1</sup> it seems the following four principles must be realised for these roles to fulfill their potential (see insex box below) If any one of these is lacking, then there may be resultant disadvantages for patient care, training and work satisfaction.</p>
<p><BOLD>MY PERSONAL EXPERIENCE OF THE EXTENDED SURGICAL TEAM</BOLD></p>
<p>My personal experience has been very positive. I have come across others who have had negative experiences; all of these have resulted from an obvious shortfall in one of the above principles. In most of these cases, practitioners have been hired to substitute rather than complement trainees (which they themselves do not wish to do!), have been hired without consideration for actual local needs, or there has been poor consultant leadership.</p>
<p>In my current department at Musgrove Park, Taunton, things work well. The extended surgical team members are invaluable to patient care and greatly beneficial to the trainees. The &#x2018;trauma coordinator&#x2019; is essential to the running of the department, coordinating all trauma operations as well as cross-specialty referrals. She also performs clinical tasks including clerking and assessment of hip fracture patients, nerve blocks, cannulation, venepuncture and requesting appropriate investigations. There are ward-based nurse practitioners who are have been assigned to specific teams of consultants (eg lower limb)</p>
<p>and optimise the continuity of inpatient patient care. As well as clinical care duties, they coordinate the admission and clerking of all elective surgical patients and also help with discharge paperwork, which means a more favourable ratio of clinical to administrative duties for the rotating foundation doctors.</p>
<p>Core trainees are supernumerary, without ward commitments and spend their time in theatres, clinics and on-call. There are a large</p>
<p><bold>EST: The NHS Employers perspective</bold></p>
<p>With increasing numbers of patients, an ageing population, more frequent comorbidities and changing service models, the need for the expansion and regulation of this group of highly trained and skilled staff has never been greater.</p>
<p>Employers need to develop a different workforce model for the future &#x2013; one that uses the most efficient mix of available staff to continue to provide the highest-quality care for patients and improve training for our trainees.</p>
<p>The extended surgical team is a key way in which we can do that. Their expansion may also be the catalyst for change that teams need to develop brand new ways of working and providing even better care for our surgical patients.</p>
<p><bold>Sarah Parsons </bold>Head of Medical Pay and Workforce, NHS Employers</p>
<p>number of experienced extended scope practitioners who again are attached to particular teams in the outpatient setting, and allow rotating registrars to see new or complex patients while being supervised by a consultant. This means trainees gain a lot from clinics as opposed to previous placements, where we have often been used as service fodder with little increase in subspecialty expertise over a six-month attachment. The ability for some</p>
<p>of the theatre staff to assist in theatre has greatly helped trainees choose which lists to attend to maximise educational benefit. This has been essential to support the consultants to carry out their lists, while also protecting registrar time off to meet contractual requirements.</p>
<p><BOLD>CONVERSATION IS KEY</BOLD></p>
<p>Think about how new roles could be used better in your own departments to improve both patient care and training. Initiate discussion with your consultants and feel free to openly agree or completely disagree with anything you have read in this article. What has you experience been? Please do write to the <italic>Bulletin </italic>to tell us about your experiences with the extended surgical team. Tell us about benefits you have experienced, anecdotes where the situation has been worsened, and ways in which you think the system could be improved.</p>
<p>For more information on EST visit www.rcseng.ac.uk/EST. We will also be publishing careers information and guidance later this year. If you have any comments on this piece, please write to bulletin&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk.</p>
<p><bold>RCS Accreditation &#x2013; part 2</bold></p>
<p><italic>The providers listed below have been recognised by the RCS as conforming to their standards of surgical education and training.</italic></p>
<p>COURSES AT ACCREDITED CENTRES	&#x00BB; Parastomal Hernia Course	Musgrove Park Post-CCT Fellowship in Bariatric and</p>
<p><italic>5 September 2017	</italic>Benign UGI Surgery</p>
<p>&#x00BB; PCNL Cadaveric Course &#x2013; day 1 of a 2-day course</p>
<p><italic>MATTU, Guildford	Musgrove Park Hospital, Taunton [re-approval]</italic></p>
<p><italic>2 October 2017</italic></p>
<p><italic>Newcastle Surgical Training Centre	</italic>RECENTLY ACCREDITED SURGICAL</p>
<p>RCS SENIOR CLINICAL FELLOWSHIP SCHEME:</p>
<p>EDUCATION CENTRES &#x00BB; Right Side Resection Course &#x2013; day 1 of a	RECENTLY APPROVED POSTS</p>
<p>2-day course	&#x00BB; Incision Academy &#x2013; online surgical</p>
<p>&#x00BB; Colchester Laparoscopic Colorectal Fellowship <italic>20 July 2017	</italic>education platform</p>
<p><italic>The ICENI Centre, Colchester [re-approval] WIMAT, Cardiff	https://www.incision.care/</italic></p>
<p>&#x00BB; The Frimley Park Hip Fellowship &#x00BB; Transanal Total Mesorectal Excision Course</p>
<p><italic>Frimley Park Hospital NHS Trust [re-approval] 11&#x2013;12 October 2017</italic></p>
<p><italic>ICENI Centre, Colchester</italic></p>
<p>RCS Quality Assurance and Accreditation Department | The Royal College of Surgeons of England | 35&#x2013;43 Lincoln&#x2019;s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3PE t: 020 7869 6236 | e: qa&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk | For further information: www.rcseng.ac.uk/surgeons/training/accreditation</p>
<p><bold>267</bold></p>
<p><bold>RESEARCH Bl</bold></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017</p>
<p><bold>The study of art and</bold></p>
<p><bold>its influence on the</bold></p>
<p><bold>education of surgeons</bold></p>
<p>A look back at some key figures in the crossover between the two disciplines.</p>
<p>AV Sterpetti1 Aggregate Professor of Surgery University of Rome M Ventura<sup>2</sup> Professor of Surgery University of L&#x2019;Aquila</p>
<p><BOLD>INTRODUCTION</BOLD></p>
<p>The study of art has the potential to refine and improve observational skills, communication ability and global perspectives, giving surgeons a spontaneous balance in a challenging style of work and life. In this study, we attempted to analyse observational and communication skills among residents in general surgery who had a special interest in art.</p>
<p><BOLD>MATERIAL AND METHODS</BOLD></p>
<p>Medical students in their final year <sc>(</sc><italic>n</italic><sc>=50) </sc>and residents in general surgery <sc>(</sc><italic>n</italic><sc>=30) </sc>at our medical centre were randomly selected; 15 residents and 25 medical students had a special interest in the arts (10 music, 15 classic literature, 15 history of art). The remaining 15 residents and 25 medical students had no special interest in the arts. Two independent staff surgeons reported a subjective judgement of their observational and communication skills. A subjective score was</p>
<p>used, from 0 to 10, with 10 as the best score (Ta ). All subjects gave informed consent and the study was approved by the Institution Board.</p>
<p><BOLD>RESULTS</BOLD></p>
<p>The 2 groups of residents shared similar characteristics: mean age (28 years), sex and family background. Residents who showed a special interest in the arts performed better in observational and communicative skills. The 2 groups of medical students were also similar in mean age (25 years), sex and family background. Medical students who had a special interest in the arts had better observational and communicative skills (Table 1).</p>
<p><BOLD>DISCUSSION</BOLD></p>
<p>An increasing number of neologisms are used to define the technological changes we see in everyday life and how they</p>
<p>- n &#x201E; 	i <italic>_</italic>ff .	l.		i	- . 1,2 <sc>ti	</sc>-	<sc>1a-</sc></p>
<p>influence and airect culture and society. <bold>1 </bold>he simultaneous</p>
<p><bold>PeerRev</bold></p>
<p><bold>Skills</bold>	<bold>Medical students</bold>	<bold>Residents</bold>	</p>
<p>	<bold>Interest</bold>	<bold>No interest</bold>	<bold>Interest</bold>	<bold>No interest</bold></p>
<p>Observational	6	5	9	7</p>
<p>Diagnostic	6	5	9	7</p>
<p>Communication	6	5.5	9	7</p>
<p>Research attitude	4	4.5	7	7</p>
<p><bold>Figure 1 </bold>Theodor Billroth (seated, centre) teaching his assistants</p>
<p>fear of and fascination with the developments in technology, and their effects on society, have constituted the background for new philosophical and creative thinking. In the 1970s, almost all universities introduced programmes in &#x2018;science, technology and society&#x2019; with the aim of analysing how technological innovations influence society from a broad perspective, including anthropology, history, political science and sociology.<sup>3,4</sup></p>
<p>The basis of judging any technological innovation and any attitude (including education), today is pragmatism &#x2013; a philosophical tradition defined and standardised at the end of the 19th century, but present in the human mind since antiquity.<sup>5</sup> Inevitably, in the pragmatic analysis of education, the study of art is going to be confined to the corner of &#x2018;something useless&#x2019;. In this paper we have tried to demonstrate how the study of art can be important in the education of surgeons, from a pragmatic and humanitarian point of view.</p>
<p><bold>The study of art to improve observational skills</bold></p>
<p>In all forms of art, from sculpture and literature to painting, details are essential. In analysing art, the student has to improve his or her capacity for looking at details, and using their imagination. This is a form of training for surgeons, and it can be highly useful in clinical practice. Observational skills can improve through the study of art, where interpretation is personal and subjective but still remains in the field</p>
<p>of rationality.<sup>6,7</sup></p>
<p><bold>The study of art helps communication</bold></p>
<p>Easy and valid communication is a cornerstone in medicine. Good communication skills are essential to facilitate collaboration among doctors and paramedics. Interpreta-<bold>Table 1 </bold>Mean score for medical students and residents</p>
<p>tion of art requires a fine, specific communication of your feelings and sensations. It is an exercise that helps refine language, which should be clear, precise, and at the same time rich in detail.<sup>8,9</sup> The study of art encourages imagination and innovation, whereas the study of medicine requires a logical, rational approach to problems and to their solution. Medical education is structured and analysed in examining tests, which determine the capability of the student to memorise accepted knowledge. There is no place for imagination or fantasy. The potential to improve upon accepted theories and create new ones requires many characteristics, including the ability to see alternatives and the courage to believe in your new ideas.</p>
<p>Art, in general, has always been the expression of people who were able to realise in painting, sculpture or music the contemporaneous general feeling, adding new ideas to the accepted status quo. The study and</p>
<p>in general surgery with a special interest in the arts</p>
<p>interpretation of these expressions emphasise the importance of your personal view, as a possible maker of new positive changes.<sup>6,7</sup></p>
<p><bold>The study of art gives importance to feelings and emotions</bold></p>
<p>The study of art revolves around emotions and feelings. It teaches the importance of those feelings in the history of human beings. Great ideas, strong feelings, and the courage to listen to our personal sensations have always survived the more transient factors such as economy, egotism and aggression. The pride in being what we want to be and listening to our sensations will make us better doctors who are better able to interact with our patients. The study of art can help us to find this courage. It is possible that we will be better prepared to control the many situations we have to face. We will be more likely to have the right answer and perspective in the inevitable situations when our professional and personal lives are affected</p>
<p>by the economy.<sup>10,11</sup></p>
<p><bold>How to prove this pedagogical hypothesis?</bold></p>
<p>Analysing how the study of art can positively influence medicine is very difficult. Too many variables are involved and it is difficult to define any eventual beneficial effect or</p>
<p><bold>269</bold></p>
<p><bold>PeerRev</bold></p>
<p>end results. Our study seems to confirm the above mentioned hypotheses. Here, we outline the history of some of the giants of modern surgery and their interest in the arts in general. The different surgeons were chosen because they were innovators in their specific field and in their own country. Owing to space limitations, we were unable to include many other giants of surgery who also had a special interest in the arts.</p>
<p><bold>John Hunter (1728&#x2013;1793)</bold></p>
<p>John Hunter is generally considered to be one of the innovators and fathers of modern surgery. One of his assistants described him as &#x2018;warm and impatient, readily provoked, and, when irritated, not easily soothed&#x2019;. Despite this, he married a poet, Anne Home, who asked him to judge all her work each day. In March 1790, he was made Surgeon General of the British Army. While in this position, he reformed the promotion of army surgeons so that it was based on merit and experience, rather than on the patronage-based system that had been in place.<sup>13</sup></p>
<p><bold>Edward Jenner (1749&#x2013;1823)</bold></p>
<p>Edward Jenner was very interested in classic literature, and he was fluent in Latin. He was</p>
<p><bold>Figure 2 </bold>Theodore Billroth teaching his students during surgery</p>
<p>a student of John Hunter and qualified in surgery in St George&#x2019;s Hospital in London. He was offered a position as a surgeon in London, but preferred to return to his home town in Gloucestershire, where he was appreciated as a family doctor and surgeon. He wrote books on many subjects, from romance to zoology. He was the pioneer of the smallpox vaccine, which was the world&#x2019;s first vaccine. Noting the common observation that milkmaids were generally immune to smallpox, Jenner thought that milkmaids could have been infected by cowpox, a mild disease, and for this reason they were</p>
<p><italic>The study of</italic></p>
<p><italic>art should be</italic></p>
<p><italic>encouraged in</italic></p>
<p><italic>high school and</italic></p>
<p><italic>college, especially</italic></p>
<p><italic>in students eager to get into medical school</italic></p>
<p>immune to smallpox. He is considered the &#x2018;father of clinical immunology&#x2019; and his work is said to have saved more lives than that of any other human being.<sup>14</sup></p>
<p><bold>Joseph Lister (1827&#x2013;1902)</bold></p>
<p>Joseph Lister had a special passion for literature, including German and French literature &#x2013; to the extent that he could read and speak German and French fluently. In hospitals, surgery was practised in insanitary conditions. There were no facilities for handwashing, either for the surgeons or the patients. A surgeon was not required to wash his hands because it was considered not necessary to prevent infection. Surgeons, often</p>
<p>washed their hands in the same dish without changing the water from one operation to another and at the end of day they took pride in the dark colour of the water as sign of their hard work.</p>
<p>In 1867 Lister championed the use of carbolic acid (phenol) as an antiseptic, which became the first widely used antiseptic in surgery. He made antisepsis a must in all procedures before, during, and after the operation. He is considered to be one of the fathers of modern surgery.<sup>15</sup></p>
<p><bold>Theodor Billroth (1829&#x2013;1894)</bold></p>
<p>Theodor Billroth is thought of as the father of modern abdominal and oncological surgery. He was an indifferent student and spent much of his time playing the piano and the violin. Once he had obtained his medical degree, he worked in Berlin as assistant to Karl Langenbuch from 1860 to 1867. First he was director of the surgical hospital in Zurich, and later director of the Vienna General Hospital. He stressed the importance of applying science and rationale to surgery. He strongly supported the publication of the results of surgery &#x2013; whether they were good or bad &#x2013; and introduced the need for audits. He also introduced the use of white coats for doctors. Billroth underlined the importance of the gradual training of surgeons through a &#x2018;residency programme&#x2019;, as introduced by his teacher Karl Langenbuch (Figure 1). Many surgeons from all over the world, including William Halsted and Theodor Kocher (a future Nobel Prize winner), visited and worked with Billroth, and all introduced the German surgical residency programme (Figure 2). He performed the first oesophagectomy, the first laryngec-tomy and the first gastrectomy. He was also a talented pianist and violinist. He became close friend of Brahms, one of the greatest composers of the time. Brahms sent all his original musical scores to ask Billroth&#x2019;s opinion. In a letter, Billroth wrote: &#x2018;It is one of the superficialities of our time to see in science and art two opposite. Imagination is the mother of both.&#x2019;<sup>16</sup></p>
<p><bold>270</bold></p>
<p><bold>PeerRev</bold></p>
<p><bold>Figure 3 </bold>Durante&#x2019;s Department of Surgery at the University Hospital Policlinico Umberto I; the bas relief shows Lister, with whom Durante trained, teaching his students (Source: Author)</p>
<p><bold>Howard Atwood Kelly (1858&#x2013;1943)</bold></p>
<p>Howard Atwood Kelly is considered to be the founder of modern gynaecology. He was very much interested in literature and theology. Kelly was educated at the University of Pennsylvania and then became a member of the faculty of medicine at McGill University in Canada. He travelled to Europe to visit the most important surgeons interested in gynaecology. During his subsequent long career at Johns Hopkins Hospital in Baltimore, he developed many new operations and instruments, such as the cystoscope. He was one of the first to treat cancer with radium and founded the Kelly Clinic, which was a leading centre for radiation therapy. He was a close friend of Henry Luis Mencken, considered one of the most influential American writers and prose stylists of the first half of the 20th century. Kelly wrote numerous medical textbooks and several theological and philosophical books.<sup>17</sup></p>
<p><bold>Francesco Durante (1844&#x2013;1934)</bold></p>
<p>Francesco Durante is considered the founder of modern surgery in Italy. After his graduation, he worked in Europe with Billroth and Lister. He founded the Italian Society of Surgery and he wrote a three-volume surgical textbook, which was at the basis of all surgical procedures in Italy for almost 50 years. He was the first to report a successful removal of a brain meningioma. Together with Guido Baccelli, he helped to plan and found the University Hospital Policlinico Umberto I, which became one of the most</p>
<p>important surgical centres in Italy. In designing the hospital, Durante took into consideration all the notions about aseptic surgery that he had learned while he was working with Lister and many details used in the building of the Johns Hopkins Hospital, which he saw in construction when he was invited to give a talk in the US about his successful operation of brain meningioma removal. He introduced the English nursing system developed by Florence Nightingale and hired Dorothy Snell, an English nurse he met while he was in England, to teach and lead the nurses in his hospital. Durante was supposed to become an artist. He was a talented sculptor and painter, and he originally went to Messina to study art. He was urged by the professor of medicine to study his subject instead. With the help of other artists, he created the bas relief that decorates his department, which shows Lister teaching his students (Figure 3).<sup>18,19</sup></p>
<p><bold>Harvey Cushing (1869&#x2013;1939)</bold></p>
<p>Harvey Cushing is considered to be the father of modern neurosurgery. His contributions to surgery and neurosurgery are impressive. Cushing was interested in painting and literature. He was awarded the 1926 Pulitzer Prize for biography or autobiography for his book recounting the life of Sir William Osler, one of the fathers of modern medicine. The book received the prize because it was a deep study of the relationships between medicine and society, disease and modernity, with a strong thread of anthropology and philosophy. Cushing was also an excellent painter. He drew the majority of the anatomical drawings for his textbooks and papers (Figures 4a and b) and also painted numerous paintings on various subjects (Figure 5).<sup>20</sup></p>
<p><bold>Rudolph Matas (1860&#x2013;1957)</bold></p>
<p>Born to a family who had emigrated from Spain, Rudolph Matas became a Professor and Chairman of the Department of Surgery at Tulane University. He is considered the father of modern vascular surgery. As a</p>
<p><bold>Figure 4a </bold>Cushing&#x2019;s drawing of the brain (1906; Cushing Center, Yale)</p>
<p>medical student, he was sent to Cuba as a laboratory assistant and interpreter with the US Yellow Fever Commission, in times when yellow fever was a serious problem. Matas spoke fluent Spanish and was immune to yellow fever because he had already contracted the disease. Matas openly supported the theory proposed by Carlos Finley that the mosquito was the vector of the disease, which was subsequently proved to be correct.</p>
<p>Matas used spinal anaesthesia for the first time in the US. He also developed the</p>
<p><bold>Figure 4b </bold>Cushing&#x2019;s drawing of the brain (1906; Cushing Center, Yale)</p>
<p><bold>271</bold></p>
<p><bold>RESEARCH PeerRev</bold></p>
<p>intravenous drip and introduced endotrache-al intubation with positive-pressure ventilation. He loved literature and the new art of &#x2018;cinema&#x2019;. His library was immense, so that he had to give many of his books to the Library of Tulane University, which he established and funded. He was a poet, and many of his poems were also published in medical journals. His dearest friend was Lafcadio Hearn, a writer. He was a close friend of William Halsted, who defined Matas as &#x2018;a great innovator&#x2019; and of Will Mayo, who said that he was &#x2018;the world&#x2019;s best-educated physician&#x2019;.<sup>21</sup></p>
<p><bold>Henry Mondor (1885&#x2013;1962)</bold></p>
<p>Henry Mondor was an innovator in surgery. He practised as a professor of surgery in Paris and published many textbooks of medicine and surgery and represented the teaching centre in the dynamic and innovative French school of surgery. He was an excellent artist and drew all the illustrations for his medical textbooks. He received several prizes for his drawings. He was the mentor of future</p>
<p><bold>Figure 5 </bold>A painting by Cushing, completed during his visit to the town of Coudes in France (circa 1900; Cushing Center, Yale)</p>
<p>famous surgeons and artists, such as Charles Dubost (a pioneer of cardiac surgery) and Jean Labellie (a famous abstract painter). He wrote also many books on poetry, literature and philosophy and was also editor of cultural and surgical journals.<sup>22</sup></p>
<p><bold>Michael DeBakey (1908&#x2013;2008)</bold></p>
<p>Michael DeBakey spoke fluent German, French and Arabic. He was a military surgeon from 1942 to 1946 during World War II and helped to develop the mobile army surgical hospital, for which he received the Legion of Merit. After the war, he joined the Baylor College of Medicine. Under his leadership, Baylor College of Medicine became the leading centre for the development of cardiovascular surgery and medicine in the world. His innovations are astonishing. He created the roller pump, which provided continuous blood flow during surgery. He was the first to use polyester as a patch and was one of the first to perform coronary artery bypass grafting. He was probably the first to perform a &#x2018;standard&#x2019; carotid endarterectomy, and first to report the successful resection of a thoracoabdominal aneurysm. He did extensive research on the implantation of the artificial heart, together with Denton Cooley. He established the DeBakey Medical Foundation to support the Texas Children&#x2019;s Cancer Center.</p>
<p>DeBakey was interested in literature and music and was an excellent saxophonist. His mother was an accomplished seamstress, who also taught sewing classes. His mother taught him to knit and sew. At the age of ten, DeBakey could cut his own shirts and paints from patterns and assemble them, and repair any subsequent tears.</p>
<p><bold>Thomas Earl Starzl (b. 1926)</bold></p>
<p>Thomas Starzl is a pioneer of modern transplantation. He performed the first successful liver transplantation in humans; he standardised the technique for successful kidney transplant and he understood and made rational the exact role of immunotherapy in transplantation. He completely changed ideas</p>
<p>about immunotherapy, defining the concept of &#x2018;chimerism&#x2019;. He performed the first simultaneous heart and liver transplantation. His studies in xenografting are revolutionary.</p>
<p>Stanzl has a great interested in humanist studies and literature. As an adolescent, he worked in the local newspaper edited by his father, doing almost any kind of job. Later, to support his medical studies, he worked in his free time in another journal, mainly as a proofreader. He wanted to became a priest, but after his mother died at age 47, he decided to dedicate his life to help sick people. He has been always interested in literature, anthropology and sociology, and is fascinated by other cultures. His book, <italic>The Puzzle People</italic>, was named by the <italic>Wa l l Street Journal </italic>as one of the best books on doctors&#x2019; lives. In this book, Starzl underlines the many challenges for surgery in the future, analysing not only the scientific aspects of the work but also the moral and sociological view in a developing society.<sup>24</sup></p>
<p><BOLD>CONCLUSIONS</BOLD></p>
<p>The study of art can undoubtedly help surgeons in several ways, including the possibility of finding the right personal balance in the continuous challenges we are forced to face when our personal feelings are in contrast with the emerging &#x2013; and sometimes oppressing &#x2013; forces of economy, efficiency and pragmatism. The study of art should be encouraged in high school and college, especially in students eager to get into medical school.</p>
<p><bold>References</bold></p>
<p>1. Bjiker WJ, Hughes TP, Pinch T, Douglas DG. <italic>The Social Construction of Technological Systems: New directions in the sociology and history of technology. </italic>Cambridge: MT Press; 2012.</p>
<p>2. Bohman J. The coming age of deliberative democracy. <italic>J Political Philosophy </italic>1998; 6: 400&#x2013;425.</p>
<p>3. Ryfe DM. Does deliberative democracy work? <italic>Ann Rev Political Sci </italic>2005; 8: 63&#x2013;64.</p>
<p>4. Woodhouse E, Sarewitz D. Science policies for reducing societal inequities. <italic>Science and Public Policy </italic>2007; <bold>34</bold>: 139&#x2013;150.</p>
<p>5. Winner L. <italic>Artifacts/Ideas and political culture. </italic>In: Teich A, ed. <italic>Technology and the Future</italic>, 6th ed. New York: St Martin&#x2019;s Press; 1993, pp283&#x2013;292.</p>
<p><bold>272</bold></p>
<p><bold>PeerRev RESEARCH</bold></p>
<p><bold>273</bold></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.274</p>
<p><bold>Re-evaluation</bold></p>
<p><bold>of three-session</bold></p>
<p><bold>theatre efficiency</bold></p>
<p>How does it compare with the 2S system?</p>
<p>AS Nadig Senior Registrar in Neurosurgery</p>
<p>ID Kamaly-Asl Consultant Paediatric Neurosurgeon</p>
<p>Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust Hospital</p>
<p><BOLD>T</BOLD></p>
<p>he first decade of the new millennium brought in a vast amount of changes in the National Health Service (NHS). There has been a need and constant drive towards efficiency and savings. Theatre utilisation has become the principal managerial measure of theatre performance across trusts in the UK.<sup>1</sup> In 2002 the Modernisation Agency published its <italic>Step Guide to Improving Theatre Performance</italic><sup>2</sup> while the Audit Commission reported on operating theatres in 2002 and 2003.<sup>3,4</sup> Theatre utilisation of 84&#x0025; has been considered an acceptable standard of theatre practice.<sup>4</sup></p>
<p>Trusts across the country have taken measures to meet the national targets such as a reduction in waiting list times for elective surgery. Enhancing theatre capacity is a key step in reducing total waiting times to under 18 weeks.<sup>1</sup> The regular two-session (2S) theatre lists have been increasingly replaced by three-session (3S) lists. The aim of this study was to compare the efficiency of 3S theatre days and 2S days at the Greater Manchester Neuroscience Centre in Salford.</p>
<p><BOLD>METHODS</BOLD></p>
<p>Data were analysed retrospectively. The initial evaluation period covered nine months (August 2007 &#x2013; April 2008). Three neuro-surgical firms with separate subspecialty interests (pituitary, vascular and oncology) were identified. The number of patients, theatre utilisation, operative time, time between cases and case mix for 3S and 2S theatre days were compared. The re-evaluation period comprised six months (February &#x2013; August 2010). Similar data collection and analysis was carried out for the same three firms.</p>
<p>Each theatre session comprised 3.5 hours (210 minutes). Theatre utilisation time was defined as the total time from the first patient on the list arriving in the department to the last patient leaving theatre to go to the recovery ward. Operative time was defined as the total anaesthetic and surgical time. The time between cases was defined as the time between a patient leaving to go to the recovery ward following surgery and the arrival of the next patient in the anaesthetic room.</p>
<p><bold>274</bold></p>
<p><bold>PeerRev RESEARCH</bold></p>
<p><bold>Table 1 </bold>Comparison of three-session (3S) and two-session (2S) theatre days in 2007&#x2013;2008 evaluation period</p>
<p><bold>2007&#x2013;2008</bold>	<bold>Number of theatre days</bold>	<bold>Number of sessions</bold>	<bold>Number of cases</bold>	<bold>Average cases per session</bold>	<italic><bold>p</italic>-value<italic></bold></italic>	<bold>Theatre utilisation</bold>	<bold>Operative time</bold>	<bold>Time</bold></p>
<p><bold>between</bold></p>
<p><bold>cases</bold>	<italic><bold>p</italic>-value<italic></bold></italic></p>
<p>3S	65	195	236	1.2	0.14	89&#x0025;	50&#x0025;	12&#x0025;	0.07</p>
<p>2S	71	140	179	1.3		98&#x0025;	54&#x0025;	10&#x0025;	</p>
<p><bold>Table 2 </bold>Comparison of three-session (3S) and two-session (2S) theatre days in 2010 evaluation period</p>
<p><bold>2010</bold>	<bold>Number of theatre days</bold>	<bold>Number of sessions</bold>	<bold>Number of cases</bold>	<bold>Average cases per session</bold>	<italic><bold>p</italic>-value<italic></bold></italic>	<bold>Theatre utilisation</bold>	<bold>Operative time</bold>	<bold>Time between cases</bold>	<italic><bold>p</italic>-value<italic></bold></italic></p>
<p>3S	71	213	255	1.2	0.02	93&#x0025;	55&#x0025;	9&#x0025;	0.21</p>
<p>2S	41	74	85	1.1		91&#x0025;	51&#x0025;	8&#x0025;	</p>
<p><bold>Table 3 </bold>Comparison of underutilised lists for three-session (3S) and two-session (2S) theatre days</p>
<p>	<bold>Underutilised lists</bold>	<bold>Average underutilised time</bold>	</p>
<p>	<bold>3S</bold>	<bold>2S</bold>	<bold>3S</bold>	<bold>2S</bold>	<italic><bold>p</italic>-value<italic></bold></italic></p>
<p>2007&#x2013;2008	47 (72&#x0025;)	34 (48&#x0025;)	103 mins	108 mins	0.80</p>
<p>2010	47 (66&#x0025;)	27 (66&#x0025;)	61 mins	112 mins	0.002</p>
<p>	<bold>Overrun lists</bold>		<bold>Average overrun time</bold>	</p>
<p>	<bold>3S</bold>	<bold>2S</bold>	<bold>3S</bold>	<bold>2S</bold>	<italic><bold>p</italic>-value<italic></bold></italic></p>
<p>2007&#x2013;2008	17 (26&#x0025;)	36 (51&#x0025;)	42 mins	88 mins	0.02</p>
<p>2010	24 (34&#x0025;)	14 (34&#x0025;)	34 mins	66 mins	0.06</p>
<p>	<bold>Spinal cases</bold>	<bold>Cranial cases</bold>	<bold>Local anaesthetic cases</bold></p>
<p>	<bold>3S</bold>	<bold>2S</bold>	<bold>3S</bold>	<bold>2S</bold>	<bold>3S</bold>	<bold>2S</bold></p>
<p>2007&#x2013;2008	40&#x0025;	50&#x0025;	40&#x0025;	26&#x0025;	19&#x0025;	24&#x0025;</p>
<p>2010	45&#x0025;	58&#x0025;	39&#x0025;	34&#x0025;	16&#x0025;	8&#x0025;</p>
<p><bold>Table 4 </bold>Comparison of overrun lists for three-session (3S) and two-session (2S) theatre days</p>
<p><bold>Table 5 </bold>Comparison of case mix for three-session (3S) and two-session (2S) theatre days</p>
<p><BOLD>RESULTS</BOLD></p>
<p>In the 2007&#x2013;2008 evaluation period, there were 65 theatre days using the 3S system (195 sessions in total) and 71 days with the 2S system (140 sessions in total because the 2S lists were converted to single-session lists on two occasions) (Table 1). On 3S days, there was a mean of 1.2 cases per session compared with 1.3 cases on 2S days (t-test, p=0.14).</p>
<p>During the 2010 evaluation period, there were 71 days with 3S lists (213 sessions) and 41 days with 2S lists (74 sessions) (Table 2). The mean number of cases operated on per session were 1.2 and 1.1 respectively (t-test, <italic>p=</italic>0.02).</p>
<p><bold>Theatre utilisation</bold></p>
<p>In the initial evaluation period, total theatre utilisation amounted to 89&#x0025; on 3S days compared with 98&#x0025; on 2S days (Table 1). The time between cases took up 12&#x0025; of the total time for 3S and 10&#x0025; for 2S lists (t-test, p=0.07). For the 3S system, the total operative time comprised 50&#x0025; of the time available; on 2S days, this comprised 54&#x0025; of the time. Almost three-quarters (72&#x0025;) of the 3S days were underutilised compared with just under half (48&#x0025;) of the 2S days (Table 3). The mean duration of underutilisation on 3S days was 103 minutes whereas for 2S days, it was 108 minutes (t-test, p=0.80). A quarter (26&#x0025;) of 3S days overran compared with half (51&#x0025;) of 2S days (Table 4). The mean overrunning time was 42 minutes on 3S days and 88 minutes on 2S days (t-test, p=0.002).</p>
<p>In the second evaluation period, 93&#x0025; of the total time available in theatre was utilised on 3S days compared with 91&#x0025; on 2S days (Table 2). The time between cases took up 9&#x0025; of the total time for 3S and 8&#x0025; for 2S lists (t-test, <italic>p=</italic>0.21). The total operative time comprised 55&#x0025; of the time available on 3S days and 51&#x0025; on 2S days. Two-thirds (66&#x0025;) of both the 3S and 2S days were underutilised (Table 3). The 3S days were underutilised by a mean of 61 minutes compared with 112 minutes for 2S days (t-test, <italic>p=</italic>0.002). A third (34&#x0025;) of both the 3S and 2S days overran (Table 4). 3S days overran by a mean of 34 minutes and 2S days by a mean of 66 minutes (t-test, <italic>p=</italic>0.06).</p>
<p>The breakdown for case mix (cranial, spinal and local anaesthetic cases) in the two time periods evaluated is shown in Table 5.</p>
<p><BOLD>DISCUSSION</BOLD></p>
<p>Theatre efficiency can be defined by appropriate theatre time utilisation (minimising overrunning and underutilisation) with a greater amount of time spent on performing procedures and less time taken up between cases. Underutilisation could be due to late starts, early finishes or more time in between cases. The surgical skills, experience and technical challenges also vary between surgeons and their case mix. These factors can influence the productivity of each oper-</p>
<p><bold>275</bold></p>
<p><bold>PeerRev</bold></p>
<p>ating session but are difficult to standardise. Nevertheless, with theatre-list planning and well-organised use of existing resources, efficiency can be increased. This can only have a positive influence on the overall productivity of theatre sessions.</p>
<p>Underutilisation of any theatre session is a form of financial waste and represents a missed opportunity to decrease waiting times for surgery. Overrunning, however, is also not sensible as it can have an adverse impact on staff morale, possibly causing problems with staff retention. This can lead to a greater requirement for agency staff, adding to the financial burden in the NHS. Furthermore, an overrunning list can affect other theatres as it puts extra pressure on staff distribution among the running theatre lists.</p>
<p>In recent years in our department, there has been an increase in use of the 3S over the 2S theatre system. There were more 3S days during the 6 months of the second evaluation period than during the 9 months of the first evaluation period.</p>
<p>In our trust, a computerised theatre patient flow system has been implemented. The current version came into use in 2009. The journey of a patient is timed and recorded for each segment of his or her pathway. It is broken down into individual times from point of arrival of a patient at theatre reception to transfer from the recovery area to his or her postoperative bed. The anaesthetic start time, time of arrival of the patient in the operating room, surgical start time, surgical finish time, time of patient moving out of the theatre to the recovery area are also documented. From this data, average times can be calculated for each case type and each individual surgeon over time. This information is used in the weekly theatre list meetings to plan the utilisation of theatre sessions.</p>
<p>In the initial evaluation period, 3S lists were still in their early phase of implementation. There appeared to be a general perception among theatre teams that the increased theatre time in the 3S system led to a lower impetus to move on between cases. There was a trend towards a greater proportion of theatre time consisting of time between cases with the 3S compared with the 2S system and the productivity per session was better on 2S theatre days (Table 1). However, 2S days overran frequently (Table 4) and so more cases were performed, with greater utilisation and operative time (Table 1). There was also a trend towards underutilisation of</p>
<p><italic>Underutilisation</italic></p>
<p><italic>could be due to late</italic></p>
<p><italic>starts, early finishes</italic></p>
<p><italic>or more time in</italic></p>
<p><italic>between cases</italic></p>
<p>theatre sessions on 3S days (Table 3), with uncertainty over how many operations could be performed over the three sessions.</p>
<p>By the second evaluation period, there was an update for the patient flow system software. The data collected were used extensively in the weekly theatre session planning meetings. This appears to have had a positive influence on theatre planning for 3S lists. Over time, the theatre teams seem to have become more familiar with the 3S system. Theatre utilisation improved (from 89&#x0025; to 93&#x0025;), the proportion of time taken up between cases reduced (from 12&#x0025; to 9&#x0025;) and there was a significant drop</p>
<p>in the proportion of underutilised lists (from 72&#x0025; to 66&#x0025;). Although there was an increase in the proportion of theatre lists overrunning, there was a drop in the average duration of overrun time (from 42 minutes to 34 minutes.</p>
<p>For 2S days on the other hand, there was an increase over time in the proportion of lists being underutilised as well as in the average duration of underutilisation time (Table 3). There was also still evidence of overrun lists (Table 4).</p>
<p>It is hard to say with certainty what factors changed between the two time periods evaluated to account for the relative changes in theatre efficiency. It is likely that there were multiple influences causing this effect. Our perception is that familiarisation with the practice, better planning, smoother running of the theatre and the expectations of the 3S system were important in this change.</p>
<p><BOLD>CONCLUSIONS</BOLD></p>
<p>Theatre days with 3S lists have the potential to be more efficient than the 2S system. The influence of familiarisation by theatre personnel and theatre planning should be considered. An internal evaluation to review the suitability of such theatre expansion for each surgical specialty should be encouraged.</p>
<p><bold>References</bold></p>
<p>1. Faiz O, Tekkis P, McGuire A <italic>et al</italic>. Is theatre utilization a valid performance indicator for NHS operating theatres? <italic>BMC Health Serv Res </italic>2008, 8: 28.</p>
<p>2. NHS Modernisation Agency. <italic>Step Guide to Improving Operating Theatre Performance. </italic>London: NHS Modernisation Agency; 2002.</p>
<p>3. Audit Commission. <italic>Operating Theatres: A Bulletin for Health Bodies. </italic>London: AC; 2002.</p>
<p>4. Audit Commission. <italic>Operating Theatres: Review of National Findings. </italic>London: AC; 2003.</p>
<p><bold>276</bold></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.277</p>
<p>This month in the</p>
<p><bold>^1</bold></p>
<p>Annals...</p>
<p>Access the Annals online at: http://publishing.rcseng.ac.uk/ann</p>
<p><bold>The <italic>Annals </italic>at 70</bold></p>
<p>To celebrate 70 years of the <italic>Annals</italic>, we are re-publishing the whole of the first issue, published in July 1947. The issue can be accessed here: http://publishing.rcseng.ac.uk/toc/ann/1/1</p>
<p>The contents of that first issue are:</p>
<p>Foreword <italic>Webb-Johnson</italic></p>
<p>Thomas Vicary Lecture: The Renaissance and its Influence on English Medicine Surgery and Public Health <italic>MacNalty</italic></p>
<p>Gangrene: Lecture delivered at The Royal College of Surgeons of England on 10 April 1947 <italic>Mitchiner</italic></p>
<p>A Hundred Years of Gastric Surgery An expanded version of an address delivered at the Centenary Meeting of the American Medical Association at Atlantic City on 11 June 1947 <italic>Ogilvie</italic></p>
<p>The Library During the War <italic>Fanu</italic></p>
<p>The Past, Present and Future of the</p>
<p>Museum of Pathology</p>
<p><italic>Willis</italic></p>
<p>Anaesthesia Centenary</p>
<p><bold>Editorial</bold></p>
<p>Seventy years of academic surgery</p>
<p><italic>Tim Lane</italic></p>
<p>A letter to Sir Heneage Ogilvie</p>
<p><italic>Tom Holme</italic></p>
<p>A letter to Major-General Philip Mitchiner</p>
<p><italic>Fiona Myint</italic></p>
<p><bold>Hunterian lecture</bold></p>
<p>The evolution of acute burn care &#x2013; retiring</p>
<p>the split skin graft</p>
<p><italic>Greenwood</italic></p>
<p><bold>Review</bold></p>
<p>The role of antimicrobial sutures in preventing surgical site infection <italic>Leaper </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Hip surgery</bold></p>
<p>Predictors of direct home discharge following fractured neck of femur <italic>Salar </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Trauma and orthopaedics</bold></p>
<p>Diagnostic use of intramedullary reaming biopsy in metastatic long bone disease <italic>Afinowi </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Colorectal surgery</bold></p>
<p>Sex differences in the splenic flexure <italic>Brookes </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Surgical sepsis</bold></p>
<p>The effect of stage of HIV disease as determined by CD<sup>4</sup> count on clinical outcomes of surgical sepsis in South Africa <italic>Green </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Plastic surgery</bold></p>
<p>Lengthening the pedicle of the rectus abdominis myocutaneous flap for repair of upper chest and neck defects <italic>Zhang </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Upper GI surgery</bold></p>
<p>Superior mesenteric artery syndrome: a single centre experience of laparoscopic duodenojejunostomy as the operation of choice <italic>Kirby </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Orthopaedic surgery</bold></p>
<p>A novel use of QR code stickers after orthopaedic cast application <italic>Gough </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Endocrine surgery</bold></p>
<p>Comparison of prognostic scoring systems in follicular thyroid cancer <italic>Te o </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Paediatric surgery</bold></p>
<p>Glisson&#x2019;s capsule cauterisation is associated with increased postoperative pain after laparoscopic cholecystectomy: a prospective case&#x2013;control study <italic>Basak </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>General surgery</bold></p>
<p>Selective non-operative management of abdominal stab wounds is a safe and cost effective strategy: A South African experience <italic>Dayananda </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>Lower GI surgery</bold></p>
<p>Intravenous fluid and electrolyte administration in elective gastrointestinal surgery: mechanisms of excessive therapy <italic>Simpson </italic>et al</p>
<p><bold>277</bold></p>
<p><bold>Emergency laparotomy, the ELC and quality improvement</bold></p>
<p>A look at what is being done to reduce morbidity and mortality in 29 hospitals in England.</p>
<p>G Aggarwal Anaesthetic Clinical Research Fellow</p>
<p>N Quiney Consultant Anaesthetist</p>
<p>Royal Surrey County Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.278</p>
<p><bold>&#x2018;T</bold></p>
<p>here is no failure except in no</p>
<p>longer trying.&#x2019;</p>
<p>Elbert Green Hubbard (1856&#x2013;1915). Emergency laparotomy has historically been a little-studied area of anaesthetic or surgical practice. The results of recent UK and international audits<sup>1,2</sup> and the publication of a timely report commissioned by The Royal College of Surgeons of England<sup>3</sup> has concentrated attention on the standards of care delivered in our hospitals to patients admitted for emergency laparotomy.</p>
<p>The overall results are startling. Mortality rates of between 14&#x0025; and 19&#x0025; have been reported from the UK, the US and Denmark.<sup>1,2,4</sup> Patients above the age of 80 years may have a mortality rate as high as 45&#x0025;.<sup>5</sup> Complications from sepsis remain the leading cause of death, followed by overwhelming malignancy. On top of the burdens arising from excess mortality rates, morbidity and prolonged hospital stay are not uncommon, adding to the financial demands such patients pose.</p>
<p><bold>278</bold></p>
<p><bold>PeerRev RESEARCH</bold></p>
<p>ros allowing clinicians to create run charts from their NELA data are available, together with publications, videos and other material. Participating hospitals will also shortly be able to compare their own performance of key metrics and outcomes across all 29 hospitals in the ELC.</p>
<p>The collaborative is being run using a tool known as the Model for Improvement. This</p>
<p>The first report by the National Emergency Laparotomy Audit (NELA) was published in 2015.<sup>6</sup> Although seen by many as common basic care of patients, a significant proportion of patients with overt sepsis still do not receive timely antibiotics within one hour of identification of sepsis. Access to emergency theatres is patchy, especially for patients deemed to be category 2a (urgent: surgery within 2&#x2013;6 hours). Fluid resuscitation is carried out in an unscientific way and intensive care unit admission is inconsistent. Consultant (both anaesthetic and surgical) involvement at night and weekends remains poor.</p>
<p>Evidence is now emerging about what strategies might be useful in addressing some of these issues. Two publications highlight the use of a care pathway to improve outcomes. A study from Denmark on patients undergoing emergency surgery for peptic ulcer perforation found a 30&#x0025; reduction in mortality<sup>7</sup> whereas the Emergency Laparotomy Pathway Quality Improvement Care bundle project (ELPQuIC)<sup>8</sup> showed a 25&#x0025; reduction in crude in-hospital mortality. The results of the EPOCH (Enhanced Peri-Operative Care for High-risk patients) trial are eagerly awaited, as are the results of a similar study in Sweden.</p>
<p>However, further efforts are already being carried out to reduce mortality and morbidity in patients admitted for emergency lapa-rotomy in 29 hospitals in England (Figure 1). This &#x2018;Emergency Laparotomy Collaborative&#x2019; (ELC) is being run as a two-year quality improvement project funded by the Health Foundation. The project not only aims to reduce mortality rates in patients undergoing emergency laparotomy but also to equip participants with a basic understanding of quality improvement methodology and develop locally based Academic Health Science Networks (AHSNs) of quality improvement and collaboration.</p>
<p>Much of the information for this project is available online (www.emergencylaparotomy. org.uk/). A care-bundle approach based on the original ELPQuIC publication<sup>8</sup> is being used with slight modifications. Excel&#x00AE; mac-</p>
<p><bold>Figure 1 </bold>Poster for hospitals participating in the Emergency Laparotomy Collaborative</p>
<p>was developed by the Associates in Process Improvement and derived from work by Shewhart and Deming.<sup>9</sup></p>
<p>The consideration of an individual hospital&#x2019;s process mapping, the development of driver diagrams and the increasing use of run charts (Figure 2) has prompted participating trusts to understand the systems in which they work, and to try new ways to improve</p>
<p><bold>279</bold></p>
<p><bold>PeerRev</bold></p>
<p><bold>Figure 2 </bold>Milestones for hospitals participating in the Emergency Laparotomy Collaborative</p>
<p><bold>References</bold></p>
<p>1. Saunders DI, Murray D, Pichel AD <italic>et al</italic>. Variations in mortality after emergency laparotomy: the first report of the UK Emergency Laparotomy Network. <italic>Br J Anaesth </italic>2012; 109: 368&#x2013;375.</p>
<p>2. Al-Temimi MH, Griffee M, Enniss TM <italic>et al</italic>. When is death inevitable after emergency laparotomy? Analysis of the American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program database. <italic>J Am Coll Surg </italic>2012; 215: 503&#x2013;511.</p>
<p>3. Nuffield Trust. <italic>Emergency General Surgery: Challenges and Opportunities. </italic>London: Nuffield Trust; 2016.</p>
<p>4. Vester-Andersen M, Lundstr&#x00F8;m H, M&#x00F8;ller MH <italic>et al</italic>. Mortality and postoperative care pathways after emergency gastrointestinal surgery in 2904 patients: a population-based cohort study. <italic>Br J Anaesth </italic>2014; 112: 860&#x2013;870.</p>
<p>5. Green G, Shaikh I, Fernandes R, Wegstapel H. Emergency laparotomy in octogenarians: a 5-year study of morbidity and mortality. <italic>World J Gastrointest Surg </italic>2013; 5: 216&#x2013;221.</p>
<p>6. Royal College of Anaesthetists <italic>The First Patient Report of the National Emergency Laparotomy Audit</italic>. London: RCoA; 2015.</p>
<p>7. M&#x00F8;ller MH, Adamsen S, Thomsen RW, M&#x00F8;ller AM.</p>
<p>Multicentre trial of a perioperative protocol to reduce mortality in patients with peptic ulcer perforation. <italic>Br J Surg </italic>2011; 98: 802&#x2013;810.</p>
<p>8. Huddart S, Peden CJ, Swart M. Use of a pathway quality improvement care bundle to reduce mortality after emergency laparotomy. <italic>Br J Surg </italic>2015; 102: 57&#x2013;66.</p>
<p>9. Langley GJ, Moen RD, Nolan KM et al. <italic>The Improvement Guide. </italic>2nd edn. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass; 2009.</p>
<p>the standard of delivery of care and reduce mortality rates. The ELC launched in September 2015 with a plenary day-long meeting (120 delegates). At the meeting, the &#x2018;current state of play&#x2019; was reviewed, as was the evidence base for the proposed bundle intervention. Subsequent plenary meetings have addressed sepsis, leadership, care of the elderly laparotomy patient, variation and sustainability.</p>
<p>Interspersed between the cross-collaborative events are more local AHSN meetings</p>
<p>of approximately 6&#x2013;14 hospitals. This is the real opportunity for trusts to present their own performance and share areas of success or ongoing difficulty. The local learning networks that are now being formed are crucial to the continuing success of the project and will hopefully continue once the collaborative has ended in July 2017.</p>
<p>For more information, please contact the Emergency Laparotomy Network at rsc-tr.emergencylaparotomy&#x0040;nhs.net</p>
<p><bold>280</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>LEGA L</BOLD></p>
<p>Cross-examination</p>
<p>Each month we take a close look at a recent legal case with implications for the surgical profession.</p>
<p>Consent for a cannula</p>
<p><bold>Robert Wheeler, Director, Department of Clinical Law, University Hospital Southampton</bold></p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.281</p>
<p>n a recent judgement, the Court of Appeal reminded clinicians of the vital importance of consent.</p>
<p>A 64-year-old lady was lying in the resuscitation room of an emergency department in London while an SHO was proposing to insert a cannula into her left arm. This was necessary because she had a suspected fracture of her right humerus. The doctor was concerned that intravenous fluids and pain relief might soon be required. Judging the injured arm to be unsuitable for cannulation, he wished instead to insert the line on the left. Ms Border refused, explaining that she had recently undergone left mastectomy and axillary clearance. She had been forewarned by her oncologists of the risks of lymphoe-dema following infection of cuts in the skin of her left arm. The doctor considered alternative sites of cannulation, including the legs, but owing to her general physical condition could not find a suitable vein. In what the court found to be a &#x2018;quick and silent calculation on his part&#x2019;, the SHO dismissed the alternative sites and, despite the patient&#x2019;s insistence, the cannula was placed in the post-mastectomy left arm without her consent. The cannula was not then immediately used for any purpose, as her medication was oral. Lymphoedema nevertheless ensued, causing her chronic disability.</p>
<p>Having heard from expert witnesses (in Accident and Emergency) for both Ms Border and the trust, the trial judge had concluded that the SHO had acted in a way that &#x2018;perhaps the great majority&#x2019; of responsible A&#x0026;E doctors would have done &#x2013; and that the decision to insert the cannula was not negligent. The judge set this out in the following terms: &#x2018;(L)ooking at it from the standpoint of the expert evidence, it would be a brave decision for an SHO not to follow standard practice... that an IV line should, if possible, be inserted in the early stage.&#x2019;</p>
<p>The trial judge dismissed the claim for damages for clinical negligence, but Ms Border disagreed and appealed.</p>
<p>The Court of Appeal found that, notwithstanding the pressures and anxieties of being a patient in a resuscitation room, during this period the claimant retained her capacity to give or withhold consent. Furthermore, because she gave no consent to the cannu-lation of her left arm then, accordingly, the doctor who chose to insert it breached his duty of care to her.</p>
<p>Those reading the judgement might reasonably question what on earth the SHO was supposed to do in these circumstances. The Court of Appeal provided no assistance with this &#x2013; although, in fairness, courts only answer the questions posed to them, rather</p>
<p>than advising generally upon the clinical dilemma that flows as a consequence of the judgement. In finding that Ms Border had capacity to make this decision, the appeal court simultaneously handed patients in her circumstances an unenviable choice as they lay in that resuscitation bay. Should such a patient take the risk of lymphoedema? Or just hope that they don&#x2019;t have to face a hypotensive crisis or intolerable pain without established vascular access?</p>
<p>If the clock could be turned back, the court presumably would expect that &#x2013; instead of cannulating without consent &#x2013; the doctor would have explicitly laid out this stark choice to his patient. He should have spelt out to Ms Border that cannulation of an adult with capacity in the absence of their consent was not lawful; but that, equally, if a patient is considered ill enough to be lying in a resuscitation room then the immediately foreseeable risks of non-can-nulation overshadow the theoretical later complications that the needle puncture might cause.</p>
<p>Should, despite this disclosure, the patient maintain the refusal then it would be prudent to revisit her capacity, record that transaction and seek another opinion before re-evaluating the situation. But, as the court reminds us, consent is required.</p>
<p><bold>281</bold></p>
<p><BOLD>CROSSWORD 2</BOLD></p>
<p><bold>Crossword</bold></p>
<p>To enter, simply send a scanned copy of your completed crossword to bulletin&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk or post a copy to: <italic>Bulletin </italic>Office, The Royal College of Surgeons of England, 35&#x2013;43 Lincoln&#x2019;s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3PE. Good luck!</p>
<p>Down</p>
<p>1.	Bone shown in <italic>The Menin Road </italic>by Paul Nash (4)</p>
<p>2.	Goat wrecked garment (4)</p>
<p>3.	Taylor-Sharp and Thompson initially arranged joint procedure (12)</p>
<p>4.	Front half of jet seen in Ordnance Survey instruments (5)</p>
<p>5.	No academic found in raising money to be charitable (3-6)</p>
<p>7.	Messy accident after Virginia is treated to produce immunity (10)</p>
<p>8.	The rejection of general ideas &#x2013; a practice in name only (10)</p>
<p>11. Add external on my excision (12)</p>
<p>13.	Sociableness is a fine feminine skill (10)</p>
<p>14.	Contest has our chap sitting up in tent (10) 16. Perform a ceremony with start here in</p>
<p>France, followed by unusual tea (9)</p>
<p>21.	Clues for main parts (5)</p>
<p>22.	A bodily fluid for anger (4)</p>
<p>23.	Time up for discharge (4)</p>
<p>24.	</p>
<p>C rossword by Escort</p>
<p>Across</p>
<p>1. Extrem ist with probe producing high-frequency vibrations (10) 6. Baked potato vend or has s tove (4)</p>
<p>9. After ho urs of da rkness, G eorge has bed ments (10)</p>
<p>1<sup>1</sup>0. C oats sent b <sup>a</sup> c k i<sup>a</sup> n fra ud (4)</p>
<p>12. A uthorisat<sub>n</sub> i <sup>i</sup>on in <sub>d</sub> <sup>o</sup> e <sub>e</sub><sup>n</sup>lectronic han dwritin g</p>
<p>snatched by bird (12) 15. T ake in ev<sub>w</sub> i <sub>i</sub>den ce that&#x2019;s tr int in d tes ted ( 9) 17. L <sub>.</sub> iam retu rns to point in compu ter</p>
<p>message (5)</p>
<p>18.	Rota with a damaged artery (5)</p>
<p>19.	Loud, turbulent tide at loch has unpleasant smell (9)</p>
<p>20.	Difficulty with self-expression? &#x2018;Canula!&#x2019; I cry. <sup>m</sup> &#x2018;It is br oken.<sup>)</sup>&#x2019; (12)</p>
<p>24.	Couple on the agenda? (4)</p>
<p>25.	Union leader is a matro n wor king in infirm ary (10)</p>
<p>26.	Still before one hairy creature (4)</p>
<p>27.	Bea<sub>n</sub> t <sub>t</sub>le ss <sub>m</sub> &#x2018; sound ha s river rhythm (10)</p>
<p>RCS Bulletin 1, crossword by &#x2018;Escort&#x2019; &#x2013; Step</p>
<p>Crossword 1 solution</p>
<p>DOI: 10.1308/rcsbull.2017.283</p>
<p><italic>Slop and decrepitude</italic></p>
<p>Our tired scribe finds the Fountain of Youth and tries not to spill the beans&#x2026; or the wine.</p>
<p><BOLD>M</BOLD></p>
<p>r Slop FRCS felt slightly bewildered as he noticed the changes at The Royal College of Surgeons of England. There seemed to have been a lot of objects ripped up since the Hunterian Museum closed and the Nuffield was filled with refugees from the Barry Building. As he tripped up the stairs to the Esteemed Editor-in-Chief&#x2019;s new temporary office, he hoped the familiar face of his tormentor would at least re-orient his befuddled brain into some kind of order.</p>
<p>Slop, who was quite breathless after climbing three flights of stairs, knocked with trepidation on the large Victorian door of the Editor&#x2019;s office.</p>
<p>&#x2018;Come in!&#x2019; shouted his boss as he looked up from his iPad while staring absent-mindedly straight at Slop, who began the traverse across the thick-knotted pile carpet.</p>
<p>&#x2018;Ah Slop. You are limping and out of breath, old man! Take a seat and have a glass of Highland Spring&#x00AE;.&#x2019;</p>
<p>Slop almost collapsed on the <italic>chaise longue </italic>by the window.</p>
<p>&#x2018;Yes, Sir! It&#x2019;s true I am a bit puffed and my right knee has an effusion and is very painful around the medial meniscus area.&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x2018;How did you do that? Or is it just the effects <italic>of anno domini </italic>in an old curmudgeon like yourself?&#x2019;</p>
<p>With that, the Esteemed Editor-in-Chief roared with laughter and started to roll back on his chair, barely able to contain himself. Slop felt highly awkward and rather humiliated.</p>
<p>&#x2018;Well,&#x2019; continued Slop. &#x2018;A week&#x2019;s skiing in Zermatt with the family started the problem and then it was not helped by a 58-mile walk on the Pembrokeshire Coastal Path.&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x2018;All completely self-inflicted, Slop! Only yourself to blame if you attempt such activities at your age. That&#x2019;s it, Slop! The perfect subject for your next article &#x2013; <italic>Ageing, Decrepitude and Surgery</italic>.&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x2018;But Sir, I think I&#x2019;d rather write about...&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x2018;Nonsense, Slop! Have it on my desk by Friday! That will be all.&#x2019;</p>
<p>Slop heaved himself painfully off the <italic>chaise longue </italic>and began the long hobble to Holborn tube station and the train back to Midhampton. As he journeyed north, he knew how sobering any account of the kind the Editor was proposing would be for his readers. However, it might help Slop face the reality that he was not the surgeon &#x2013; let alone the man &#x2013; he once was.</p>
<p>When Slop first arrived at Midhampton General Hospital more than a quarter of a century ago, he had run two full day-lists each week as well as endoscopy, outpatients and ward rounds. He would think nothing of operating until eight o&#x2019;clock each evening and, in those far-off days, no one much tried to stop him. Of course, he would feel a tad sore in the foot department by the end of the long day but he would be up at six o&#x2019;clock the next morning none the worse for wear and chomping at the bit to get going again.</p>
<p>Nowadays his routine would have quite a different texture to it. After swallowing his felodipine and statin, Slop would sit on his</p>
<p>toilet looking out at the copper beech tree swaying in the breeze while trying not to strain too hard. If he did, his piles &#x2013; despite liberal application of AnusolHC&#x00AE; &#x2013; would create merry hell for the rest of the morning and interfere with his day-care list. By midday his dyspepsia would require a gulp of Gaviscon&#x00AE; and his left acromio-clavicular joint would need an urgent massage after performing a laparoscopic hernia repair.</p>
<p>By lunchtime, all four of his malleoli would be hidden under a light covering of spongy oedema and the anaesthetic gases would have irritated his chronic bronchitis enough for him to be suffering from bouts of gentle coughing. During the afternoon colonoscopy list, Slop&#x2019;s right wrist would become sore enough from the constant torque required to negotiate the colon that he would be forced to rub it hard to improve the circulation. By the evening, as he strolled slowly to his car, he would notice that his neck would be stiff and his gait uneven as the arthritis of his right hip began to make its presence known to him.</p>
<p>It is true, of course, that an hour in the gym would normally solve most of these problems. However, Mr Slop knew what the real remedy for his ageing was, even though the Nursing Sister might have different ideas on the subject. A couple of glasses of Merlot followed by a nightly tot of Famous Grouse&#x00AE;!</p>
<p>Slop recalled, with some unpleasantness, his meeting with the Editor-in-Chief the two weeks before but, after much reflection, finally realised the solution to his health problems. Just start the Merlot at breakfast time!</p>
<p><bold>283</bold></p>
<p><bold>Money</bold>Doctor</p>
<p>wealth management</p>
<p>Your trusted <bold>financial adviser I</bold></p>
<p>We have over <bold>90 years experience</bold></p>
<p>providing fnancial advice to Medical Professionals and are specialists in Wealth Management and NHS Pensions.</p>
<p>MoneyDoctor takes a holistic approach to Wealth Management, helping you to accumulate and preserve your wealth. We are here to advise you independently, with access to other industry experts.</p>
<p><bold>Get in touch, we&#x2019;re ready to help</bold></p>
<p>We can advise on your <bold>NHS pension </bold>and can also help with:</p>
<p><bold>01564 779382 </bold>advice&#x0040;moneydr.co.uk <bold>www.moneydr.co.uk</bold></p>
<p><bold>Money </bold>Doctor MoneyDoctor Wealth Management is a trading style of MoneyDoctor Financial Planning Ltd. Authorised and Regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority</p>
<p>Your home or property may be repossessed if you do not keep up repayments on your mortgage. The value of investments may fall as well as rise and so you may wealth management	<sub><bold>+</sub> ,<sub></bold></sub></p>
<p>not get back the original value invested.</p>
