<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>XPays, INC., Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>INTERNET COMMERCE GROUP, INC., an Arizona corporation; SK INTERTAINMENT, INC., an Illinois corporation; ADULT PROFIT, a Danish business entity of unknown form; LUCINA S.L., a Spanish business entity of unknown form; WEB TRAFFIC, INC., an Australian corporation; TARASANT, a Singaporean business entity of unknown form; and VEROTEL MERCHANT SERVICES B.V., a Dutch business entity of unknown form, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 06-05688 DDP (FFMx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 06-05688 DDP (FFMx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:06-cv-05688-DDP-VBK</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 05/14/2008</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER DENYING DEFENDANT’S MOTION TO COMPEL JOINDER</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center">[Motion filed on March 10, 2008]</headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center">[Amended Motion filed on April 7, 2008]</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">DEAN D. PREGERSON United States District Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">This matter comes before the Court on Defendant SK Entertainment, Inc.'s (&#x201C;SK&#x201D;) motion to dismiss for lack of subject matter jurisdiction, joined by Defendant Internet Commerce Group (&#x201C;ICG&#x201D;), and SK's motion for summary judgment. and individual Defendants' motion for summary judgment. After reviewing the papers submitted by the parties and hearing oral argument, the Court denies the motion to dismiss. The Court grants in part and denies in part the motion for summary judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">This case concerns copyright, trademark, and unfair competition claims arising from a company's use of the Paris Hilton sex video (&#x201C;Video&#x201D;), entitled &#x201C;One Night in Paris.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Plaintiff XPays is a California internet company. In 2004, XPays obtained rights to use the Video for profit. The parties dispute whether those rights were exclusive or nonexclusive. Since 2004, XPays has run a webmaster affiliate program for the Video on XPays.com. XPays has also earned revenue on the Video through the websites hotelheiress.com and trustfundgirls.com. XPays has earned millions of dollars in revenue from marketing and promotion related to the Video.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Defendant SK is an Illinois corporation that operates MrSkin.com, &#x201C;a popular review site reviewing nude scenes of popular actresses in mainstream film.&#x201D; (Derek Meklir Declaration (&#x201C;Meklir Decl.&#x201D;) &#182; 2.) MrSkin.com has earned substantial revenue through subscriptions to its review website. Defendant ICJ is an internet company that like SK is a party to this action for its use of the Video.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">On or about June 21, 2004, SK posted a review of the Video. The review was accompanied by several images and three clips of the Video. While the Video has an approximate running time of sixty-two minutes, the three clips used by SK were each less than 59 seconds. (SK's Mot. 5; SK Ex. C.) The three clips &#8212; occurring at the four minute, twenty-four minute, and one hour and one minute marks of the Video &#8212; show sexually explicit content.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> (Supplemental Declaration of Evan Horowitz (&#x201C;Suppl. Decl. of Horowitz&#x201D;) &#182; 5-6.) The review discusses some of the content from those clips. (<underscore>See</underscore> Meklir Decl., SK Ex. C) (providing the full text of the review).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p7">&#8195;The three clips show: (1) Paris Hilton and Rick Salomon engaged in sexual intercourse; (2) Paris Hilton engaged in sexually explicit conduct with a champagne bottle; and (3) some portion of the final scene, where Paris Hilton is performing oral sex on Rick Salomon. (Suppl. Decl. of Horowitz &#182;&#182; 5-6; Suppl. Decl. of Hajir Ardebili &#182;&#182; 5-6.)</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">SK had FlashCash.com, a seller of website subscriptions, promote its use of the Video. FlashCash.com has a network of marketing affiliates through which it markets website subscriptions. FlashCash either shares revenues with SK or is paid a fixed fee for its marketing activities on SK's behalf. When SK created the Video review, SK arranged for FlashCash.com (&#x201C;FlashCash&#x201D;) to send out an announcement to its affiliates that the Video was on MrSkin.com. On July 1, 2004, Flashcash.com sent the announcement to the affiliates.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">The announcement stated: &#x201C;Mr. Skin sales have already started to see an increase this week. Why? The Paris Hilton tape has been added to Mr. Skin and surfers are drooling.&#x201D; It also stated: &#x201C;Make sure your Celeb traffic is pointed towards Paris and Mr. Skin to maximize your money!&#x201D; The announcement also included a &#x201C;tour&#x201D; of MrSkin.com webpages, which provides a potential customer with access to a sample of webpages and aims to generate interest in purchasing a subscription. The front page of the tour contained three images from the Video and stated: &#x201C;<ital>SEE THE INFAMOUS PARIS HILTON VIDEOS HERE!</ital>&#x201D; The tour also reads &#x201C;INSTANT ACCESS.&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> Hank Butler Declaration (&#x201C;Butler Decl.&#x201D;), Ex. A.) It is undisputed that the full Video has never been available for purchase at MrSkin.com.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">The parties dispute whether it is SK or FlashCash that is responsible for the announcement and tour. SK claims that FlashCash independently controls the development and dissemination of its announcements and tours. SK further asserts that FlashCash is responsible for policing its affiliates' actions. (SK Mot. 6-7.) XPays claims that SK licensed Flashcash to use its content and exercised control over its marketing activities. Additionally, XPays maintains that SK authorized the FlashCash announcement and tour, and even approved its content. (XPays' Opp'n 3-6.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Evan Horowitz, co-owner of XPays, contacted SK on July 19, 2004 informing them that he believed the FlashCash announcement and tour to be &#x201C;deceptive.&#x201D; (Meklir Decl., Ex. F.) Subsequently, a clarification was circulated by FlashCash explaining that neither Flashcash nor SK had any rights to the Video, and that MrSkin.com only had limited footage related to its review. (Declaration of Evan Horowitz (&#x201C;Horowitz Decl.&#x201D;), Ex. E.) Following the clarification, some FlashCash affiliates continued to misrepresent the availability of the Video on MrSkin.com. According to SK, SK and Flashcash would take immediate action when XPays notified SK of any misrepresentations in advertising. (SK Mot. 7.) On one occasion, Derek Meklir, SK's person most knowledgable regarding the review, wrote to Mr. Horowitz that &#x201C;we [SK] have the right to promote our nudity reviews of actresses, including Paris Hilton, on the FlashCash tour so long as it isn't misleading people to believe we have the full<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> Hilton Video.&#x201D; (Meklir Decl. 18, Ex. H.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">XPays argues that SK realized substantial profits resulting from increased web traffic subsequent to the announcement and tour that the Video was on MrSkin.com. (Declaration of Paul Berra (&#x201C;Berra Decl.&#x201D;), Ex. B.). SK counters that there is no correlation between the review and its profits. SK further argues that it took no profits away from XPays.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">In July 2005, MrSkin.com removed all graphic sex materials from the website. Sometime in 2006, SK ceased reviews of adult films altogether. In July 2006, SK removed all material related to the Video, including the review.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">XPays instituted this action against SK for copyright infringement, false designation of origin, unfair competition, and accounting and constructive trust claims. SK brings a motion to dismiss for lack of standing, joined by ICJ. SK also brings a motion for summary judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. DEFENDANTS' MOTION TO DISMISS</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A. <underscore>Legal Standard</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Defendant SK and ICG's (&#x201C;Defendants&#x201D;) motion to dismiss for lack of subject matter jurisdiction maintains that XPays lacks standing to sue for copyright infringement, and its related claims of false designation and unfair competition.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">When a 12(b)(1) motion to dismiss raises plaintiff's lack of standing as an affirmative defense, a court generally may consider extrinsic evidence and resolve factual disputes. <underscore>Warren v. Fox Family Worldwide, Inc.</underscore>, 328 F.3d 1136, 1139 (9th Cir. 2003). However, if a court's jurisdiction is intertwined with factual disputes underlying the merits of a claim, a court must &#x201C;assume[] the truth of the allegations in a complaint<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> unless controverted by undisputed facts in the record.&#x201D; <underscore>Id., citing Roberts v. Corrothers</underscore>, 812 F.2d 1173, 1177 (9th Cir. 1987).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Here, Defendants argue that XPays lacks standing because it is not the owner or exclusive licensee of the copyright. The determination whether a plaintiff is an owner or exclusive licensee is an element of a copyright infringement claim. <underscore>See Feist Publications, Inc. V. Rural Telephone Service Co.</underscore>, 499 U.S. 340, 361 (1991) (stating that proof of ownership of a valid copyright is required to establish copyright infringement) Therefore, the standing issue is intertwined with the merits of the copyright claim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">While SK brings a motion to dismiss to challenge Plaintiff's standing, SK incorporates the lack of standing argument in its motion for summary judgment. (Def.'s MSJ 9.) Further, XPays argues that a summary judgment standard is appropriate to determine its standing at this stage of the litigation. (Pl.'s Opp'n MSJ.) Therefore, the Court considers the issue of standing under a summary judgment standard: viewing the evidence in a light most favorable to XPays, is there a genuine issue of fact whether XPays has standing.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> If there is an issue of fact, the Court cannot dismiss the claim for lack of standing.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p19">&#8195;This approach is consistent with the standard for a 12(b)(1) motion when standing and the merits are intertwined. The Court may only dismiss if the undisputed extrinsic evidence establishes a lack of standing. <underscore>See Roberts</underscore>, 812 F.2d at 1177.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">B. <underscore>Standing</underscore></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center">1. <underscore>The Copyright Act</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">&#x201C; One who owns a copyright in a work has the exclusive right to reproduce, adapt, publish, perform, and display the work.&#x201D; <underscore>Foad Consulting Group v. Musil Govan Azzalino</underscore>, 270 F.3d 821, 825 (9th Cir. 2001), <underscore>citing</underscore> 17 U.S.C. &#167; 106. The Copyright Act defines a &#x201C;transfer of copyright ownership&#x201D; as effective upon &#x201C;an assignment, mortgage, exclusive license, or any other conveyance<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> of a copyright or of any of the exclusive rights comprised in a copyright<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> but not including a nonexclusive license.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 101. The Copyright Act allows for copyright divisibility, as &#x201C;any of the rights specified by section 106, may be transferred<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> and owned separately.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C &#167; 201(d)(2).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">A transfer of copyright ownership, including an exclusive license, must be in writing. 17 U.S.C. &#167; 204(a); <underscore>see also Effects Assoc., Inc. v. Cohen</underscore>, 908 F.2d 555, 556 (9th Cir. 1990). The writing should identify &#x201C;precisely what rights are being transferred<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; <underscore>See Effects</underscore>, 908 F.2d at 559. A court may &#x201C;rely on state law to provide the canons of contractual construction provided that such rules do not interfere with federal copyright law or policy&#x201D; when interpreting a copyright license. <underscore>Sun Microsys., Inc. v. Microsoft Corp.</underscore>, 188 F.3d 1115, 1122 (9th Cir. 1999) (internal quotation marks and citation omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Section 501(b) of the Copyright Act authorizes copyright infringement actions by &#x201C;[t]he legal or beneficial owner of an exclusive right under a copyright<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> for any infringement of that particular right committed while he or she is the owner of it.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 501(b); <underscore>see also Silvers v. Sony Pictures Entm't, Inc.</underscore>, 402 F.3d 881 (9th Cir. 2005) (finding that the Copyright Act grants standing for infringement lawsuits to owners and exclusive licensees of copyright rights). Where an exclusive licensee has been transferred a particular right enumerated under section 106, that licensee has standing to bring a claim for &#x201C;infringement of that particular right.&#x201D; <underscore>See</underscore> 17 U.S.C &#167; 501(b).<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p23">&#8195;The Act elsewhere states that an exclusive licensee is entitled to bring an infringement claim &#x201C;to the extent of [the transferred] right[s].&#x201D; 17 U.S.C &#167; 201(d)(2).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">However, there are limitations on transfer of copyright rights. Under the Act, &#x201C;[t]he bare assignment of an accrued cause of action is impermissible.&#x201D; <underscore>Silvers</underscore>, 402 F.3d at 890. Further, &#x201C;the [Copyright] Act does not allow a copyright licensee to transfer its rights under an exclusive license, without the consent of the original licensor.&#x201D; <underscore>Gardner v. Nike, Inc.</underscore>, 279 F.3d 774. 780 (9th Cir. 2002).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">2. <underscore>XPays' Standing</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Defendants argue that XPays lacks standing because it does not own the copyright and is not an exclusive licensee of the Video; at best, they assert, XPays is a non-exclusive licensee. Further, whatever rights XPays did acquire in the Video, Defendants argue that XPays did not acquire those rights until after the complaint was filed. XPays responds that copyright law bars alleged infringers, such as Defendants, from avoiding liability by challenging the validity of XPays' copyright ownership or licensee rights. ((Opp'n MTD 5.) XPays also counters that it &#x201C;owns a portion of the copyright in the Video.&#x201D; (Opp'n MTD 9.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">a. <underscore>Copyright Ownership and License History</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">In support of their motion, Defendants attach evidence that documents the transfer history related to the copyright in the Video. XPays does not dispute this history, but rather, disputes Defendants' claim that XPays did not own or have an exclusive license in the copyright at times relevant to this action.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Rick Salomon registered the Video with the U.S. Copyright Office on November 10, 2003. (Defs.' Ex. A.) On March 4, 2004, he granted Jim Salomon, his brother, an exclusive license to reproduce and distribute the Video on the internet in a written license agreement. (Defs.' Ex. B.) There was not a clause allowing Jim to sub-license his rights in that agreement. Jim Salomon then assigned his exclusive license to Merlin Designs and later memorialized that assignment in an undated document. (Defs.' Ex. C.) On or around May 6, 2004, Rick and Jim Salomon entered into an undated written agreement entitled the &#x201C;Assignment of Copyrights and Clarification of Litigation Rights.&#x201D; (Defs.' Ex. D.) This agreement expressly granted to Jim the right to assign his exclusive license, although that license had already been assigned to Merlin Designs.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">On April 20, 2004, Merlin and XPays entered a written partnership agreement &#x201C;for [t]he [e]xclusive [m]arketing of Merlin Designs Ltd. [i]ntellectual [p]roperty.&#x201D; (Defs.' Ex. E.) The agreement provided for the joint marketing and promotion of the Video on a website HotelHeiress.com. After XPays filed the complaint in this action, (<underscore>see</underscore> Horowitz Depo. 119:23-120:7, Defs.' Ex. G.), XPays and Merlin Designs entered another agreement titled &#x201C;Copyright Assignment.&#x201D; (Defs.' Ex. F.) The agreement states that the April 20 writing assigned Merlin's &#x201C;limited copyrights&#x201D; to XPays &#x201C;to be exercised by XPays for the purpose of protecting and enforcing its rights to commercially exploit and profit from the Video on the worldwide internet.<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; Then the agreement provides that the assignment to XPays &#x201C;does not include Merlin's copyrights to protect and enforce its rights to commercially exploit and profit from the Video on the worldwide internet<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> as these rights pertain to Google/YouTube, Yahoo, Microsoft/MSN, IAC/Interactive/IAC Search &#38; Media, [etc.] (collectively the &#x201C;Google entities&#x201D;).&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">b. <underscore>Section 204(a) Writing Requirement</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Defendants argue that the various written assignment agreements do not establish that XPays is an owner or exclusive licensee with standing to bring a copyright claim. XPays responds that Defendants are not entitled to make this argument. XPays cites to <underscore>Eden Toys, Inc. V. Florelee Undergarment, Inc.</underscore>, 697 F.2d 27, 36 (2nd Cir. 1982), where the Second Circuit held that a later writing memorializing an earlier &#x201C;informal&#x201D; grant of a license&#x201D; meets the section 204(a) writing requirement. <underscore>Id.</underscore> There, an alleged infringer had argued that the lack of a writing indicated that the plaintiff did not have an exclusive license at the time of the infringing activity. The Second Circuit found that an alleged infringer may not invoke the lack of a section 204(a) writing to defeat a copyright infringement claim as long as no dispute exists between the copyright holder and licensor. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">XPays is correct that Defendants may not invoke the lack of a writing alone to establish a lack of standing. &#x201C;A prior oral grant that is confirmed by a later writing becomes valid as of the time of the oral grant, even if the writing is subsequent to the initiation of litigation on the copyright infringement.&#x201D; <underscore>Magnuson v. Video Yesteryear</underscore>, 85 F.3d 1424, 1428 (9th Cir. 1996) (citations omitted) (citing <underscore>Eden Toys</underscore> with approval).<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> XPays may maintain this action so long as it was assigned the necessary rights prior to this action. The &#x201C;Copyright Assignment&#x201D; could still be a valid writing, even if the writing occurred after the filing of the complaint. <underscore>See Magnuson</underscore>, 85 F.3d at 1428.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p31">&#8195;<underscore>Magnuson</underscore> notes that the Ninth Circuit opinion in <underscore>Konigsberg Int'l, Inc. v. Rice</underscore>, 16 F.3d 355 (9th Cir. 1994), suggested the requirement of a contemporaneous writing and expressed some disagreement with the Second Circuit's opinion in <underscore>Eden Toys</underscore>. However, the Ninth Circuit in <underscore>Magnuson</underscore> found that language in <underscore>Konigsberg</underscore> to be confined to its facts or dicta. <underscore>See Magnuson</underscore>, 85 F.3d at 1429 n.1.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">However, Defendants may argue that XPays was not a copyright owner or exclusive licensee at the time the alleged infringement occurred. Similarly, Defendants may rely on the written assignment agreements as evidence that XPays was not assigned the necessary rights to become a copyright owner or exclusive licensee. <underscore>See Silvers</underscore>, 402 F.3d at 885.<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> This makes sense because only a copyright owner or exclusive licensee has standing to sue an alleged infringer. If the Court finds that XPays did not have exclusive rights conferring standing to bring suit, the Court has the power to dismiss XPays or to &#x201C;require the joinder<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> of any person having or claiming an interest in the copyright [at issue]&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 501(b).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p33">&#8195;The Ninth Circuit in <underscore>Silvers</underscore> noted that &#x201C;the plaintiff must have a legal or beneficial interest in at least one of the exclusive rights described in &#167; 106&#x201D; and that &#x201C;for a plaintiff to be &#x2018;entitled<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> to institute an action&#x2019; for infringement, the infringement must be &#x2018;committed while he or she is the owner of&#x2019; the particular exclusive right allegedly infringed.&#x201D; <underscore>Silver</underscore>, 402 F.3d at 885.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">c. <underscore>Whether XPays was an Exclusive Licensee</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Defendants argue that XPays is at best a non-exclusive licensee. First, the marketing agreement with Merlin Designs only establishes that XPays would assist with marketing and promotion of the Video. Second, the joint partnership agreement reserves the same licensing rights for both Merlin and XPays, which makes XPays a nonexclusive licensee. (Defs. MTD 8-9.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">Conversely, XPays asserts that it became a partial owner of the copyright and exclusive licensee when a verbal agreement was reached between Merlin, with Jim Salomon speaking on Merlin's behalf, and XPays in March 2004. (Pl.'s Opp'n MTD 10, <underscore>citing</underscore> Declaration of Jim Salomon 2-6; Declaration of Evan Horowitz 3-4.) Thus, XPays argues that it had copyright ownership before June 2006 when the alleged infringing activity began.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">There is an issue of fact whether XPays was an exclusive licensee. If XPays was only transferred marketing rights with respect to the Video, this would not give XPays standing because ownership of marketing rights is not one of the exclusive rights outlined in section 106 that provides standing to bring suit. However, XPays offers evidence disputing Defendants' contention that the transfer of ownership was limited to marketing rights. Specifically, the declarations of Horowitz and Salomon aver that the agreement was intended to transfer Merlin's rights to XPays as its partner.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">Although Defendants argue that Merlin's and XPays' shared ownership of the license created a nonexclusive license, this is not clear from the language in the joint partnership agreement. There is language that suggests Merlin retained rights with respect to particular entities, while XPays was given rights with respect to other entities. This at least supports an inference that the agreement divided Merlin's license into two exclusive licenses. <underscore>See Silvers</underscore>, 402 F.3d at 887, <underscore>citing</underscore> H.R. Rep. No. 94-1476, at 61, reprinted in 1976 U.S.C.C.A.N. at 5674. (pointing to legislative history explaining that &#x201C;each of the five enumerated rights may be subdivided indefinitely&#x201D;). Even if Merlin and XPays shared the same license, two partners sharing a license does not create a nonexclusive license. <underscore>See Oddo v. Ries</underscore>, 743 F.2d 630, 633 (9th Cir. 1984) (citations omitted) (&#x201C;[E]ach co-owner has an independent right to use or license the use of the copyright.&#x201D;)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">Accordingly, the Court finds that dismissal for lack of standing would be inappropriate given the existence of issues of fact whether XPays was an exclusive licensee.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">d. <underscore>Whether XPays was Assigned a Bare Right to Bring a Lawsuit</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">In <underscore>Silvers</underscore>, the Ninth Circuit held that &#x201C;[t]he bare assignment of an accrued [copyright] cause of action is impermissible.&#x201D; <underscore>Silvers</underscore>, 402 F.3d at 890. Defendants assert that XPays only was assigned the right to sue for infringement, and was not assigned any other section 106 rights. Based on the above reasoning, the Court also finds an issue of fact whether XPays was only assigned the right to bring lawsuits, which alone would not be enough for standing, or whether it was given an exclusive license to sell, market, and exploit the Video on the internet.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">e. <underscore>Whether the Sublicense to XPays had the Consent of the Original Licensors</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">In <underscore>Gardner</underscore>, 279 F.3d 774, the Ninth Circuit held that &#x201C;an exclusive licensee has the burden of obtaining a licensor's consent before it may assign its rights, absent explicit contractual language to the contrary.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 781. Here, there appears to have been contractual language such that Merlin did not require consent from Rick or Jim Salomon in order to assign rights to XPays. The Assignment of Copyrights and Clarification of Litigation Rights contains a waiver of consent by Rick Salomon that allows Jim Salomon to assign to any third parties. The agreement between Jim Salomon and Merlin Designs contains the same waiver. (<underscore>See</underscore> XPays' Ex. B and D.) Therefore, Merlin did not need consent to assign rights to XPays.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">Even in the absence of the waiver, the Court notes that Defendants would not be entitled to raise lack of licensor consent as a defense. The policy behind the consent rule is to protect copyright owners from infringement and avoid litigation that would arise if licensees were not required to get consent. <underscore>Gardner</underscore>, 279 F.3d at 780-81. For these reasons, the Court finds that Merlin did not need consent to assign rights to XPays.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">3. <underscore>Summary</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">The Court finds an issue of fact with respect to XPays' standing. For this reason, Defendants arguments for dismissal of the Lanham Act and unfair competition claims based on XPays' lack of standing fail. Defendants' additional arguments for dismissal of those claims are also raised in SK's motion for summary judgment. Accordingly, the Court will consider those arguments in addressing the motion for summary judgment.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="0">///</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. DEFENDANTS' MOTION FOR SUMMARY JUDGMENT</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A. <underscore>Legal Standard</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">Summary judgment is appropriate if there is no genuine issue as to any material fact and a party is entitled to judgment as a matter of law. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c). The moving party bears the initial burden of demonstrating the absence of a genuine issue of material fact. <underscore>Celotex Corp. v. Catrett</underscore>, 477 U.S. 317, 323 (1986). Summary judgment cannot be granted where a genuine dispute exists as to any material fact. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c). A &#x201C;material&#x201D; fact is one which might affect the outcome of the case under the applicable law. <underscore>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc.</underscore>, 477 U.S. 242, 248 (1986). A dispute about a material fact is genuine if a reasonable jury could return a verdict for the non-moving party. <underscore>Id.</underscore> When the moving party has the burden of persuasion at trial, it must be shown that there is no material fact on the elements of a claim or defense. <underscore>S. Cal. Gas Co. v. City of Santa Ana</underscore>, 336 F.3d 885, 888 (9th Cir. 2003).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">In deciding a motion for summary judgment, the evidence is viewed in the light most favorable to the non-moving party, and all justifiable inferences are to be drawn in its favor. <underscore>Anderson</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 255. Moreover, &#x201C;credibility determinations, the weighing of the evidence, and the drawing of legitimate inferences from the facts are jury functions, not those of a judge [when] he is ruling on a motion for summary judgment.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">B. <underscore>Copyright Infringement</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">&#x201C;To establish [copyright] infringement, two elements must be proven: (1) ownership of a valid copyright and (2) copying of constituent elements of the work that are original.&#x201D; <underscore>Feist Publications, Inc.</underscore>, 499 U.S. at 361. The Court has already concluded that dismissal is inappropriate on the issue whether XPays' was an exclusive licensee with standing to sue Defendants for copyright infringement, and reaches the same conclusion on that issue for purposes of summary judgment.<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference> The Court turns to the other arguments raised by SK in its motion for summary judgment.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p47">&#8195;The Court notes that there is no dispute that Rick Salomon has valid copyright ownership, as he has registered the Video with the Copyright Office.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">1. <underscore>Fair Use Defense</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p48" level="1">Fair use is an affirmative defense to copyright infringement that &#x201C;permits the use of copyrighted works without the copyright owner's consent under certain situations.&#x201D; <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc. v. Amazon.com, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d 701, 719 (9th Cir. 2007). &#x201C;[T]he fair use of a copyrighted work<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> for purposes such as criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching,<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> scholarship, or research<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> is not an infringement of copyright.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 107.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">Whether a defendant has made a &#x201C;fair use&#x201D; of a copyright is a mixed question of law and fact. <underscore>Kelly v. Arriba Soft Corp.</underscore>, 336 F.3d 811, 816 (9th Cir. 2003). &#x201C;If there are no genuine issues of material fact, or if, even after resolving all issues in favor of the opposing party, a reasonable trier of fact can reach only one conclusion, a court may conclude as a matter of law whether the challenged use qualifies as a fair use of the copyrighted work.&#x201D; <underscore>Hustler Magazine, Inc. v. Moral Majority, Inc.</underscore>, 796 F.2d 1148, 1151 (9th Cir. 1996).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">The Copyright Act sets forth a four-factor test to determine whether a particular use of a copyrighted work was fair use. A court is to consider:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p51" first-line="1" turnover="1">(1) the purpose and character of the use, including whether such use is of a commercial nature or is for nonprofit educational purposes;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p52" first-line="1" turnover="1">(2) the nature of the copyrighted work;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p53" first-line="1" turnover="1">(3) the amount and substantiality of the portion used in relation to the copyrighted work as a whole; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p54" first-line="1" turnover="1">(4) the effect of the use upon the potential market for or value of the copyrighted work.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p55" contd-flag="y">17 U.S.C. &#167; 107.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p56" level="1">While SK bears the burden of proving fair use, it need not prove that all of the &#167; 107 factors support a finding of fair use. See <underscore>Sega Enters. Ltd. v. Accolade, Inc.</underscore>, 977 F.2d 1510, 1522 (9th Cir. 1992). After consideration of each factor, a court must balance the factors &#x201C;in light of the purposes of copyright.&#x201D; <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 725, <underscore>citing Campbell v. Acuff-Rose Music, Inc.</underscore>, 510 U.S. 569, 590 (1994).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">a. <underscore>Purpose and Character of the Use</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p57" level="1">The Court first must consider &#x201C;the purpose and character of the use, including whether such use is of a commercial nature or is for nonprofit educational purposes.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 107(1). This factor concentrates inquiry on whether the defendant engages in a &#x201C;transformative&#x201D; use that adds &#x201C;something new, with a further purpose or different character, altering the [original] with new expression, meaning, or message,&#x201D; and does not &#x201C;merely supersede the objects of the original creation.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 579.; <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 720-21 (internal citations and quotations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p58" level="1">SK argues that its use of the Video was transformative because it used short clips and still images in connection with a review of the Video. SK characterizes its review as a satirical commentary on the &#x201C;sexual escapades&#x201D; of Rick Salomon and Paris Hilton, and more generally on &#x201C;America's fascination with the sex lives of &#x2018;celebrities.&#x2019;&#x201D; (SK's Mot. 11.) Comparing its commentary to the movie reviews of Ebert and Roeper, SK contends that its review was concerned with saying something about the Video, whereas XPays was solely concerned with sale of the Video. (SK's Mot. 10.).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p59" level="1">The Supreme Court has recognized fair use of a copyrighted work when the purpose or character of that use is criticism, commentary, or parody. <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 579-80. Whether commentary is &#x201C;in good taste or bad does not and should not matter for fair use.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 582. SK's review provides commentary on the Video, combining explicit sexual imagery, metaphor, and puns, to address the ironic connection between Paris Hilton's inherited wealth, the sex tape, and the heiress's meteoric rise to pop culture phenomenon. Even if the review only reinforces the role of sex and celebrity in American culture, its satirical review of the Video nevertheless has a claim to transformative value. <underscore>Cf. Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 579-80 (noting that &#x201C;parody has an obvious claim to transformative value&#x201D; because &#x201C;it can provide social benefit, by shedding light on an earlier work, and in the process, creating a new one&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p60" level="1">This distinguishes MrSkin.com from the website database in <underscore>Video Pipeline, Inc. V. Buena Vista Home Entertainment, Inc.</underscore>, 342 F.3d 191 (3d Cir. 2003). In <underscore>Video Pipeline</underscore>, the court found that a company did not engage in fair use by composing video clips of Disney films into its own movie previews, and making the previews available to clients on a website database. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 194-95, 203. In finding no transformative use, the court considered it &#x201C;useful to compare the clip previews with a movie review, which might also display two-minute segments copied from a film.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 200. The court explained:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p61" first-line="1" turnover="1">The movie reviewer does not simply display a scene from the movie under review but as well provides his or her own commentary and criticism. In so doing, the critic may add to the copy sufficient &#x201C;new expression, message, or meaning&#x201D; to render the use fair. Here, in contrast, the fact that &#x201C;a substantial portion,&#x201D; indeed almost all, &#x201C;of the infringing work was copied verbatim from the copyrighted work&#x201D; with no additional creative activity &#x201C;reveals a dearth of transformative character or purpose.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p62" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Id.</underscore> (quoting <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 579, 587) (internal citations omitted). Similar to the movie reviewer, the review of the Video on MrSkin.com says something new, placing the Video in a &#x201C;different context such that the plaintiff's work is transformed into a new creation.&#x201D; <underscore>See Wall Data Inc. v. L.A. County Sheriff's Dep't</underscore>, 447 F.3d 769, 778 (9th Cir. 2006).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p63" level="1">That a use of copyrighted material has some transformative value in providing commentary and criticism, however, does not dictate weighing this factor in favor of a defendant. A commercial purpose, although it does not render use presumptively unfair, weighs against finding fair use. <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 585; <underscore>see also id.</underscore> at 584 (noting that many transformative uses, including commentary and parody, &#x201C;are generally conducted for profit.&#x201D;); Harper <underscore>&#38; Row, Publishers, Inc. v. Nation Enterprises</underscore>, 471 U.S. 539, 562 (&#x201C;The crux of the profit/nonprofit distinction is not whether the sole motive is monetary gain but whether the user stands to profit from exploitation of the copyrighted material without paying the customary price.&#x201D;). Any commercial purpose must be viewed relative to the degree of the work's transformative quality: &#x201C;[t]he more transformative the new work, the less will be the significance of other factors, like commercialism, that may weigh against a finding of fair use.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 579.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p64" level="1">MrSkin.com provides a database of images and clips showing female nudity in film accompanied by reviews, that are available on the internet to paying subscribers. While the review of the Video is transformative to some degree, it is reasonable to infer that SK's purpose in making clips of the Video available to its subscribers is substantially similar to that of XPays: to exploit for profit the display of nudity and sexually explicit conduct. The Flashcash tour and announcement, which makes no mention of the review, but rather informs potential subscribers that they can access the Video at MrSkin.com, suggests at the very least that SK aimed to attract subscribers that wanted to view clips of nudity, rather than a review of that material.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p65" level="1">To be sure, SK only makes use of three short, sexually explicit clips in the sixty-two minute Video. However, in light of the possibility that MrSkin.com appeals to the same audience of consumers as the Video, <underscore>see LANS v. KCAL-TV Channel 9</underscore>, 108 F.3d 1119, 1121 (9th Cir. 1997), a reasonable factfinder might conclude that SK's compilation of sexually explicit clips from the Video will supersede demand for the original. The core value to a consumer of the Video is the spectacle of a famous person engaged in sexually explicit acts--to show some of it may be to supersede it.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p66" level="1">The Court finds that SK's use involved a mixed transformative and commercial purpose, and that weighing this factor in favor of SK is not the only conclusion that could be reached by a reasonable finder of fact.<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p67">&#8195;The Court does not weigh XPays' assertion of bad faith on the part of SK. First, whether SK did or did not obtain permission from Red Light District Video to use the Video is irrelevant to fair use. <underscore>See Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 585 n.18. Second, the Court notes that <underscore>Campbell</underscore> questions the relevancy of bad faith to analysis of the fair use defense. <underscore>See id.</underscore></paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">b. <underscore>Nature of the Copyrighted Work</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p68" level="1">A creative work is &#x201C;closer to the core of intended copyright protection than are more fact-based works.&#x201D; <underscore>Perfect 10</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 723, <underscore>citing Kelly v. Arriba Soft Corp.</underscore>, 336 F.3d 811, 820 (9th Cir. 2003). The Video, like a news broadcast, is clearly a work of a factual nature. <underscore>See Feist Publications, Inc.</underscore>, 499 U.S. at 359 (contrasting a film with a news broadcast, finding the latter to receive a lesser degree of copyright protection). Use of such factual works are more likely considered fair. <underscore>Sony Corp. v. Universal City Studios, Inc.</underscore>, 464 U.S. 417, 455 n.40 (1984).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p69" level="1">This factor is of little help in determining fair use when one parodies an original work, &#x201C;since parodies almost invariably copy publicly known, expressive works.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 586. Here, in contrast, this factor is relevant because SK provided commentary on a work of factual nature, not an expressive work closer to the core of copyright protection. <underscore>See Feist Publications, Inc.</underscore>, 499 U.S. at 359. What's more, at the time of SK's use, the Video was available in DVD and on the Internet, and thus was &#x201C;no longer entitled to the enhanced protection available for an unpublished work.&#x201D; <underscore>See Perfect 10</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 723. The factual nature of the work, and its publication prior to SK's use, entitles the Video to a reduced level of protection. Thus, the Court finds that any reasonable factfinder will weigh this factor in favor of SK.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">c. <underscore>Amount and Substantiality of Use of Copyrighted Work</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p70" level="1">&#x201C;The third factor asks whether the amount and substantiality of the portion used in relation to the copyrighted work as a whole<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> are reasonable in relation to the purpose of the copying.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 586. It is undisputed that SK used three clips of the sixty-two minute Video, all less than 59 seconds. Quantitatively, the length of the clips appears reasonable for the purpose of giving viewers a context for the review.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p71" level="1">However, this factor focuses on amount and substantiality of use, &#x201C;call[ing] for thought not only about the quantity of the materials used, but about their quality and importance, too.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 587. The parties' arguments focus on whether the use appropriates &#x201C;the heart&#x201D; of the original work. <underscore>See Harper &#38; Row</underscore>, 471 U.S. at 565; <underscore>see also L.A. News Serv. v. CBS Broad., Inc.</underscore>, 305 F.3d 924, 940 (9th Cir. 2002) (describing the &#x201C;heart&#x201D; of a copied work as &#x201C;the most valuable and pertinent portion&#x201D;). SK argues that use of short clips of sexually explicit content from the Video, when it is mostly comprised of such content, cannot be substantial. SK further argues that the Video has no heart, as it has no plot, no message, and &#x201C;no objective core of expression.&#x201D; (SK's Suppl. Br. 6-7 (quoting <underscore>NXIVM Corp. v. Ross Inst.</underscore>, 364 F.3d 471, 481 (2d Cir. 2004)).) Similarly, SK notes that its use of the clips does not &#x201C;&#x2018;give away&#x2019; the ending of a movie, or ruin other intended surprises for viewers of the full-length films.&#x201D; (SK's Suppl. Br. 7 (quoting <underscore>Video Pipeline, Inc.</underscore>, 342 F.3d at 201).) XPays counters that the clips &#x201C;went directly to the heart of the copy-protected material,&#x201D; (XPays Opp'n 11), and asserts that SK posted the most popular and marketable clips from the Video. (XPays Suppl. Br. 6-7.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p72" level="1">The Supreme Court has indicated the importance of considering this factor in light of the extent of transformative use: whether the critical element of a work is &#x201C;slight or great, and the copying small or extensive in relation to the [critical] element,&#x201D; is relevant as a work with &#x201C;slight [critical] element and extensive copying will be more likely to merely &#x2018;supersede the objects&#x2019; of the original.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore> 510 U.S. at 583 n.16. A reasonable factfinder may determine that SK's use was quantitatively and qualitatively extensive relative to the review's potentially minimal transformative use. A less substantial use of clips may have been sufficient to provide context for the review. Alternatively, a reasonable factfinder could reach the opposite conclusion, that SK's use of the Video did not appropriate the &#x201C;heart&#x201D; of the Video and was limited to the amount necessary for its review. <underscore>See Kelly v. Arriba Soft Corp.</underscore>, 336 F.3d 811, 820-21 (9th Cir. 2003) (&#x201C;If the secondary user copies as much as is necessary for his or her intended use, then this factor will not weigh against him or her.&#x201D;) A reasonable factfinder might weigh this factor in favor of either party.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">d. <underscore>Effect of the Use on the Market or Value of Copyrighted Work</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p73" level="1">The fourth factor is &#x201C;the effect of the use upon the potential market for or value of the copyrighted work.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 107(4); <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 724.<footnote.reference ID="fr8" refid="f8" style="percent_n">8</footnote.reference> This factor requires the Court to consider &#x201C;the extent of market harm caused by the particular actions of the alleged infringer, but also whether unrestricted and widespread conduct of the sort engaged in by the defendant<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> would result in a substantially adverse impact on the potential market for the original.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 589. This factor has been considered in terms of market substitution. When a use copies the original material such that it becomes a &#x201C;market replacement,&#x201D; market harm is probable. &#x201C;[W]hen<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> the second use is transformative, market substitution is at least less certain, and market harm may not be so readily inferred.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 591.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f8"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN8.</label.designator><paratext ID="p74">&#8195;SK's reliance on <underscore>Polar Bear Prods. v. Timex Corp.</underscore>, 384 F.3d 700 (9th Cir. 2004), to argue that XPays has the burden of proof on this factor is misplaced. <underscore>Polar Bear Prods.</underscore> concerned a plaintiff's burden when seeking to prove damages for infringement, not the burden of proof for a fair use defense, which lies with the defendant. SK's arguments that XPays has not established market harm, or that SK garnered substantial profits, do not help SK satisfy its burden of proof.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p75" level="1">The Court has already found that SK's use was transformative. However, the Court also determined that SK's transformative use was interrelated with a commercial purpose. SK argues that a correlation between an increase in its profits and the review of the Video does not establish market harm to XPays. Further, it claims that the review may have helped XPays' Internet DVD sales. XPays argues that SK's substantial profits, after the announcement and tour, establish market harm.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p76" level="1">SK may have seen an increase in profits after posting the review, but this alone does not suggest that the review caused XPays market harm. The notoriety of the Video could drive consumer interest in seeing the MrSkin.com review of the Video. Absent some evidence that people did not buy the Video because the review supplants the Video, XPays' assertion of market harm is uncertain. While SK's transformative use makes market substitution &#x201C;less certain,&#x201D; however, it is reasonable to infer that SK and XPays were in competition for the market of consumers interested in viewing the Video's sexually explicit content. <underscore>See Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 591.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p77" level="1">On the one hand, SK's review is a creation that goes beyond the Video in its commentary and satire, and may attract subscribers precisely because it does not merely copy the Video, but offers some interpretation of the content. On the other hand, it is theoretically possible that some SK subscribers would see the short clips on MrSkin.com, believe they have seen enough, and conclude that there is no need to download the entire Video at an additional price. The Court finds that a reasonable factfinder could weigh this factor for either party.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">e. <underscore>Conclusion on Fair Use</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p78" level="1">Ultimately, a court must weigh all factors together &#x201C;in light of the purposes of copyright.&#x201D; <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 725, <underscore>citing Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 578. The purposes of copyright law are to promote sciences and the arts, and to advance the public welfare. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 720. Although the second factor weighs in favor of SK's fair use as the Video is a factual work, the Court holds that a reasonable factfinder could weigh the first, third, and fourth factors in favor of XPays under the circumstances.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">2. <underscore>Secondary Liability</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p79" level="1">In addition to its direct infringement claim, XPays raises secondary liability theories of contributory infringement and vicarious infringement.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">a. <underscore>Contributory Infringement</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p80" level="1">A plaintiff has a claim for contributory infringement when a defendant &#x201C;with knowledge of the infringing activity, induces, causes or materially contributes to the infringing conduct of another.&#x201D; <underscore>A&#38;M Records, Inc. v. Napster, Inc.</underscore>, 239 F.3d 1004 (9th Cir. 2001) (internal quotations and citations omitted). The nature of XPays' contributory infringement claim is unclear from XPays' papers as XPays does not articulate the theory's application to the facts of this case. Presumably, XPays believes that SK has contributed to infringement by FlashCash or its affiliates.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p81" level="1">XPays does not provide evidence that Flashcash or its affiliates infringed its copyright. Rather, XPays's copyright infringement claim is centrally focused on the MrSkin.com's compilation of clips and images. While the Flashcash announcement and tour includes three images from the Video, XPays nowhere argues that this was an infringing use. The announcement and tour are primarily relevant to the consumer confusion alleged in XPays' Lanham Act and unfair competition claims. Therefore, the Court holds that XPays does not raise a genuine issue of fact whether SK contributed to others' copyright infringement.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">b. <underscore>Vicarious Infringement</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p82" level="1">Even if a defendant lacks actual knowledge of infringement, a plaintiff may establish vicarious infringement by showing that a defendant (1) supervises or controls the party engaged in direct infringement and (2) profits from the direct infringement. <underscore>Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Studios, Inc. v. Grokster, Ltd.</underscore>, 545 U.S. 913, 930 (2005).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p83" level="1">For similar reasons, the Court finds no issue of fact on vicarious infringement. XPays does not argue that FlashCash infringed its copyright by circulating the announcement and tour. Further, the evidence does not support a vicarious infringement claim.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">3. <underscore>Willfulness</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p84" level="1">Under 504(c)(2) of the Copyright Act, a court may increase an award of statutory damages for copyright infringement upon a showing of willfulness. &#x201C;Willful&#x201D; means acting &#x201C;with knowledge that the defendant's conduct constitutes copyright infringement.&#x201D; <underscore>Columbia Pictures Television v. Krypton Broad.</underscore>, 106 F.3d 284, 293 (9th Cir. 1997) (internal quotation marks and citation omitted), rev'd on other grounds sub nom. &#x201C;To refute evidence of willful infringement, [the defendant] must not only establish its good faith belief in the innocence of its conduct, it must also show that it was reasonable in holding such a belief.&#x201D; <underscore>Peer Int'l Corp. v. Pausa Records, Inc.</underscore>, 909 F.2d 1332, 1336 (9th Cir. 1990).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p85" level="1">Having determined that there are issues of fact regarding SK's fair use defense, the Court also finds issues of fact whether SK engaged in willful infringement of the copyright. SK argues that it had a good faith belief that its conduct was not infringement based upon the advice of corporate counsel that it made a fair use of the footage and the fact that it acted like a movie reviewer. Nevertheless, SK has not provided any evidence to document this advice of corporate counsel, and despite likening its use to that of a movie reviewer, a reasonable factfinder could still determine that SK did not engage in fair use and willfully infringed the copyright.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">C. <underscore>Lanham Act Claim: Initial Interest Confusion</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p86" level="1">The Lanham Act section 43(a) provides a cause of action when a defendant's false designation of origin, or false or misleading statements create consumer confusion.<footnote.reference ID="fr9" refid="f9" style="percent_n">9</footnote.reference> XPays claims that SK has made false or misleading statements regarding the Video as to create actionable &#x201C;initial interest confusion.&#x201D; <underscore>See Playboy Enterprises, Inc. v. Netscape Communications Corp.</underscore>, 354 F.3d 1020, 1025 (9th Cir. 2004) (describing the &#x201C;initial interest confusion&#x201D; theory). SK argues that the Lanham Act claim impermissibly conflicts with the Copyright Act. SK further maintains that there was no consumer confusion as a matter of law.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f9"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN9.</label.designator><paratext ID="p87">&#8195;Section 43(a) of the Lanham Act provides in relevant part: (1) Any person who, on or in connection with any goods or services, or any container for goods, uses in commerce any word, term, name, symbol, or device, or any combination thereof, or any false designation of origin, false or misleading description of fact, or false or misleading representation of fact, which--</paratext>
<paratext ID="p88" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">(A) is likely to cause confusion, or to cause mistake, or to deceive as to the affiliation, connection, or association of such person with another person, or as to the origin, sponsorship, or approval of his or her goods, services, or commercial activities by another person<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill></paratext>
<paratext ID="p89" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">shall be liable in a civil action by any person who believes that he or she is or is likely to be damaged by such act.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">1. <underscore>The Copyright Act and Lanham Act Claims in This Case Are Compatible</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p90" level="1">As an initial matter, in both the motion to dismiss and motion for summary judgment, SK argues that the Supreme Court decision in <underscore>Dastar Corp. v. Twentieth Century Fox Film Corp.</underscore>, 539 U.S. 23, 28-38 (2003) rejected Lanham Act claims that are brought in conjunction with copyright infringement claims and relate to the requirements of the Copyright Act. The Court believes that SK reads <underscore>Dastar</underscore> too broadly.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p91" level="1">In <underscore>Dastar</underscore>, the defendant corporation had copied substantial portions of a 1949 television series based on Dwight Eisenhower's book, <underscore>Crusade in Europe</underscore>. At the time the defendant copied the footage, it was in the public domain. The defendant then sold the minimally edited footage as its own for less than plaintiffs, the companies that owned the distribution rights for the 1949 series. Plaintiffs sued for copyright infringement and &#x201C;failure to credit&#x201D; under section 43(a) of the Lanham Act. <underscore>Dastar</underscore>, 539 U.S. 25-29.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p92" level="1">The issue in <underscore>Dastar</underscore> was the definition of the term &#x201C;origin&#x201D; for &#x201C;false designation of origin&#x201D; claims under the Lanham Act. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 31. The Court held that the &#x201C;origin of goods&#x201D; is the producer of the actual goods, not the original creator of the idea, product, or communication. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 37. The Court reasoned that to hold the latter would cause a conflict between trademark and copyright law; anyone that used formerly copyrighted material could face trademark infringement claims for failing to credit the original creators. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 33-34. Relevant here, the Court noted that a false designation claim alleging consumer confusion as to the origin of goods &#x201C;would undoubtedly be sustained if [the defendant] had bought [plaintiff's] videotapes and merely repackaged them as its own.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 31.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p93" level="1">This last statement indicates that <underscore>Dastar</underscore> did not recognize a conflict between trademark and copyright law when the &#x201C;origin of goods&#x201D; is the producer of the actual goods. Here, XPays alleges that it is the source of the Video and SK has made false or misleading statements that created initial interest confusion regarding the origin. Contrary to SK's argument that the Lanham Act &#x201C;does not deal with origin of goods with respect to intellectual property,&#x201D; <underscore>Dastar</underscore> does not foreclose a false designation claim predicated on the conduct alleged here. Now the Court will consider whether the Lanham Act claim presents genuine issues of fact for trial.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">2. <underscore>Initial Interest Confusion</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p94" level="1">A person may incur liability for false designation of origin by (1) use in commerce (2) any word, false designation [*8] of origin, false or misleading description, or representation of fact, which (3) is likely to cause confusion or misrepresents the characteristics of his or another person's goods or services. 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1125(a). The test for trademark infringement and false designation of origin claims is the same. <underscore>Am. Circuit Breaker Corp. v. Or. Breakers, Inc.</underscore>, 406 F.3d 577, 584 (9th Cir. 2005), <underscore>citing New West Corp. v. NYM Co.</underscore>, 595 F.2d 1194, 1201 (9th Cir. 1979). &#x201C;The core element of trademark infringement is the likelihood of confusion, i.e., whether the similarity of the marks is likely to confuse customers about the source of the products.&#x201D; <underscore>Abercrombie &#38; Fitch Co. v. Moose Creek, Inc.</underscore>, 486 F.3d 629, 633 (9th Cir. 2007).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p95" level="1">As one theory of infringement, &#x201C;initial interest confusion is customer confusion that creates initial interest in a competitor's product.&#x201D; <underscore>Playboy Enterprises v. Netscape Communs. Corp.</underscore>, 354 F.3d 1020, 1025 (9th Cir. 2004). XPays argues that the evidence establishes SK has engaged in initial interest confusion. XPays maintains that SK authorized the FlashCash announcement and tour, which contain false and misleading statements regarding the Video. The announcement statements were that the Video was &#x201C;added to Mr. Skin&#x201D; and that affiliates should &#x201C;[m]ake sure<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> Celeb traffic is pointed towards Paris and Mr. Skin to maximize<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> money.&#x201D; The tour contained the statement &#x201C;SEE THE INFAMOUS PARIS HILTON VIDEOS HERE!&#x201D; XPays argues that this was a marketing scheme was designed to direct internet traffic to MrSkin.com by making consumers believe they would be able to access the Video there.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p96" level="1">The Court initially notes the similarity of this XPays' theory to other cases of initial interest confusion. In <underscore>Brookfield Communications, Inc. v. West Coast Entertainment Corporation</underscore>, 174 F.3d 1036 (9th Cir. 1999), the Ninth Circuit reversed denial of a preliminary injunction where a company may have engaged in initial interest confusion by use of a trademark-protected term to direct internet traffic to its website, effectively steering traffic away from the trademark owner's website. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1057. Similarly, in <underscore>Playboy Enterprises</underscore>, 354 F.3d 1020, the Ninth Circuit held that an initial interest confusion theory survived summary judgment where an alleged infringer used Playboy's trademarked terms as part of adult-oriented advertisements on the internet. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1025. The Ninth Circuit held that the use of the terms could lead consumer to click on those advertisements, believing the terms to be connected to Playboy. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1029.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p97" level="1">As in those cases, the Court finds XPays' theory of initial interest confusion viable. There are disputed facts whether FlashCash was SK's agent, or whether SK otherwise authorized and approved the allegedly infringing announcement and tour. The statements in the announcement and tour themselves are undisputed. It is a plausible inference that consumers believed that MrSkin.com had access to the Video, and that by going to the website or subscribing to MrSkin.com, the consumer would have access to the Video.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p98" level="1">&#x201C;To evaluate the likelihood of confusion, including initial interest confusion, the so-called Sleekcraft factors provide non-exhaustive guidance.&#x201D; <underscore>Interstellar Starship Servs. v. Epix, Inc.</underscore>, 304 F.3d 936, 942 (9th Cir. 2000). Although neither XPays nor SK address their arguments under the factors articulated in <underscore>AMF Inc. v Sleekcraft Boats</underscore>, 599 F.2d 341 (9th Cir. 1979), for determining likelihood of confusion, the Court believes that XPays raises genuine issues for trial when the facts are considered under those factors.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p99" level="1">The factors are: (1) strength of the mark, (2) proximity or relatedness of the goods, (3) similarity of the sight, sound and meaning of the mark, (4) evidence of actual confusion, (5) degree to which the marketing channels converge, (6) types of goods and degree of care consumers are likely to exercise when purchasing, (7) intent of defendants in selecting the infringing mark, and (8) likelihood that the parties will expand their product lines. <underscore>Dreamwerks Prod. Group, Inc. v. SKG Studio</underscore>, 142 F.3d 1127, 1129 (9th Cir. 1998). When alleged infringement occurs on the internet, the three most important factors are the similarity of the marks, the relatedness of the goods or services, and the parties' simultaneous use of the internet in marketing. <underscore>GoTo.com, Inc. v. Walt Disney Co.</underscore>, 202 F.3d 1199, 1205 9th Cir. 2000).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p100" level="1">At the relevant time to this action, SK and XPays were in the business of adult film and entertainment. One provided access to the Video, while the other provided a review of the Video. This supports the relatedness of the goods or services. The announcement and tour's promotion of the presence of the Video on MrSkin.com, along with its use of images from the Video, supports similarity of the claimed mark, i.e., &#x201C;the Video.&#x201D; Consumers can be expected to be easily diverted when searching the internet for adult films, showing evidence of lack of consumer care. Finally, both parties appear to primarily conduct business and market their products through the internet. At the very least, the evidence provides sufficient support to create an issue of fact.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p101" level="1">Therefore, SK cannot show no likelihood of confusion as a matter of law. Whether SK or FlashCash made the false or misleading statements is irrelevant, since a plaintiff may establish direct or contributory infringement. The Court also notes that SK argues it quickly responded to XPays' concerns about infringement and worked with FlashCash to send out a clarification when some affiliates continued to use the original announcement and tour. SK further claims that XPays cannot show damages. These arguments do not defeat summary judgment and may be more relevant to the issue of damages, then liability.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p102" level="0">///</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p103" level="1">The disputed facts raise genuine issues whether SK created initial interest confusion as to the location and source of the Video, drawing consumers to MrSkin.com through potentially false or misleading statements. The Court denies summary judgment on the Lanham Act claim as there are genuine issues of fact for trial.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">D. <underscore>Unfair Competition</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p104" level="1">To succeed on its unfair competition claim, XPays also must prove a likelihood of confusion. <underscore>See Cleary v. News Corp.</underscore>, 30 F.3d 1255,, 1262-63 (9th Cir. 1994 (stating that claims under California Business and Professions Code &#167; 17200 are &#x201C;&#x2018;substantially congruent&#x2019;&#x201D; to claims made under the Lanham Act&#x201D;) (internal citations omitted); <underscore>Walter v. Mattel, Inc.</underscore>, 210 F.3d 1108, 1111 (9th Cir. 2000) (stating that false designation under the Lanham Act, as well as statutory unfair competition claims, require a showing of likelihood of confusion).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p105" level="1">XPays' state law unfair competition claim is distinct from its copyright infringement claim based upon the incorporated allegations of false and misleading statements aimed at directing internet traffic to MrSkin.com. Because there are genuine issues of fact whether SK's conduct created a likelihood of confusion, the Court also denies summary judgment on the unfair competition claim.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">E. <underscore>Equitable Claims for Accounting and Constructive Trust</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p106" level="1">SK's primary argument for granting summary judgment on the accounting and constructive trust claims are that XPays' other claims fail as a matter of law. Where the Court finds genuine issues of fact on the Lanham Act and unfair competition claims, the Court will find the same for the equitable claims.<footnote.reference ID="fr10" refid="f10" style="percent_n">10</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f10"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN10.</label.designator><paratext ID="p107">&#8195;The Court does not find the equitable claims to be preempted, nor does it find SK's single sentence asserting preemption to constitute sufficient argument on this point.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p108" level="0">///</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p109" level="0">///</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p110" level="0">///</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p111" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court DENIES SK's motion to dismiss. The Court GRANTS in part and DENIES in part summary judgment:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p112" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">1. The Court DENIES SK summary judgment on XPays' direct copyright infringement claim and willful infringement. The Court GRANTS SK summary judgment on XPays' secondary liability theories of copyright infringement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p113" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">2. The Court DENIES SK summary judgment on XPays' Lanham Act claim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p114" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">3. The Court DENIES SK summary judgment on XPays' unfair competition claim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p115" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">4. The Court DENIES SK summary judgment on XPays' equitable claims.</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p116" level="0">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p117" level="0">Dated: January 10, 2008</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>