<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><bold>CIVIL MINUTES &#8211; GENERAL</bold></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>Farhad Fazli, et al.</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>ConocoPhillips Co., et al.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 03-04938-FMC (VBKx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 03-04938-FMC (VBKx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:03-cv-04938-FMC-VBK</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 08/25/2008</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Roxanne Horan, Deputy Clerk, Attorneys Present for Plaintiffs: None Present</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Court Reporter / Recorder, Attorneys Present for Defendants: None Present</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Tape No.</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Proceedings: DEFENDANT'S MOTION FOR DISCOVERY</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">The Victor B. Kenton, United States Magistrate Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="0">Following the issuance of the Court's Tentative Decision, counsel for both parties informed the Court that they intend to submit on the Tentative Decision. Consequently, the hearing calendared for August 26, 2008 is <bold>HEREBY VACATED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="0">The Court has received and reviewed the following documents:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="0">&#x201C;ConocoPhillips Company's Notice of Motion and Motion to Compel Farhad Fazli's Responses to Requests for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions;&#x201D; &#x201C;Local Rule 37-2.1 Joint Stipulation in Support of ConocoPhillips Company's Motion to Compel Farhad Fazli's Responses to Requests for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions;&#x201D; &#x201C;Declaration of Jonathan A. Eldredge in Support of ConocoPhillips Company's Motion to Compel Farhad Fazli's Responses to Requests for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions;&#x201D; &#x201C;Local Rule 37-2.1 Joint Stipulation in Support of ConocoPhillips Company's Motion to Compel Farhad Fazli's Responses to Requests for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions [Including Plaintiff's Contentions];&#x201D; &#x201C;Plaintiff Farhad Fazli's Supplemental Memorandum in Opposition to Defendant, ConocoPhillips Company's Motion to Compel Responses to Request for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions Pursuant to Local Rule 37-2.3;&#x201D; &#x201C;Declaration of Gannady L. Lebedev in Support of Plaintiff Farhad Fazli's Supplemental Memorandum in Opposition to Defendant, ConocoPhillips Company's Motion to Compel Responses to Request for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions Pursuant to Local Rule 37-2.3;&#x201D; &#x201C;ConocoPhillips Company's Local Rule 37-2.3 Supplemental Memorandum in Support of its Motion to Compel Farhad Fazli's Responses to Requests for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions;&#x201D; &#x201C;Supplemental Declaration of Gannady L. Lebedev in Support of Plaintiff Farhad Fazli's Memorandum in Opposition to Defendant, ConocoPhillips Company's Motion to Compel Responses to Request for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions Pursuant to Local Rule 37-2.3;&#x201D; &#x201C;ConocoPhillips Company's Local Rule 37-2.3 Supplemental Memorandum in Support of its Motion to Compel Farhad Fazli's Responses to Requests for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions;&#x201D; and &#x201C;Supplemental Declaration of Jonathan A. Eldredge in Support of ConocoPhillips Company's Motion to Compel Farhad Fazli's Responses to Requests for Production of Documents and for Monetary Sanctions.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>FACTUAL BACKGROUND</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="0">Plaintiff Farhad Fazli (&#x201C;Fazli&#x201D;), as an individual through a dba, operated Fountain Valley 76, a service station that marketed petroleum products, the premises of which was owned by Defendant ConocoPhillips (&#x201C;Conoco&#x201D;). Fazli had a Lease and Franchise Agreement (&#x201C;Agreement&#x201D;) with Conoco. On or about April 22, 2003, Conoco notified Fazli that Conoco intended to not renew the Agreement based upon its decision to sell the service station premises. Conoco gave Fazli a purported &#x201C;bona fide offer&#x201D; for the sale of the land, equipment and improvements for a particular price. Fazli thereafter accepted the offer &#x201C;under protest&#x201D; and submitted a deposit into escrow. Conoco accepted that deposit and escrow was opened; however, the sale was cancelled. In December 2003, Fazli filed this lawsuit challenging the offer on several grounds, including his contention that the sale price exceeded and failed to approach fair market value. On May 25, 2004, Conoco gave Fazli a new purported offer of right of first refusal of a third party offer, for the same price as the first &#x201C;bona fide&#x201D; offer made approximately a year earlier. The effective date for non-renewal is October 31, 2004.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="0">This case arises under the Petroleum Marketing Practices Act (&#x201C;PMPA&#x201D;), 15 U.S.C. &#167;2801, <underscore>et seq</underscore>. Under the provisions of 15 U.S.C. &#167;2805(d)(1), if the franchisee (e.g., Fazli) prevails in any action which asserts failure to comply with the requirements of the PMPA, the franchisee shall be entitled to actual damages &#x201C;consistent with the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure,<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="0">The discovery dispute at issue here concerns Requests for Production of Documents, No. 11, propounded by Conoco to Fazli, which requests the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p7" first-line="1" turnover="1">&#x201C;All DOCUMENTS that evidence, refer or RELATE TO state, federal or other tax returns filed by YOU for the years 1997 to 2007, including without limitation any attachments to or documents filed or prepared in support of such tax returns.&#x201D; (Joint Stipulation [&#x201C;JS&#x201D;] at 5.)</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p8" contd-flag="y">Fazli responded by objecting that the request is overly broad and burdensome, compound, vague and ambiguous. Fazli also asserted that the request seeks information protected by the attorney-client privilege and attorney work product doctrine and prematurely seeks information that is the subject of expert opinion. Finally, Fazli asserted that the request seeks information not calculated to lead to discovery of admissible evidence and seeks information protected by the right to privacy and the taxpayer privilege.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="0">Conoco asserts that Fazli is seeking an unspecified amount of damages in the form of lost income related to Conoco's non-renewal of its franchise with Fazli. Conoco contends that Fazli has therefore placed his income at issue, and that the information sought is relevant to the question of damages, in particular, to mitigation of damages.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="0">The parties indicate that Fazli has produced tax returns for his d/b/a Fountain Valley 76, but has refused to produce his personal tax returns, invoking a California &#x201C;taxpayer privilege&#x201D; which assertedly precludes such discovery.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>ANALYSIS</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="0">Fazli has turned to state law privilege provisions to support his assertion that his personal tax returns are protected from discovery. This contention is unavailing, because this is a federal question case under the PMPA, and pursuant to Rule 501 of the Federal Rules of Evidence, federal privilege law is applicable. There is no federal privilege against disclosure of tax returns, and they are consequently subject to civil discovery in appropriate circumstances. <underscore>See Heathman v. United States District Court for Central District</underscore>, 503 F.2d 1032 (9<super style="percent_r">th</super> Cir. 1974). Tax returns, however, do possess by statute a character of confidentiality, and thus a Court will be cautious in ordering their disclosure. <underscore>See In re Reading Tube Corp.</underscore>, 73 Bankr Rep 99 (Bankr Ct. Ed. Pa 1987). Thus, production of tax returns will not generally be ordered in the absence of a compelling need for the information, such as that it is not otherwise readily obtainable. <underscore>See Wiesenberger v. W.E. Hutton &#38; Co.</underscore>, 35 F.R.D. 556 (S.D. N.Y. 1964); <underscore>Eglin Federal Credit Union v. Cantor Fitzgerald Securities Corp.</underscore>, 91 F.R.D. 414 (N.D. Ga 1981); <underscore>Shaver v. Yacht Outward Bound</underscore>, 71 F.R.D. 561 (N.D. Ill 1976); <underscore>Biliske v. American Live Space Stock Insurance Co.</underscore>, 73 F.R.D. 124 (W.D. Okla 1977). Federal income tax returns will be subject to discovery in federal civil actions where the taxpayer-litigant opposing discovery has raised an issue as to amount of income, including the issue of the amount of damages. (<underscore>See Shaver, supra</underscore>; <underscore>Biliske, supra</underscore>; <underscore>In re Reading Tube Corp., supra</underscore>.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="0">The next questions, which are interconnected, are whether the principle of mitigation of damages is applicable in PMPA cases, and if so, whether the personal tax returns of Fazli which Conoco seeks are relevant to discovery as to mitigation of damages.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="0">With regard to the first question, courts have held that mitigation of damages is applicable in PMPA cases. For example, in <underscore>Four Corners Service Station, Inc. v. Mobiloil Corp.</underscore>, 51 F.3d 306 (1<super style="percent_r">st</super> Cir. 1995), a gasoline service station franchisee brought an action against the franchiser, alleging an unlawful non-renewal of the franchise agreement in violation of the PMPA. Four Corners was a retail gasoline distributor, and had been a party to a series of renewable franchise agreements with Mobil. Mobil notified Four Corners of its decision not to renew the franchise agreement due to asserted breach of certain terms of their agreements. Four Corners initiated an action in federal District Court alleging that Mobil had wrongfully refused to renew the franchise agreement in violation of PMPA. The complaint sought reinstatement of the franchise, actual and exemplary damages, attorneys fees and costs. (<underscore>See</underscore>, 51 F.3d at 309.) Four Corners, in the meantime, had opened an expanded and modernized service station at the same site under new ownership and management, and this new station purchased its gasoline supplies from another supplier. Following a court trial, the District Court found that Mobil had violated PMPA by refusing to renew the franchise. The parties submitted supplemental briefs to the Court on the right to recover lost profits. The Court rejected Four Corners' lost profits calculation finding, in part, that Four Corners actually succeeded in selling more gasoline from its successor suppliers following Mobil's non-renewal than it could have sold under the agreement it had with Mobil. As the appellate court observed, the District Court concluded that &#x201C;Four Corners experienced an increase in profits not a reduction<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; Because Four Corners proved no actual damages, the Court exercised its discretion, under 15 U.S.C. &#167;2805(d)(1)(C) and denied an attorneys fee award. (<underscore>Id</underscore>. at 310.) On appeal, Four Corners challenged the ruling of the trial court denying compensatory damages and attorneys fees. The appellate court addressed the issue of calculation of compensatory damages under PMPA, observing the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p14" first-line="1" turnover="1">&#x201C;<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> nor is there anything in PMPA's language or legislative history to suggest that Congress intended to deviate from the normal presumption, uniformly applied to numerous other causes of action arising under federal remedial statutes, that compensatory damages may not exceed the amount necessary to make the injured party whole. <underscore>See, e.g., Midwest Petroleum Co. v. American Petrofina Mktg., Inc.</underscore>, 644 F.Supp. 1067, 1071 (E.D. Mo. 1986)(noting PMPA franchisee is not entitled to &#x2018;double recovery&#x2019; where it has otherwise mitigated harmful effects of defendant's violation); <underscore>see also Russo v. Texaco, Inc.</underscore>, 630 F.Supp. 682, 687 (E.D. N.Y.) (PMPA is a diminution of franchiser&#x2019; common-law contract rights, and its remedial provisions should not be unduly extended beyond statute's express language and purpose), <underscore>aff'd</underscore>, 808 F.2d 221 (2d Cir. 1986).&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>. at 313.)</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="0">In another action brought under PMPA, <underscore>Roberts v. Amoco Oil Co.</underscore>, 740 F.2d 602 (8<super style="percent_r">th</super> Cir. 1984), the appellate court reversed a grant of summary judgment in favor of Amoco and in the following language, remanded the case for trial:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="1" turnover="1">&#x201C;We remand the case for trial so that Roberts may attempt to prove that Amoco's bad faith offer of sale caused him to vacate the premises out of practical business necessity. Roberts may also introduce evidence of actual damages pursuant to the statute. Amoco, of course, is free to present its defense concerning both whether it coerced Roberts into leaving the Penn Avenue station, and whether Roberts mitigated his damages, if any.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>. at 609.)</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p17" contd-flag="y">Fazli asserts in the JS,</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p18" first-line="1" turnover="1">&#x201C;If Plaintiff is successful in his claim that ConocoPhillips' nonrenewal of the franchise was in violation of the Petroleum Marketing Practices Act, 15 U.S.C. &#167;2801, et seq. (&#x2018;PMPA&#x2019;), he could recover damages that include the amount of profit that <underscore>the business</underscore> would have generated from the time Plaintiff vacated the property until today. Plaintiff is also seeking the goodwill value of the business at the present time and any appreciation in the value of the real estate on which the station is located. Thus, the only income that is relevant or in any way could be reasonably calculated to lead to admissible evidence is the income generated by the gasoline station business itself.&#x201D; (JS at 8, emphasis in original.)</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p19" first-line="1" turnover="1">Fazli, however, asserts that he has already produced the necessary and sufficient financial data in the form of financial records pertaining to the gas station business itself, including all of the tax returns and income and expense records, such as profit and loss statements, for the business. (<underscore>See</underscore> JS at 8-9.) Fazli avers that, &#x201C;The tax records being sought by way of this motion solely pertain to Plaintiff's individual tax returns through the present day, which have absolutely no connection to the subject gas station itself.&#x201D; (JS at 9.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="0">Fazli does not specifically address the issue of whether PMPA allows evidence concerning mitigation of damages. The Court concludes that mitigation of damages is applicable and, in a PMPA case, therefore, documents pertinent to mitigation of damages are discoverable.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Certainly, since Fazli operated the gasoline station as an individual under a d.b.a, it would seem relevant to mitigation of damages to obtain evidence concerning Fazli's subsequent income. As stated in Am. Jur., Second Edition, &#167;355:</paratext>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p21">&#8195;The Court makes this finding of relevance only insofar as it extends to the discovery dispute. It is within the trial court's exclusive jurisdiction to determine the admissibility of evidence.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p22" first-line="1" turnover="1">&#x201C;The fact that a reasonably prudent person acting under the facts and circumstances facing the nondefaulting party would have minimized the claimed losses by entering into other contracts with a third party may be shown in reduction of damages. However, if the plaintiffs cannot, after expending reasonable effort, readily negotiate a substitute contract, the damages will not be mitigated.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p23" contd-flag="y">The concept of mitigation of damages emanates from the doctrine of avoidable consequences, which states that a party cannot recover damages flowing from consequences that the party could reasonably have avoided. <underscore>See Chesapeake &#38; O.Ry. Co. v. Kelly</underscore>, 241 U.S. 485, 36 S.Ct. 630 (1916).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="0">As stated in the Restatement 2<super style="percent_r">nd</super> Contracts, &#167;350(2),</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p25" first-line="1" turnover="1">&#x201C;The injured party is not precluded from recovery<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> to the extent that he has made reasonable but unsuccessful efforts to avoid loss.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p26" contd-flag="y">Citing Restatement, 2<super style="percent_r">nd</super>, Contracts 2d, Judge Wardlaw in the case of <underscore>Alltel Information Services, Inc. v. Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation</underscore>, 970 F.Supp. 775 (C.D. Ca. 1997), observed that,</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p27" first-line="1" turnover="1">&#x201C;Moreover, the law of contracts is clear that the non-breaching party has a duty to mitigate damages. <underscore>Id</underscore>. &#167;350 (unless a party has made reasonable efforts to avoid a loss, &#x2018;damages are not recoverable for loss that the injured party could have avoided without undue risk, burden or humiliation&#x2019;).&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>. at 780.)</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="0">Thus, the Court concludes that in this case, Conoco has a right to obtain discovery relevant to mitigation of damages. The Court fails to see how production of the financial records of the service station during the time period it was operated by Fazli would provide sufficient information as to subsequent mitigation of damages. Contrary to Conoco's contention that as a matter of law Fazli is required to mitigate his damages (<underscore>see</underscore> JS at 5), he is not under any such duty, but the failure to mitigate damages is relevant to the ultimate calculation of damages actually suffered. Conoco seeks Fazli's income tax records from 1997 to 2004 &#x201C;to establish a baseline for Plaintiff's income prior to the non-renewal and from 2005 to 2007 to show Plaintiff's efforts, if any, to mitigate his damages.&#x201D; (JS at 6.) The Court is persuaded that the time frame requested is reasonable, as it provides evidence for approximately three years before the commencement of the franchise agreement between Fazli and Conoco, and approximately three years subsequent to the termination of the agreement. Moreover, Fazli has not suggested an alternative means by which this relevant information may be obtained. The Court is mindful that production of personal tax returns is typically a &#x201C;last resort&#x201D; form of discovery to obtain such information; however, in the absence of Fazli's suggestion of any alternative, the Court sees none. Certainly, the tax returns which the Court will order to be produced will be subject to the highest confidentiality. Conoco will restrict the use of these documents, and the information contained therein, to this litigation only. The documents and the information contained therein will not be disclosed to any person or entity, other than Conoco's litigation counsel, essential members of counsel's staff, and any expert witnesses properly designated in this case. The documents will not be copied, and will be returned to Fazli at the conclusion of the litigation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="0">For the foregoing reasons, the Court <bold>GRANTS</bold> Conoco's Motion. The documents will be produced within thirty (30) calendar days of the date of this Order. The request for sanctions is <bold>DENIED WITHOUT PREJUDICE</bold> and will be denied with prejudice if documents are produced which are complete (assuming they are in Fazli's possession or control<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference>) and timely. Only federal tax returns need to be produced.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p30">&#8195;The Court notes that Fazli has not contended he is not in possession or control of the tax returns.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="0"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="0">Initials of Preparer <underscore>RH</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>