<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><bold>CIVIL MINUTES &#8211; GENERAL</bold></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment><bold>JANEE JOHNSON</bold></title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment><bold>SUNRISE SENIOR LIVING MANAGEMENT, INC. ET AL.</bold></title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. <bold>CV 16-00443-BRO (RAOx)</bold></docket.line>
<docket.number><bold>CV 16-00443-BRO (RAOx)</bold></docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:16-cv-00443-BRO-RAO</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 05/05/2016</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1"><underscore>Renee A. Fisher</underscore>, Deputy Clerk, Attorneys Present for Plaintiffs: Not Present</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1"><underscore>Not Present</underscore>, Court Reporter, Attorneys Present for Defendants: Not Present</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1"><underscore>N/A</underscore>, Tape No.</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Proceedings:</bold> (IN CHAMBERS) <bold>ORDER DENYING PLAINTIFF'S MOTION FOR RECONSIDERATION [27] AND GRANTING IN PART AND DENYING IN PART DEFENDANT'S MOTION TO DISMISS PLAINTIFF'S FIRST AMENDED COMPLAINT [28]</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">The Honorable <underscore><bold>BEVERLY REID O'CONNELL, United States District Judge</bold></underscore></judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. INTRODUCTION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Pending before the Court are two motions: (1) Plaintiff Janee Johnson's (&#x201C;Plaintiff&#x201D;) Motion for Reconsideration, (Dkt. No. 27); and, (2) Defendant Sunrise Senior Living Management, Inc.'s (&#x201C;Defendant&#x201D;) Motion to Dismiss Plaintiff's First Amended Complaint (&#x201C;FAC&#x201D;) pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6), (Dkt. No. 28). After considering the papers filed in support of and in opposition to the instant Motions, the Court deems these matters appropriate for resolution without oral argument of counsel. <ital>See</ital> Fed. R. Civ. P. 78; C.D. Cal. L.R. 7-15. For the following reasons, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Plaintiff's Motion for Reconsideration and <bold>GRANTS in part</bold> Defendant's Motion to Dismiss.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Factual Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">From approximately 2011 to 2014, Defendant employed Plaintiff as a concierge, care manager, and medication care manager in Los Angeles County. (First Am. Compl. (&#x201C;FAC&#x201D;) &#182;&#182; 2&#8211;3.) According to Plaintiff, Defendant deposits employees' wages with a third party called Money Network. (FAC &#182; 8.) Defendant also issues final wages to its employees through a debit card kit (&#x201C;Pay Kit&#x201D;) that includes a pre-paid debit card (&#x201C;Pay Card&#x201D;) and three blank checks (&#x201C;Checks&#x201D;). (<ital>Id.</ital>) Plaintiff claims that Defendant issues the Pay Kit in Defendant's name rather than the employees' names and that Defendant does not explain how to use the Pay Kit. (FAC &#182; 9.) She also avers that Defendant does not permit employees to choose an alternative form of payment for the employees' final paycheck. (<ital>Id.</ital>) Thus, according to Plaintiff, the Pay Kit program is mandatory, not optional. (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">In order to utilize the mandatory Pay Kit, Defendant allegedly requires its employees to open an account with Money Networks. (FAC &#182; 12.) Plaintiff alleges that, in doing so, &#x201C;Plaintiff and the other putative class members were required to agree to onerous and unconscionable terms and conditions to access their earned wages, including but not limited to a purported waiver of liability, the right to set off, penalties and fees, and an arbitration provision.&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 10.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Plaintiff further maintains that the Checks provided in the Pay Kit were not immediately cashable, as the instructions indicated. (FAC &#182; 11.) Specifically, Plaintiff alleges that when she followed the Pay Kit's instructions to access her wages using the Checks&#8212;e.g., by dialing the telephone number which purportedly connects the employee to a service that provides the code necessary to complete the transaction&#8212;Plaintiff was unable to obtain the required authorization number. (<ital>Id.</ital>) She also claims that when she presented the Pay Kit to her bank,<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> it refused to honor both the Checks and the Pay Card, as they were issued in Defendant's name, not Plaintiff's. (FAC &#182; 18.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p5">&#8195;At the time, Plaintiff held an account with Chase bank. (<ital>See</ital> FAC &#182; 18.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">After the bank refused to honor the Pay Kit, Plaintiff used an ATM to obtain her wages. (<ital>Id.</ital>) However, Plaintiff alleges she was only able to withdraw $300 per transaction, she incurred a $2.50 fee per transaction, and because the ATM only dispensed $20 bills, a $3.00 balance remains on her Pay Card. (<ital>Id.</ital>) According to Plaintiff, her inability to access the full amount of her wages is not unique, as approximately 70% of those who received the Pay Kit used the Pay Card, incurred the associated fees as a result, and thus failed to receive all of their earned wages. (FAC &#182; 14.) Moreover, Plaintiff alleges that on or about February 20, 2014, one of Plaintiff's co-workers notified Defendant in writing of the confusion associated with utilizing the Pay Kit; thus, Defendant has been aware of its employees' inability to access the full amount of their wages since at least that time. (FAC &#182; 15.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">Finally, Plaintiff alleges that Defendant maintains a policy of failing to provide an accurate itemized statement with the Pay Kit. (FAC &#182; 16.) Namely, Plaintiff states that &#x201C;Defendant either fails to provide a paystub at all, or[,] when it does, the itemized statements fails [sic] to set forth the inclusive dates of the period for which the employee is paid and also fails to set forth the name and address of the legal entity that is the employer.&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">According to Plaintiff, Defendant's alleged violations apply to all of its employees who quit or are terminated. (<ital>See</ital> FAC &#182;&#182; 8, 16&#8211;18.) Consequently, Plaintiff filed the instant class action seeking to represent a class defined as: &#x201C;All persons employed in California whose employment was separated for any reason (voluntary or involuntary), including without limitation, resignation, termination, and/or lay-off, from December 31, 2010 to the present and received their final wages in the form of a Pay Kit (the &#x2018;Pay Kit Class&#x2019;).&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 19.) Plaintiff also seeks to represent a sub-class, defined as: &#x201C;All persons who used the ATM Card component of the Pay Kit and incurred fees or other charges (thereby resulting in a failure to pay all wages due) upon separation of employment (the &#x2018;ATM Card Sub-Class&#x2019;).&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Plaintiff's FAC alleges four causes of action: (1) violation of California Labor Code sections 201 through 202; (2) violation of California Labor Code section 226; (3) civil penalties pursuant to the Private Attorneys General Act (&#x201C;PAGA&#x201D;), California Labor Code section 2699 <ital>et seq.</ital>, for violation of California Labor Code sections 201 through 203, 206, 206.5, 212 through 213, 226, and 432.5; and, (4) violation of California Business and Professions Code section 17200 <ital>et seq.</ital> (&#x201C;UCL&#x201D;). (FAC &#182;&#182; 29&#8211;55.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Procedural History</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Plaintiff filed her Complaint in the Superior Court of California, County of Los Angeles, on December 31, 2014. (Dkt. No. 1-1.) Defendant first removed the action to this Court on March 27, 2015, alleging this Court's jurisdiction under the Class Action Fairness Act of 2005 (or &#x201C;CAFA&#x201D;), 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1332(d). (<ital>Johnson v. Sunrise Senior Living Mgmt., Inc.</ital>, Case No. 2:15-cv-02297-BRO-VBK (hereinafter, &#x201C;Case No. 15-2297&#x201D;), Dkt. No. 1.) On June 18, 2015, the Court granted Plaintiff's Motion to Remand, providing that &#x201C;Defendant &#x2018;may once again attempt to remove this case to federal court&#x2019; if it &#x2018;later discovers evidence that the jurisdictional bar is met.&#x2019;&#x201D; (Case No. 15-2297, Dkt. No. 34 at 15 (quoting <ital>Garibay v. Archstone Cmtys. LLC</ital>, 539 F. App'x 763, 765 (9th Cir. 2013)).)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">On January 20, 2016, Defendant once again removed the case, claiming federal jurisdiction under CAFA. (Dkt. No. 1.) On January 27, 2016, Defendant moved to dismiss the first and third causes of action in Plaintiff's Original Complaint. (Dkt. No. 14.) On February 8, 2016, Plaintiff filed a Motion to Remand. (Dkt. No. 16 (hereinafter, &#x201C;Remand Mot.&#x201D;).)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">On March 8, 2016, the Court denied Plaintiff's Motion to Remand and granted, in part, Defendant's Motion to Dismiss. (Dkt. No. 25 (hereinafter, &#x201C;Order&#x201D;).) As to Plaintiff's first claim alleging violation of California Labor Code<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> sections 201 through 203, the Court concluded that Plaintiff failed to state a claim &#x201C;because Defendant provided at least one free transaction.&#x201D; (Order at 16.) The Court therefore granted Defendant's Motion as to Plaintiff's first claim, with leave to amend. (Order at 17.) The Court added that, because Plaintiff assumed a contrary position to that which she maintained in her Reply in support of her first Motion to Remand, the doctrine of judicial estoppel precluded her from arguing that Defendant violated sections 201 through 203 because its payment of final wages was &#x201C;not unconditional.&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital>) The Court denied Defendant's Motion as to Plaintiff's third cause of action, (Order at 18), but the Court dismissed Plaintiff's PAGA claim without prejudice given her failure to comply with PAGA's notice requirement, (Order at 18&#8211;19).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p13">&#8195;Unless otherwise specified, all statutory references hereinafter relate to the California Labor Code.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">On March 18, 2016, Plaintiff filed her FAC. (Dkt. No. 26.) On April 4, 2016, she filed the instant Motion for Reconsideration. (Dkt. No. 27 (hereinafter, &#x201C;Mot. for Recons.&#x201D;).) Namely, Plaintiff argues that the Court failed to consider the material fact that Defendant's Pay Kit is mandatory, not optional, (Mot. for Recons. at 4&#8211;6), and that the Court committed manifest error by applying the doctrine of judicial estoppel, (Mot. for Recons. at 6&#8211;12). Defendant timely opposed on April 11, 2016, (Dkt. No. 29), and Plaintiff timely replied, (Dkt. No. 32).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Defendant also filed its Motion to Dismiss on April 4, 2016, seeking dismissal of Plaintiff's entire FAC pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6). (Dkt. No. 28 (hereinafter, &#x201C;MTD&#x201D;).) Defendant's Motion is accompanied by a Request for Judicial Notice (&#x201C;RJN&#x201D;). (Dkt. No. 28-1.) Plaintiff filed a timely Opposition, (Dkt. No. 30 (hereinafter, &#x201C;Opp'n to MTD&#x201D;)), which was accompanied by her own RJN, (Dkt. No. 31). Defendant timely replied. (Dkt. No. 33 (hereinafter, &#x201C;MTD Reply&#x201D;).)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. PLAINTIFF'S MOTION FOR RECONSIDERATION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Legal Standard</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">A final order may be reconsidered &#x201C;under either Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 59(e) (motion to alter or amend a judgment) or Rule 60(b) (relief from judgment).&#x201D; <ital>Sch. Dist. No. 1J, Multnomah Cty., Or. v. ACandS Inc.</ital>, 5 F.3d 1255, 1262 (9th Cir. 1993). If the motion is filed within twenty-eight days of entry of judgment, it is treated as a Rule 59(e) motion. <ital>See Am. Ironworks &#38; Erectors Inc. v. N. Am. Constr. Corp.</ital>, 248 F.3d 892, 899 (9th Cir. 2001) (referring to a previous version of Rule 59(e) requiring the motion to be filed within ten days of judgment instead of twenty-eight); Fed. R. Civ. P. 59(e) (requiring a motion to alter or amend a judgment to be filed within twenty-eight days after entry of judgment); <ital>see also</ital> Fed. R. Civ. P. 59 advisory committee's notes to 2009 Amendments. Otherwise, the motion is treated as a Rule 60(b) motion. <ital>Am. Ironworks &#38; Erectors</ital>, 248 F.3d at 899.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Under Rule 59(e), reconsideration is appropriate if (1) the court &#x201C;is presented with newly discovered evidence,&#x201D; (2) the court &#x201C;committed clear error or the initial decision was manifestly unjust,&#x201D; or (3) &#x201C;if there is an intervening change in controlling law.&#x201D; <ital>Sch. Dist. No. 1J</ital>, 5 F.3d at 1263. Other highly unusual circumstances may also warrant reconsideration under the rule. <ital>Id.</ital> Rule 60(b) sets forth the following grounds for relief from a final judgment: (1) &#x201C;mistake, inadvertence, surprise, or excusable neglect&#x201D;; (2) &#x201C;newly discovered evidence that, with reasonable diligence, could not have been discovered in time to move for a new trial&#x201D;; (3) fraud; (4) a void judgment; (5) a satisfied, released, or discharged judgment; or (6) &#x201C;any other reason that justifies relief.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 60(b); <ital>see also Am. Ironworks &#38; Erectors</ital>, 248 F.3d at 899.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The Central District's Local Rules further limit the grounds for reconsideration. Under Local Rule 7-18, a party may seek reconsideration only upon a showing of one of the following: (1) &#x201C;a material difference in fact or law&#x201D; from that initially presented to the Court, which the party could not have known by exercising reasonable diligence; (2) &#x201C;the emergence of new material facts or a change of law&#x201D; after the Court's order; or (3) &#x201C;a manifest showing of a failure to consider material facts presented to the Court.&#x201D; C.D. Cal. L.R. 7-18. Local rules have the force and effect of law so long as they are not inconsistent with a statute or the Federal Rules. <ital>See Atchison, Topeka &#38; Santa Fe R.R. Co. v. Hercules Inc.</ital>, 146 F.3d 1071, 1074 (9th Cir. 1998). A court should not depart from the local rules unless the effect on the parties' rights would be &#x201C;so slight and unimportant that the sensible treatment is to overlook it.&#x201D; <ital>Prof'l Programs Grp. v. Dep't of Commerce</ital>, 29 F.3d 1349, 1353 (9th Cir. 1994).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Discussion</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">As discussed above, Plaintiff raises two arguments in support of her Motion. First, Plaintiff contends that the Court failed to consider the material fact that Defendant's Pay Kit program was not optional. (Mot. for Recons. at 4&#8211;6.) Second, Plaintiff maintains that the Court erred by applying the doctrine of judicial estoppel. (Mot. for Recons. at 6&#8211; 12.) The Court will address each argument in turn.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>1. Mandatory v. Voluntary Pay Kit</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">Plaintiff's first argument is that although the Court relied on two opinion letters issued by the California Division of Labor Standards Enforcement (&#x201C;DLSE&#x201D;) in dismissing Plaintiff's first cause of action, the Court failed to consider that those opinions are inapplicable to this matter; namely, because Defendant's Pay Kit was mandatory and the DLSE letters &#x201C;are predicated on the assumption that the employee voluntarily consented to&#x201D; the alternative form of wage payment. (Mot. for Recons. at 4.) Thus, according to Plaintiff, the Court should reconsider its Order. (Mot. for Recons. at 5&#8211;6.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">The Court disagrees. The fact that the Court did not analyze the voluntary/mandatory issue establishes that there is nothing to reconsider. The Court's conclusion was limited to the fact that, as pleaded, the Original Complaint failed to &#x201C;plausibly allege a violation of section 203 because Defendant provided at least one free transaction.&#x201D; (Order at 16.) Given that the Court did not render an opinion as to the mandatory characteristic of the Pay Kit, there is no law of the case<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> application precluding Plaintiff from arguing that, because the Pay Kit is mandatory, it violates the California Labor Code. In fact, Plaintiff does just that in her Opposition to Defendant's Motion to Dismiss. (<ital>See</ital> Opp'n to MTD at 9&#8211;11.) Finally, the Court granted Plaintiff leave to amend her Complaint, and she filed her FAC on March 18, 2016&#8212;over two weeks before she filed the instant Motion. Accordingly, Plaintiff's reconsideration &#x201C;request is moot in light of the fact that the Court has already granted Plaintiff leave to file a First Amended Complaint in this matter.&#x201D; <ital>Heilman v. Cook</ital>, No. 14 CV 1412 GPC JMA, 2014 WL 3728171, at *2 (S.D. Cal. July 25, 2014).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p22">&#8195;&#x201C;The &#x2018;law of the case&#x2019; doctrine states that the decision on a legal issue by the same or a superior court must be followed in all subsequent proceedings in the same case.&#x201D; <ital>Vanleeuwen v. Keyuan Petrochemicals, Inc.</ital>, No. CV 11-9495 PSG JCGx, 2013 WL 2247394, at *7 (C.D. Cal. May 9, 2013) (citing <ital>Planned Parenthood of Cent. &#38; N. Ariz. v. Arizona</ital>, 718 F.2d 938, 949 (9th Cir. 1983)). &#x201C;For the doctrine to apply, &#x2018;the issue in question must have been decided explicitly or by necessary implication in [the] previous disposition.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> (quoting <ital>Milgard Tempering, Inc. v. Selas Corp. of Am.</ital>, 902 F.2d 703, 715 (9th Cir. 1990)). In the previous Order, the Court neither explicitly, nor through &#x201C;necessary implication,&#x201D; rendered any conclusions regarding the fact the Pay Kit is mandatory.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">For these reasons, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Plaintiff's Motion for Reconsideration based on this argument.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>2. Judicial Estoppel</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Plaintiff next maintains that the Court committed manifest error by applying the doctrine of judicial estoppel<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> to preclude Plaintiff from claiming that Defendant's &#x201C;conditional&#x201D; payment of wages violates sections 201 through 203. (Mot. for Recons. at 6&#8211;12; <ital>see also</ital> Order at 17.) In the previous Order, the Court noted that, in her Reply in support of her first Motion to Remand, Plaintiff argued that although &#x201C;Defendant's conditional payment of wages violates other sections of the California Labor Code, this allegation does not affect the Section 203 waiting time penalty.&#x201D; (Order at 17 (citing Case No. 15-2297, Dkt. No. 27 at 5&#8211;6).) Given that Plaintiff contradicted this statement by arguing in her Opposition to Defendant's first Motion to Dismiss that Defendant's &#x201C;conditional&#x201D; payment of wages violates section 203, the Court judicially estopped her from raising that inconsistent argument. (Order at 17.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p25">&#8195;&#x201C;[W]here a party assumes a certain position in a legal proceeding, and succeeds in maintaining that position, he may not thereafter, simply because his interests have changed, assume a contrary position. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; <ital>See Baughman v. Walt Disney World Co.</ital>, 685 F.3d 1131, 1133 (9th Cir. 2012) (quoting <ital>New Hampshire v. Maine</ital>, 532 U.S. 742, 749 (2001)).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">According to Plaintiff, her arguments have always remained consistent. (Mot. for Recons. at 6.) Specifically, Plaintiff explains that her Reply included an argument that her complaint did not support a 100% section 203 <ital>penalty</ital> assumption, not that Defendant's Pay Kit program did not result in a 100% <ital>violation</ital> of section 201 or 202. (<ital>Id.</ital>) In other words, Plaintiff claims she was attempting to convey that not every putative class member would be entitled to the full thirty-day penalty under section 203, but that each putative class member could establish a violation of either section 201 or 202. (Mot. for Recons. at 8&#8211;10.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Despite Plaintiff's explanation, the Court concludes that, based on the information before the Court at the time, it did not err in concluding that Plaintiff's arguments were contradictory. For example, in Plaintiff's Reply, she argued that although &#x201C;Defendant's conditional payment of wages violates other sections of the California Labor Code,&#x201D; it would not affect the section 203 waiting time penalty. (Case No. 15-2297, Dkt. No. 27 at 5.) Plaintiff went on to clarify that the allegedly unlawful conditions Defendant imposed gave &#x201C;rise to Plaintiff's other claims for civil penalties under the Private Attorneys General Act <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> in her third cause of action,&#x201D; but that &#x201C;an employee could still receive all of their pay for purposes of Section 203 (first cause of action).&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital>) Plaintiff also maintained that &#x201C;the Complaint does not support a 100% violation assumption,&#x201D; and repeatedly referred to the absence of a &#x201C;100% violation rate&#x201D; when referring to her first cause of action. (<ital>See</ital> Case No. 15-2297, Dkt. No. 27 at 5&#8211;6.) Given the language Plaintiff used in her Reply, the Court interpreted her argument to contradict her subsequent contention that Defendant's conditional pay violated section 203. Accordingly, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Plaintiff's Motion based on this argument.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Notwithstanding the Court's conclusion, after considering Plaintiff's explanation, the Court is persuaded that Plaintiff never intended to argue in her Reply that Defendant's conditional payment of wages did not violate section 203. It appears that, instead, Plaintiff intended to argue that a 100% <ital>penalty</ital> assumption should not apply as to section 203, even though she repeatedly stated that a 100% <ital>violation</ital> rate should not apply. (<ital>See id.</ital>) Given that the circumstances have changed since the previous Order, the Court will not apply the law of the case to preclude Plaintiff from arguing that Defendant's conditional pay violated sections 201 through 203. <ital>See United States v. Cuddy</ital>, 147 F.3d 1111, 1114 (9th Cir. 1998) (noting that a court has discretion to depart from the law of the case if, among other reasons, &#x201C;changed circumstances exist&#x201D;).<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p29">&#8195;The Court notes that this decision is in accord with the Ninth Circuit's general policy in favor of deciding cases on their merits. <ital>See Eitel v. McCool</ital>, 782 F.2d 1470, 1472 (9th Cir. 1986) (citing <ital>Pena v. Seguros La Comercial</ital>, S.A., 770 F.2d 811, 814 (9th Cir. 1985)).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. DEFENDANT'S MOTION TO DISMISS PLAINTIFF'S FIRST AMENDED COMPLAINT</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">The Court now turns to Defendant's Motion to Dismiss, which seeks dismissal of Plaintiff's entire FAC pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6). (MTD at 8&#8211; 25.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Legal Standard</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Under Rule 8(a), a complaint must contain a &#x201C;short and plain statement of the claim showing that the [plaintiff] is entitled to relief.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 8(a). If a complaint fails to do this, the defendant may move to dismiss it under Rule 12(b)(6). Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(b)(6). &#x201C;To survive a motion to dismiss, a complaint must contain sufficient factual matter, accepted as true, to &#x2018;state a claim that is plausible on its face.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Ashcroft v. Iqbal</ital>, 556 U.S. 662, 678 (2009). A claim is plausible on its face &#x201C;when the plaintiff pleads factual content that allows the court to draw the reasonable inference that the defendant is liable for the misconduct alleged.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> &#x201C;Factual allegations must be enough to raise a right to relief above the speculative level.&#x201D; <ital>Bell Atl. Corp. v. Twombly</ital>, 550 U.S. 544, 555 (2007). Thus, there must be &#x201C;more than a sheer possibility that a defendant has acted unlawfully.&#x201D; <ital>Iqbal</ital>, 556 U.S. at 678. &#x201C;Where a complaint pleads facts that are &#x2018;merely consistent with&#x2019; a defendant's liability, it &#x2018;stops short of the line between possibility and plausibility&#x2019;&#x201D; that the plaintiff is entitled to relief. <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">Where a district court grants a motion to dismiss, it should provide leave to amend unless it is clear that the complaint could not be saved by any amendment. <ital>Manzarek v. St. Paul Fire &#38; Marine Ins. Co.</ital>, 519 F.3d 1025, 1031 (9th Cir. 2008) (&#x201C;Dismissal without leave to amend is improper unless it is clear, upon de novo review, that the complaint could not be saved by any amendment.&#x201D;). But leave to amend &#x201C;is properly denied <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> if amendment would be futile.&#x201D; <ital>Carrico v. City &#38; County of San Francisco</ital>, 656 F.3d 1002, 1008 (9th Cir. 2011).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Requests For Judicial Notice</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">When considering a motion to dismiss, a court typically does not look beyond the complaint in order to avoid converting a motion to dismiss into a motion for summary judgment. <ital>See Mack v. S. Bay Beer Distribs., Inc.</ital>, 798 F.2d 1279, 1282 (9th Cir. 1986), <ital>overruled on other grounds by Astoria Fed. Sav. &#38; Loan Ass'n Solimino</ital>, 501 U.S. 104 (1991). Notwithstanding this precept, a court may properly take judicial notice of (1) material which is included as part of the complaint or relied upon by the complaint, and (2) matters in the public record. <ital>See Marder v. Lopez</ital>, 450 F.3d 445, 448 (9th Cir. 2006); <ital>Lee v. City of Los Angeles</ital>, 250 F.3d 668, 688&#8211;89 (9th Cir. 2001). Under Federal Rule of Evidence 201(b), a judicially noticed fact must be one &#x201C;not subject to reasonable dispute in that it (1) is generally known within the territorial jurisdiction of the trial court; or (2) can be accurately and readily determined from sources whose accuracy cannot reasonably be questioned.&#x201D; Further, a court &#x201C;must take judicial notice if a party requests it and the court is supplied with the necessary information.&#x201D; <ital>See</ital> Fed. R. Evid. 201(c)(2); <ital>In re Icenhower</ital>, 755 F.3d 1130, 1142 (9th Cir. 2014).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>1. Defendant's Request</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">In support of its Motion to Dismiss, Defendant requests that the Court take judicial notice of one opinion letter issued by the DLSE. (<ital>See</ital> Dkt. No. 28-1, Ex. A.) As a record of a state administrative agency, this opinion letter is properly the subject of judicial notice. <ital>See Abdullah v. U.S. Sec. Assocs., Inc.</ital>, 731 F.3d 952, 959 (9th Cir. 2013) (taking judicial notice of several California DLSE opinion letters); <ital>Louis v. McCormick &#38; Schmick Rest. Corp.</ital>, 460 F. Supp. 2d 1153, 1155 n.4 (C.D. Cal. 2006) (taking judicial notice of opinion letters issued by federal and state regulatory agencies). The Court therefore <bold>GRANTS</bold> Defendant's request as to this document.<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p35">&#8195;The Court also takes judicial notice of the two DLSE opinion letters upon which the Court relied in its previous Order. (<ital>See</ital> Order at 12; <ital>see also</ital> Dkt. No. 14-1, Exs. A, B.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>2. Plaintiff's Request</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">In support of its Opposition to Defendant's Motion, Plaintiff requests that the Court take judicial notice of the following seven documents: (1) <ital>Siciliano v. Mueller</ital>, Case No. 2013-07010, Luzerne County, Pennsylvania, Opinion Denying Summary Judgment, May 29, 2015; (2) Proposed Assembly Bill No. 51, December 6, 2010; (3) Assembly Committee on Labor and Employment on AB 51, April 13, 2011; (4) Assembly Committee on Banking and Finance on AB 51, May 2, 2011; (5) Assembly Committee on Labor and Employment on AB 51, June 22, 2011; (6) Assembly Committee on Appropriations on AB 51, May 27, 2011; and, (7) Assembly Third Reading on AB 51. (Dkt. No. 31, Exs. A&#8211;G.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">Courts may take judicial notice of records and reports of administrative bodies as well as legislative history. <ital>See Anderson v. Holder</ital>, 673 F.3d 1089, 1094 n.1 (9th Cir. 2012). Courts may also take judicial notice of another court's opinion; however, &#x201C;it may do so &#x2018;not for the truth of the facts recited therein, but for the existence of the opinion, which is not subject to reasonable dispute over its authenticity.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Lee</ital>, 250 F.3d at 690 (quoting <ital>S. Cross Overseas Agencies, Inc. v. Wah Kwong Shipping Group Ltd.</ital>, 181 F.3d 410, 426&#8211;27 (3d Cir. 1999)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">Given that each of these documents is a record and report of an administrative body, legislative history, or another court's opinion, the Court <bold>GRANTS</bold> Plaintiff's RJN in its entirety.<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p39">&#8195;The Court notes that it takes judicial notice of <ital>Siciliano v. Mueller</ital> only &#x201C;for the existence of the opinion, which is not subject to reasonable dispute over its authenticity.&#x201D; <ital>Lee</ital>, 250 F.3d at 690 (internal quotation marks omitted).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Discussion</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>1. Plaintiff's First Cause of Action</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">To begin, the Court notes that Plaintiff's first and third causes of action overlap, as violations of sections 201 and 202 are alleged in both. (<ital>Compare</ital> FAC &#182;&#182; 29&#8211;33, <ital>with</ital> FAC &#182; 40.) This appears to be because Plaintiff's section 201 and 202 claims are predicated, in part, on her allegations that Defendant violated sections 212 and 213. (<ital>See</ital> Opp'n to MTD at 12&#8211;13.) As such, in addition to sections 201 and 202, the Court will address sections 212 and 213 in this portion of the Order. The Court will also address Plaintiff's section 450 claim in this subsection.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">Plaintiff's first cause of action seeks penalties under California Labor Code section 203 for alleged violations of sections 201 and 202. (FAC &#182;&#182; 29&#8211;33.) Under section 201, &#x201C;[i]f an employer discharges an employee, the wages earned and unpaid at the time of discharge are due and payable immediately.&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 201. If an employee quits without providing previous notice of at least seventy-two hours, section 202 applies and requires an employer to pay all wages due within seventy-two hours of the employee's resignation. Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 202. Section 203 applies if the employer willfully violates either of these statutes. Specifically, section 203 provides that</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p42" first-line="1" turnover="1">[i]f an employer willfully fails to pay, without abatement or reduction, in accordance with Sections 201, 201.3, 201.5, 201.9, 202, and 205.5, any wages of an employee who is discharged or who quits, the wages of the employee shall continue as a penalty from the due date thereof at the same rate until paid or until an action therefor is commenced; but the wages shall not continue for more than 30 days.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p43" contd-flag="y">Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 203. These are known as the &#x201C;final pay&#x201D; statutes, as they apply to an employer's obligation to promptly tender an employee's wages due at the conclusion of his or her employment. <ital>See, e.g., Pena v. Taylor Farms Pac., Inc.</ital>, No. 2:13-CV-01282-KJM-AC, 2013 WL 5703505, at *6 (E.D. Cal. Oct. 15, 2013) (referring to sections 201 and 202 as the &#x201C;California final pay statutes&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">According to Plaintiff, Defendant willfully violated sections 201 and 202 by mandating that its employees participate in the Pay Kit program, which did not allow Plaintiff and the putative class members to receive the full amount of their wages due immediately, in part, because the program failed to comply with sections 212 and 213. (<ital>See</ital> FAC &#182;&#182; 18, 31b, 31e.) Both sections 212 and 213 regulate the methods by which an employer may pay an employee. Section 212 prohibits the payment of wages by:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p45" first-line="1" turnover="1">(1) Any order, check, draft, note, memorandum, or other acknowledgment of indebtedness, unless it is negotiable and payable in cash, on demand, without discount, at some established place of business in the state, the name and address of which must appear on the instrument, and at the time of its issuance and for a reasonable time thereafter, which must be at least 30 days, the maker or drawer has sufficient funds in, or credit, arrangement, or understanding with the drawee for its payment.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p46" contd-flag="y">Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 212(a)(1). Section 213 limits the scope of section 212, stating,</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p47" first-line="1" turnover="1">[n]othing contained in Section 212 shall <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> [p]rohibit an employer from depositing wages due or to become due or an advance on wages to be earned in an account in any bank, savings and loan association, or credit union of the employee's choice with a place of business located in this state, provided that the employee has voluntarily authorized that deposit. If an employer discharges an employee or the employee quits, the employer may pay the wages earned and unpaid at the time the employee is discharged or quits by making a deposit authorized pursuant to this subdivision, provided that the employer complies with the provisions of this article relating to the payment of wages upon termination or quitting of employment.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p48" contd-flag="y">Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 213(d). In other words, section 213 permits employers to pay employees via direct deposit into an account of the employee's choosing, so long as the employee authorizes that deposit. <ital>See id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">Defendant argues that its Pay Kit program complies with both the final pay statutes and sections 212 and 213. (MTD at 8&#8211;19.) Defendant relies upon the DLSE letters discussed in the previous Order, (<ital>see</ital> Order at 15&#8211;16), as well as the decisions of district courts in the Ninth Circuit concluding that payroll debit card programs were lawful under the California Labor Code, <ital>see Ortiz v. Randstad N. Am., L.P.</ital>, No. C&#8211;13&#8211;5050 MMC, 2015 WL 1152177, at *4 (N.D. Cal. Mar. 12, 2015); <ital>Holak v. Kmart Corp.</ital>, No. 1:12&#8211; CV&#8211;00304 AWI MJS, 2012 WL 6202298, at *6&#8211;7 (E.D. Cal. Dec. 12, 2012). Defendant also argues that Plaintiff predicates her &#x201C;final pay&#x201D; claims on the fact she was unable to access all of her wages using the Pay Cards; however, she was not required to use the Pay Cards, as she could have instead utilized the Checks to acquire the full amount of her wages due. (MTD at 16.) Finally, Defendant contends that section 213 creates an exception to section 212's requirements. (MTD at 13.) Thus, according to Defendant, &#x201C;a particular form of payment's failure to satisfy Labor Code Section 213's requirements does not give rise to a violation of that section; rather, the method of payment at issue will simply be subject to Labor Code Section 212's otherwise applicable rules.&#x201D; (MTD at 13&#8211;14.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">In the prior Order, the Court concluded that Plaintiff failed to state a plausible claim because, as previously pleaded, Defendant provided at least one free transaction&#8212; either through the Checks or Pay Cards&#8212;allowing immediate and free access to the employees' wages in full. (<ital>See</ital> Order at 16.) However, in Plaintiff's FAC, she adds allegations which alter the Court's previous analysis. Namely, Plaintiff now alleges specific facts demonstrating that in order to use the checks, the employee must first obtain a transaction code. (FAC &#182; 11.) This transaction, or &#x201C;authorization code,&#x201D; could be obtained only by dialing a telephone number, which, when connected, directed Plaintiff to call yet another number, which, in turn, provided additional instructions that ultimately precluded Plaintiff from utilizing the Checks.<footnote.reference ID="fr8" refid="f8" style="percent_n">8</footnote.reference> (<ital>Id.</ital>) Even when Plaintiff brought the Checks to her bank, it declined to honor them because they were not issued in Plaintiff's name. (FAC &#182; 18.) Thus, according to Plaintiff, she was required to use the Pay Cards. (<ital>See</ital> FAC &#182; 13.) The plausibility of this claim is strengthened by Plaintiff's allegation that approximately 70% of those who received the Pay Kit also used the Pay Cards. (FAC &#182; 14; <ital>cf.</ital> Order at 14&#8211;17.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f8"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN8.</label.designator><paratext ID="p51">&#8195;Defendant implies that any inability to obtain the full amount of wages due was caused by Plaintiff's and the other putative class members' failures to follow the Pay Kit instructions. (<ital>See</ital> MTD at 15.) Such a contention is properly made at the summary judgment stage after the parties have completed discovery. Although Defendant does request the Court to convert this Motion to Dismiss into a summary judgment motion&#8212;to the extent the Court concludes that certain documents are not properly incorporated by reference&#8212;the Court declines to do so. (<ital>See</ital> MTD at 20 n.11.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p52" level="1">Finally, Plaintiff alleges that the Pay Cards did not allow her to access the full amount of wages due because ATMs do not dispense exact change. (FAC &#182; 18.) Specifically, Plaintiff alleges that her Pay Card has an outstanding balance of $3. (FAC &#182; 14.) She further avers that the other 70% of putative class members who used the Pay Cards have also failed to receive the full amount of their earned wages. (<ital>Id.</ital>) Given these new facts, the Court concludes that Plaintiff sufficiently pleads her claims under sections 201 and 202, as she has plausibly alleged that she was unable to immediately access the entire amount of her wages due. (FAC &#182; 18.) Plaintiff also plausibly alleges that Defendant's conduct was willful, as she claims that Defendant was aware of its employees' inability to receive their entire wages due at least as of February 2014. (FAC &#182;&#182; 15, 31e.) Accordingly, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Defendant's Motion as to Plaintiff's section 201, 202, and 203 claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p53" level="1">As to Plaintiff's claim that Defendant violated section 212, the fact that Defendant's Pay Kit program is mandatory, not optional, is troubling. In the two letters upon which the Court relied in its previous Order, and upon which Defendant relies in the instant Motion, the DLSE examined the legality of alternative pay programs as they related to both checks and pay cards.<footnote.reference ID="fr9" refid="f9" style="percent_n">9</footnote.reference> In those opinion letters, the DLSE deemed both methods to be in compliance with section 212. (<ital>See</ital> Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. A at 6; Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. B. at 9.) However, in so deciding, the DLSE heavily relied upon the fact that the pay programs were optional, thereby allowing an employee to either participate in the program or receive his or her pay in some other way, such as direct deposit. Specifically, the DLSE opined that &#x201C;[t]he success of the described procedure, in practice, will of course require that <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> it is presented as an <ital>alternative</ital> method for wage payment for which [the employees'] participation is optional.&#x201D; (Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. A at 6&#8211;7; Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. B. at 9.) The DLSE also stated, &#x201C;It is significant that the program does not mandate employee participation in the Money Network Service and that it is designed to provide an alternative for employees receiving their wage payment. Employees are also given the option of having their pay direct deposited into an account of their choosing. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; (Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. A at 3&#8211;4.) The DLSE further explained that</paratext>
<footnote ID="f9"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN9.</label.designator><paratext ID="p54">&#8195;&#x201C;While DLSE opinion letters are not entitled to deference, district courts have looked to them as a source of persuasive authority.&#x201D; <ital>Pace v. PetSmart, Inc.</ital>, No. SACV 13&#8211;00500 DOC(RNBx), 2014 WL 2511297, at *2 (C.D. Cal. June 3, 1014) (citing <ital>Cardenas v. McLane FoodServices, Inc.</ital>, 796 F. Supp. 2d 1246, 1251&#8211;52 (C.D. Cal. 2011)); <ital>see also Ortiz</ital>, 2015 WL 1152177, at *3 (citing and following a DLSE opinion letter); <ital>Holak</ital>, 2012 WL 6202298, at *6&#8211;7 (same).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p55" first-line="1" turnover="1">[t]he optional nature of the Money Network Service is mandated under federal laws. Specifically, the Federal Reserve Board's Regulation E states: &#x201C;No financial institution or other person may require a consumer to establish an account for receipt of electronic fund transfers with a particular institution as a condition of employment or receipt of governmental benefit.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p56" contd-flag="y">(Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. A at 4 n.4 (citing CFR &#167; 205.10(e)) (emphasis omitted); <ital>see also</ital> Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. B at 6 (citing CFR &#167; 205.10(e)).)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p57" level="1">Additionally, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System has acknowledged that Regulation E &#x201C;precludes an employer from requiring an employee to receive a payroll card and suggests that employees always be given some other option, such as direct deposit to a financial institution of their choice.&#x201D; Sarah Jane Hughes, Stephen T. Middlebrook &#38; Broox W. Peterson, <ital>Developments in the Law Concerning Stored Value and Other Prepaid Payment Products</ital>, 62 <csc>Bus. Law.</csc> 229, 238 (2006) (citing Electronic Fund Transfers, 71 Fed. Reg. 1473-01, 1479 (Jan. 10, 2006)). Moreover, courts citing and applying the DLSE opinion letters have done so only where the pay program was optional, not mandatory. <ital>See Ortiz</ital>, 2015 WL 1152177, at *4 (holding, in part, that the pay card program &#x201C;complie[d] with the requirements of California law&#x201D; because &#x201C;participation in the program [was] optional&#x201D;); <ital>Holak</ital>, 2012 WL 6202298, at *6&#8211;7 (noting that &#x201C;the DLSE opined that payroll debit card programs do not violate the Labor Code where the employees are fully informed of the service and it is represented as an alternative method for wage payment for which their participation is optional,&#x201D; and holding that the payroll debit cards at issue did not violate section 212, in part, because they were optional). No court in this circuit has held that a mandatory pay program complies with section 212. Notably, however, it appears no court in this circuit has yet faced this nuanced issue.<footnote.reference ID="fr10" refid="f10" style="percent_n">10</footnote.reference> Accordingly, there is no in-circuit case law guiding this Court's decision.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f10"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN10.</label.designator><paratext ID="p58">&#8195;The Court notes that in <ital>Pace</ital>, a court in this district certified a class predicated on a claim that the employer failed to obtain the employees' voluntary authorization before paying the employees their wages with an ATM card. <ital>See Pace</ital>, 2014 WL 2511297, at *2, 13 (C.D. Cal. June 3, 2014). The court, however, declined to address the merits of that claim. <ital>Id.</ital> at *11.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p59" level="1">Given the dearth of precedent, the Court is persuaded by the DLSE's and Federal Reserve Board's opinions. As discussed above, the DLSE explicitly requires that a pay program be optional.<footnote.reference ID="fr11" refid="f11" style="percent_n">11</footnote.reference> This, in conjunction with the Federal Reserve Board's acknowledgement that Regulation E specifically precludes an employer from requiring an employee to accept a payroll card, leads the Court to conclude that Plaintiff has sufficiently pleaded a violation of section 212.<footnote.reference ID="fr12" refid="f12" style="percent_n">12</footnote.reference> Accordingly, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Defendant's Motion as it relates to Plaintiff's section 212 claim.<footnote.reference ID="fr13" refid="f13" style="percent_n">13</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f11"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN11.</label.designator><paratext ID="p60">&#8195;Defendant attempts to distinguish the DLSE letters on the ground that they addressed pay card and check payment programs which were used on a recurring basis, whereas the Pay Kit program here involved only a final payment. (MTD Reply at 4.) The Court is unpersuaded by this argument. As noted in one of the DLSE letters, &#x201C;California has a long history of ensuring the protection of wages for California workers.&#x201D; (Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. B at 8.) The Court is unaware of, nor does Defendant cite to, any authority indicating that a worker's rights to protected wages are somehow diminished merely because they are the worker's final wages. Given the lack of authority supporting Defendant's argument, the Court interprets the DLSE letters as applying equally to both recurring and final wages.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f12"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN12.</label.designator><paratext ID="p61">&#8195;Further supporting this conclusion is the fact that &#x201C;the prompt payment of wages due an employee is a fundamental public policy of this state.&#x201D; <ital>Gould v. Md. Sound Indus., Inc.</ital>, 31 Cal. App. 4th 1137, 1147 (Cal. Ct. App. 1995); <ital>Pressler v. Donald L. Bren Co.</ital>, 32 Cal. 3d 831, 837 (Cal. 1982) (&#x201C;Public policy has long favored the full and prompt payment of wages due an employee. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> [W]ages are not ordinary debts. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> [B]ecause of the economic position of the average worker and, in particular, his family, it is essential to the public welfare that he receive his pay promptly.&#x201D;) (internal quotation marks and citations omitted).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f13"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN13.</label.designator><paratext ID="p62">&#8195;Plaintiff argues that her section 201 and 202 claims may be predicated upon violations of section 212. (Opp'n to MTD at 12&#8211;13.) The Court need not address that issue at this time, as Plaintiff sufficiently pleads a violation of sections 201/202 and 212 independently.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p63" level="1">Finally, with respect to section 213, the Court agrees with Defendant that section 213 provides an alternative method of payment, thereby allowing employers to circumvent section 212 by complying with section 213. However, the Court does not agree that an employer's failure to comply with section 213 &#x201C;does not give rise to a violation of that section.&#x201D; (MTD at 13.) For example, at least one court in the Ninth Circuit has held that an employer violated section 213(d) by requiring an employee to receive his wages via direct deposit into a program account, in violation of section 213(d)'s voluntariness requirement. <ital>See Fobroy v. Video Only, Inc.</ital>, No. C-13-4083 EMC, 2014 WL 6306708, at *7 (N.D. Cal. Nov. 14, 2014) (denying the defendant's summary judgment motion as to the plaintiff's section 213(d) claim because there was a genuine dispute as to whether the defendant required the employee to receive wages via direct deposit).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p64" level="1">Further, in one of the DLSE opinion letters, the DLSE analyzed a payroll card system similar to that of the Pay Kit program's.<footnote.reference ID="fr14" refid="f14" style="percent_n">14</footnote.reference> (<ital>See</ital> Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. B at 1&#8211;2.) In the letter, the DLSE indicated that the payroll program there, like the Pay Kit program in the instant matter, used direct deposit as a component of the system. (Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. B at 5.) Accordingly, the DLSE analyzed whether the payroll card system complied with section 213(d). (<ital>Id.</ital>) The DLSE's analysis as to section 213 was similar to its analysis regarding section 212&#8212;it relied heavily upon the fact that the payroll program was optional in concluding that it did not violate section 213(d). Namely, the DLSE stated,</paratext>
<footnote ID="f14"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN14.</label.designator><paratext ID="p65">&#8195;Specifically, the payroll program described in the DLSE opinion letter involved the employer directly depositing the employee's wages into an account the employee voluntarily established at the program bank. (Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. B at 6.) The Pay Kit program here is similar in that Defendant allegedly deposits the employees' wages with Money Network and the employees access the money through an account they are required to open with Money Network. (FAC &#182;&#182; 8, 12.) The key difference, however, is that Defendant's Pay Kit program is mandatory. (<ital>See</ital> FAC &#182; 9.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p66" first-line="1" turnover="1">[s]ince an employee's participation in the payroll card program is optional and provided that the employee has voluntarily and specifically authorized the deposit, the payroll card programs simply provide another alternative for employees to receive their wage payments by direct deposit. Thus, [payroll program] sufficiently satisfy the voluntary requirement in Labor Code &#167; 213(d).</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p67" contd-flag="y">(Dkt. No. 14-1, Ex. B at 6.) As discussed above, the Court is persuaded that the voluntariness requirement is vital to the legality of pay programs similar to the one at issue in this action. Given that, as alleged, participation in Defendant's Pay Kit is mandatory, and because the Pay Kit involves an aspect of direct deposit, the Court concludes that Plaintiff sufficiently states a claim for a violation of section 213. Defendant's Motion as to Plaintiff's section 213 claim is therefore <bold>DENIED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p68" level="1">Plaintiff also alleges that Defendant violated California Labor Code section 450, which provides that &#x201C;[n]o employer <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> may compel or coerce any employee, or applicant for employment, to patronize his or her employer, or any other person, in the purchase of any thing of value.&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 450(a). Specifically, Plaintiff alleges that &#x201C;Defendant coerced employees to use the Pay Kit,&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 31d), and that the Pay Kit &#x201C;unlawfully requires the putative class and aggrieved employees to patronize a particular bank and/or business, i.e., Walmart&#x201D; and &#x201C;open an account with Money Networks,&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 12).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p69" level="1">Defendant argues that the FAC includes no allegation that Defendant compelled Plaintiff or the putative class members to &#x201C;purchase any thing of value&#x201D; from either Defendant or any other person or entity. (MTD at 17); <ital>see also</ital> Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 450(a). The lack of any alleged payment, according to Defendant, establishes that Plaintiff fails to state a claim for a section 450 violation. (MTD at 17.) Plaintiff contends that, although she was not compelled to purchase anything in particular, she was charged a $2.95 monthly account maintenance fee when funds remained in the account for over sixty days, and she was charged a $2.50 ATM fee to withdraw funds. (<ital>See</ital> Opp'n to MTD at 16&#8211;17; FAC &#182; 18.) This, according to Plaintiff, constitutes patronage. (<ital>See</ital> Opp'n to MTD at 16&#8211;17.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p70" level="1">In <ital>McDaniel v. Wells Fargo Investments, LLC</ital>, 717 F.3d 668 (9th Cir. 2013), the Ninth Circuit addressed the scope of section 450. <ital>See id.</ital> at 677&#8211;78. Namely, it noted that &#x201C;[t]he plain language of section 450(a) forbids mandatory &#x2018;free&#x2019; accounts just as it forbids paid ones.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 677. It further clarified that &#x201C;a &#x2018;free accounts&#x2019; policy would amount to forced patronage.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> The court went on to explicitly reject an argument that &#x201C;[o]ne is not forced to patronize an employer <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> unless one is required to pay it for something.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> It further explained that &#x201C;[t]o patronize is &#x2018;to trade with; to frequent as a customer&#x2019; or to act as &#x2018;[o]ne who supports a commercial enterprise.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> (quoting <ital>Webster's New International Dictionary</ital> 1793, 1794 (2d ed. 1936)).<footnote.reference ID="fr15" refid="f15" style="percent_n">15</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f15"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN15.</label.designator><paratext ID="p71">&#8195;Notably, the court concluded by pointing out that &#x201C;in California[,] &#x2018;[a] remedial statute must be liberally construed so as <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> to suppress the mischief at which it is directed&#x2019; (here, &#x2018;employer coercion&#x2019;).&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 678 (quoting <ital>Cal. State Rest. Ass'n v. Whitlow</ital>, 58 Cal. App. 3d 340 (1976) (interpreting section 450)).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p72" level="1">Although the <ital>McDaniel</ital> court analyzed section 450 in the context of an employer forcing an employee to patronize the employer, as opposed to &#x201C;any other person,&#x201D; <ital>see</ital> Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 450, the Court finds no reason to interpret the Ninth Circuit's analysis as narrowly applying to forced patronage of the employer. Instead, because the <ital>McDaniel</ital> court's reasoning addressed the &#x201C;patronize&#x201D; versus &#x201C;purchase&#x201D; dichotomy, rather than &#x201C;employer&#x201D; versus &#x201C;any other person,&#x201D; the Court adopts the Ninth Circuit's reasoning and applies it to the present context&#8212;where the employer, Defendant, required the employees, Plaintiff and the putative class members, to open an account with a third party, Money Networks. (<ital>See</ital> FAC &#182; 12.) Thus, the Court rejects Defendant's argument that Plaintiff and the putative class members must have &#x201C;paid&#x201D; for something to avail themselves of section 450's protection. As <ital>McDaniel</ital> instructs, forcing an employee to open an account&#8212;even a free one&#8212;runs afoul of section 450. <ital>See McDaniel</ital>, 717 F.3d at 677&#8211;78. Accordingly, the Court concludes that Plaintiff has sufficiently pleaded her section 450 claim, as she alleges that Defendant required her and the putative class members to open an account with Money Networks to access their Pay Kits. (FAC &#182; 12.) Defendant's Motion is therefore <bold>DENIED</bold> as to this claim.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>2. Plaintiff's Second Cause of Action</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p73" level="1">In Plaintiff's second cause of action, she alleges that Defendant violated Labor Code section 226, which requires an accurate and itemized statement providing, among other things, &#x201C;the inclusive dates of the period for which the employee is paid,&#x201D; and &#x201C;the name and address of the legal entity that is the employer.&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 226(6), (8). Namely, Plaintiff avers that Defendant failed to provide Plaintiff and the putative class members with a pay stub or itemized statement that indicated the payment period as well as Defendant's address and legal entity name. (FAC &#182; 35.) Plaintiff also alleges that Defendant did so knowingly and intentionally. (FAC &#182; 36.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p74" level="1">Defendant argues that Plaintiff fails to state a claim because (1) she fails &#x201C;to allege that [Defendant] did not issue a compliant wage statement on a semimonthly basis&#8212; which is precisely how [Defendant] made Plaintiff's wage statement available to her,&#x201D; and (2) Plaintiff's factual claims contradict an electronic paystub incorporated by reference in the FAC, which, according to a DLSE opinion letter, is a sufficient method of providing the wage statement. (MTD at 19.) In opposition, Plaintiff claims never to have received the alleged electronic statement; rather, she maintains that Defendant provided her with a noncompliant paper stub at the time of her termination. (Opp'n to MTD at 18.) She also contends that, even assuming she received the electronic pay stub, Defendant offered Plaintiff no choice to receive a paper stub&#8212;a prerequisite to the permissibility of an electronic pay stub, according to Plaintiff. (Opp'n to MTD at 18&#8211; 19.) In reply, Defendant contends that because Plaintiff did not respond to its first of two arguments, she conceded the issue, thereby warranting dismissal of her section 226 claim. (MTD Reply at 6.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p75" level="1">To begin, the Court declines to dismiss Plaintiff's section 226 claim merely because she did not address Defendant's first argument. Plaintiff responded to Defendant's general contention that her section 226 claim should be dismissed. Thus, she has not conceded that her cause of action is insufficiently pleaded.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p76" level="1">Turning to the claim's merits, Defendant is correct that section 226 permits an employer to provide a wage statement either &#x201C;semimonthly or at the time of each payment of wages.&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 226(a). However, the Court disagrees with Defendant that Plaintiff must specifically allege that Defendant did not provide the wage statements on a semimonthly basis. In her FAC, Plaintiff alleges that Defendant <ital>never</ital> provided a pay stub or itemized statement that indicated the inclusive dates of the payment period or the name and address of &#x201C;the legal entity that is the employer.&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 35 (quoting Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 226(a)(8)).) This necessarily implies that Defendant did not provide a wage statement either &#x201C;semimonthly or at the time of each payment of wages.&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 226(a). Finally, the Court will not entertain the factual dispute regarding an electronic wage statement Defendant purportedly provided to Plaintiff. Such a dispute is more appropriately resolved by a jury; certainly not by the Court at the pleadings stage. Focusing on the FAC, rather than additional extraneous evidence, the Court concludes that Plaintiff sufficiently pleads her second cause of action. Accordingly, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Defendant's Motion as to Plaintiff's section 226 claim.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>3. Plaintiff's Third Cause of Action</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p77" level="1">Plaintiff's third cause of action is a PAGA claim, alleging Defendant's violation of California Labor Code sections 201, 202, 203, 206, 206.5, 212, 213, and 432.5. (FAC &#182;&#182; 39&#8211;46.) Given that the Court has already addressed Plaintiff's sections 201, 202, 203, 212, and 213 claims, the Court will now discuss Plaintiff's FAC as it relates to the remaining allegedly violated provisions.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p78" level="1">Section 206 provides that, &#x201C;[i]n case of a dispute over wages, the employer shall pay, without condition and within the time set by this article, all wages, or parts thereof, conceded by him to be due, leaving to the employee all remedies he might otherwise be entitled to as to any balance claimed.&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 206(a). Under section 206.5, &#x201C;[a]n employer shall not require the execution of a release of a claim or right on account of wages due, or to become due, or made as an advance on wages to be earned, unless payment of those wages has been made.&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 206.5(a). Finally, section 432.5 states, in part, that &#x201C;[n]o employer <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> shall require any employee or applicant for employment to agree, in writing, to any term or condition which is known by such employer <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> to be prohibited by law.&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 432.5.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p79" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that Defendant violated these provisions by requiring her and the putative class members to &#x201C;agree to onerous and unconscionable terms and conditions to access their earned wages, including but not limited to a purported waiver of liability, the right to set off, penalties and fees, and an arbitration provision.&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 10; <ital>see also</ital> FAC &#182; 40.) Defendant argues first that section 206 is inapplicable because there was no dispute over the amount of wages due at the time of Plaintiff's termination. (MTD at 22.) Second, Defendant contends that Plaintiff fails to state a claim for a section 206.5 violation, as the FAC is devoid of any allegation that Defendant coerced Plaintiff to settle claims or conditioned payment of amounts due upon the execution of a settlement agreement. (<ital>Id.</ital>) Defendant also points to Plaintiff's failure to plead that Defendant required employees to release claims for wages due. (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p80" level="1">First, the Court notes that case law is unclear as to whether an employee may state a claim under sections 206, 206.5, and 432.5 where there was no actual dispute over the amount of wages due. However, California courts instruct that section 206.5 is to be read in light of section 206. <ital>Watkins v. Wachovia Corp.</ital>, 172 Cal. App. 4th 1576, 1586&#8211;87 (Cal. Ct. App. 2009). &#x201C;Read together, sections 206 and 206.5 provide that amounts required to be paid under section 206, <ital>i.e.</ital>, amounts concededly due, may not be released.&#x201D; <ital>Young v. AmeriGas Propane, Inc.</ital>, No. 14&#8211;cv&#8211;00583&#8211;BAS(RBB), 2014 WL 5092878, at *4 (S.D. Cal. Oct. 9, 2014) (citing <ital>Watkins</ital>, 172 Cal. App. 4th at 1587). &#x201C;In other words, wages are not considered &#x2018;due&#x2019; and unreleasable under Labor Code section 206.5, unless they are required to be paid under Labor Code section 206.&#x201D; <ital>Watkins</ital>, 172 Cal. App. 4th at 1587.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p81" level="1">In light of this authority, the Court must first determine whether there is any amount &#x201C;due&#x201D; under section 206, which, according to section 206, is the amount the employer concedes it owes. <ital>See</ital> Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 206. Here, the Court interprets Defendant's offering of the Pay Kits as Defendant's concession that Plaintiff and the putative class members were &#x201C;due&#x201D; their final wages. Although there was no specific &#x201C;dispute&#x201D; over these wages prompting Defendant's &#x201C;concession&#x201D; for purposes of section 206, one recent California case indicates that a lack of an actual dispute does not preclude section 206's application. In <ital>Singh v. Southland Stone, U.S.A., Inc.</ital>, 186 Cal. App. 4th 338 (Cal. Ct. App. 2010), the court explicitly declined to follow a California case from 1946, which held &#x201C;that section 206 was inapplicable because there was no dispute between the parties as to the amount of wages due at the time the check was tendered.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 365 (citing <ital>Sayre v. W. Bowl</ital> 76 Cal. App. 2d 793, 799 (Cal. Ct. App. 1946)) (&#x201C;In our view, an employer is required to timely pay wages due under Labor Code section 201 or 202 unconditionally and cannot require an employee to sign a waiver as a condition of payment.&#x201D;). Thus, California case law supports the proposition that no actual dispute must arise prior to the tender of wages for a section 206 claim to be viable.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p82" level="1">Accordingly, the Court concludes that Defendant was required to comply with section 206 in its offering of the Pay Kit, as it necessarily conceded the wages due by offering the package. (<ital>See, e.g.</ital>, FAC &#182;&#182; 9, 31a.) Given that Plaintiff sufficiently states a claim under sections 201 and 202&#8212;i.e., that Defendant failed to pay all wages within the time period provided in those provisions&#8212;she also states a claim under section 206. Defendant's Motion is therefore <bold>DENIED</bold> as to Plaintiff's section 206 claim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p83" level="1">As to the section 206.5 claim, Defendant argues that there was no violation because Plaintiff never released her &#x201C;claims for wages due.&#x201D; (MTD at 21&#8211;22.) In opposition, Plaintiff contends that &#x201C;the release itself pertains to all damages arising from or relating to the products and services provided&#x201D; within the Pay Kit, and the product or service provided is the final paycheck containing the wages. (Opp'n to MTD at 21.) Thus, according to Plaintiff, &#x201C;any dispute related to the Pay Kit is necessarily related to wages due.&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p84" level="1">The Court agrees with Plaintiff. If Plaintiff has sufficiently alleged that Defendant required her to waive all claims relating to the Pay Kit, which necessarily includes claims relating to the amount of wages provided through the Pay Kit, then she has sufficiently stated a claim for a section 206.5 violation. However, Plaintiff fails to plead the specifics of the purported waiver. The extent of her allegations is that there was a &#x201C;waiver of liability, the right to set off, penalties and fees, and an arbitration provision.&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 10.) Further, Plaintiff fails to cite the portion of the terms and conditions she references in her Opposition. (<ital>See</ital> Opp'n to MTD at 21.) Because Plaintiff fails to sufficiently plead that Defendant required her to waive her right to claims for wages due, Defendant's Motion is <bold>GRANTED with leave to amend</bold> as to Plaintiff's section 206.5 claim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p85" level="1">Finally, to state a claim for a section 432.5 violation, Plaintiff must sufficiently plead that Defendant knew the terms and conditions were prohibited by law. <ital>See</ital> Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 432.5. Although Plaintiff alleges that Defendant knew employees were confused by the Pay Kit's instructions, (FAC &#182; 31e), she fails to allege that Defendant knew its Pay Kit was unlawful. Defendant's Motion is therefore <bold>GRANTED with leave to amend</bold> as to this cause of action.<footnote.reference ID="fr16" refid="f16" style="percent_n">16</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f16"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN16.</label.designator><paratext ID="p86">&#8195;The Court notes that in support of her UCL claim, Plaintiff alleges that &#x201C;Defendant knowingly and intentionally engaged in these sharp, unlawful, and unfair payroll practices so that it could save money and bolster its bottom line.&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 49.) However, it is unclear from this allegation whether Plaintiff intended the word &#x201C;knowingly&#x201D; to modify the word &#x201C;unlawful.&#x201D; Thus, the Court will permit Plaintiff to file an amended pleading to clarify this allegation.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p87" level="1">In light of the foregoing, given that Plaintiff sufficiently pleads a violation of at least some of the provisions upon which she predicates her PAGA clam, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Defendant's Motion to Dismiss Plaintiff's PAGA cause of action.<footnote.reference ID="fr17" refid="f17" style="percent_n">17</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f17"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN17.</label.designator><paratext ID="p88">&#8195;Further, the Court notes that Plaintiff has now complied with PAGA's notice requirement. (<ital>See</ital> FAC &#182;&#182; 28, 46; <ital>cf.</ital> Order at 18&#8211;19.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>4. Plaintiff's Fourth Cause of Action</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p89" level="1">California's UCL prohibits &#x201C;any unlawful, unfair or fraudulent business act or practice and unfair, deceptive, untrue or misleading advertising.&#x201D; Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167; 17200. The UCL provides a separate theory of liability under the &#x201C;unlawful,&#x201D; &#x201C;unfair,&#x201D; or &#x201C;fraudulent&#x201D; prongs. <ital>Stanwood v. Mary Kay, Inc.</ital>, 941 F. Supp. 2d 1212, 1222 (C.D. Cal. 2012) (citing <ital>Lozano v. AT&#38;T Wireless Servs., Inc.</ital>, 504 F.3d 718, 731 (9th Cir. 2007)). Here, Plaintiff alleges violations of the UCL's &#x201C;unlawful&#x201D; and &#x201C;unfair&#x201D; prongs. (<ital>See</ital> Opp'n to MTD at 24.) Namely, Plaintiff alleges that Defendant violated the UCL by &#x201C;failing to pay all wages due upon separation of employment, failing to obtain an employee's voluntary authorization before paying his/her wages through the use of the Pay Kit, and failing to provide an accurately itemized paystub.&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 48.) Plaintiff also alleges that Defendant engaged in these unlawful and unfair business practices to &#x201C;save money and bolster its bottom line.&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 49.) Plaintiff further avers that she and the putative class members have been harmed by such conduct, and she seeks restitution &#x201C;of all of the wages earned and due to them and any other of Defendant's ill begotten gains from Defendant's engaging&#x201D; in the alleged unfair business practices. (FAC &#182; 52.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p90" level="1">Although &#x201C;[t]he standard for determining what business acts are &#x2018;unfair&#x2019; in consumer actions under the UCL is currently unsettled,&#x201D; <ital>Zhang v. Superior Court</ital>, 57 Cal. 4th 364, 380 n.9 (Cal. 2013), the alleged &#x201C;unfair&#x201D; conduct must be &#x201C;tethered to a violation of a constitutional, statutory or regulatory provision,&#x201D; <ital>Graham v. Bank of Am., N.A.</ital>, 226 Cal. App. 4th 594, 613 (Cal. Ct. App. 2014). As to the &#x201C;unlawful&#x201D; prong, the UCL prohibits &#x201C;unlawful&#x201D; practices &#x201C;forbidden by law, be it civil or criminal, federal, state, or municipal, statutory, regulatory, or court-made.&#x201D; <ital>Saunders v. Super. Ct.</ital>, 27 Cal. App. 4th 832, 838 (Cal. Ct. App. 1994). The UCL &#x201C;thus creates an independent action when a business practice violates some other law.&#x201D; <ital>Walker v. Countrywide Home Loans, Inc.</ital>, 98 Cal. App. 4th 1158, 1169 (Cal. Ct. App. 2002).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p91" level="1">Here, Plaintiff satisfies the <ital>Twombly</ital>/<ital>Iqbal</ital> standard as to her UCL claim under both the &#x201C;unfair&#x201D; and &#x201C;unlawful&#x201D; prongs, as she has sufficiently pleaded violations of sections 201, 202, 203, 206, 212, 213, 226, and 450. Accordingly, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Defendant's Motion as to Plaintiff's UCL claim.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>V. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p92" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> Plaintiff's Motion for Reconsideration and <bold>GRANTS in part</bold> Defendant's Motion to Dismiss. The Court <bold>DISMISSES</bold> Plaintiff's claims under California Labor Code sections 206.5 and 432.5 <bold>with leave to amend</bold>. Plaintiff shall file a Second Amended Complaint, if she chooses, <bold>on or before Friday, May 20, 2016</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p93" level="1"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p94" level="1">Initials of Preparer <underscore>rf</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>