<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>RAYMOND BERNAL, an individual, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>UNITED PARCEL SERVICE CO., a Delaware corporation doing business in California as United Parcel Service Co. (Air); and DOES 1 through 50, inclusive, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. EDCV 08-01579-VAP (OPx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>EDCV 08-01579-VAP (OPx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">5:08-cv-01579-VAP-OP</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 12/08/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER GRANTING DEFENDANTS' MOTION FOR SUMMARY JUDGMENT [Motion filed on October 19, 2009]</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">VIRGINIA A. PHILLIPS United States District Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Plaintiff Raymond Bernal (&#x201C;Plaintiff&#x201D;) worked for Defendant United Parcel Service Co. (&#x201C;Defendant&#x201D;) for over sixteen years before his discharge on March 25, 2008. He brought this action against Defendant alleging various claims relating to his discharge. Defendant now moves for summary judgment or, in the alternative, summary adjudication, as to all claims against it.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Uncontroverted Facts</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">The following material facts are supported adequately by admissible evidence and are uncontroverted. They are &#x201C;admitted to exist without controversy&#x201D; for the purposes of this Motion. <underscore>See</underscore> Local Rule 56-3.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Plaintiff began working for Defendant on November 25, 1991. (Def.'s Stmt. of Uncontroverted Facts (&#x201C;SUF&#x201D;) &#182; 1; Compl. &#182; 5.) Plaintiff was hired as a full-time utility employee for Defendant's facility in Ontario, California. (Def.'s SUF &#182; 1.) Plaintiff remained in this position throughout his employment with Defendant. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">In September 2003, Plaintiff internally reported the illegal disposition of hazardous waste.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> (Pl.'s Stmt. of Genuine Issues of Material Fact (&#x201C;SGI&#x201D;) &#182; 1; Decl. of Raymond Bernal (&#x201C;Bernal Decl.&#x201D;) &#182; 3.) In October 2003, Plaintiff was discharged. (Bernal Decl. &#182; 3.) In that same month, Defendant offered to reinstate Plaintiff, and Plaintiff accepted. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Plaintiff took a disability leave, and eventually returned to work in December 2004. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p5">&#8195;Plaintiff does not specify to whom this violation was reported.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">In November 2005, Plaintiff filed a complaint with the California Environmental Protection Agency relating to the storage of hazardous chemicals at Defendant's Ontario facility. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 4.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">At an unspecified time in 2003, Plaintiff began experiencing panic attacks and anxiety. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 3.) Plaintiff was certified for leave under the Family Medical Leave Act (&#x201C;FMLA&#x201D;) in May 2005. (Def.'s SUF &#182; 3; Bernal Decl. &#182; 6). Plaintiff first took FMLA leave in 2005. (Def.'s SUF &#182; 3.) Plaintiff was recertified for, and took, FMLA leave in 2006 and 2007. (Def.'s SUF &#182; 4&#8211;5.) Plaintiff was not recertified for FMLA leave until March 13, 2008. (Bernal Decl. &#182; 6.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Between 2005 and 2008, Defendant held hearings or meetings at unspecified times involving unspecified persons to discuss Plaintiff's FMLA leave. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> at &#182; 8.) Procedures regarding FMLA leave changed an unspecified number of times during this period, including the telephone number Plaintiff was to call to notify Defendant of his leave and the required reporting documents. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Plaintiff received telephone calls about documents relating to his FMLA leave from Defendant's human resources department. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Plaintiff was required to re-submit documents relating to his FMLA leave on an unspecified number of occasions. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Defendant required Plaintiff to explain his FMLA leave an unspecified number of times. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Plaintiff's supervisors and managers required him to arrange in advance for his FMLA leave an unspecified number of times. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Plaintiff's supervisors and managers made unspecified remarks at unspecified times that Plaintiff perceived as derogatory concerning his FMLA leave. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) During unspecified meetings and at unspecified other times, Plaintiff's supervisors and managers rolled their eyes concerning his FMLA leave. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Plaintiff was absent from work on November 1, 2007 and November 26, 2007. (Def.'s SUF &#182;&#182; 8, 10.) Plaintiff informed Defendant that he was using FMLA leave on those days.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> (<underscore>Id.</underscore>; Compl. &#182;&#182; 8, 9.) Through the investigation of Marsha Drescher, then employed by Defendant as Aircraft Materials Distribution Manager, Defendant learned that Plaintiff appeared in the Superior Court of California for the County of San Bernardino on those dates concerning an unlawful detainer proceeding. (Decl. of Marsha Drescher (&#x201C;Drescher Decl.&#x201D;) &#182;&#182; 14&#8211;18; Def.'s SUF &#182;&#182; 7, 9; Bernal Decl. &#182;&#182; 11, 12.) Ms. Drescher discovered these facts while searching court records on the internet for the names of all her friends and family, as well as every employee in the utility department at Defendant's Ontario facility. (Drescher Decl. &#182; 15.)<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p10">&#8195;The parties dispute whether or not Plaintiff's use of FMLA leave on those days was legitimate. (<underscore>See</underscore> Mot. 14:9 &#8211;16:17; Opp'n at 8:11&#8211;9:19).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p11">&#8195;Plaintiff disputes, but fails to controvert, this fact. Plaintiff characterizes this testimony as &#x201C;so unbelievable it [sic] that it shows Ms. Drescher is hiding the truth and that there were other, insidious reasons for her court website search.&#x201D; (Opp'n at 11:13&#8211;15.) Other than unfounded speculation, however, Plaintiff provides no evidence contradicting the account of Ms. Drescher's investigation appearing in her sworn declaration.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Plaintiff arrived late to work on March 10, 2008. (Def.'s SUF &#182; 13; Bernal Decl. &#182; 13.) Plaintiff had informed Defendant before March 10, 2008 that he would be late to work that day due to an appointment.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> (Def.'s SUF &#182; 11; Bernal Decl. &#182; 13.) Plaintiff attended his arraignment on disorderly conduct charges in the San Bernardino County Superior Court that morning.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p13">&#8195;The parties dispute whether Plaintiff stated that he would be late due to a doctor's appointment, or simply due to an appointment. (<underscore>See</underscore> Mot. at 5 n.7; Bernal Decl. &#182; 13). The dispute is not material to the determination of the Motion.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Plaintiff informed Defendant that he would be late to work on March 25, 2008 due to another appointment. (Def.'s SUF &#182; 13.) Plaintiff attended another hearing in the San Bernardino County Superior Court on March 25, 2008, and then arrived late to work. (Def.'s SUF &#182;&#182; 12, 14.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Upon Plaintiff's arrival at work on March 25, 2008, Defendant held a hearing to determine whether Plaintiff had legitimately used FMLA leave on November 1, 2007, November 26, 2007, and March 10, 2008. (Pl.'s SUF &#182; 15.) On that same day, Defendant discharged Plaintiff from his employment. Defendant provided Plaintiff with a letter dated March 25, 2008 (the &#x201C;Discharge Letter&#x201D;) stating he had been discharged because because he had &#x201C;engaged in dishonesty by misrepresenting to the Company that [he was] legitimately using FMLA leave on November 1 &#38; 26, 2007 and March 10, 2008 when [he] in fact [was] not doing so, but in fact [was] in court.&#x201D; (Drescher Decl. Ex. P.)<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> The decision to discharge Plaintiff was made by Tom Baggett, Labor Relations Manager; Bob Ragar, District Labor Relations Manager; and Jack Arnold, Aircraft Materials Division Manager. (Def.'s SUF &#182;&#182; 17&#8211;19.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p16">&#8195;Defendant now concedes that Plaintiff did not represent that he was using FMLA leave on March 10, 2008, but maintains Plaintiff was dishonest in describing the reason for his tardiness on that date. (<underscore>See</underscore> Mot. at 12:12&#8211;20; 14:5&#8211;7.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Procedural Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">On November 6, 2008, Plaintiff filed a Complaint asserting claims against Defendant for (1) interference with rights and discrimination under the FMLA;<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference> (2) wrongful termination; (3) intentional infliction of emotional distress; and (4) negligent infliction of emotional distress.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p18">&#8195;Though Plaintiff characterizes this claim as one for both interference and discrimination under the FMLA, his allegations are directed solely towards an interference claim. Plaintiff offers no evidence or argument that he has opposed any practice made unlawful by the FMLA, only that he has attempted to exercise his own FMLA rights and that Defendant has interfered with that exercise. <underscore>Compare</underscore> 29 U.S.C. &#167; 2615(a)(1), (2). Accordingly, summary judgment against Plaintiff is appropriate to the extent he asserts a claim for discrimination under the FMLA.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">On October 19, 2009, Defendant filed this Motion for Summary Judgment or, in the Alternative, Summary Adjudication (&#x201C;Motion&#x201D;). Plaintiff's Opposition and Defendant's Reply were timely filed.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Evidentiary Objections</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">Both parties submitted a number of objections to the other side's evidence. Plaintiff's objections are overruled in their entirety as moot, as the Court has not relied on the documents objected to in reaching its determination.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Defendant filed objections to portions of the Bernal Declaration and the Declaration of Jason K. Feldman (&#x201C;Feldman Declaration&#x201D;). Defendant objects to a number of documents attached to the Feldman Declaration on the basis of Plaintiff's failure to comply with the Court's Standing Order, which requires parties to cite specific page and line numbers in depositions and paragraph numbers in affidavits. While such generalized citations may be insufficient to create a genuine issue of fact on summary judgment, <underscore>see Greenwood v. F.A.A.</underscore>, 28 F.3d 971, 977 (9th Cir. 1994), the Court's Standing Order does not provide a basis for an independent evidentiary objection. Defendant's evidentiary objections based on the Court's Standing Order are overruled.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">The remainder of Defendant's objections, though labeled as evidentiary, are more properly characterized as argument concerning the nature and strength of the evidence offered. All Defendant's remaining objections are overruled. The Court relies only on the facts and evidence set forth above in deciding the Motion.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. LEGAL STANDARD</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">A motion for summary judgment shall be granted when there is no genuine issue as to any material fact and the moving party is entitled to judgment as a matter of law. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c); <underscore>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc.</underscore>, 477 U.S. 242, 247-48 (1986). The moving party must show that &#x201C;under the governing law, there can be but one reasonable conclusion as to the verdict.&#x201D; <underscore>Anderson</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 250.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Generally, the burden is on the moving party to demonstrate that it is entitled to summary judgment. <underscore>Margolis v. Ryan</underscore>, 140 F.3d 850, 852 (9th Cir. 1998); <underscore>Retail Clerks Union Local 648 v. Hub Pharmacy, Inc.</underscore>, 707 F.2d 1030, 1033 (9th Cir. 1983). The moving party bears the initial burden of identifying the elements of the claim or defense and evidence that it believes demonstrates the absence of an issue of material fact. <underscore>Celotex Corp. v. Catrett</underscore>, 477 U.S. 317, 323 (1986).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Where the non-moving party has the burden at trial, however, the moving party need not produce evidence negating or disproving every essential element of the non-moving party's case. <underscore>Celotex</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 325. Instead, the moving party's burden is met by pointing out that there is an absence of evidence supporting the non-moving party's case. <underscore>Id.</underscore> The burden then shifts to the non-moving party to show that there is a genuine issue of material fact that must be resolved at trial. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(e); <underscore>Celotex</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 324; <underscore>Anderson</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 256. The non-moving party must make an affirmative showing on all matters placed in issue by the motion as to which it has the burden of proof at trial. <underscore>Celotex</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 322; <underscore>Anderson</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 252. <underscore>See also</underscore> William W. Schwarzer, A. Wallace Tashima &#38; James M. Wagstaffe, <underscore>Federal Civil Procedure Before Trial</underscore> &#167; 14:144.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">A genuine issue of material fact will exist &#x201C;if the evidence is such that a reasonable jury could return a verdict for the non-moving party.&#x201D; <underscore>Anderson</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 248. In ruling on a motion for summary judgment, the Court construes the evidence in the light most favorable to the non-moving party. <underscore>Barlow v. Ground</underscore>, 943 F.2d 1132, 1135 (9th Cir. 1991); <underscore>T.W. Electrical Serv. Inc. v. Pacific Elec. Contractors Ass'n</underscore>, 809 F.2d 626, 630-31 (9th Cir. 1987).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>III. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Plaintiff Fails to Demonstrate a Genuine Issue of Fact Exists as to His FMLA Claim</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">In asserting that summary judgment is appropriate as to Plaintiff's first claim for relief, Defendant argues (1) Plaintiff fails to set forth sufficient evidence to show that Defendant considered Plaintiff's use of FMLA leave as a negative factor in discharging him, and (2) Plaintiff has no evidence to rebut Defendant's legitimate reason for discharging Plaintiff. As the Court agrees that Plaintiff fails to set forth admissible evidence in support of its FMLA interference claim, it does not reach Defendant's argument that it had a legitimate reason to discharge Plaintiff.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">The FMLA and its implementing regulations make it unlawful for an employer to &#x201C;use the taking of FMLA leave as a negative factor in employment actions, such as hiring, promotions or disciplinary actions.&#x201D; <underscore>Bachelder v. America West Airlines, Inc.</underscore>, 259 F.3d 1112, 1122 (9th Cir. 2001); 29 C.F.R. &#167; 825.220(c); <underscore>see also</underscore> 29 U.S.C. &#167; 2615(a). An employer who uses the taking of FMLA leave as a negative factor in employment actions violates the prohibition on interference with the exercise of FMLA rights set forth at 29 U.S.C. &#167; 2615(a)(1). <underscore>See Bachelder</underscore>, 259 F.3d at 1124&#8211;25. Accordingly, in order to survive summary judgment, Plaintiff must demonstrate that a genuine issue of fact exists as to (1) whether or not he legitimately took FMLA leave on the days in question, and (2) if so, whether or not Defendant relied on the use of such leave as a negative factor in discharging Plaintiff.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Although a genuine issue of fact appears to exist with respect to whether or not Plaintiff was legitimately using FMLA leave on the days in question,<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference> that issue does not preclude summary judgment here. Even assuming that Plaintiff was legitimately using FMLA leave on those days, Plaintiff offers no evidence that Defendant considered his use of leave as a negative factor in discharging him. The only evidence Plaintiff relies on in support of his argument that his use of leave was a negative factor is the Discharge Letter. (<underscore>See</underscore> Opp'n at 7:17&#8211;8:10.) The Discharge Letter, however, does not state that Plaintiff was discharged because he took FMLA leave, or that his use of FMLA leave was a negative factor in his discharge. Instead, the Discharge Letter states &#x201C;[y]ou have been terminated for violating Article 8, Section 1.b.1 of the Agreement. You have engaged in dishonesty by misrepresenting to the Company that you were legitimately using FMLA leave on November 1 and 26, 2007 and March 10, 2008<footnote.reference ID="fr8" refid="f8" style="percent_n">8</footnote.reference> when you in fact were not doing so, but in fact were in court.&#x201D; (Drescher Decl. Ex. P.) Nowhere does it state Plaintiff's use of FMLA leave is a negative factor in his discharge.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p30">&#8195;Defendant argues that Plaintiff's appearance at court hearings on November 1, 2007 and November 26, 2007 belie his claim that he stayed home due to a panic attack. (Mot. at 14:9 &#8211;16:17.) Plaintiff responds that he did in fact have panic attacks on those days, and that his attendance at court hearings is not inconsistent with that fact. (Opp'n at 8:11&#8211;9:19.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f8"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN8.</label.designator><paratext ID="p31">&#8195;As noted above, Defendant concedes Plaintiff did not represent he was using FMLA leave on March 10, 2008. This erroneous statement in the Discharge Letter does not change the outcome here, however.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">The Discharge Letter does not help Plaintiff, and he relies on no other evidence to show that his discharge was causally related to his use of FMLA leave. Accordingly, Plaintiff fails to demonstrate the existence of a genuine issue of material fact with respect to a necessary element of his FMLA interference claim. Summary judgment in Defendant's favor is appropriate.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Plaintiff Fails to Establish a Genuine Issue of Fact as to His Wrongful Termination Claim</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">To establish a claim for wrongful termination under California law, a plaintiff must establish &#x201C;(1) that he engaged in activity protected by a statute or regulation of public importance, and (2) that he would not have been terminated but for his participation in the protected activity.&#x201D; <underscore>Walker v. Boeing Corp.</underscore>, 218 F. Supp. 2d 1177, 1187 (C.D. Cal. 2002), citing <underscore>Turner v. Anheuser-Busch, Inc.</underscore>, 7 Cal. 4th 1238, 1257&#8211;58 (1994).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Plaintiff bases his wrongful termination claim (1) on Defendant's alleged violation of the FMLA, (<underscore>see</underscore> Opp'n at 9:22&#8211;10:3), and (2) on an alleged pattern of harassment and retaliation relating to Plaintiff's claimed whistle blower status. (<underscore>See</underscore> Opp'n at 10:4&#8211;11:22.) For the reasons discussed above, Plaintiff's FMLA interference claim fails; summary judgment is therefore appropriate concerning Plaintiff's wrongful termination claim to the extent it is premised on a violation of the FMLA.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">Summary judgment is also appropriate to the extent Plaintiff's wrongful termination claim is premised on a pattern of retaliation and harassment. Plaintiff alleges that he &#x201C;reported hazardous waste violations by UPS in October 2003 and October 2005,&#x201D; (Opp'n at 10:6&#8211;7; Bernal Decl. &#182;&#182; 3, 4), and that he suffered a pattern of harassment after the 2005 incident culminating in his March 2008 discharge.<footnote.reference ID="fr9" refid="f9" style="percent_n">9</footnote.reference> (Opp'n at 3:13&#8211;4:8.) Plaintiff fails, however, to offer any evidence that those responsible for his discharge were aware that he had made these reports. Without any evidence of such knowledge, Plaintiff cannot establish that he would not have been discharged but for his participation in protected activity. <underscore>See Raad v. Fairbanks North Star Borough School Dist.</underscore>, 323 F.3d 1185, 1197 (9th Cir. 2003); <underscore>Walker</underscore>, 218 F. Supp. 2d at 1188.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f9"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN9.</label.designator><paratext ID="p36">&#8195;Defendant argues Plaintiff should be estopped from arguing any facts relating to this asserted &#x201C;pattern of harassment&#x201D; because such facts do not appear in the Complaint, and when asked at his deposition whether all his allegations against Defendant were contained in the Complaint, Plaintiff responded affirmatively. (<underscore>See</underscore> Reply at 5:15 &#8211;6:3.) This argument fails. While such an answer given in response to a contention interrogatory may have the effect of a judicial admission, it does not have such effect when given at a deposition. &#x201C;As a practical matter, a party-deponent cannot reasonably be held to the same precision of expression, breadth of knowledge, or legal expertise as a party responding through counsel to a written interrogatory.&#x201D; <underscore>Guadagno v. Wallack Ader Levithan Assocs.</underscore>, 950 F. Supp. 1258, 1261 (S.D.N.Y. 1997). <underscore>Wasco Products, Inc. v. Southwall Techs., Inc.</underscore>, 435 F.3d 989 (9th Cir. 2006), relied on by Defendant, is not to the contrary, as it did not concern whether deposition testimony may qualify as a judicial admission. In general, of course, plaintiffs may rely on facts outside the complaint at the summary judgment stage.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Plaintiff's Claims for Intentional and Negligent Infliction of Emotional Distress Fail as a Matter of Law</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>1. Intentional Infliction of Emotional Distress</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">Defendant argues that summary judgment is appropriate as to Plaintiff's claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress because (1) Plaintiff's discharge does not constitute outrageous conduct, (<underscore>see</underscore> Mot. at 21:6&#8211;28), and (2) there is no evidence that the relevant decision makers intended to cause Plaintiff distress. (<underscore>See</underscore> Mot. at 22:1&#8211;12.) The Court agrees that Plaintiff's discharge does not constitute outrageous conduct as a matter of law, and therefore does not reach Defendant's second argument.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">In order to establish a claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress under California law, a plaintiff must show (1) extreme and outrageous conduct by the defendant; (2) intention to cause, or reckless disregard of the probability of causing, emotional distress; (3) severe emotional suffering; and (4) actual and proximate causation of the emotional distress. <underscore>King v. AC &#38; R Adver.</underscore>, 65 F.3d 764, 769 (9th Cir. 1995); <underscore>see also Cole v. Fair Oaks Fire Protection Dist.</underscore>, 43 Cal. 3d 148, 155 n.7 (1987). &#x201C;Conduct, to be outrageous, must be so extreme as to exceed all bounds of that usually tolerated in a civilized society.&#x201D; <underscore>King</underscore>, 65 F.3d at 770.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">Under California law, &#x201C;[m]anaging personnel is not outrageous conduct beyond the bounds of human decency. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> A simple pleading of personnel management activity is insufficient to support a claim of intentional infliction of emotional distress, even if improper motivation is alleged. If personnel management decisions are improperly motivated, the remedy is a suit against the employer for discrimination.&#x201D; <underscore>Janken v. GM Hughes Elecs.</underscore>, 46 Cal. App. 4th 55, 80 (1996); <underscore>see also Heller v. Pillsbury Madison &#38; Sutro</underscore>, 50 Cal. App. 4th 1367, 1389 (1996) (&#x201C;[T]he distress of being terminated does not by itself give rise to a viable emotional distress cause of action.&#x201D;); <underscore>Pitman v. City of Oakland</underscore>, 197 Cal. App. 3d 1037, 1047 (1988). Applying these principles, courts have held that summary judgment of intentional infliction of emotional distress claims is appropriate where such claims are based on mere discharge, absent any significant aggravating factors. <underscore>See King</underscore>, 65 F.3d at 770; <underscore>Walker</underscore>, 218 F. Supp. 2d at 1190 (&#x201C;Terminating an employee for improper or discriminatory reasons, like many other adverse personnel management decisions, is insufficiently extreme or outrageous to give rise to a claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress.&#x201D;); <underscore>Bartalini v. Blockbuster Entm't, Inc.</underscore>, No. C-98-3943-SC, 1999 WL 1012383, at *10 (N.D. Cal. Nov. 8, 1999) (&#x201C;As a matter of law, the general shame, humiliation, and emotional distress experienced by people who have lost their jobs cannot support a claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">Here, Plaintiff alleges that &#x201C;UPS's conduct towards plaintiff was clearly &#x2018;outrageous,&#x2019;&#x201D; (<underscore>see</underscore> Opp'n at 11:25&#8211;26); however, it is unclear what specific conduct Plaintiff believes to have been outrageous. To the extent that Plaintiff's claim is based on his discharge, his claim fails as a matter of law. <underscore>Walker</underscore>, 218 F.3d at 1190; <underscore>Bartalini</underscore>, 1999 WL 1012383, at *10. Plaintiff also claims &#x201C;[t]here is evidence of repeated public humiliations in the course of the employer-employee relationship and that humiliation continues today,&#x201D; (Opp'n at 12:12&#8211;13), yet fails to explain what that evidence is or provide any details concerning these claimed public humiliations. The only specific act of public humiliation alleged is that Defendant &#x201C;memorialized the reasons for termination as dishonesty and misuse of FMLA despite the fact that there was no dishonesty in plaintiff's use of FMLA leave.&#x201D; (Opp'n at 12:16&#8211;17.) Standing alone, however, memorializing reasons for discharge in a letter is not outrageous conduct beyond the bounds of human decency. Furthermore, improper motives for a discharge do not give rise to a claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress. <underscore>See Janken</underscore>, 46 Cal. App. 4th at 80.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">Relying on <underscore>Huber v. Standard Ins. Co.</underscore>, 841 F.2d 980 (9th Cir. 1988), Plaintiff argues that a claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress exists where an employee has been discharged without notice for reasons he believes to be false, and where the reasons for discharge have been memorialized in writing. (<underscore>See</underscore> Opp'n at 12:21&#8211;26.) The Ninth Circuit has distinguished the conduct at issue in <underscore>Huber</underscore>, however, as being particularly outrageous because the employee was not given the contractually-required 30 days notice of termination and because the termination was contrary to the company's standard practice of allowing terminated employees to remain until their pensions vest. <underscore>King</underscore>, 65 F.3d at 770. Plaintiff here has not identified any contractual provision requiring that he be provided with pre-discharge notice, nor has he identified any company policy or practice that was violated by his discharge. <underscore>Huber</underscore> does not aid Plaintiff's claim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">To the extent Plaintiff bases his claim on allegations that Defendant &#x201C;engaged in a pattern of harassment since on or about October 2003 aimed at driving him out of the company culminating in a false accusation of dishonesty and misuse of FMLA [leave],&#x201D; (Opp'n at 13:23&#8211;25), his claim also fails. Plaintiff alleges myriad types of harassment, examples of which include Defendant holding meetings or hearings to discuss Plaintiff's FMLA absences, making &#x201C;unwarranted and repeated phone calls about a given FMLA document,&#x201D; requiring Plaintiff &#x201C;re-file FMLA documents <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> over and over,&#x201D; and supervisors and managers making &#x201C;derogatory remarks and roll[ing] their eyes concerning [his] FMLA condition and leav[ing] during meetings and elsewhere.&#x201D; (Bernal Decl. &#182; 8.) None of the examples of harassment set forth in the Bernal Declaration, however, are sufficiently outrageous to allow a reasonable trier of fact to conclude they are beyond all bounds of civilized society.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">Liability for intentional infliction of emotional distress generally &#x201C;does not extend to mere insults, indignities, threats, annoyances, petty oppressions, or other trivialities, but only to conduct so extreme and outrageous as to go beyond all possible bonds of decency.&#x201D; <underscore>Ankeny v. Lockheed Missiles &#38; Space Co.</underscore>, 88 Cal. App. 3d 531, 537 (1979) (citation omitted) (affirming demurrer with respect to claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress). Perhaps the paradigmatic examples of such outrageous conduct in the employment context are when an employer uses racial epithets against an employee or sexually harasses an employee. <underscore>See, e.g., Robinson v. Hewlett-Packard Corp.</underscore>, 183 Cal. App. 3d 1108, 1128&#8211;30 (1986) (racial slurs); <underscore>Fisher v. San Pedro Peninsula Hospital</underscore>, 214 Cal. App. 3d 590, 617&#8211;18 (1989) (sexual harassment). The conduct alleged by Plaintiff simply does not approach this level of seriousness. The California Supreme Court has recognized that &#x201C;demotions, promotions, criticism of work practices, and frictions in negotiations as to grievances&#x201D; are &#x201C;typical employer actions.&#x201D; <underscore>Vacanti v. State Comp. Ins. Fund</underscore>, 24 Cal. 4th 800, 821 (2001). The conduct alleged by Plaintiff, while perhaps regrettable, thus is typical of the employment relationship, and does not go beyond all possible bounds of decency.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>2. Negligent Infliction of Emotional Distress</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">Finally, Plaintiff argues summary judgment with respect to his claim for negligent infliction of emotional distress is inappropriate. Defendant argues the intentional conduct Plaintiff alleges cannot form the basis of a claim for negligence and Plaintiff has no evidence showing that Defendant failed to exercise due care. The Court agrees Plaintiff's claim for negligent infliction of emotional distress fails as a matter of law.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">The California Supreme Court has recognized that &#x201C;the <ital>negligent</ital> causing of emotional distress is not an independent tort, but the tort of <ital>negligence.</ital> The traditional elements of duty, breach of duty, causation, and damages apply.&#x201D; <underscore>Burgess v. Super. Ct.</underscore>, 2 Cal. 4th 1064, 1072 (1992) (emphasis in original), quoting <underscore>Marlene F. v. Affiliated Psychiatric Med. Clinic, Inc.</underscore>, 48 Cal. 3d 583, 588 (1989).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">Plaintiff first argues Defendant may be held liable for negligence because &#x201C;at a minimum, UPS should have known of plaintiff's sensitivity and acted negligently.&#x201D; (Opp'n at 14:5&#8211;6.) This argument fails, however. Where a claim for negligence arises out of a discharge of an employee, &#x201C;the foreseeability of risk of harm to plaintiff's emotional health&#x201D; standing alone is insufficient to establish a duty to refrain from discharging the employee. <underscore>Semore v. Pool</underscore>, 217 Cal. App. 3d 1087, 1105 (1990). Assuming that Defendant was aware of Plaintiff's heightened &#x201C;sensitivity,&#x201D; this fact is insufficient to establish a claim for negligence.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p47" level="1">Plaintiff next argues that &#x201C;there is evidence that UPS's investigation into the circumstances surrounding plaintiff's termination was a smokescreen and pretext to terminate an employee who was a whistleblower and a spokesperson for employee rights and because of his FMLA status.&#x201D; (Opp'n at 14:7&#8211;10.) As an initial matter, Plaintiff offers no evidence whatsoever demonstrating he acted as a &#x201C;spokesperson for employee rights.&#x201D; Moreover, even assuming these facts to be true, they would constitute intentional &#8212; not negligent &#8212; conduct. Intentional conduct cannot form the basis of a negligence claim. <underscore>Walker</underscore>, 218 F. Supp. 2d at 1185; <underscore>Semore</underscore>, 217 Cal. App. 3d at 1105.<footnote.reference ID="fr10" refid="f10" style="percent_n">10</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f10"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN10.</label.designator><paratext ID="p48">&#8195;The Court further notes that although it appears likely that Plaintiff's claim for negligence is preempted by California's worker's compensation law, <underscore>see, e.g., Vacanti</underscore>, 24 Cal. 4th at 811&#8211;12, Defendant fails to raise this argument. Accordingly, the Court expresses no opinion as to whether this claim is pre-empted.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court GRANTS Defendant's Motion.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">Dated: <underscore>December 8, 2009</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>