<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>ASCANIO CARIMATI DI CARIMATI, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>GINSGLOBAL INDEX FUNDS, et al., Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV09-02373 DMG (RZx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV09-02373 DMG (RZx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-02373-DMG-RZ</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 06/13/2011</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER RE (1) PLAINTIFF'S MOTION FOR SUMMARY ADJUDICATION OF THE LIABILITY OF THE GINSGLOBAL DEFENDANTS AND ANTHONY GINSBERG AND (2) PLAINTIFF'S MOTION FOR SUMMARY ADJUDICATION OF ISSUES AGAINST DEFENDANT JOHN J. MCCLOY II</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">DOLLY M. GEE UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">This matter is before the Court on (1) Plaintiff's Motion for Summary Adjudication of the Liability of the GinsGlobal Defendants and Anthony Ginsberg [Doc. # 62] (&#x201C;GG Motion&#x201D;), and (2) Plaintiff's Motion for Summary Adjudication of Issues Against Defendant John J. McCloy II [Doc. # 63] (&#x201C;McCloy Motion&#x201D;). The Court held a hearing on February 11, 2011. Having duly considered the respective positions of the parties, as presented in their briefs and at oral argument, the Court now renders its decision. For the reasons set forth below, Plaintiff's GG Motion is GRANTED in part and DENIED in part and Plaintiff's McCloy Motion is DENIED.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. <underscore>PROCEDURAL HISTORY</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On April 6, 2009, Plaintiff Ascanio Carimati di Carimati filed a Complaint in this Court. Plaintiff subsequently filed a First Amended Complaint on May 19, 2009, a Second Amended Complaint on November 9, 2009, and the operative Third Amended Complaint on May 3, 2010. Plaintiff alleges the following claims: (1) breach of contract; (2) breach of fiduciary duty; (3) fraud; (4) negligent misrepresentation; (5) unjust enrichment; and (6) intentional interference with contract. Plaintiff alleges the first through fifth causes of action against the following Defendants: GinsGlobal Index Funds, a California corporation (&#x201C;GG California&#x201D;); GinsGlobal Index Funds Ltd., a Mauritius company (&#x201C;GG Mauritius&#x201D;); GinsGlobal Investment Management Ltd., a Mauritius company (&#x201C;GG Management&#x201D;); GinsGlobal Index Funds Ltd., a South Africa company (&#x201C;GG South Africa&#x201D;) (collectively, the &#x201C;GG Entities&#x201D;); and Anthony Ginsberg (together with the GG Entities, the &#x201C;GG Defendants&#x201D;). Plaintiff alleges the sixth cause of action against John J. McCloy II.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">On November 5, 2010, Plaintiff filed the GG Motion and the McCloy Motion. On November 29, 2010, the GG Defendants filed an Opposition. On December 2, 2010, Plaintiff filed a Reply in support of the McCloy Motion and on December 8, 2010, Plaintiff filed a Reply in support of the GG Motion. On December 23, 2010, McCloy filed an Opposition to the McCloy Motion and on January 5, 2011, Plaintiff filed a Reply in support of the McCloy Motion.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">//</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">//</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">//</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">//</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">//</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. <underscore>FACTUAL BACKGROUND</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Except where noted, the facts material to the Court's decision are undisputed by the parties.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p10">&#8195;Plaintiff raises a number of evidentiary objections. To the extent the challenged evidence is not material to the Court's decision, the Court need not address such objections and denies them as moot.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. <underscore>The Parties</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Ginsberg, an investment manager and certified public accountant, is the managing director of GG California, and an officer and director of GG Mauritius, GG South Africa, and GG Management. (Decl. of Anthony Ginsberg (&#x201C;Ginsberg Decl&#x201D;) &#182; 1.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">GG Management is the parent company of GG California, GG Mauritius, and GG South Africa. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 2.) GG Management owns 100% of both GG California and GG Mauritius and 52% of GG South Africa. (<ital>Id.</ital>) The remaining 48% of GG South Africa is owned by South African nationals, including Ginsberg and five other individuals. (<ital>Id.</ital>) GG Management is the 50% owner of the two Hindsight Investment Group entities that were formed by Plaintiff to conduct the business of the parties' joint venture. (Pl.'s Facts in Supp. of GG Mot. (&#x201C;Pl.'s Facts&#x201D;) &#182; 10; GinsGlobal Parties' Resp. (&#x201C;Defs.' Disputes&#x201D;) &#182; 10.) GG Mauritius holds the third party assets that it manages, while GG Management receives and retains the fee for managing those assets. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 4.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">GG California, which was incorporated in California on or about December 29, 2007, was established to conduct the business of the GG Entities in the United States. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 11.) Ginsberg is the sole employee of GG California. (<ital>Id.</ital> &#182; 13.) GG California has no assets and earns no revenue. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 13; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 13.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. <underscore>The Business Plan</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Plaintiff was introduced to Ginsberg in February 2007, at which time Ginsberg introduced Plaintiff to the Hindsight Product concept.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 18; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 18.) Prior to meeting with Plaintiff, the GG Defendants had never marketed or sold Hindsight Products in Europe. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 19; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 19.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p15">&#8195;The Hindsight Product allows an investor to choose two or more products for his or her &#x201C;basket,&#x201D; and to retroactively &#x201C;choose&#x201D; the best performer and discard the worst performer. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 15; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 15.) The Hindsight Product also offers a capital guarantee so, at a minimum, the investor may cap his or her losses, and in the case of a 100% capital guarantee, is assured of receiving his or her entire principal back. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 17; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 17.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">In the summer and fall of 2007, prior to agreeing to enter into a joint venture with GG California, Plaintiff conducted due diligence related to the Hindsight Product. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 21; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 21.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">In early November 2007, Plaintiff and Ginsberg began preparing the Hindsight Business Plan (the &#x201C;Business Plan&#x201D;). (Decl. of Ascanio Carimati di Carimate in Supp. of GG Motion (&#x201C;Carimati GG Decl.&#x201D;) &#182; 21.) Ginsberg thoroughly reviewed, commented upon, and approved the Business Plan. Ginsberg also complimented Plaintiff on his preparation of the Business Plan. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 26; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 26.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">Section 4.1 of the Business Plan, dated November 29, 2007, is entitled &#x201C;Partner Responsibilities&#x201D; and provides:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p19" first-line="1" turnover="1">GinsGlobal will create and price all products as per Hindsight Products' instructions. It will offer sales support and product support. It will make available contacts that are pertinent to European market development. It will be in constant communication with Hindsight Investments and keep H.I. abreast of all market developments and trends applicable to Hindsight products. Finally GinsGlobal will enter into an irrevocable licensing and non-compete agreement with H.I.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p20" contd-flag="y">(Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 21; Pl.'s App. of Evid. in Supp. of GG Motion (&#x201C;GG PAE&#x201D;) Exs. 17(a) and (b).)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">//</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. <underscore>The January 9, 2008 Memorandum of Understanding</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">On January 9, 2008, Plaintiff and Ginsberg met in New York and executed the Memorandum of Understanding (&#x201C;MOU&#x201D;) between Plaintiff and GG California. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 29, GG PAE Ex. 21.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">The MOU provides:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p24" first-line="2" turnover="2">1. The parties hereby acknowledge and agree that this arrangement will be a joint venture and a new company (Newco) will be incorporated to represent the parties' interests in this joint venture.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" first-line="2" turnover="2">2. The parties hereby acknowledge and agree that AC will only be remunerated for any of the net fees he generates from his sales and distribution efforts in Europe.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" first-line="2" turnover="2">3. The parties hereby acknowledge and agree that an exclusivity arrangement between them in relation to the clients and the distribution of the said product is in order. Neither party shall enter into any competitive agreements or business transactions for the duration of this Agreement. This exclusivity arrangement shall remain in full force and effect for a period of five (5) years from the date of this Agreement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" first-line="2" turnover="2">* * *</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" first-line="2" turnover="2">6. The parties hereby acknowledge and agree that this Memorandum of Understanding shall be binding upon them upon signature by each of them.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" first-line="2" turnover="2">* * *</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" first-line="2" turnover="2">8. This Agreement shall be construed, governed and interpreted in accordance with the laws of the [sic] Delaware. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 29, GG PAE Ex. 21.)</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Pursuant to the terms of the MOU, Plaintiff began the process of incorporating Hindsight Investment Group (&#x201C;HIG&#x201D;) to conduct all of the joint venture's Hindsight business. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 30; Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 20.) Plaintiff caused two HIG entities to be incorporated&#8212;one in the British Virgin Islands and one in Switzerland. (<ital>Id.</ital>) Even though GG California was the signatory to the MOU, GG Management was registered as the 50% owner of the two HIG entities. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 31.) In March 2008, Plaintiff made an initial capital investment of 100,000 Swiss Francs required under Swiss law to establish a new company in Switzerland. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 32.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>D. <underscore>Further Negotiations Between the Parties</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">In January and February 2008, after the January 2008 MOU was signed, Plaintiff asked for assurance that if he was able to sell the Hindsight product outside of Europe that he would still be compensated in accordance with the terms of the MOU. Ginsberg assured Plaintiff that they would honor all of his introductions worldwide on the same 50-50 sharing basis spelled out in the MOU. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 21.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>1. <underscore>The February 2008 Verbal Agreement</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">On February 15, 2008, Plaintiff sent an email to Ginsberg that stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p34" first-line="2" turnover="2">As I mentioned, I wanted to confirm with you GinsGlobal's intention to pass all Hindsight product business through Hindsight Investments Group, regardless of geographical location. Proceeds will be divided as agreed.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p35" contd-flag="y">(Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 33, GG PAE Ex. 33.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">On February 18, 2008, Ginsberg sent an email to Plaintiff that stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p37" first-line="2" turnover="2">Yes we intend to pass through all such hindsight [sic] business through Hindsight Investments &#8211; that has been initiated through our joint efforts. [&#182;] However existing business such as AIG, South Africa, US CD's or Taiwan that already produces hindsight monies for the past 5 years can clearly not be credited to your efforts. It is easy to differentiate existing versus new business initiatives so I don't foresee any problem. [&#182;] Clearly Hindsight Investment should be the recipient of all new business inflows that result from our joint initiative &#8211; between ourselves.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p38" contd-flag="y">(<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">Plaintiff then responded to Ginsberg, also on February 18, 2008, as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p40" first-line="2" turnover="2">My understanding of our discussion is that we would pass all future Hindsight business (including renewals on past business, but understandably excluding AIG as it is better to let sleeping dogs lie) in order to build the &#x2018;Hindsight&#x2019; brand and have a company that would have a strong intrinsic value in the future. [&#182;] I hope you did not misunderstand my reasoning behind my request: I do not expect to be paid on initiatives that are yours in any way (neither past, nor future). [&#182;] I did however understand that we would use the new company as the channel for both your and my Hindsight business and then sort the payout according to what has been agreed <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> Let me know if this is a correct understanding of our talks, as this is an important issue for me to make clear not only for myself, but to clarify things also for any current and future collaborators.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p41" contd-flag="y">(<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">On February 19, 2008, Ginsberg emailed a response to Plaintiff that stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p43" first-line="2" turnover="2">Yes I agree with your comments re splitting all future initiatives using Hindsight Investment entity &#8211; no problem. I just wanted to ensure there was [sic] no misunderstandings either repast [sic] business initiatives!</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p44" contd-flag="y">(<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">Ginsberg asserts that he never intended to agree to run all Hindsight business (regardless of who initiated it) through HIG. He intended only to confirm the limited change to the MOU that Plaintiff would share only in fees or benefit from business that he helped generate. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 24.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>2. <underscore>The May 2008 Negotiation and Termination</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">In May 2008, the parties exchanged additional emails and letters in an attempt to negotiate a new agreement. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182;&#182; 43-46.) On May 28, 2008, Ginsberg sent an email to Plaintiff terminating the business relationship and cancelling the January 2008 MOU. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 46; GG PAE Ex. 40.) Ginsberg stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p47" first-line="2" turnover="2">Unfortunately since it seems we are now at an impasse re agreeing on the terms for a new agreement and cannot find a middle ground as how to best to move forward from here, I have been advised that it is best for both of us to not continue to develop and pursue our business relationship at this point <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p48" first-line="2" turnover="2">* * *</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" first-line="2" turnover="2"><charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> After much soul-searching, I believe it is therefore best for both of us to go our separate ways unfortunately. [&#182;] GinsGlobal therefore hereby notifies you of its immediate cancellation of our agreement dated January 9, 2008. We believe we can no longer perform under the existing agreement and hereby tender our notice of cancellation and cease all our related activities with yourself, forthwith.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p50" contd-flag="y">(<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>E. <underscore>Alleged False Representations Made by the GG Defendants</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p51" level="1">According to Plaintiff, the GG Defendants made a number of false representations to induce Plaintiff to enter into the MOU. According to Plaintiff, it was after concluding his due diligence, including review of the various third party brochures and documentation from such companies as Transamerica and American General Life (a division of AIG), that Plaintiff proposed to Ginsberg that they form a joint venture dedicated to the marketing and sale of Hindsight Products in Europe. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 20.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p52" level="1">The GG Defendants emphasize that only two of the alleged misrepresentations occurred prior to January 9, 2008, the date on which Plaintiff entered into the January 2008 MOU. Ginsberg also emphasizes that Plaintiff never asked for any profit and loss statements, balance sheets, tax returns, or any other information concerning any of the GG Entities or specifically concerning Hindsight sales. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 43.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>a. <underscore>Misrepresentations Regarding Transamerica Life Canada</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p53" level="1">On October 31, 2007, Ginsberg sent Plaintiff an email of &#x201C;promotional materials&#x201D; that attached the Transamerica Life Insurance brochure and excerpts from the AIG 2006 Annual Report. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 18; GG PAE Ex. 49.) According to Plaintiff, Ginsberg directed his attention to the references to GinsGlobal in the Transamerica report and to the Elite Global product in the AIG Annual Report. (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p54" level="1">On April 5, 2008, Ginsberg sent an email to Plaintiff that stated that Transamerica Life Canada had achieved approximately C$600 million in sales between 2004 and 2006, which information Ginsberg knew Plaintiff would use in his efforts to market HIG and its products. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 56; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 56; Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 19; GG PAE Ex 32.) At his deposition, however, Ginsberg admitted that his representations were &#x201C;clearly [] an exaggeration,&#x201D; and that in fact the Transamerica product &#x201C;generated no sales.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 57; Defs' Disputes &#182; 57; Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 19.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p55" level="1">Ginsberg argues that &#x201C;prior to entering into the MOU, all [Ginsberg] told [Plaintiff] was that the GinsGlobal Parties had designed a product that was being marketed by Transamerica beginning in 2004 and that it was no longer being marketed by Transamerica.&#x201D; (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 45(c).) Ginsberg emphasizes that the email was prepared after Plaintiff decided to move forward with the transaction and was prepared only to help Plaintiff prepare a business plan. (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p56" level="1">//</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>b. <underscore>Misrepresentations Regarding American General Life</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p57" level="1">According to Plaintiff, Ginsberg explained during their initial meetings that GG California had entered into an agreement with American General Life Insurance Company (&#x201C;American General Life&#x201D; or &#x201C;AIG&#x201D;), under which American General Life was successfully marketing and selling a Hindsight insurance product, Elite Global, in the United States. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 6.) Ginsberg told Plaintiff that Elite Global was the number one product of its kind in the United States, accounting for sales with a policy face value of approximately $3 billion in life cover by the end of 2007. (<ital>Id.</ital>) Plaintiff claims, however, that Ginsberg failed to inform him that none of the GG Entities had any contract with American General Life. (<ital>Id.</ital> &#182; 7.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p58" level="1">Plaintiff also asserts that the GG Defendants materially misrepresented the revenues earned by Defendants from American General Life. Plaintiff points to a November 14, 2007 email from Ginsberg to Plaintiff, in which Ginsberg stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p59" first-line="2" turnover="2">In the case of our AIG product (AIG Elite Global), the entire investment (cash) value generated by the product is tied to an underlying Hindsight Option. AIG pay [sic] GinsGlobal 1% of all collected premium on this policy. AIG do not require the principal protection piece given their wide bond portfolio holdings which generate sufficient historical returns to ensure clients will receive their principal plus 2.5% annualized return back &#8211; regardless of the Hindsight Option's performance.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p60" contd-flag="y">(Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 11; GG PAE Ex. 28.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p61" level="1">According to Ginsberg, the email was sent to Plaintiff not for the purpose of helping him evaluate whether to do business with Ginsberg, but in order to assist Plaintiff in preparing a business plan that Plaintiff needed in order to secure participation by Carthesio, S.A., an international banking firm and prospective joint venture partner. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 45(a).)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p62" level="1">Plaintiff also presents a February 22, 2008 email from Ginsberg to Plaintiff, which attached &#x201C;a recent AIG advertisement re the Hindsight product's success within their life policy (Elite Global)!&#x201D; The advertisement stated, &#x201C;Producer response to the AIG Elite Global IUL has been phenomenal with more than $83 million of target premium placed in 2007.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 48; Defs.' Disputes 48; Carimati GG Decl. &#182;&#182; 13-15; GG PAE Exs. 29-30.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p63" level="1">On February 22, 2008, Plaintiff wrote to Ginsberg and asked:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p64" first-line="2" turnover="2">Please excuse my ignorance but could you explain what they mean by &#x2018;over $83 million of target premium placed in 2007.&#x2019; (Why is this number so different from the $5 billion we have discussed as assets placed through Elite Global?)</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p65" contd-flag="y">(Pl.'s Facts &#182; 49; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 49; Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 14; GG PAE Ex. 29.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p66" level="1">Ginsberg responded:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p67" first-line="2" turnover="2">PS &#8211; re target premium issue on the advertisement, we get remunerated on the amount of life cover which is approaching $5bn. The advertisement only focuses on one specific area of premium they are collecting &#8211; i.e., it does not count all the premium commitments so far &#8211; via different platforms.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p68" contd-flag="y">(Pl.'s Facts &#182; 50; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 50; Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 15; GG PAE Ex. 29.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p69" level="1">At his deposition, Ginsberg testified that his statement did not &#x201C;give a full picture&#x201D; and that he knew that GinsGlobal was not getting paid 1% of $5 billion, but on target or commissionable premiums. (Rutenberg Decl. &#182; 3l; GG PAE Ex. 3; Deposition of Anthony Ginsberg (&#x201C;Ginsberg Depo.&#x201D;) at 26-27, 47-48, 52.) Defendants, in fact, earned only 1% of &#x201C;commissionable first year premiums.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 52; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 52.) The first year &#x201C;commissionable premiums&#x201D; derived from American General Life's sale of Hindsight Products in 2007 were $92 million. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 54; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 54.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p70" level="1">Finally, Plaintiff contends that Ginsberg misrepresented to Plaintiff that Defendants earned a yearly licensing fee from American General Life. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 12.) Defendants never earned a yearly licensing fee from American General Life. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 53; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 53.) Ginsberg denies making this representation to Plaintiff and states instead:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p71" first-line="2" turnover="2">What I did tell him was that in the context of the business plan he was preparing for Carthesio, it would be a fair assumption that if he were able to sell a European variable life insurance product, a license fee would be a legitimate form of compensation in connection with that type of product. I never told Carimati that the GinsGlobal parties had sold that type of product or collected that licensing fee.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p72" contd-flag="y">(Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 45(b).)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>c. <underscore>Misrepresentations Regarding Hindsight's Past Success</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p73" level="1">Ginsberg sent Plaintiff the May 9 draft with a cover email, in which he wrote;</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p74" first-line="2" turnover="2">As you are aware we are not a 1 hit wonder with [American General Life] re Hindsight &#8211; having also secured approximately $100mn in Hindsight CD business last year alone and a few hundred million in other Hindsight structures the past 36 months.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p75" contd-flag="y">(Carimati Decl. &#182; 44; Pl.'s Facts &#182; 74; Defs' Disputes &#182; 74.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p76" level="1">At his deposition, Ginsberg admitted that these statements were false. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 75; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 75.) In fact, GinsGlobal secured only about $8 million in Hindsight CD business the previous year and had not secured &#x201C;a few hundred million&#x201D; in other Hindsight structures either. (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p77" level="1">//</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p78" level="1">//</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p79" level="1">//</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>d. <underscore>False Promise to Use HIG for Future Hindsight Business</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p80" level="1">As set forth <ital>supra</ital>, Plaintiff contends that Defendants falsely promised to use HIG for all future Hindsight business. Plaintiff highlights Ginsberg's February 18, 2008 email, in which Ginsberg stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p81" first-line="2" turnover="2">Yes I agree with your comments re splitting all future initiatives using Hindsight Investment entity &#8211; no problem.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p82" contd-flag="y">(Pl.'s Facts &#182; 60; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 60.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p83" level="1">Plaintiff states that Ginsberg's response came after Plaintiff stated the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p84" first-line="2" turnover="2">I did however understand that we would use the new company as the channel for both your and my Hindsight business and then sort the payout according to what has been agreed <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> Let me know if this is a correct understanding of our talks, as this is an important issue for me to make clear not only for myself, but to clarify things also for any current and future collaborators.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p85" contd-flag="y">(<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p86" level="1">Plaintiff contends that Ginsberg contradicted his own position in a letter dated May 22, 2008, in which Ginsberg wrote the following to Plaintiff:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p87" first-line="2" turnover="2">I do not have a majority voting interest in GinsGlobal and my Board has opposed the granting an exclusive worldwide license and inserting all our Hindsight activities into 1 company with an ultimate 50-50 shareholding <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> I realize in recent months you have requested additional commitments such as the exclusive world-wide license and sharing 50-50 globally on all our Hindsight fees, but I do not have the sole power to give this to you and this was not the original intent when we first began to work together.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p88" contd-flag="y">(Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 34; GG PAE Ex. 34.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p89" level="1">//</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>F. <underscore>McCloy's Alleged Interference with Plaintiff's Contract</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p90" level="1">Plaintiff approached Defendant McCloy to join their joint venture as a member of the Board of Advisors, with a financial interest in the business that McCloy generated for the enterprise. (Decl. of Ascanio Carimati di Carimate in Supp. of McCloy Motion (&#x201C;Carimati McCloy Decl.&#x201D;) &#182;&#182; 9-10, 17-18.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p91" level="1">McCloy refused to discuss the offer to be an advisor to HIG with Carimati and instead sought a position as a director on GinsGlobal's Board of Directors (Carimati McCloy Decl. &#182;&#182; 17-18.). McCloy asked to become a stockholder in GinsGlobal (McCloy Decl. &#182; 12) and disparaged Carimati's performance to Ginsberg, including criticizing Carimati's presentation skills (Carimati McCloy Decl. &#182; 21).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p92" level="1">After the deal with Plaintiff was terminated, GG Mauritius entered into a written agreement with McCloy under which McCloy became an &#x201C;official authorized marketing representative and distributor of GinsGlobal products&#x201D; including Hindsight Products. (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 85; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 85.) GG Mauritius entered into similar agreements with Stockard and von Dalwigk. ((Pl.'s Facts &#182; 86; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 86.) In November 2009, GG Mauritius entered into a Design and Consulting Agreement with Actuarial Development Services, LLC to, among other things, &#x201C;promote, market and develop products which utilize the GinsGlobal Hindsight Index product.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 87; Defs.' Disputes &#182; 87.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>III. <underscore>LEGAL STANDARD</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p93" level="1">Summary judgment should be granted &#x201C;if the movant shows that there is no genuine dispute as to any material fact and the movant is entitled to judgment as a matter of law.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(a); <ital>accord Munoz v. Mabus</ital>, __ F.3d __, 2010 WL 5263141, at *2 (9th Cir. Dec. 27, 2010). Material facts are those that may affect the outcome of the case. <ital>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc.</ital>, 477 U.S. 242, 248, 106 S.Ct. 2505, 91 L.Ed.2d 202 (1986). An issue is genuine &#x201C;if the evidence is such that a reasonable jury could return a verdict for the nonmoving party.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p94" level="1">The moving party bears the initial burden of establishing the absence of a genuine issue of material fact. <ital>Celotex Corp. v. Catrett</ital>, 477 U.S. 317, 323, 106 S.Ct. 2548, 91 L.Ed.2d 265 (1986). Once the moving party has met its initial burden, Rule 56(c) requires the nonmoving party to &#x201C;go beyond the pleadings and by her own affidavits, or by the &#x2018;depositions, answers to interrogatories, and admissions on file,&#x2019; designate &#x2018;specific facts showing that there is a genuine issue for trial.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 324 (quoting Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c), (e) (1986)); <ital>see also Norse v. City Of Santa Cruz</ital>, __ F.3d __, 2010 WL 5097749, at *4 (9th Cir. Dec. 15, 2010) (<ital>en banc</ital>) (&#x201C;Rule 56 requires the parties to set out facts they will be able to prove at trial.&#x201D;). &#x201C;[T]he inferences to be drawn from the underlying facts <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> must be viewed in the light most favorable to the party opposing the motion.&#x201D; <ital>Matsushita Elec. Indus. Co. v. Zenith Radio Corp.</ital>, 475 U.S. 574, 587, 106 S.Ct. 1348, 89 L.Ed.2d 538 (1986).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>IV. <underscore>DISCUSSION</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. <underscore>Plaintiff's GinsGlobal Motion for Summary Adjudication</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p95" level="1">Plaintiff seeks summary adjudication of the GG Defendants' liability for: (1) breach of contract; (2) breach of fiduciary duty; (3) fraud; and (4) negligent misrepresentation. Plaintiff also seeks summary adjudication that Ginsberg and the GG Entities are alter egos.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>1. <underscore>Plaintiff's First Cause of Action for Breach of Contract</underscore></bold><footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p96">&#8195;The parties appear to agree that the terms of their February 2008 verbal agreement are disputed. (Pl.'s Mot. at 6; Defs.' Opp'n at 13.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p97" level="1">Plaintiff seeks summary adjudication only as to Defendant GG California's breach of the January 2008 MOU.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> (Pl.'s GG Mot. at 6 n.3.) Plaintiff argues that GG California breached the January 2008 MOU by its unilateral termination thereof on May 28, 2008. Plaintiff further argues that the GG Defendants were required to comply with section 273 of the Delaware General Corporation Law, but failed to do so.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p98">&#8195;Plaintiff contends that GG California is liable for breach of contract as the contractual counterparty, but that the other GG Entities are liable as alter egos of GG California. Plaintiff also notes that GG Management is a party to the joint venture agreement because it became a 50% owner of the two HIG entities. (Pl.'s Mot at 19.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p99" level="1">To state a claim for breach of contract under Delaware law, a plaintiff must allege: (1) the existence of a contract; (2) the breach of an obligation imposed by that contract; and (3) the resultant damage to the plaintiff. <ital>Kuroda v. SPJS Holdings, L.L.C.</ital>, 971 A.2d 872, 883 (Del. Ch. 2003). If the contract allows a party to terminate unilaterally, a proper repudiation ends the contract and the parties' contractual obligations. <ital>Rochdale Village, Inc. v. Public Service Emp. Union, Local No. 80, Intern. Broth. of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen and Helpers of America</ital>, 605 F.2d 1290, 1297 (2d Cir. 1979). If the contract does not provide a right to terminate unilaterally, repudiation breaches the contract. <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p100" level="1">A repudiation of a contract is an outright refusal by a party to perform a contract or its conditions. <ital>PAMI-LEMB I Inc. v. EMB-NHM, L.L.C.</ital>, 857 A.2d 998, 1014 (Del. Ch. 2004) (citing <ital>CitiSteel USA, Inc. v. Connell Ltd. P'ship</ital>, 758 A.2d 928, 931 (Del. 2000)). A party's stated intent not to perform unless terms different from the original contract are met is a repudiation. <ital>Id.</ital> A unilateral attempt to terminate a contract is also a repudiation. <ital>Delaware Financial Mgmt Corp. v. Lynch</ital>, 2003 WL 21235314 (Del. Com. Pl. Apr. 7, 2003) (citing <ital>Rochdale Village, Inc. v. Public Service Employees Union</ital>, 605 F.2d 1290, 1297 (2d Cir. 1979).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p101" level="1">In this case, the parties do not dispute that the January 2008 MOU is an agreement between Plaintiff and GG California. (Defs.' Opp'n at 1.) The January 2008 MOU does not allow either party to terminate unilaterally. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 29, GG PAE Ex. 21.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p102" level="1">The GG Defendants argue that Plaintiff's GG Motion fails because Plaintiff repudiated the January 2008 MOU by taking the position in May 2008 that unless GG California accepted his proposed modifications, Plaintiff would not continue with the venture.<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> In support of their position, the GG Defendants offer Ginsberg's testimony that Plaintiff &#x201C;became increasingly hostile, threatening and belligerent&#x201D; and &#x201C;threatened litigation if [Ginsberg] did not accede to his demand and in substance <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> told [Ginsberg] that he would not continue in the venture unless all Hindsight business was run through HIG.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference> (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 30.) Plaintiff argues that Ginsberg's declaration is insufficient to create a genuine issue of material fact because it contradicts his deposition testimony and interrogatory responses. The Court disagrees.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p103">&#8195;According to the GG Defendants, because Plaintiff's May 2008 negotiation position &#x201C;goes to the heart of&#x201D; of the terms of the February 2008 verbal agreement, which are disputed by the parties, whether Plaintiff's position is a repudiation of the January 2008 MOU is also disputed.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p104">&#8195;Plaintiff objects to Ginsberg's testimony on the basis that it is double hearsay. The objection is denied. Plaintiff's alleged statements to Ginsberg admissions by a party-opponent. Fed. R. Evid. 801(d)(2).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p105" level="1">Ginsberg testified at his deposition that Plaintiff &#x201C;did not seem willing to operate under the initial MOU.&#x201D; (Rutenberg Decl. &#182; 4, Ex. 4; Ginsberg Depo. at 252-53.) Furthermore, in an email dated May 22, 2008 from Plaintiff to Ginsberg, Plaintiff raised doubts about the terms of the parties' January 2008 MOU. Plaintiff stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p106" first-line="2" turnover="2">Anthony, not only did we come to a very specific verbal agreement over several extended discussions in February, which so far no draft gives consideration to, but for a second time I have received a draft which requires me to give up rights I already have.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p107" first-line="2" turnover="2">* * *</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p108" first-line="2" turnover="2">However, asking me to relinquish terms I already have in place is unreasonable, and I interpret it as an attempt to make me take a step back from our partnership <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> I still remain totally open to finding an adequate solution, but I expect any new solution to use what I already have in place with you as the <underscore>starting point</underscore>. From there we can find ways to respect the verbal agreements we came to in Feb, while totally addressing your newly expressed concerns. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill></paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p109" contd-flag="y">(DAE Ex. 122) (emphasis in original).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p110" level="1">While the GG Defendants' evidence is not dispositive of Plaintiff's outright refusal to perform his obligations under the January 2008 MOU, upon viewing the evidence in the light most favorable to the non-moving party, the Court finds that a genuine issue of material fact exists as to whether Plaintiff repudiated the January 2008 MOU during the course of the May 2008 negotiations.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p111" level="1">Plaintiff's contention that GG California was required to comply with the requirements of section 273 of the Delaware General Corporation Law in order to dissolve a joint venture is also unavailing.<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference> Section 273 applies to the dissolution of a joint venture of a Delaware corporation and none of the GG Entities are incorporated in Delaware. Although the January 2008 MOU provides that the January 2008 MOU would be &#x201C;construed, governed, and interpreted in accordance with the laws of Delaware,&#x201D; the parties do not dispute that pursuant to the terms of the January 2008 MOU, Plaintiff caused two HIG entities to be incorporated&#8212;one in the British Virgin Islands and one in Switzerland. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 30; Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 20.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p112">&#8195;Section 273 provides:</paratext>
<paratext ID="p113" contd-flag="y" first-line="3" turnover="3">If the stockholders of a corporation of this State, having only 2 stockholders each of which own 50% of the stock therein, shall be engaged in the prosecution of a joint venture and if such stockholders shall be unable to agree upon the desirability of discontinuing such joint venture and disposing of the assets used in such venture, either stockholder may, unless otherwise provided in the certificate of incorporation of the corporation or in a written agreement between the stockholders, file with the Court of Chancery a petition stating that it desires to discontinue such joint venture and to dispose of the assets used in such venture in accordance with a plan to be agreed upon by both stockholders or that, if no such plan shall be agreed upon by both stockholders, the corporation be dissolved.</paratext>
<paratext ID="p114" contd-flag="y" first-line="1" turnover="1">8 Del. C. &#167; 273.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p115" level="1">The Court therefore finds that a genuine issue of material fact exists as to whether Plaintiff or GG California repudiated the January 2008 MOU and denies Plaintiff's GG Motion as to his first cause of action.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>2. <underscore>Plaintiff's Second Cause of Action for Breach of Fiduciary Duty</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p116" level="1">Plaintiff contends that the MOU confirmed an express joint venture agreement under which the GG Defendants owed Plaintiff a fiduciary duty. According to Plaintiff, the GG Defendants' termination of the MOU in order to enter into more favorable deals with Defendant McCloy and others constitutes a breach of that duty.<footnote.reference ID="fr8" refid="f8" style="percent_n">8</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f8"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN8.</label.designator><paratext ID="p117">&#8195;While Plaintiff claims that the GG Defendants misrepresented the volume of Hindsight business as a basis for his fraud and negligent misrepresentation claims, for some inexplicable reason Plaintiff does not appear to rely upon those facts for his breach of fiduciary duty claim in the GG Motion. (Pl.'s Mot. at 19-20.) The Court's denial of Plaintiff's GG Motion as to the breach of fiduciary duty claim is without prejudice to a claim that the same facts underlying the post-January 2008 MOU misrepresentation claims also may give rise to potential liability for breach of fiduciary duty.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p118" level="1">A claim for breach of fiduciary duty requires proof of two elements: (1) that a fiduciary duty existed; and (2) that the defendant breached that duty. <ital>Beard Research, Inc. v. Kates</ital>, 8 A.3d 573, 601 (Del. Ch. 2010). The relationship of joint venturers is fiduciary in character and imposes on its participants &#x201C;the utmost good faith, fairness and honesty in dealing with each other with respect to the enterprise.&#x201D; <ital>J. Leo Johnson, Inc. v. Carmer</ital>, 156 A.2d 499, 502 (Del. 1959); <ital>see also Universal Studios Inc. v. Viacom Inc.</ital>, 705 A.2d 579, 593 (Del. Ch. 1997). Insofar as the Court finds disputed issues of fact as to whether GG California breached the January 2008 MOU or Plaintiff repudiated the MOU, the Court also finds triable issues as to Plaintiff's breach of fiduciary duty claim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p119" level="1">The Court notes that neither side addresses whether Plaintiff's breach of fiduciary duty claim survives to the extent it overlaps with the same facts underlying his breach of contract claim and the duty he seeks to enforce arises from the parties' contractual, as opposed to fiduciary, relationship. Under Delaware law, courts dismiss claims for breach of fiduciary duty where contractual and fiduciary claims arise from the same alleged facts and underlying conduct. <ital>See, e.g., Blue Chip Capital Fund II Ltd. Partnership v. Tubergen</ital>, 906 A.2d 827, 833 (Del. Ch. 2006) (dismissing fiduciary claim that the board breached its duty of loyalty where the claim was &#x201C;substantially the same&#x201D; as the implied contract claim and would be &#x201C;superfluous&#x201D;). As the parties have not briefed this issue, the Court declines to address it <ital>sua sponte.</ital></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>3. <underscore>Plaintiff's Third Cause of Action for Fraud and Fourth Cause of Action for Negligent Misrepresentation</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p120" level="1">In his third and fourth causes of action, Plaintiff contends (1) that the GG Defendants fraudulently induced Plaintiff to enter into the joint venture and (2) that Defendant Ginsberg continued to make false statements to Plaintiff during the course of the joint venture regarding the GG Defendants' intent to conduct business through HIG and their financial success selling Hindsight products in order to further induce Plaintiff to continue making introductions to potential clients and distributors.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>a. <underscore>Legal Standards for Fraud and Negligent Misrepresentation under Delaware Law</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p121" level="1">In order to establish a claim for fraud, Plaintiff must establish: (1) a false representation, usually one of fact; (2) the defendant's knowledge or belief that the representation was false, or was made with reckless indifference to the truth; (3) an intent to induce the plaintiff to act or to refrain from acting; (4) the plaintiff's action or inaction taken in justifiable reliance upon the representation; and (5) damage to the plaintiff as a result of such reliance. <ital>Hauspie v. Stonington Partners, Inc.</ital>, 945 A.2d 584, 586 (Del. 2008). The false statement must have been material. <ital>NAACO Industries, Inc. v. Applica Inc.</ital>, 997 A.2d 1, 29 (Del. Ch. 2009). The representation must also concern &#x201C;an essential part of the transaction.&#x201D; <ital>Princeton Ins. Co. v. Vergano</ital>, 883 A.2d 44, 54 (Del. Ch. 2055) (internal quotations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p122" level="1">Fraud may also occur through deliberate concealment of material facts, or by silence in the face of a duty to speak. <ital>Stephenson v. Capano Dev., Inc.</ital>, 462 A.2d 1069, 1074 (Del. 1983). In such cases, a defendant may be liable for a misrepresentation even if he did not know of the falsity of his statements. <ital>Kronenberg v. Katz</ital>, 872 A.2d 568, 585 (Del. Ch. 2004).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p123" level="1">A negligent misrepresentation claim is in essence a fraud claim with a reduced state of mind requirement. <ital>Snowstorm Acquisition Corp. v. Tecumseh Products Co.</ital>, 739 F. Supp. 2d 686, 709 (D. Del. 2010). In order to establish a claim for negligent misrepresentation, a plaintiff must prove: (1) a pecuniary duty to provide accurate information; (2) the supplying of false information; (3) failure to exercise reasonable care in obtaining or communicating information; and (4) a pecuniary loss caused by justifiable reliance upon the false information. <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>b. <underscore>Whether the GG Defendants Made False Representations About Their Financial Success</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p124" level="1">Plaintiff contends that Defendant Ginsberg made the following false representations: (1) Transamerica was doing business with the GG Defendants (in an email dated October 31, 2007); (2) the GG Defendants earned a yearly licensing fee from AIG; (3) that the GG Defendants earned 1% of all collected premiums from American General Life (in an email dated November 14, 2007); (4) the GG Defendants were compensated on the amount of life cover, which was approaching $5 billion (in an email dated February 22, 2008); and (5) Transamerica had sold over C$600 million of a Hindsight insurance product designed by the GG Defendants (in an email dated April 5, 2008).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p125" level="1">The GG Defendants argue that Plaintiff's third and fourth causes of action fail because Plaintiff does not establish the alleged misrepresentations: (1) were false; (2) were intended to induce Plaintiff's reliance; and (3) were material. According to the GG Defendants, none of the alleged misrepresentations played any part in Plaintiff's decision to enter into the joint venture because Plaintiff made the decision in late summer or early fall of 2007 and the parties were drafting their agreement by October 31, 2007. The GG Defendants further posit that because Plaintiff never asked for financial information concerning the level of sales of Hindsight product, Plaintiff cannot now demonstrate either that Plaintiff relied on Ginsberg's alleged misrepresentations in making his decision or that Ginsberg intended for Plaintiff to rely on them.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>(i) <underscore>Pre-January 2008 MOU Representation</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p126" level="1">Among the alleged misrepresentations identified by Plaintiff, three occurred prior to January 9, 2008, the date on which the parties entered into the January 2008 MOU.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p127" level="1">Plaintiff first contends that Ginsberg falsely represented that the GG Defendants were doing business with Transamerica. Plaintiff points to an email dated October 31, 2007, which Ginsberg sent to Plaintiff, and which attached &#x201C;promotional materials&#x201D; including the Transamerica Life Insurance brochure and excerpts from the AIG 2006 Annual Report. (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 18; GG PAE Ex. 49.) Plaintiff asserts that Ginsberg directed his attention to the references to GinsGlobal in the Transamerica report and to the Elite Global product in the AIG Annual Report. (<ital>Id.</ital>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p128" level="1">The GG Defendants deny that Ginsberg ever made such representations to Plaintiff. Ginsberg asserts that &#x201C;all [he] told Carimati was that the GinsGlobal Parties had designed a product that was being marketed by Transamerica beginning in 2004 and that it was no longer being marketed by Transamerica.&#x201D; (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 45(c).) In fact, the brochure that both Plaintiff and the GG Defendants reference provides:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p129" first-line="2" turnover="2">In 2006, more than 70 percent of sales through independent distributors came from products introduced or revised within the past two years, such as the recently launched AIG Elite Global IUL, a ground-breaking universal life product that credits interest based in part on the performance of three global large-cap indices.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p130" contd-flag="y">(Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 18; GG PAE Ex. 49.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p131" level="1">On the evidence presented, the Court finds that the GG Defendants raise a triable issue whether Ginsberg falsely represented that the GG Defendants were going business with Transamerica. While the brochure to which the parties cite mentions the Hindsight product, a mere reference to the GG Defendants' product is inconclusive of Ginsberg's purported representation about the GG Entities' business dealings with Transamerica. The Court therefore denies Plaintiff's motion on this ground.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p132" level="1">Plaintiff next argues that Ginsberg falsely represented that the GG Defendants earned a yearly licensing fee from AIG. In support of his position, Plaintiff cites Ginsberg's testimony that he reviewed the Business Plan to ensure that it was accurate (Rutenberg Decl. &#182; 3, PAE Ex. 3; Ginsberg Depo. at 16-18) and emphasizes the following statement in the Business Plan: &#x201C;In addition, we have historically been able to add a <ital>yearly</ital> licensing fee (charged to the insurer, not the retail client) of about 75bps for the life of the product.&#x201D; (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 21; PAE Ex. 17 at 220; emphasis in original.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p133" level="1">Ginsberg denies ever representing to Plaintiff that the GG Entities earned a yearly licensing fee from AIG. Ginsberg states that he told Plaintiff &#x201C;that in the context of the business plan he was preparing for Carthesio, it would be a fair assumption that if we were able to sell a European variable life insurance product, a license fee would be a legitimate form of compensation in connection with that type of product.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr9" refid="f9" style="percent_n">9</footnote.reference> (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 45(b).) Indeed, the statement to which Plaintiff refers states that the GG Defendants have &#x201C;historically&#x201D; earned yearly licensing fees and makes no representation about whether such a fee was then currently earned by the GG Defendants.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f9"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN9.</label.designator><paratext ID="p134">&#8195;Plaintiff objects to Ginsberg's testimony on the basis that it is hearsay. The objection is denied. Ginsberg's statement is not being offered for the truth of the matter asserted therein. Fed. R. Evid. 801(c).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p135" level="1">Drawing all reasonable inferences from the evidence in favor of Defendants, the Court finds that whether Ginsberg made a false representation concerning a yearly licensing fee is also a disputed fact for a jury to resolve and denies Plaintiff's motion accordingly.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p136" level="1">Finally, Plaintiff contends Ginsberg falsely represented the amount of commissions the GG Defendants received from American General Life. In an email dated November 14, 2007 from Ginsberg to Plaintiff, Ginsberg told Plaintiff that &#x201C;AIG pay [sic] GinsGlobal 1% of all collected premium on this policy.&#x201D; (Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 11; GG PAE Ex. 28.) Although Ginsberg now claims that the email was sent not for the purpose of helping Plaintiff evaluate whether to do business with Ginsberg, but in order to assist Plaintiff in preparing the Business Plan (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 45(a)), Ginsberg testified at his deposition that his statement did not &#x201C;give a full picture&#x201D; and that he knew that GinsGlobal was not getting paid 1% of $5 billion, but on target or &#x201C;commissionable first year premiums.&#x201D; (Rutenberg Decl. &#182; 3l; GG PAE Ex. 3; Ginsberg Depo. at. 26-27, 47-48, 52.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p137" level="1">Even if Ginsberg was not certain of the amount of commissions the GG Defendants were to receive in their contract with AIG, he certainly knew that they were not getting paid 1% of $5 billion. Furthermore, Ginsberg's rationalization for why he provided Plaintiff with misleading information also fails to controvert the undisputed facts that Plaintiff conducted due diligence related to the Hindsight Product in the summer and fall of 2007, that Plaintiff and Ginsberg began preparing the Business Plan in early November 2007, and that the parties entered into the January 2008 MOU on January 9, 2008. The Court also finds that there is no triable issue of fact as to whether Ginsberg's misrepresentation was material to Plaintiff's decision to enter into the joint venture or that Plaintiff justifiably relied upon that misrepresentation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p138" level="1">Ginsberg's representation related to an essential part of the parties' joint venture transaction, <ital>i.e.</ital>, the amount of commissions the GG Entities were receiving from sales of Hindsight products, and the GG Defendants do not dispute that Ginsberg's representation as to the amount of commissions being earned by the GG Entities was made in the course of a business or transaction in which Ginsberg had a pecuniary interest and from which Ginsberg arguably expected to profit.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p139" level="1">The Court therefore finds that the GG Defendants fail to raise a triable issue as to whether GG California and Ginsberg are liable for fraud in the inducement and for negligent misrepresentation based on Ginsberg's November 14, 2007 email to Plaintiff. In light of the Court's ruling, <ital>infra</ital>, that disputed issues of fact exist as to whether the other GG Entities are alter egos, the Court finds that there is a triable issue of fact as to which, if any, of the other GG Defendants are also liable on the third and fourth causes of action.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>(ii) <underscore>Post-January 2008 MOU Representations</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p140" level="1">The other alleged misrepresentations regarding the GG Defendants' financial success identified by Plaintiff occurred after the parties entered into their January 9, 2008 MOU, <ital>i.e.</ital>, in emails dated February 22, 2008 and April 5, 2008. Plaintiff asserts that he relied on Ginsberg's misrepresentations in his &#x201C;decisions regarding how to effectively market and sell Hindsight products&#x201D; and they further induced him to &#x201C;continue performing under the MOU, including by making large cash disbursement to capitalize the joint venture and pay its expenses.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Reply at 12-13.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p141" level="1">In their opposition, the GG Defendants argue that &#x201C;[t]he statements made after the MOU was entered into under no circumstance can be actionable representations and are not addressed herein.&#x201D; (Defs.' Opp'n at 16 n.4.) Insofar as they were joint venturers, the parties do not dispute that their relationship was that of fiduciaries and they owed each other a duty of utmost good faith, fairness and honesty. As discussed <ital>supra</ital>, Ginsberg testified at his deposition that the GG Entities were not getting paid 1% of $5 billion by AIG. Ginsberg also testified that his representations regarding Transamerica in April 2008 were &#x201C;clearly [] an exaggeration,&#x201D; and that in fact the Transamerica product &#x201C;generated no sales.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Facts &#182; 57; Defs' Disputes &#182; 57; Carimati GG Decl. &#182; 19.) The GG Defendants fail to controvert Plaintiff's evidence that Ginsberg made false statements that induced Plaintiff's continued performance under the January 2008 MOU, which gave rise to pecuniary damage.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p142" level="1">The Court therefore also finds that the GG Defendants fail to raise a triable issue whether GG California and Ginsberg are liable for fraud and negligent misrepresentation on the basis of Ginsberg's statements in the February 22, 2008 and April 5, 2008 emails to Plaintiff. The Court finds, however, that there is a triable issue of fact as to which, if any, of the other GG Defendants are liable on these claims.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>c. <underscore>Whether the GG Defendants Made a False Promise to Pass all Hindsight Business Through HIG</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p143" level="1">Plaintiff contends that Ginsberg made a false promise to pass all Hindsight business through HIG.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p144" level="1">Plaintiff's position is puzzling in light of Plaintiff's own acknowledgment that disputed issues of fact exist as to the parties' February 2008 agreement. Plaintiff states:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p145" first-line="2" turnover="2">Recognizing the District Court's finding that triable issues of fact likely exist regarding the terms of the amendment to the MOU as set forth in the February 2008 emails between Carimati and Ginsberg, Carimati only seeks summary adjudication of Defendants' breach of the January 2008 MOU by this motion, and will prove Defendants' breach of the terms of the February 2008 emails at trial.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p146" contd-flag="y">(Pl.'s GG Mot. at 6 n.3.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p147" level="1">Given Plaintiff's own admission that genuine issues of material fact exist as to the parties' February 2008 agreement, the Court denies Plaintiff's GG Motion as to whether the GG Defendants are liable for fraud and negligent misrepresentation for their alleged promise to pass all Hindsight business through HIG.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>4. <underscore>Whether Ginsberg and the GG Entities are Alter Egos</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p148" level="1">Plaintiff contends that Ginsberg and the GG Entities are alter egos. A court may disregard the corporate form in the interest of justice when such matters as fraud, contravention of law or contract, public wrong, or where equitable considerations among members of the corporation are involved. <ital>Maloney-Refaie v. Bridge at School, Inc.</ital>, 958 A.2d 871, 881 (Del. Ch. 2008).</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p149" first-line="2" turnover="2">[A]n alter ego analysis must start with an examination of factors which reveal how the corporation operates and the particular defendant's relationship to that operation. These factors include whether the corporation was adequately capitalized for the corporate undertaking; whether the corporation was solvent; whether dividends were paid, corporate records kept, officers and directors functions properly, and other corporate formalities were observed; whether the dominant shareholder siphoned corporate funds; and whether, in general, the corporation simply functioned as a facade for the dominant shareholder.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p150" contd-flag="y"><ital>Id.</ital> (citing <ital>Harco Nat'l Ins. Co. v. Green Farms, Inc.</ital>, 1989 WL 110537 at * 4 (Del. Ch. Sept. 19, 1989)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p151" level="1">In order to pierce the corporate veil based on an agency or &#x201C;alter ego&#x201D; theory, &#x201C;the corporation must be a sham and exist for no other purpose than as a vehicle for fraud.&#x201D; <ital>In re Sunstates Corp. Shareholder Litigation</ital>, 788 A.2d 530, 534 (Del. Ch. 2001) (citing <ital>Wallace ex rel. Cencom Cable Income Partners II, Inc. v. Wood</ital>, 752 A.2d 1175, 1184 (Del. 1999)) (internal quotations omitted). &#x201C;Persuading a Delaware court to disregard the corporate entity is a difficult task.&#x201D; <ital>Wallace</ital>, 752 A.2d at 1183-84 (internal quotations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p152" level="1">Plaintiff argues that GG California is a sham because it is merely a front for the other GG Entities. In fact, the GG Defendants do not dispute that GG California has no assets and earns no revenue and exists only to pay Ginsberg's salary with money it receives from GG Mauritius. (Pl.'s GG Facts &#182; 13; GG Defs.' Disputes &#182; 13.) Plaintiff argues that GG Management is a sham because it is the 50% owner of HIG, but there was no formal documentation reflecting that GG Management purchased the 50% HIG ownership from GG California, the original contracting party to the January 2008 MOU. Plaintiff further argues that GG Mauritius is liable because it took over the joint venture's business after Plaintiff's termination. (Pl.'s GG Facts &#182;&#182; 85-86; GG Defs.' Disputes &#182; 85-86.) Finally, Plaintiff argues that Ginsberg is the majority shareholder in GG Mauritius and GG Management, which is the 100% shareholder of GG California.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p153" level="1">The GG Defendants, on the other hand, provide evidence that GG Management, which owns GG California and GG Mauritius, was established in November 2001 with an initial capitalization of $200,000, obtained a subsequent capitalization of $275,000, keeps corporate records, and issues annual dividends. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182;&#182; 3-8; DAE, Exs. 60-65.) GG California, a wholly owned subsidiary of GG Management, was incorporated on or about December 29, 2007 and Ginsberg is the sole employee of GG California. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182;&#182; 11-13.) Ginsberg attests that all of the GG Entities have separate boards of directors, maintain their own corporate records, and issue Board and Shareholder resolutions from time to time in order to effectuate the business of the GG entities. (Ginsberg Decl. &#182; 14; DAE, Exs. 71-118.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p154" level="1">Drawing all reasonable inferences in the GG Defendants' favor, as it must on this motion for summary adjudication, the Court finds that Plaintiff fails to establish that there are no triable issues of fact as to whether the GG Entities exist &#x201C;for no other purpose than as a vehicle for fraud.&#x201D; <ital>Sunstates Corp.</ital>, 788 A.2d at 534. Furthermore, although Plaintiff alleges that Ginsberg made allegedly false representations to him, as discussed <ital>supra</ital>, Plaintiff does not contend that Ginsberg used the corporate structure of the GG Entities to defraud him or to perpetuate some other injustice. The Court therefore denies Plaintiff's GG Motion as to whether Ginsberg and the GG Entities are alter egos.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. <underscore>Plaintiff's McCloy Motion for Summary Adjudication</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p155" level="1">Plaintiff moves for partial summary judgment on Defendant McCloy's alleged liability for intentional interference with contract. McCloy argues, <ital>inter alia</ital>, that Plaintiff's claim fails as a matter of law because it is barred by the agent's immunity rule. McCloy is correct.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p156" level="1">A stranger to a contract may be liable for intentionally interfering with the performance of the contract. <ital>Pacific Gas &#38; Electric Co. v. Bear Stearns &#38; Co.</ital>, 50 Cal. 3d 1118, 1126 (1990). In order to prevail on his claim for intentional interference with contract, Plaintiff must prove: (1) a valid contract between plaintiff and a third party; (2) defendant's knowledge of this contract; (3) defendant's intentional acts designed to induce a breach or disruption of the contractual relationship; (4) actual breach or disruption of the contractual relationship; and (5) resulting damage. <ital>Quelimane Co., Inc. v. Stewart Title Guaranty Co.</ital>, 19 Cal. 4th 26, 55 (1998). Under the agent's immunity rule, however, duly acting agents and employees cannot be held liable for conspiring with their own principals. <ital>Applied Equipment Corp. v. Litton Saudi Arabia Ltd.</ital>, 7 Cal. 4th 503, 512, 28 Cal. Rptr. 2d 475 (1994). An entity with a direct interest or involvement in the relationship is not usually liable for harm caused by pursuit of its interests. <ital>ViChip Corp. v. Lee</ital>, 438 F. Supp. 2d 1087, 1097 (N.D. Cal. 2006).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p157" level="1">Plaintiff first argues that the agent's immunity privilege does not apply because (1) the January 2008 MOU is not a contract of the joint venture, but instead, the agreement entered into between Plaintiff and GG California that created the joint venture, and (2) McCloy was not an agent of either of the contracting parties, but rather, an agent of HIG, the entity created by the joint venture. Plaintiff's position is unpersuasive.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p158" level="1">Plaintiff argues that &#x201C;the suggestion that a salesperson hired by a joint venture is privileged to interfere with the contract that formed the venture itself, is absurd.&#x201D; (Pl.'s McCloy Reply at 5.) Plaintiff asserts that the court's holding in <ital>ViChip</ital> is inapposite. The Court disagrees and, instead, finds <ital>ViChip</ital> to be instructive in this case. In <ital>ViChip</ital>, the defendant brought a counterclaim for intentional interference with contract. The plaintiff/counterdefendant, which was the company created by a joint venture agreement, argued that it could not be liable for intentional interference with the contract because it was not a stranger to the contract. The court in <ital>ViChip</ital> agreed. Analogizing the plaintiff to a third party beneficiary, the court determined that the company was &#x201C;<ital>the</ital> economic interest&#x201D; established by the joint venture agreement and that its &#x201C;fundamental existence&#x201D; depends on the performance of such agreement. <ital>ViChip</ital>, 438 F. Supp. 2d at 1097-98 (emphasis in original). &#x201C;Although not named as a party to the joint venture agreement, it has a direct interest or involvement in the relationship embodied among the parties to the joint venture agreement.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 1097.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p159" level="1">Here, Plaintiff presents evidence that he was the one who approached McCloy to join their joint venture as a member of the Board of Advisors, with a financial interest in the business that McCloy generated for the enterprise. (Carimati McCloy Decl. &#182;&#182; 9-10, 17-18.) Thus, even though McCloy is not named as a party to the joint venture agreement, there is evidence to suggest that he has a direct interest and involvement in the relationship embodied among the parties to the joint venture.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p160" level="1">Plaintiff's reliance on the court's statement in <ital>Mintz v. Blue Cross of California</ital>, 172 Cal. App. 4th 1594 (2009), that the agent's immunity rule &#x201C;has no direct applicability to a claim for interference with contract rights&#x201D; and that the rule applies only to claims of conspiracy to commit a tort or violate a statute, <ital>id.</ital> at 1605, is also misplaced. In <ital>Mintz</ital>, the plaintiff, who was an insurance plan member and who had entered into a contract with CalPERS, asserted the defendant intentionally interfered with the contract. The plaintiff urged the court to find that because the defendant acted for its own financial advantage, the agent's immunity rule did not apply. On those facts, the court determined that the agent's immunity rule did not apply in his case. Emphasizing that a representative of a contracting party could not be held liable for the tort of interfering with its principal's contract, the court nevertheless held that the defendant acted as an agent in administering the contract and therefore was not a stranger to the contractual relationship.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p161" level="1">Drawing all reasonable inferences in favor of the non-moving party, the Court finds that a jury could find that McCloy was not just &#x201C;a mere salesman,&#x201D; as Plaintiff characterizes him. A genuine dispute exists as to whether McCloy was a stranger to the joint venture, or had a direct interest and involvement in the relationship. The Court therefore denies Plaintiff's McCloy Motion.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>V. <underscore>CONCLUSION</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p162" level="1">In light of the foregoing:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p163" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">1. Plaintiff's GG Motion is GRANTED as to Defendants Ginsberg and GG California's liability for fraud and negligent misrepresentation as a result of Ginsberg's misrepresentations in the November 14, 2007, February 22, 2008, and April 5, 2008 emails, but a triable issue of fact exists as to which, if any, of the other GG Defendants is liable for these claims;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p164" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">2. Plaintiff's GG Motion is DENIED in all other respects; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p165" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">3. Plaintiff's McCloy Motion is DENIED.</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p166" level="1">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p167" level="1">DATED: June 13, 2011</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>