<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
<venue.name>WESTERN DIVISION</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>NORTON, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>FEDERAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATIONS, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>No. ED CV 08-01829-VAP (VBK)</docket.line>
<docket.number>ED CV 08-01829-VAP (VBK)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">5:08-cv-01829-VAP-VBK</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 07/27/2010</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">REPORT AND RECOMMENDATION OF UNITED STATES MAGISTRATE JUDGE</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">VICTOR B. KENTON UNITED STATES MAGISTRATE JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">This Report and Recommendation is submitted to the Honorable Virginia A. Phillips, United States District Judge, pursuant to 28 U.S.C. &#167;636 and General Order 05-07 of the United States District Court for the Central District of California.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>PROCEEDINGS</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On January 13, 2009, Jennifer Norton (hereinafter referred to as &#x201C;Plaintiff&#x201D;) filed a &#x201C;Civil Rights Complaint Pursuant to an Order re Leave to File Action Without Prepayment of Filing Fee.&#x201D; Plaintiff named as Defendants the Federal Bureau of Investigation (&#x201C;FBI&#x201D;), Russ Leach, the Riverside Police Department, Thomas (Night shift Sergeant for Riverside Police Department), Arnold Schwarzenegger and Does 1-10.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">On February 10, 2009, Defendants Russ Leach and the City of Riverside (erroneously sued as Riverside Police Department) filed an Answer to the Complaint.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">On January 28, 2010, an &#x201C;Order (1) Accepting and Adopting the Report and Recommendation of United States Magistrate Judge and (2) Granting Defendant FBI's Motion to Dismiss&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> and &#x201C;Judgment&#x201D; were issued by United States District Judge Virginia A. Phillips dismissing Defendant FBI from this action.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">On June 11, 2010, Defendants City of Riverside and Russ Leach filed a document entitled &#x201C;Defendants' Notice of Motion and Motion to Dismiss for Failure to Comply with F.R.C.P. 37; Memorandum in Support Thereof; and Declarations of James E. Brown and Jeff Collopy;&#x201D; &#x201C;Declaration of Jeff Collopy in Support of Motion to Dismiss;&#x201D; &#x201C;Declaration of James E. Brown in Support of Motion to Dismiss&#x201D; and &#x201C;[Proposed] Order Granting Motion to Dismiss.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">On June 16, 2010, the Court issued a Minute Order ordering Plaintiff to file an Opposition or Statement of Non-Opposition to the Motion within 21 days.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">As of the date of this Report and Recommendation, Plaintiff has failed to respond to the Court's Minute Order. Having reviewed the Complaint and Defendants' Motion to Dismiss, the Court hereby recommends that Defendants Russ Leach and City of Riverside's Motion to Dismiss be granted and Plaintiff's Complaint be dismissed.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p8">&#8195;On March 12, 2009, Defendant FBI filed a document entitled &#x201C;Notice of Motion and Motion to Dismiss; and Memorandum of Points and Authorities; Declaration of Rose M. Mells&#x201D; (&#x201C;MTD&#x201D;) pursuant to Fed.R.Civ.P. 12(b)(1) and 12(b)(6) for lack of subject matter jurisdiction because Plaintiff's constitutional tort claims brought pursuant to 42 U.S.C. &#167;1983 are barred because the FBI is a federal agency and does not act under &#x201C;color of state law,&#x201D; Plaintiff has failed to exhaust administrative remedies under the Federal Tort Claims Act, the Complaint is &#x201C;patently insubstantial,&#x201D; and fails to state a claim.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>BACKGROUND</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Plaintiff has characterized this action as a &#x201C;writ of replevin&#x201D; wherein she alleges that Defendant FBI in conjunction with Defendant the Riverside Police Department illegally seized property &#x201C;belonging exclusively&#x201D; to her which contained &#x201C;case sensitive federal documents&#x201D; constituting &#x201C;evidence of crimes&#x201D; committed by the Defendants. (<underscore>See</underscore> Complaint, I-Introduction.) Plaintiff asserts that Defendants have violated her rights under the Fourth Amendment of the United States Constitution, engaged in a conspiracy to violate her constitutional rights and have inflicted &#x201C;emotional stress&#x201D; upon her. (<underscore>See</underscore> Complaint, V-Plaintiff's Causes of Action.) Plaintiff requests that the Court order Defendants to return her &#x201C;federal documents and personal property and provide a reason for their removal while in her fiance's possession&#x201D; under &#x201C;Rule 41(g) and 18 U.S.C. &#167;3107.&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> Complaint, V-Plaintiff's Causes of Action; VI-Prayer for Relief.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>DEFENDANTS' MOTION RE PLAINTIFF'S NON-APPEARANCE AT DEPOSITION</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Defendants Russ Leach and the City of Riverside initially noticed Plaintiff's deposition for Tuesday, May 18, 2010 at 9:00 a.m. in the offices of co-Defendants' counsel, the United States Attorney located at 300 North Los Angeles Street, Los Angeles, California 90012. The Notice of Deposition was served, by mail, on Plaintiff at her address of record with the Court, 1191 Magnolia, Suite D-242, Corona, California 928279-3215. (<underscore>See</underscore> Exhibit [&#x201C;Ex.&#x201D;] 1 attached to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss &#8211; &#x201C;Notice of Taking Deposition of Plaintiff.&#x201D;) Defendants' counsel asked his investigator to attempt to locate Plaintiff personally to serve the Notice of Deposition. The investigator was unable to locate Plaintiff. The investigator learned that the address on file with the Court was actually a Post Office box rather than a residence or office. (Declaration of Jeff Collopy, &#182;&#182; 2, 3.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Plaintiff failed to appear for the scheduled deposition on May 18, 2010. An Affidavit of Non-Appearance was taken. (<underscore>See</underscore> Ex. 2 attached to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss.) On that date, James Brown, counsel for Defendants, attempted to call Plaintiff at her phone number provided to the Court, 951-201-1479. (Declaration of James Brown, &#182; 6.) When the call was attempted, Defendants' counsel learned that the phone number was disconnected or no longer in service. <underscore>Id</underscore>. Defendants' counsel waited approximately 50 minutes prior to releasing the court reporter. <underscore>Id</underscore>. at &#182; 5. The Notice of Deposition was not returned to Defendants' counsel by the Postal Service as undeliverable for any reason. (<underscore>Id</underscore>. at &#182; 7.) Moreover, the Notice of Deposition was sent to the address of record filed with the Court. <underscore>Id</underscore>. at &#182; 4.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Defendants' counsel sent Plaintiff a letter confirming her non-appearance at her noticed deposition on May 18, 2010 and advising her that her deposition would be rescheduled for May 28, 2010. Plaintiff was further informed that if she failed to attend the deposition Defendants would seek sanctions including dismissal of the action. (<underscore>See</underscore> Ex. 4 to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss.) Plaintiff's deposition was noticed for Friday, May 28, 2010 at 9:00 a.m. at the office of the City Attorney, City Hall, 3900 Main Street, Riverside, California 92522. (<underscore>See</underscore> Ex. 3 to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss.) The Notice of Deposition and letter were again served by mail on Plaintiff. On May 28, 2010, after waiting for approximately 50 minutes, Plaintiff again failed to appear for her duly noticed deposition. Plaintiff did not contact counsel and provide any explanation for her failure to appear. (Declaration of James Brown, &#182;&#182; 9-11.) An affidavit of non-appearance of witness was prepared. (<underscore>See</underscore> Ex. 5 to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>STATEMENT OF ALLEGATIONS</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">The Complaint contains a series of bizarre and vague allegations that are related to another lawsuit filed by Plaintiff against Defendant FBI, which has since been dismissed. In that earlier lawsuit, as Plaintiff acknowledges, she had alleged constitutional rights violations &#x201C;that include prejudice and basically socialist laws that have pitted the entire town and its people into acts of profiling and discrimination based on the socio-economic backgrounds of people.&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> Complaint, III-Statement of Facts.) Specifically, Plaintiff claimed that Defendant FBI had been conducting an ongoing investigation into her &#x201C;activities&#x201D; and was &#x201C;illegally eavesdropping and wiretapping her home, phones, television, computer and tracking her vehicle with GPS.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">In the within lawsuit, Plaintiff alleges that she became engaged to Lieutenant Kevin Feimer, a police officer with the Riverside Police Department, and that they began to build a &#x201C;legal case&#x201D; against Defendants the Riverside Police Department and the FBI, both of whom have been &#x201C;actively engaging in embracery, witness tampering, collusion, extortion, falsifying evidence and crimes against humanity.&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> Complaint, III-Statement of Facts.) Plaintiff alleges that when &#x201C;Defendants&#x201D; discovered she and Feimer were in a romantic relationship and that they were working together to &#x201C;expose&#x201D; the two law enforcement entities for &#x201C;their conspiratorial acts of fraud and for their abuses upon innocent people,&#x201D; Defendants dismissed Feimer from the Riverside Police Department and &#x201C;stole the files&#x201D; that belonged to Feimer and herself in a &#x201C;premeditated act of conspiracy to collect the federal evidence that the two intended to use in their federal lawsuits against [the entities].&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that on September 29, she dropped off over 20,000 pages of &#x201C;federal documents&#x201D; at the Riverside Police Station that stem from numerous government lawsuits that she and Feimer had &#x201C;pending in the United States Supreme Court.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>.) Plaintiff had &#x201C;prearranged the pickup&#x201D; with Feimer and had specifically &#x201C;communicated to [him] that the federal files of personal documents <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> remain in his possession at all times.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>.) Plaintiff alleges that &#x201C;[j]ust days after parting with her files, [she] was informed that those files were illegally seized from [Feimer] by both the Riverside Police Department and [the FBI].&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>.) Plaintiff states that on October 10, 2008, she &#x201C;made contact&#x201D; with the Riverside Police Department seeking the return of the property and requesting a copy of the search warrant that provided the &#x201C;reasonable cause for the seizure of her property.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>.) Plaintiff claims that such requests were met &#x201C;with evasion and denials.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Plaintiff states that she filed a &#x201C;theft report&#x201D; with the Riverside Police Department. (<underscore>Id</underscore>.) Plaintiff attached a document purported to be the &#x201C;incident report&#x201D; to the Complaint; which contains a &#x201C;Statement Form&#x201D; from which Plaintiff recounts that she dropped off documents and discs which were anticipated to be used against Defendants in the cases &#x201C;Norton v. FBI,&#x201D; &#x201C;Norton v. CIA,&#x201D; &#x201C;Norton v. ATF,&#x201D; and &#x201C;Norton v. Mukasey, et al.&#x201D; (Exhibit to Complaint, Statement Form.) Plaintiff further states that the documents were left in front of the Riverside Police Station located at 10540 Magnolia Avenue in Riverside, California and that she had &#x201C;left those documents on the front sidewalk to be picked up by <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> Feimer who was a Lieutenant on the midnight shift.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>.) Plaintiff claims that &#x201C;[w]hen [Feimer] arrived to pick up the files, they were missing and therefore stolen, <underscore>likely by the Defendants who I am suing.</underscore>&#x201D; (<underscore>Id</underscore>. [Plaintiff's emphasis added].)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>DISCUSSION</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">For all of the following reasons, the Complaint should be dismissed.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. <underscore>Plaintiff's Willful Failure to Cooperate in Discovery Warrants Dismissal of the Case</underscore></bold>.</headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">Plaintiff's intentional failure to cooperate in discovery and her failure to appear for deposition on repeated occasions justify the dismissal of this action. Rule 37 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure authorizes the District Court to impose sanctions upon a party or its counsel for failure to comply with rules of discovery. <underscore>National Hockey League v. Metropolitan Hockey Club</underscore>, 427 U.S. 639, 96 S.Ct. 2778 (1976). Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 37(d)(1)(A) provides in pertinent part:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p19" first-line="2" turnover="1">&#x201C;The Court where the action is pending may, on motion, order sanctions if: (i) a party <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> fails, after being served with proper notice, to appear for that person's deposition; the sanctions available to the Court pursuant to F.R.C.P. 37(d)(1)(3) include &#x2018;dismissing the action or proceeding in whole or in part.&#x2019; <underscore>See</underscore> F.R.C.P. Rule 37(b)(2)(A)(v).&#x201D;</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">&#x201C;Dismissal is a proper sanction under Rule 37(d) for a serious or total failure to respond to discovery even without a prior order.&#x201D; <underscore>Sigliano v. Mendoza</underscore>, 642 F.2d 309, 310 (9<super style="percent_r">th</super> Cir. 1981). Dismissal is proper under Rule 37(b) where a party has disobeyed a discovery order. <underscore>See Wanderer v. Johnston</underscore>, 910 F.2d 652, 656 (9<super style="percent_r">th</super> Cir. 1990).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Here, Defendants properly noticed and served two separate Notices of Deposition on Plaintiff. Accompanying the second Notice of Deposition was a letter from Defendants' counsel specifically informing Plaintiff that Defendant would seek sanctions including dismissal of the action if Plaintiff failed to appear for the deposition. Nonetheless, Plaintiff failed to appear at her duly noticed deposition. Plaintiff provided no explanation for her failure to appear at the noticed depositions. Plaintiff failed to contact counsel regarding her depositions. As such, dismissal is an appropriate sanction.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">In determining whether to dismiss this case as a punitive measure, the Court must weigh five factors: &#x201C;(1) the public's interest in expeditious resolution of litigation; (2) the Court's need to manage its docket; (3) the risk of prejudice to the defendant; (4) the public policy favoring disposition of cases on their merits; and (5) the availability of less drastic sanctions.&#x201D; <underscore>Henderson v. Duncan</underscore>, 779 F.2d 1421, 1423 (9<super style="percent_r">th</super> Cir. 1986)(citing <underscore>Ash v. Cvetkov</underscore>, 739 F.2d 493, 496 (9<super style="percent_r">th</super> Cir. 1984); <underscore>Link v. Wabash R.R.</underscore>, 370 U.S. 626, 633, 82 S.Ct. 1386 (1962); <underscore>see also Wanderer</underscore>, 910 F.2d at 656.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Here, the factors weigh heavily in favor of dismissal. The case has been pending for over a year and a half, yet Plaintiff has twice been uncooperative in Defendants' attempt to take her deposition. Plaintiff's failure to appear at her deposition has impeded the Court's ability to insure the steady progress of this litigation. Further, Plaintiff's delays have also risked prejudice to the Defendants as their efforts to properly prepare for trial have been hindered. Because they have not been able to depose Plaintiff, Defendants risk proceeding to trial without an adequate means of discovering the merits of her claims, or to effectively cross-examine or impeach Plaintiff should she choose to testify. In <underscore>Wanderer</underscore>, the Ninth Circuit found the existence of prejudice &#x201C;palpable&#x201D; where a party repeatedly failed to appear at depositions. 910 F.2d at 656. As in <underscore>Wanderer</underscore>, Plaintiff's failure to appear constitutes a &#x201C;clear interference&#x201D; with Defendants' ability to defend the case.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">While there a public policy favoring disposition of cases on the merits, it is the inaction of Plaintiff herself that has resulted in the inability of the parties to complete discovery and proceed to trial. In addition to Plaintiff's failure to cooperate in the completion of her deposition, the Court also notes Plaintiff's failure to respond to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss and apparent indifference to whether the case is resolved on the merits.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">While the Court is free to levy monetary sanctions in lieu of the sanction of dismissal, the Plaintiff is proceeding <underscore>In Forma Pauperis</underscore>, and is unlikely to have the means to pay a modest sanction.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">This Court finds that Plaintiff's failure to appear at her depositions and apparent disinterest in failing to respond to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss are indicative of her lack of interest in the entire case.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Plaintiff has been warned that failure to comply with this Court's Order may result in the sanction of dismissal, she will be given further notice by service of this Report and Recommendation and she will have the opportunity to file Objections to it.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>RECOMMENDATION</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">For all of the foregoing reasons, <bold>IT IS HEREBY RECOMMENDED</bold> that the District Court issue an Order: (1) approving and adopting this Report and Recommendation; (2) granting Defendants Russ Leach and the City of Riverside's Motion to Dismiss; and (3) directing that Judgment be entered dismissing Plaintiff's Complaint and the entire action.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">DATED: <underscore>July 27, 2010</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>NOTICE</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">Reports and Recommendations are not appealable to the Court of Appeals, but are subject to the right of any party to timely file Objections as provided in the Local Rules Governing the Duties of the Magistrate Judges, and review by the District Judge whose initials appear in the docket number. No Notice of Appeal pursuant to the Federal Rules of Appellate Procedure should be filed until entry of the Judgment of the District Court.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>