<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>JAMES F. DODARO, as an individual and on behalf of all other similarly situated, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>STANDARD PACIFIC CORP., et al., Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line><ital><bold>Case Nos. EDCV 09-01666-VAP</bold></ital></docket.line>
<docket.line>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01668-VAP</docket.line>
<docket.line>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01669-VAP</docket.line>
<docket.line>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01670-VAP</docket.line>
<docket.line>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01671-VAP</docket.line>
<docket.line>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01672-VAP</docket.line>
<docket.line>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01673-VAP</docket.line>
<docket.line>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01674-VAP</docket.line>
<docket.line>(DTBx)</docket.line>
<docket.number><ital><bold>EDCV 09-01666-VAP</bold></ital></docket.number>
<docket.number>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01668-VAP</docket.number>
<docket.number>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01669-VAP</docket.number>
<docket.number>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01670-VAP</docket.number>
<docket.number>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01671-VAP</docket.number>
<docket.number>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01672-VAP</docket.number>
<docket.number>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01673-VAP</docket.number>
<docket.number>(DTBx); EDCV 09-01674-VAP</docket.number>
<docket.number>(DTBx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">5:09-cv-01666-VAP-DTB</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 03/26/2012</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER GRANTING DEFENDANTS' MOTION TO DISMISS [Motion filed on December 22, 2011]</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">VIRGINIA A. PHILLIPS United States District Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Plaintiffs in these eight cases allege Defendants gulled them, and many others, into buying houses in neighborhoods populated by subprime mortgagors and investors.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> With the collapse of the housing market, Plaintiffs allege such neighborhoods became seas of empty houses, the owners of which were either forced out by foreclosures, or decided rationally to abandon their investments rather than pay off debts greater than their properties' values. As Plaintiffs' neighborhoods were blighted with abandoned houses, the value of their own houses declined. While admitting this phenomenon is widespread in the current housing market, Plaintiffs allege it had an especially pernicious effect in their neighborhoods, where Defendants sold houses zealously to buyers who could not afford them. Saddled with their own devalued houses, Plaintiffs brought this putative nationwide class action against Defendants.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p2">&#8195;Plaintiffs are James Dodaro (No. 09-1666); Stella Stephens and Timothy Young (No. 09-1668); Edilberto Lumalu, Brian Dietz, Brenda Dietz, and Candice McDonald (No. 09-1669); Gaspare Oneto, Paul Nakabayashi, Sandra Nakabayashi, John Butler, and Linda Butler (No. 09-1670); Sylvester Maya and Ofer Masachi (No. 09-1671); Remedios Martinez (No. 09-1672); Matthew Nielsen and Nicole Nielsen (No. 09-1673); and Solomon Kelly and James Molina (No. 09-1674).</paratext>
<paratext ID="p3" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">Defendants are Standard Pacific Corp. (No. 09-1666); Lennar Corp. and Lennar Homes of California, Inc. (No. 09-1668); Richmond American Homes Corp., M.D.C. Holdings, Inc., and Richmond American Homes of Maryland, Inc. (No. 09-1669); The Ryland Group, Inc. and Ryland Homes of California, Inc. (No. 09-1670); Centex Corp., Centex Homes Corp., and Centex Homes, G.P. (No. 09-1671); D.R. Horton, Inc. (No. 09-1672); Shea Homes, Inc. and J.F. Shea Co., Inc. (No. 09-1673); and Beazer Homes USA, Inc. and Beazer Homes Holding Corp. (No. 09-1674).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Defendants, for their part, insist they did nothing improper as a matter of law, that they owed no duty to disclose to Plaintiffs the financial wherewithal of their neighbors, and in any event, the statute of limitations has run on Plaintiffs' claims (each of these arguments calling for dismissal for failure to state a claim, per Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6)). As an initial matter, Defendants also argue Plaintiffs cannot demonstrate that Defendants' practices led to the devaluation of their houses, and consequently lack standing to sue (calling for dismissal pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(1)). Defendants therefore filed Motions to Dismiss, which the Court GRANTS, without leave to amend, for the reasons discussed below.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Factual Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">In the early years of this century, low interest rates stimulated demand for new houses among prospective buyers, and various companies built entirely new residential neighborhoods to supply that demand.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> Defendants were among those companies: Defendant Standard Pacific Corp. sold over 30,000 houses around the country between 2004 and 2006 (<underscore>see</underscore> Second Am. Compl. (&#x201C;Dodaro SAC&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1666, Doc. No. 73) &#182; 13); Defendant Lennar Corp., over 120,000 (<underscore>see</underscore> Second Am. Compl. (&#x201C;Stephens SAC&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1668, Doc. No. 68) &#182; 16); Defendant M.D.C. Holdings, Inc., over 40,000 (Second Am. Compl. (&#x201C;Lumalu SAC&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1669, Doc. No. 55) &#182; 18); Defendant The Ryland Group, Inc., more than 47,000 (Second Am. Compl. (&#x201C;Oneto SAC&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1670, Doc. No. 59) &#182; 18); Defendant D.R. Horton, Inc., nearly 150,000 (Second Am. Compl. (&#x201C;Martinez SAC&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1672, Doc. No. 71) &#182; 14); and Defendant Beazer Homes Holdings Corp., over 50,000 (Second Am. Compl. (&#x201C;Kelly SAC&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1674, Doc. No. 60) &#182; 16).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p6">&#8195;Consequently, the Court DENIES AS MOOT Defendants' Motions to Strike.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p7">&#8195;In deciding Defendants' Motions, the Court takes as true facts pled by Plaintiffs, <underscore>Colony Cove Properties, LLC v. City of Carson</underscore>, 640 F.3d 948, 955 (9th Cir. 2011), as well as adjudicative facts that are subject to judicial notice, <underscore>id.</underscore>; <underscore>see</underscore> Fed. R. Evid. 201. &#x201C;&#x2018;Adjudicative facts are facts about the parties and their activities, businesses, and properties, usually answering the questions of who did what, where, when, how, why, with what motive or intent; adjudicative facts are roughly the kind of facts that go to a jury in a jury case.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Marshall v. Sawyer</underscore>, 365 F.2d 105, 111 (9th Cir. 1966) (quoting Kenneth Culp Davis, <underscore>The Requirement of a Trial-Type Hearing</underscore>, 70 Harv. L. Rev. 193, 199 (1956)). Where, as here, the Court discusses facts not relied upon for its disposition of the case, it does so to place the matter in context for the reader; in any event, that low interest rates stimulated a demand for houses, which were built in large numbers shortly after the turn of the century, is by now something &#x201C;&#x2018;like the obvious fact that surgery is painful and can have dire consequences,&#x2019;&#x201D; and therefore not a forbidden observation, <underscore>United States v. Berber-Tinoco</underscore>, 510 F.3d 1083, 1091 (9th Cir. 2007) (quoting <underscore>United States v. Mariscal</underscore>, 285 F.3d 1127, 1131-32 (9th Cir. 2002)).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Not only were companies building and selling large numbers of houses; Plaintiffs allege companies like Defendants were vertically integrating their businesses to finance those sales, themselves. (<underscore>See</underscore> Dodaro SAC &#182;&#182; 15-21, 24.)<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> Consequently, Defendants were able to build, appraise, advertise, broker the sales of, and finance houses. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 24.) Owing in part to this vertical integration, Defendants were able to finance the sale of the houses they built to subprime borrowers: people who, though &#x201C;cash-poor,&#x201D; would find themselves &#x201C;house-rich&#x201D; in a market where housing prices continued to rise. (<underscore>See id.</underscore> &#182; 26; <underscore>In re First Alliance Mortg. Co.</underscore>, 471 F.3d 977, 984 (9th Cir. 2006) (discussing the practice of subprime lending).) Plaintiffs contend they thus found themselves in neighborhoods &#x201C;saturat[ed]&#x201D; with people who paid only 10 percent of the price of their houses, borrowing 90 percent against the properties themselves (<underscore>see</underscore> Dodaro SAC &#182; 27). Those buyers staked the collateral &#8211; their houses &#8211; on the notion that the increasing equity in the houses would exceed the debt secured by the houses rapidly.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Plaintiffs were unaware their neighborhoods were filled with such buyers, whom they view as generally &#x201C;not qualified&#x201D; to borrow large amounts of money. (<underscore>See id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 26-27.) Defendants instead led Plaintiffs to believe they were buying houses in &#x201C;traditional neighborhoods with stable owners who occupied their homes and who were vested in the community and neighborhood.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 30.) To Plaintiffs, it was &#x201C;[i]mplicit&#x201D; that Defendants were &#x201C;making a good-faith effort to sell homes to buyers [they] expected could afford to buy the houses and would be stable neighbors.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p10">&#8195;For propositions that are substantially similar across the eight sets of pleadings in Plaintiffs' case, the Court relies on Plaintiff Dodaro's Second Amended Complaint, and will distinguish among Plaintiffs' pleadings only when necessary on a particular point.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Bolstering this expectation, Defendants &#x201C;repeatedly represented that the homes they were selling were single-family homes that were designed and located in communities that are optimal for buyers with families that would occupy the homes,&#x201D; and &#x201C;that only buyers who intended to occupy the homes as their primary residence for at least one year would be permitted to purchase homes in these developments. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 31-32.) Further convincing Plaintiffs that Defendants were policing the stability of their neighborhoods, Defendants required buyers to submit financing materials (or to finance the purchases through Defendants' own mortgage subsidiaries), &#x201C;to ensure that buyers were qualified to purchase their homes.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 35.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Having been involved in the financing of the houses they were selling, Defendants were in a position to know that they were selling houses to &#x201C;unqualified&#x201D; or &#x201C;high-foreclosure-risk buyers,&#x201D; but they did not disclose the presence of those buyers to Plaintiffs, who therefore paid more than they would have if they had known of the unqualified buyers in their midst. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 40-43, 53.) Plaintiffs entered into contracts to purchase houses (all in Riverside County or adjacent San Bernardino County) from Defendants: Plaintiff James Dodaro on July 24, 2005 (<underscore>id.</underscore> &#182; 56); Plaintiff Stella Stephens on June 25, 2005 (Stephens SAC &#182; 57) and Plaintiff Timothy Young on July 22, 2006 (<underscore>id.</underscore> &#182; 67); Plaintiff Edilberto Lumalu on June 4, 2005 (Lumalu SAC &#182; 61), Plaintiffs Brian and Brenda Dietz on November 10, 2005 (<underscore>id.</underscore> &#182; 67), and Plaintiff Candice McDonald on March 12, 2006 (<underscore>id.</underscore> &#182; 75); Plaintiff Gaspare Oneto on January 27, 2005 (Oneto SAC &#182; 58), Plaintiffs Paul and Sandra Nakabayashi on August 16, 2006 (<underscore>id.</underscore> &#182; 67), and Plaintiffs John and Linda Butler on September 30, 2005 (<underscore>id.</underscore> &#182; 76); Plaintiff Sylvester Maya and Plaintiff Ofer Masachi in June 2005 (Corrected Second Am. Compl. (&#x201C;Maya SAC&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1671, Doc. No. 77-1) &#182;&#182; 58, 69); Plaintiff Remedios Martinez on May 23, 2006 (Martinez SAC &#182; 55); Plaintiffs Matthew and Nicole Nielsen on April 29, 2006 (Second Am. Compl. (&#x201C;Nielsen SAC&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1673, Doc. No. 57) &#182; 57); Plaintiff Solomon Kelly on June 11, 2005 (Kelly SAC &#182; 59) and Plaintiff James Molina in January 2006 (<underscore>id.</underscore> &#182; 68).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">And then the demand for new houses evaporated. The value of existing houses began to spiral downward, houses hemorrhaged the equity that made them viable collateral for subprime lending, and neighborhoods with many heavily leveraged owners suffered commensurately large numbers of foreclosures and short sales (<underscore>see</underscore> Dodaro SAC &#182; 3). Owners either walked away from investments that now cost more than they were worth, or were evicted after losing the means of paying their residential loans in a collapsing economy.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Thereafter, Plaintiffs realized they were in neighborhoods populated heavily with subprime buyers and investors; the vacant houses left by departure of those owners depressed the values of Plaintiffs' property excessively. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 45-47.) Thus, Plaintiffs, who were &#x201C;qualified and low-foreclosure-risk buyers,&#x201D; and &#x201C;who did everything right,&#x201D; suffered grievous economic damage. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 45.) Plaintiffs therefore brought this lawsuit.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Procedural History</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Plaintiffs first filed Complaints on September 3, 2009; they amended their Complaints on December 21, 2009. Plaintiffs' First Amended Complaints made five claims against Defendants: (1) for unfair business practices under California Business and Professions Code &#167;&#167; 17200, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>; (2) for false advertising under California Business and Professions Code &#167;&#167; 17500, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>; (3) for fraud; (4) for negligent misrepresentation; and (5) for breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing. (<underscore>See, e.g.</underscore>, First Am. Compl. (Case No. 09-1666, Doc. No. 32).)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">On April 1, 2010, the Court granted Defendants' Motions to Dismiss Plaintiffs' First Amended Complaints, with prejudice, holding that Plaintiffs failed to demonstrate they had standing to sue in federal court. As Article III of the United States Constitution empowers federal courts to hear only &#x201C;cases&#x201D; and &#x201C;controversies,&#x201D; <underscore>see</underscore> U.S. Const. art. III, &#167; 2, matters must satisfy the various justiciability criteria, like standing, developed for determining whether a matter is a case or controversy. Demonstrating standing requires a plaintiff to show that he has suffered, or imminently will suffer, an injury that is &#x201C;concrete and particularized,&#x201D; can be fairly traced back to the defendant's conduct, and can be redressed by a court's favorable resolution of the matter. <underscore>Lujan v. Defenders of Wildlife</underscore>, 504 U.S. 555, 560-61 (1992). The Court held that Plaintiffs failed to plead a cognizable injury because any reduction in the value of their houses would not be concrete until they tried to sell those houses, and any claim that Plaintiffs overpaid for their houses because of Defendants' conduct likewise depended too much on economic fluctuations to be concrete. <underscore>Dodaro v. Standard Pac. Corp.</underscore>, No. EDCV 09-01666-VAP (OPx), 2010 WL 1330889, at *4-*8 (C.D. Cal. Apr. 1, 2010). The Court further held that Plaintiffs failed to plead adequately that Defendants caused any injury they may have suffered, because the array of prevailing economic factors and general decline of the housing market tied in knots any chain of causation linking Plaintiffs' alleged injuries to Defendants' conduct. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at *8-*11.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Plaintiffs appealed. The court of appeals held Plaintiffs alleged standing adequately as to injuries that occurred at the time they bought their houses, <underscore>i.e.</underscore>, damages that accrued when Plaintiffs paid more than they would have for the houses they bought. <underscore>Maya v. Centex Corp.</underscore>, 658 F.3d 1060, 1069-70 (9th Cir. 2011). It further held Plaintiffs alleged a cognizable injury when they stated the current value of their properties had been reduced inordinately by Defendants' sales practices, even though Plaintiffs had yet to sell their houses. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1071. In any event, the court of appeals observed, the excessive blight caused by the extraordinary number of foreclosures Plaintiffs attributed to Defendants' conduct was a concrete injury. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1071-72.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">But whether the foreclosures in Plaintiffs' neighborhoods could be attributed properly to Defendants' sales practices was a question left open by the court of appeals, which held Plaintiffs &#x201C;have not established how [Defendants'] actions <underscore>necessarily</underscore> result in foreclosure. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1072 (emphasis in original).<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> The court of appeals therefore remanded the case to this Court, with instructions to &#x201C;permit&#x201D; Plaintiffs &#x201C;to amend their complaint and attach expert testimony on causation&#x201D; as to the alleged devaluation of their houses. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1073.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p19">&#8195;The court of appeals observed that Plaintiffs alleged only that foreclosures on neighboring houses caused the devaluation of their own houses, and not that Plaintiffs' houses lost value based on &#x201C;the <underscore>risk</underscore> posed by their neighbors (even absent foreclosures).&#x201D; <underscore>Maya</underscore>, 658 F.3d at 1072.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">On December 2, 2011, Plaintiffs filed eight Second Amended Complaints purporting to address the issue identified by the court of appeals and raising the same five claims they raised in their First Amended Complaints. On December 22, Defendants filed Motions to Dismiss Plaintiffs' Second Amended Complaints and simultaneously, Motions to Strike various portions of Plaintiffs' pleadings. On January 9, 2012, Plaintiffs filed timely Oppositions, and on January 18, 2012, Defendants filed Replies. Both Plaintiffs and Defendants split the issues they briefed among the various Plaintiffs and Defendants; each Plaintiff and Defendant incorporated portions of other Plaintiffs' and Defendants' briefing by reference.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">The principal arguments Defendants advance are: (1) Plaintiffs still have not demonstrated the causal connection between Defendants' conduct and Plaintiffs' injury necessary to show standing to sue (<underscore>see</underscore> Mot. to Dismiss (&#x201C;Stephens MTD&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1668, Doc. No. 74) at 20-25; Mot. to Dismiss (&#x201C;Martinez MTD&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1672, Doc. No. 77) at 20-22; Mot. to Dismiss (&#x201C;Kelly MTD&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1674, Doc. No. 65) at 7-8); (2) the statute of limitations has expired on Plaintiffs' fraud claims (<underscore>see</underscore> Mot. to Dismiss (&#x201C;Maya MTD&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1671, Doc. No. 69) at 21-23); (3) Defendants' allegedly fraudulent statements about the character of Plaintiffs' neighborhoods were puffery (<underscore>see</underscore> Maya MTD at 15-17; Martinez MTD at 9-10; Mot. to Dismiss (&#x201C;Nielsen MTD&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1673, Doc. No. 59-1) at 10-12); (4) Plaintiffs could not have relied on those statements reasonably in buying their houses (<underscore>see</underscore> Mot. to Dismiss (&#x201C;Lumalu MTD&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1669, Doc. No. 56) at 17-18; Mot. to Dismiss (&#x201C;Oneto MTD&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1670, Doc. No. 64) at 16-19; Martinez MTD at 12-14; Nielsen MTD at 16-17); (5) in any event, Plaintiffs fail to plead fraud with the requisite specificity (<underscore>see</underscore> Stephens MTD at 6-8; Oneto MTD at 7-10; Maya MTD at 23-24; Nielsen MTD at 8-10; Kelly MTD at 17-20); and (6) Defendants had no duty to disclose the facts Plaintiffs allege they fraudulently concealed (<underscore>see</underscore> Stephens MTD at 10-12; Lumalu MTD at 12-15; Maya at 18-19; Nielsen at 12-16).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">The Court analyzes Defendants' standing argument as a challenge to its subject-matter jurisdiction under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(1); the remaining arguments go to Plaintiffs' ability to state a claim, and are analyzed pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6). The Court thus sets forth the standards for applying those two rules.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. LEGAL STANDARDS</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(1)</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(1), a district court must dismiss an action if the court lacks jurisdiction over the subject matter of the suit. Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(b)(1). The party seeking to invoke federal jurisdiction bears the burden of establishing that jurisdiction exists. <underscore>Scott v. Breeland</underscore>, 792 F.2d 925, 927 (9th Cir. 1986). A complaint will be dismissed under Rule 12(b)(1) for lack of subject matter jurisdiction if (1) the cause does not &#x201C;arise under&#x201D; any federal law or the United States Constitution, (2) there is no &#x201C;case or controversy&#x201D; within the meaning of that constitutional term, or (3) the cause is not one described by any jurisdictional statute. <underscore>Baker v. Carr</underscore>, 369 U.S. 186, 198 (1962).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6)</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6) allows a party to bring a motion to dismiss for failure to state a claim upon which relief can be granted. Rule 12(b)(6) is read in conjunction with Rule 8(a), which requires only a short and plain statement of the claim showing that the pleader is entitled to relief. Fed. R. Civ. P. 8(a)(2); <underscore>Conley v. Gibson</underscore>, 355 U.S. 41, 47 (1957) (holding that the Federal Rules require that a plaintiff provide &#x201C;&#x2018;a short and plain statement of the claim&#x2019; that will give the defendant fair notice of what the plaintiff's claim is and the grounds upon which it rests.&#x201D;) (quoting Fed. R. Civ. P. 8(a)(2)); <underscore>Bell Atlantic Corp. v. Twombly</underscore>, 550 U.S. 544, 555 (2007). When evaluating a Rule 12(b)(6) motion, a court must accept all material allegations in the complaint &#8211; as well as any reasonable inferences to be drawn from them &#8211; as true, and construe them in the light most favorable to the non-moving party. <underscore>See Doe v. United States</underscore>, 419 F.3d 1058, 1062 (9th Cir. 2005); <underscore>ARC Ecology v. U.S. Dep't of Air Force</underscore>, 411 F.3d 1092, 1096 (9th Cir. 2005); <underscore>Moyo v. Gomez</underscore>, 32 F.3d 1382, 1384 (9th Cir. 1994).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">&#x201C;While a complaint attacked by a Rule 12(b)(6) motion to dismiss does not need detailed factual allegations, a plaintiff's obligation to provide the &#x2018;grounds&#x2019; of his &#x2018;entitlement to relief&#x2019; requires more than labels and conclusions, and a formulaic recitation of the elements of a cause of action will not do.&#x201D; <underscore>Twombly</underscore>, 550 U.S. at 555 (citations omitted). Rather, the allegations in the complaint &#x201C;must be enough to raise a right to relief above the speculative level.&#x201D; <underscore>Id</underscore>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">To survive a motion to dismiss, a plaintiff must allege &#x201C;enough facts to state a claim to relief that is plausible on its face.&#x201D; <underscore>Twombly</underscore>, 550 U.S. at 570; <underscore>Ashcroft v. Iqbal</underscore>, 556 U.S. 662, 129 S. Ct. 1937, 1949 (2009). &#x201C;The plausibility standard is not akin to a &#x2018;probability requirement,&#x2019; but it asks for more than a sheer possibility that a defendant has acted unlawfully. Where a complaint pleads facts that are &#x2018;merely consistent with&#x2019; a defendant's liability, it stops short of the line between possibility and plausibility of &#x2018;entitlement to relief.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Iqbal</underscore>, 129 S. Ct. at 1949 (quoting <underscore>Twombly</underscore>, 550 U.S. at 556). Recently, the Ninth Circuit clarified that a complaint must (1) &#x201C;contain sufficient allegations of underlying facts to give fair notice and to enable the opposing party to defend itself effectively&#x201D; and (2) &#x201C;the factual allegations that are taken as true must plausibly suggest an entitlement to relief, such that it is not unfair to require the opposing the party to be subjected to the expense of discovery and continued litigation.&#x201D; <underscore>Starr v. Baca</underscore>, 652 F.3d 1202, 1216 (9th Cir. 2011).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Although the scope of review is limited to the contents of the complaint, the Court may also consider exhibits submitted with the complaint, <underscore>Hal Roach Studios, Inc. v. Richard Feiner &#38; Co.</underscore>, 896 F.2d 1542, 1555 n.19 (9th Cir. 1990), and &#x201C;take judicial notice of matters of public record outside the pleadings,&#x201D; <underscore>Mir v. Little Co. of Mary Hosp.</underscore>, 844 F.2d 646, 649 (9th Cir. 1988).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>III. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Subject-matter jurisdiction is the sine qua non of proceeding in federal court; consequently, the Court begins by analyzing Defendants' challenge to Plaintiffs' standing to sue. Finding Plaintiffs have alleged the necessary facts to establish standing (<underscore>see infra</underscore> Section A), the Court turns next to Defendants' argument that Plaintiffs' fraud-related claims are time-barred. As discussed below, the Court concludes Plaintiffs fail to plead adequately when they discovered Defendants' alleged fraud. (<underscore>See infra</underscore> Section B.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">The Court will not, however, grant Plaintiffs leave to amend their pleadings again to correct this error, because the amendment would be futile: the Court concludes that Plaintiffs otherwise fail to state any claim on which relief can be granted, for the reasons discussed below. (<underscore>See infra</underscore> Sections C-F.) The Court therefore GRANTS Defendants' Motions to Dismiss, without leave to amend.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Plaintiffs Establish Standing Successfully</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">As discussed above, to demonstrate his standing to sue, a plaintiff must show he has suffered (or will suffer imminently) a concrete and particular injury, traceable to the defendant's conduct, and redressable by the court. <underscore>Lujan</underscore>, 504 U.S. at 560-61. The strength required of the plaintiff's showing is commensurate with when in the litigation it is made; &#x201C;[a]t the pleading stage, general factual allegations of injury resulting from the defendant's conduct may suffice. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 561; <underscore>see, e.g., Cent. Delta Water Agency v. United States</underscore>, 306 F.3d 938, 947 (9th Cir. 2002) (observing that even at the summary judgment stage, a plaintiff need not prove standing, but instead demonstrate merely &#x201C;that there is a genuine question of material fact as to the standing elements&#x201D;). Plaintiffs now carry that burden successfully.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Previously, this Court concluded Plaintiffs failed to allege standing adequately because they failed to allege concrete and particular injuries, and failed to causally link those injuries to Defendants' conduct. The Ninth Circuit reversed and remanded, leaving to this Court to determine whether, after amending their pleadings, Plaintiffs can establish a causal connection between Defendants' alleged acts and the devaluation of Plaintiffs' houses (or the surrounding blight). <underscore>See Maya</underscore>, 658 F.3d at 1072-73.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">Plaintiffs now adequately allege a causal connection between Defendants' behavior and the diminished value of their houses. Citing &#x201C;[a]n analysis performed by an economist,&#x201D; Plaintiffs allege that if in 2006, a buyer in Riverside County purchased a house from a builder that sold 70 percent of its houses to buyers who financed 90 percent or more of the cost of their houses, a buyer could expect to receive $60,000 less for his house than would someone who purchased a house from a builder that sold only 20 percent of its houses to such heavily leveraged buyers.<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference> (<underscore>See</underscore> Dodaro SAC &#182; 47.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p33">&#8195;The diminution in the value of Plaintiffs' houses therefore is not traceable directly to Defendants' alleged failure to disclose the presence of subprime mortgagors; it is instead traceable directly to Defendants' decision to sell to so many subprime mortgagors in the first place. Though that decision is not, itself, culpable conduct, for the purpose of the standing inquiry, the culpability of a defendant's conduct is immaterial; the only question is whether the conduct caused the plaintiff's injury, not whether it can form the basis of a meritorious claim. <underscore>See Catholic League for Religious &#38; Civil Rights v. City &#38; Cnty. of S.F.</underscore>, 624 F.3d 1043, 1049 (9th Cir. 2010) (en banc) (distinguishing standing analysis, &#x201C;which prevents a claim from being adjudicated for lack of jurisdiction,&#x201D; from merits analysis, &#x201C;which determines whether a claim is one for which relief can be granted if factually true&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Defendants contend this allegation is insufficient to establish the requisite connection between Defendants' alleged sales to subprime mortgagors and the subsequent devaluation of the Homebuyers' property, for two reasons. First, Defendants argue Plaintiffs' allegation defies the Ninth Circuit's instruction that Plaintiffs &#x201C;attach expert testimony on causation,&#x201D; <underscore>Maya</underscore>, 658 F.3d at 1073, and is contrary to Plaintiffs' representation that their Second Amended Complaints would demonstrate causation by &#x201C;attaching an expert report&#x201D; (Joint Case Mgmt. Statement (Case No. 09-1666, Doc. No. 67) at 11). (<underscore>See</underscore> Stephens MTD at 22.) Second, Defendants argue Plaintiffs' allegation lacks substance, as it does not address Defendants' conduct and instead is directed at builders in general. (<underscore>See id.</underscore> at 23-24.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">As an initial matter, Plaintiffs' standing to seek relief for devaluation of their houses is no longer a dispositive issue in this case. The court of appeals concluded already that Plaintiffs have standing to seek relief on the separate premise that they never would have purchased their houses in the first place, had Defendants disclosed the number of highly leveraged buyers in their neighborhoods, <underscore>see Maya</underscore>, 658 F.3d at 1069-70. <underscore>See Friends of Earth, Inc. v. Laidlaw Envtl. Servs. (TOC), Inc.</underscore>, 528 U.S. 167, 185 (2000) (&#x201C;[A] plaintiff must demonstrate standing separately for each form of relief sought.&#x201D;); <underscore>see, e.g., City of Los Angeles v. Lyons</underscore>, 461 U.S. 95, 109 (holding that a plaintiff had standing to seek damages for an injury even if he lacked standing to seek injunctive relief on the basis of the same injurious conduct); <underscore>Sacks v. Office of Foreign Assets Control</underscore>, 466 F.3d 764, 771-72 (9th Cir. 2006) (distinguishing among a plaintiff's claims for the purpose of determining those he lacks standing to assert).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">The Court turns to Defendants' first argument, that Plaintiffs fail to attach to their pleadings an expert report &#x201C;distinguishing the effect of defendants' actions from general economic influences,&#x201D; <underscore>Maya</underscore>, 658 F.3d at 1072-73, and therefore fail to meet the court of appeals requirement for establishing standing. (<underscore>See</underscore> Stephens MTD at 23.) As the court of appeals noted, &#x201C;[e]xpert testimony can be used to explain the causal connection between defendants' actions and plaintiffs' injuries, even in the context of other market forces.&#x201D; <underscore>Maya</underscore>, 658 F.3d at 1073 (citing <underscore>Barnum Timber Co. v. U.S. Envtl. Protection Agency</underscore>, 633 F.3d 894, 900-01 (9th Cir. 2011)). Just because expert testimony can be used to explain a causal connection, however, does not mean that expert testimony must be used to explain that connection, a requirement that would fly in the face of the policy that &#x201C;&#x2018;general factual allegations of injury resulting from the defendant's conduct may suffice&#x2019;&#x201D; to demonstrate standing at the pleading stage, <underscore>Maya</underscore>, 658 F.3d at 1068 (quoting <underscore>Lujan</underscore>, 504 U.S. at 561). Thus, the court of appeals elsewhere held that when a plaintiff both &#x201C;allege[s] specific facts plausibly explaining causality and supported by competent declarations,&#x201D; the plaintiff &#x201C;<underscore>more than [meets] its burden</underscore> to demonstrate the causal connection element of Article III standing at the pleading stage.&#x201D; <underscore>Barnum Timber</underscore>, 633 F.3d at 899 (emphasis added).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">The Ninth Circuit found that on the basis of their First Amended Complaints, Plaintiffs failed to allege the requisite causal connection between their houses' depreciation and Defendants' conduct, but &#x201C;permitting [Plaintiffs] to amend their complaint[s] and attach expert testimony on causation,&#x201D; <underscore>Maya</underscore>, 658 F.3d at 1073, is not the same as requiring Plaintiffs to attach expert testimony on causation &#8211; as long as Plaintiffs otherwise amend their complaints in a manner sufficient to allege a causal connection. An otherwise satisfactory allegation is not lacking simply because Plaintiffs did not provide the expert report they discussed in the Joint Case Management Statement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">Thus the Court turns to Defendants' second argument, <underscore>i.e.</underscore>, that Plaintiffs' allegation of a causal connection between Plaintiffs' injuries and Defendants' conduct remains insufficient, expert report or not. Defendants make much of the fact that linking one of many possible causes to an effect is, in a market context, notoriously difficult, because multiple actors can affect a market simultaneously. <underscore>See San Diego Cnty. Gun Rights Comm. v. Reno</underscore>, 98 F.3d 1121, 1130 (9th Cir. 1996) (citing <underscore>Common Cause v. Dep't of Energy</underscore>, 702 F.2d 245, 251 (D.C. Cir. 1983)). To be sure, it may be difficult, but it is not impossible.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">In <underscore>Barnum Timber</underscore>, Barnum, the plaintiff, alleged that when the Environmental Protection Agency designated Redwood Creek as impaired by effluent, it lowered the value of Barnum's adjacent property. 633 F.3d at 896. The district court dismissed Barnum's complaint, finding it lacked standing to sue. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 896-97. On appeal, the Ninth Circuit found Barnum pled standing successfully, contrasting the case with <underscore>San Diego County</underscore>; in that case &#x201C;the plaintiffs contested government action that affected entire markets and correspondingly alleged price increases to the market as a whole, in which they merely hoped to be buyers.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 900. Barnum, on the other hand, alleged &#x201C;that the economic value of <underscore>its</underscore> property has been affected by the government action on an adjoining waterway[,] leav[ing] open the possibility that Barnum could isolate the effects of the government action on its property.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> (emphasis in original).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">Further, the Ninth Circuit recognized Barnum's allegations and the declarations supporting them &#x201C;offer[ed] a commonsense assessment of the market for real property,&#x201D; <underscore>i.e.</underscore>, that &#x201C;regulatory restrictions on one property that affect the uses to which a second property can be put will lower the second property's value.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> Additionally, the court did not require Barnum to &#x201C;allege that EPA is the sole source of the devaluation of its property.&#x201D; As long as &#x201C;Barnum has alleged that at least EPA's listing of Redwood Creek has affected the value of its property[,] [i]t need not eliminate other contributing causes to establish its standing.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 901; <underscore>see also Ocean Advocates v. U.S. Army Corp. of Eng'rs</underscore>, 402 F.3d 846, 860 (9th Cir. 2005) (holding that even though &#x201C;other factors may also cause additional [oil] tanker traffic,&#x201D; the construction of a dock extension, &#x201C;when considered alone or in tandem with other industrial projects in the <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> region, would contribute&#x201D; to the increased risk of an oil spill, the alleged injury).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">In this case, Plaintiffs allege a correlation between the decline in value of a builder's houses in Riverside County and the number of houses the builder sold to buyers who financed 90 percent or more of the cost of a house. (<underscore>See</underscore> Dodaro SAC &#182; 47.) They then allege that Defendants sold a sufficient number of houses to such buyers to cause a greater decline in value to their own houses than prevailing economic factors would have otherwise caused (<underscore>see id.</underscore> &#182; 49), and that Defendants did in fact cause such an incremental decline in the value of Plaintiffs' houses (<underscore>see id.</underscore> &#182; 75).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">Plaintiffs correctly point out that they are not required, at this time, to prove that Defendants' actions actually caused the excessive devaluation of their houses &#8211; indeed, it may later turn out that they are unable to prove it, scuttling a portion of their case. <underscore>See Lujan</underscore>, 504 U.S. at 561 (discussing the resolution of a party's standing at trial). For the time being, Plaintiffs must only allege a non-tenuous connection between Defendants' actions and their losses. Justiciability doctrines (like standing) do not exist simply to give defendants an additional means of moving to dismiss cases on the pleadings; they exist to &#x201C;limit the business of federal courts to questions presented in an adversary context and in a form historically viewed as capable of resolution through the judicial process.&#x201D; <underscore>Flast v. Cohen</underscore>, 392 U.S. 83, 95 (1968). In that light it becomes clear that Plaintiffs have alleged standing successfully.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">In sum, Plaintiffs allege Defendants' sales of houses to droves of heavily leveraged buyers primed entire neighborhoods for economic devastation; Defendants sold Plaintiffs houses in those neighborhoods, and the values of those houses have been affected inordinately as a result. The Court concludes that these allegations meet the threshold, at the pleading stage, of establishing Plaintiffs' standing to pursue relief for the diminution in the value of their houses.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Plaintiffs' Allegations Fail to Establish the Timeliness of Their Claims for Fraud, Negligent Misrepresentation, and False Advertising</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">Next, the Court turns to Defendants' contention that Plaintiffs' claims for fraud, negligent misrepresentation, and false advertising are time-barred. (<underscore>See</underscore> Maya MTD at 21-23.) The Court applies the relevant California statutes of limitations. <underscore>Bancorp Leasing &#38; Fin. Corp. v. Agusta Aviation Corp.</underscore>, 813 F.2d 272, 274 (9th Cir. 1987). In California, fraud claims are subject to a three-year statute of limitations, running from the time fraud is, or should have been, discovered (the so-called &#x201C;discovery rule&#x201D;). Cal. Civ. Proc. Code &#167; 338(d); <underscore>Fox v. Ethicon Endo-Surgery, Inc.</underscore>, 35 Cal. 4th 797, 807-09 (2005). A false advertising claim under California Business and Professions Code &#167;&#167; 17500, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>, is likewise subject to a three-year statute of limitations. Cal Civ. Proc. Code &#167; 338(a); <underscore>StreamCast Networks, Inc. v. Skype Techs., S.A.</underscore>, No. CV 06-391 FMC (Ex), 2006 WL 5441237, at *9 n.8 (C.D. Cal. 2006). A negligent misrepresentation claim, however, is subject to either a two or three year limitations period, depending on the essence of the conduct underlying the claim. <underscore>Fanucci v. Allstate Ins. Co.</underscore>, 638 F. Supp. 2d 1125, 1133 (N.D. Cal. 2009); <underscore>Ventura Cnty. Nat'l Bank v. Macker</underscore>, 49 Cal. App. 4th 1528, 1530-31 (1996). Under even a three-year limitations period, the Court concludes Plaintiffs' negligent misrepresentation claims, along with their fraud and false advertising claims, are time-barred.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">Plaintiffs Paul and Sandra Nakabayashi were the last Plaintiffs to enter a purchase agreement to buy a house from a Homebuilder, on August 16, 2006. Plaintiffs' Complaints were filed on September 3, 2009, a few weeks beyond the three-year limitations period. Consequently, at first glance, all Plaintiffs' fraud, negligent misrepresentation, and false advertising claims appear time-barred. Plaintiffs allege, however, that they &#x201C;did not become aware&#x201D; of Defendants' fraud &#x201C;until well within two years prior to filing of the subject complaint, and there was no reasonable way [Plaintiffs] would have learned the information earlier than that time frame.&#x201D; (Dodaro SAC &#182; 72.) Defendants respond that this conclusory allegation provides an insufficient basis to invoke the discovery rule. The Court agrees.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">The discovery rule exists in fraud cases because a fraud defendant's &#x201C;deceptive conduct may prevent a plaintiff from even <underscore>knowing</underscore> that he or she has been defrauded.&#x201D; <underscore>Merck &#38; Co., Inc. v. Reynolds</underscore>, 130 S. Ct. 1784, 1793 (2010) (emphasis in original). Without the discovery rule, if a defendant managed to conceal his fraud throughout the limitations period, &#x201C;&#x2018;the law which was designed to prevent fraud&#x2019; could become &#x2018;the means by which it is made successful and secure.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1793-94 (quoting <underscore>Bailey v. Glover</underscore>, 88 U.S. (21 Wall.) 342, 349 (1875)). The discovery rule therefore shifts the point in time at which the limitations period runs from the time when the defendant committed the fraud to the time when the plaintiff discovered it &#8211; or should have discovered it. <underscore>Merck &#38; Co.</underscore>, 130 S. Ct. at 1794; <underscore>Fox</underscore>, 35 Cal. 4th at 807-07.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p47" level="1">So the question becomes: at what point should a plaintiff have discovered he or she was being defrauded? It is not always an easy question to answer. <underscore>Compare Betz v. Trainer Wortham &#38; Co., Inc.</underscore>, 519 F.3d 863, 865-78 (9th Cir. 2008) (Kozinski, C.J., dissenting from denial of reh'g en banc) (arguing that a securities fraud plaintiff who claimed to be defrauded into making an allegedly risk-free investment should have inquired into the possibility of fraud after receiving a statement showing a decline in the value of her investment) <underscore>with id.</underscore> at 878-79 (holding for the panel that there remained a factual question when said plaintiff was on notice of the alleged securities fraud), <underscore>vacated</underscore>, 130 S. Ct. 2400. In California, the limitations period begins to run when a plaintiff &#x201C;has reason at least to suspect a factual basis for [a claim's] elements,&#x201D; <underscore>Fox</underscore>, 35 Cal. 4th at 807 (internal quotation omitted), though not in the &#x201C;hypertechnical&#x201D; sense, <underscore>id.</underscore> Thus, &#x201C;[r]ather than examining whether [a plaintiff] suspect[s] facts supporting each specific legal element of a particular cause of action, we look to whether the plaintiff[] ha[s] reason to at least suspect that a type of wrongdoing has injured him.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p48" level="1">To invoke the discovery rule, a plaintiff &#x201C;must specifically plead facts to show (1) the time and manner of discovery <underscore>and</underscore> (2) the inability to have made earlier discovery despite reasonable diligence.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 808 (internal quotation omitted) (emphasis in original); <underscore>see, e.g., Lauter v. Anoufrieva</underscore>, 642 F. Supp. 2d 1060, 1099 (C.D. Cal. 2009) (applying <underscore>Fox</underscore>). Plaintiffs have not pled facts to show when and how they discovered Defendants' alleged fraud; they pled only that the triggering event happened sometime within the limitations period. (<underscore>See</underscore> Dodaro SAC &#182; 72.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">The closest Plaintiffs come to pleading when they discovered the alleged fraud is the allegation &#x201C;[w]hen the real estate bubble burst, the truth was revealed <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> [i]t was only then that the inflated prices, and the resulting damage, became clear.&#x201D; (Dodardo SAC &#182; 3.) But &#x201C;when the real estate bubble burst&#x201D; is not a specific point in time, or in any event, not one pled by Plaintiffs.<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p50">&#8195;To demonstrate the emptiness of the phrase &#x201C;when the real estate bubble burst,&#x201D; consider the following details, which the Court provides only to emphasize the necessity that Plaintiffs make a less conclusory allegation:</paratext>
<paratext ID="p51" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">By early March 2006, both buyers and sellers were wary of an impending downturn in the housing market. <underscore>See</underscore> Vikas Bijaj &#38; David Leonhardt, <underscore>Hoping for Best in Home Sales, 2 Sides Sit Tight</underscore>, N.Y. Times, Mar. 4, 2006, at A1. By the end of March, the Commerce Department reported that in February &#x201C;new-home sales fell 10.5 percent <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>, the biggest one-month decline in nine years.&#x201D; <underscore>Gains Are Slim in Week of Wariness on Fed's Next Move</underscore>, N.Y. Times, Mar. 25, 2006, at C6. Nevertheless, the depth of the market's descent in Riverside and San Bernardino Counties was, by the end of March, still a matter of speculation in some venues, which reported on a &#x201C;cooling&#x201D; market (as opposed to a collapsing one). <underscore>See</underscore> Josh Brown, <underscore>Study Forecasts Slower Growth in California Economy</underscore>, The Press-Enterprise (Riverside, CA), Mar. 29, 2006, <underscore>available at</underscore> 2006 WLNR 5210688.</paratext>
<paratext ID="p52" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">By October 2006, however, one forecast predicted &#x201C;home prices in Riverside and San Bernardino counties will fall 11.4 percent from their peak earlier&#x201D; in the year, and that &#x201C;by late 2008, the <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> region will have experienced among the steepest declines of 379 metropolitan areas in the country and will be among 20 areas where prices for single-family homes on the resale market will fall by double digits.&#x201D; <underscore>Sharp Drop Forecast for Inland Housing Prices</underscore>, The Press-Enterprise, Oct. 4, 2006, <underscore>available at</underscore> 2006 WLNR 17198198. In November, sales were down &#x201C;21 percent in San Bernardino County and 24 percent in Riverside County from a year earlier,&#x201D; but still, the median prices of houses in both counties were higher than they had been the year before. Leslie Berkman, <underscore>Incentives Thrown in to Sell Homes</underscore>, The Press-Enterprise, Nov. 15, 2006, <underscore>available at</underscore> 2006 WLNR 19798525.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p53" level="1">At the March 5, 2012, hearing on Defendants' Motions, Plaintiffs argued that a holding of the court of appeals, in <underscore>Cervantes v. Countrywide Home Loans, Inc.</underscore>, 656 F.3d 1034 (9th Cir. 2011), relieves them of the burden of pleading facts sufficient to invoke the discovery rule, and instead places the burden on Defendants to prove that Plaintiffs' claims are time-barred. <underscore>Cervantes</underscore>, however, dealt with the equitable tolling of a statute of limitations that indisputably began to run when the plaintiffs executed loan documents, 656 F.3d at 1045-46; this case presents the different question of when the statute of limitations began to run in the first place.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p54" level="1">Nevertheless, the Court considers Plaintiffs' broader point, <underscore>i.e.</underscore>, that Plaintiffs do not bear the burden of disproving an affirmative defense &#8211; here, that the statute of limitations has run on their claims; instead, Defendants bear the burden of proving it. <underscore>See Tovar v. U.S. Postal Serv.</underscore>, 3 F.3d 1271, 1284 (9th Cir. 1993) (&#x201C;In every civil case, the defendant bears the burden of proof as to each element of an affirmative defense.&#x201D;) Defendants, however, met that burden, as the Second Amended Complaints set forth, on their faces, the times &#8211; beyond the limitations period &#8211; at which Plaintiffs entered into purchase agreements with Defendants. Plaintiffs therefore bear the burden of alleging their claims accrued at some other time, <underscore>i.e.</underscore>, the time at which they discovered the fraud. <underscore>See, e.g., Hopkins v. Dow Corning Corp.</underscore>, 33 F.3d 1116, 1120 (9th Cir. 1994) (&#x201C;To invoke the discovery rule, <underscore>plaintiff must plead facts</underscore> which show &#x2018;(1) the time and manner of discovery and (2) the inability to have made earlier discovery despite reasonable diligence.&#x2019;&#x201D;) (quoting <underscore>Saltier v. Pierce Bros. Mortuaries</underscore>, 81 Cal. App. 3d 292, 297 (1978)) (emphasis added).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p55" level="1">Accordingly, the Court dismisses Plaintiffs' fraud, negligent misrepresentation, and false advertising claims. The Court does so without leave to amend, because as is discussed immediately below, amendment would be futile; Plaintiffs' claims all fail on their merits. <underscore>See C.F. ex rel. Farnan v. Capistrano Unified Sch. Dist.</underscore>, 654 F.3d 975, 985 &#38; n.5 (9th Cir. 2011) (citing <underscore>Foman v. Davis</underscore>, 371 U.S. 178, 182 (1962)) (noting that leave to amend may be denied properly if amended would be futile).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Plaintiffs Fail to State Claims for Fraud</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p56" level="1">Defendants attack Plaintiffs' fraud claims by arguing first that they are not pled with the requisite specificity, and then that the claims fail as a matter of law, in any event. The Court takes these arguments in turn.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>1. Plaintiffs' Fraud Claims Are Pled With the Necessary Specificity</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p57" level="1">Defendants argue Plaintiffs fail to plead their fraud claims with the required degree of particularity. (<underscore>See</underscore> Stephens MTD at 6-8; Oneto MTD at 7-10; Maya MTD at 23-24; Nielsen MTD at 8-10; Kelly MTD at 17-20.) While the issue is close, ultimately the Court disagrees; Plaintiffs have pled at least some fraudulent acts with the requisite particularity.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p58" level="1">Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 9(b) requires a party alleging fraud to &#x201C;state with particularity the circumstances constituting fraud.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 9(b). Rule 9 applies not just to a claim denominated &#x201C;fraud,&#x201D; but also to other claims that arise from &#x201C;a unified course of fraudulent conduct.&#x201D; <underscore>Kearns v. Ford Motor Co.</underscore>, 567 F.3d 1120, 1125 (9th Cir. 2009). Pleading fraud with particularity requires a plaintiff to state &#x201C;&#x2018;the who, what, when, where, and how&#x2019; of the misconduct charged,&#x201D; <underscore>Vess v. Ciba-Geigy Corp. USA</underscore>, 317 F.3d 1097, 1106 (9th Cir. 2003) (internal citation omitted), as well as &#x201C;&#x2018;what is false or misleading&#x2019;&#x201D; about an allegedly false statement, &#x201C;&#x2018;and why it is false,&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>id.</underscore> (quoting <underscore>In re GlenFed, Inc. Sec. Litig.</underscore>, 42 F.3d 1541, 1548 (9th Cir. 1994)). Ultimately, the purpose of requiring particularized pleadings is threefold: (1) to give defendants adequate notice of what representations they are expected to defend &#x201C;and deter plaintiffs from the filing of a complaint &#x2018;as a pretext for the discovery of unknown wrongs&#x2019;&#x201D;; (2) to protect the reputations of fraud defendants; and (3) to prevent plaintiffs &#x201C;&#x2018;from unilaterally imposing upon the court, the parties and society enormous social and economic costs absent some factual basis.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Kearns</underscore>, 567 F.3d at 1125 (internal citation omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p59" level="1">In this case, each of Plaintiffs' claims arises from what is alleged to be a unified course of fraudulent conduct, and indeed each claim is at its heart a fraud claim &#8211; with the exception of the claim for breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing. Thus, with the exception of the claim for breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing, each of Plaintiffs' claims is subject to Rule 9(b)'s pleading requirements.<footnote.reference ID="fr8" refid="f8" style="percent_n">8</footnote.reference> With that in mind, the Court turns to the relevant allegations.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f8"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN8.</label.designator><paratext ID="p60">&#8195;Plaintiffs contend that in addition to their claim for breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing, portions of their claims under California Business and Professions Code &#167;&#167; 17200, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>, are also exempt from Rule 9(b)'s requirements. Plaintiffs point specifically to their allegations that in addition to being fraudulent, Defendants' conduct was unlawful, because it violated California Civil Code &#167;&#167; 1709-10, and unfair, because it &#x201C;offend[ed] legislative intent regarding income verification, as set forth in 66 Fed. Reg. 65604-01 (2001).&#x201D; (Dodaro SAC &#182; 104.) These arguments lack merit. Sections 1709 and 1710 create liability for the act of &#x201C;fraudulent deceit,&#x201D; unquestionably a species of fraud to which Rule 9(b) applies. <underscore>See, e.g., Nu&#241;ag-Tanedo v. E. Baton Rouge Parish Sch. Bd.</underscore>, 790 F. Supp. 2d 1134, 1141-43 (C.D. Cal. 2011) (applying Rule 9(b) to California Civil Code &#167; 1709). Inasmuch as the pages of the Federal Register cited by Plaintiffs discuss any regulations, those regulations are meant to protect borrowers from predatory lending, &#x201C;<underscore>excluding home-purchase loans</underscore>.&#x201D; 66 Fed. Reg. 65601, 65605 (Dec. 20, 2001) (emphasis added). Here, any &#x201C;unqualified&#x201D; borrowers received home-purchase loans; Defendants therefore did not engage in the unfair conduct Plaintiffs allege, regardless whether Rule 9(b) applies or not. (<underscore>See infra</underscore> Section F.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p61" level="1">Plaintiffs allege Defendants' marketing brochures advertised &#x201C;[l]arge homes with large number [sic] of bedrooms,&#x201D; &#x201C;providing &#x2018;[g]enerous proportions&#x2019; for &#x2018;family spaces,&#x2019; and that nearby schools would &#x2018;assure <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> family's needs.&#x2019;&#x201D; (Dodaro SAC &#182; 31.) One Plaintiff, by way of example, received materials stating that his neighborhood would include &#x201C;&#x2018;two parks and an inviting recreational center&#x2019; <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> located near &#x2018;fine Beaumont public schools, [and] new shopping and dining. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x2019;&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 58.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p62" level="1">Further, Plaintiffs were presented with agreements containing statements akin to this one: &#x201C;&#x2018;Seller desires to sell the Property only to a buyer who will occupy the Property as that buyer's principal residence.&#x2019;&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 59.) The reason for this &#x201C;desire,&#x201D; another sales document stated, was &#x201C;&#x2018;to maintain a stabilized community of owner-occupied homes.&#x2019;&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 61.) Provisions by which Plaintiffs authorized Defendants to &#x201C;&#x2018;communicate directly with&#x2019;&#x201D; their mortgage lenders &#x201C;&#x2018;for purposes of determining Buyer's ability to obtain loan approval and confirm that Buyer has sufficient funds to close Escrow&#x201D; led Plaintiffs to believe Defendants &#x201C;would ensure that only qualified buyers would purchase homes in the community.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 62.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p63" level="1">Defendants argue that allegations like this fail to meet Rule 9's particularity requirements, because they do not set forth explicitly the who, what, when, where, and how of the alleged fraud. (<underscore>See, e.g.</underscore>, Nielsen MTD at 8-10.) On one hand, Defendants are correct that Plaintiffs do not identify precisely the marketing materials in which the allegedly false statements are contained, nor do they allege who gave them those materials, nor when. On the other, printed marketing materials are not ephemeras; they are not the representations of a faceless agent, known only by a first name, made over the telephone at a time since forgotten &#8211; and now relied upon by a plaintiff to accuse the agent's principal of fraud. This is true, to a greater extent, for statements allegedly contained in agreements executed by Plaintiffs at an identifiable point in time. (<underscore>See, e.g.</underscore>, Dodaro SAC &#182;&#182; 56, 57, 59, 61.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p64" level="1">That is not to say Plaintiffs meet the Rule 9(b) standard throughout their pleadings; there is nothing, for instance, to indicate what is false or misleading about the statement that a neighborhood will include &#x201C;&#x2018;two parks and an inviting recreational center&#x2019;&#x201D; (<underscore>id.</underscore> &#182; 58). The Rule is, however, satisfied by documents expressing Defendants' desire to populate a neighborhood with owner-occupied residences, coupled with Plaintiffs' allegations that Defendants had no such intent &#8211; and only said they did to entice Plaintiffs to buy houses. At bottom, Rule 9(b) is meant to force plaintiffs to make allegations &#x201C;&#x2018;specific enough to give defendants notice of the particular conduct which is alleged to constitute the fraud charged so that they defend against the charge and not just deny that they have done anything wrong.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Neubronner v. Milken</underscore>, 6 F.3d 666, 671 (9th Cir. 1993) (quoting <underscore>Semegen v. Weidner</underscore>, 780 F.2d 727, 731 (9th Cir. 1985)). In this case, Plaintiffs' pleadings give Defendants sufficient information to defend against Plaintiffs' claims effectively. Plaintiffs thus succeed in apprising Defendants of their alleged wrongdoing, but as the Court will now discuss, Defendants' alleged bad acts are not culpable conduct as a matter of law.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>2. Plaintiffs' Fraud Claims Nevertheless Fail on their Merits</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p65" level="1">In California, the elements of a fraud claim are: &#x201C;(1) a misrepresentation (false representation, concealment, or nondisclosure); (2) knowledge of falsity (or scienter); (3) intent to defraud <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>; (4) justifiable reliance; and (5) resulting damage.&#x201D; <underscore>Robinson Helicopter Co. v. Dana Corp.</underscore>, 34 Cal. 4th 979, 990 (2004). If a fraud claim relies on a defendant's concealment of a fact, the defendant must have had a duty to disclose the particular information that he allegedly concealed. <underscore>Hahn v. Mirda</underscore>, 147 Cal. App. 4th 740, 748 (2007). Plaintiffs contend that Defendants both affirmatively misrepresented the character of the neighborhoods in which they were selling houses, and concealed (or failed to disclose) the presence of unqualified buyers (<underscore>i.e.</underscore>, foreclosure risks). (<underscore>See, e.g.</underscore>, Dodaro SAC &#182;&#182; 62, 70.) Defendants respond that Plaintiffs could not justifiably rely on the alleged misrepresentations, because those representations were puffery, and the contracts signed by Plaintiffs foreclosed reliance on those statements, in any event. Defendants also argue that they had no duty to disclose the presence of so-called unqualified buyers. Defendants are correct on both points.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>a. Defendants' Alleged Misrepresentations Are Largely, if not Wholly, Puffery</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p66" level="1">&#x201C;[A] general, subjective claim about a product is non-actionable puffery.&#x201D; <underscore>Newcal Indus., Inc. v. Ikon Office Solution</underscore>, 513 F.3d 1038, 1053 (9th Cir. 2009). &#x201C;A statement that is quantifiable, that makes a claim as to the &#x2018;specific or absolute characteristics of a product,&#x2019;&#x201D; however, is not. <underscore>Id.</underscore> (quoting <underscore>Cook, Perkiss, &#38; Liehe v. N. Cal. Collection Serv., Inc.</underscore>, 911 F.2d 242, 245 (9th Cir. 1990)); <underscore>see Sterling Drug, Inc. v. Fed. Trade Comm'n</underscore>, 741 F.2d 1146, 1150 (9th Cir. 1984) (noting that puffery consists of claims that &#x201C;are either vague or highly subjective&#x201D;); <underscore>Sensible Foods, LLC v. World Gourmet, Inc.</underscore>, No. 11-2819 SC, 2012 WL 566304, at *6 (N.D. Cal. Feb. 21, 2012) (&#x201C;Actionable statements are &#x2018;capable of being proved false or of being reasonably interpreted as a statement of objective fact.&#x2019;&#x201D;) (quoting <underscore>Coastal Abstract Serv., Inc. v. First Am. Title Ins. Co.</underscore>, 173 F.3d 725, 731 (9th Cir. 1999)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p67" level="1">Plaintiffs stake their allegations of reliance on statements regarding the &#x201C;stability&#x201D; of Defendants' neighborhoods, but there is nothing quantifiable, falsifiable, specific, or absolute about the terms &#x201C;stability&#x201D; or &#x201C;stable.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr9" refid="f9" style="percent_n">9</footnote.reference> Here, it appears that the standard by which Plaintiffs would measure their neighborhoods' stability appears to be the number of unqualified buyers (<underscore>i.e.</underscore>, subprime mortgagors or investors) in the neighborhood, or perhaps the number of completed or pending non-judicial foreclosures. The Second Amended Complaints plead only the bald conclusion that Plaintiffs' neighborhoods are unstable.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f9"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN9.</label.designator><paratext ID="p68">&#8195;Thus, in another context: &#x201C;I find the statements that the Company's sales force was &#x2018;stable, large, experienced,&#x2019; and &#x2018;very successful&#x2019; to fall on their face within the penumbra of non actionable &#x2018;puffing.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>In re Boston Scientific Sec. Litig.</underscore>, No. 10-10593-DPW, 2011 WL 4381889, at *11 (D. Mass. Sept. 19, 2011).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p69" level="1">Plaintiffs protest that Defendants' statements about stability are neither general nor subjective claims; in support of their argument, they cite <underscore>Continental Airlines, Inc. v. McDonnell Douglas Corp.</underscore>, 216 Cal. App. 3d 388 (1989). (Opp'n (&#x201C;Kelly Opp'n&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1674, Doc. No 72) at 4.) In that case, the plaintiff, Continental Airlines, purchased DC-10 aircraft from the defendant, McDonnell Douglas, based in part on representations that &#x201C;&#x2018;[t]he fuel tank will not rupture under crash load conditions&#x2019;; that the landing gear &#x2018;are designed for wipe-off without rupturing the wing fuel tank&#x2019;&#x201D; and &#x201C;that &#x2018;the support structure is designed to a higher strength than the gear to prevent fuel tank rupture due to accidental landing gear overload.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Continental Airlines</underscore>, 216 Cal. App. 3d at 400 (brackets in original). Continental sued McDonnell Douglas after, on one flight, &#x201C;two tires burst on the left landing gear,&#x201D; causing the gear to &#x201C;br[e]ak through the tarmac, burrow[] into the ground, and [be] ripped from the wing, making a 3.7 foot hole which allowed fuel to pour from the wing fuel tanks.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 399. In sum, an airplane manufacturer represented specifically that the collapse of its aircrafts' landing gear would not rupture their fuel tanks, but that is precisely what happened. The level of specificity in McDonnell Douglas's misrepresentation, quoted above, is an order of magnitude apart from the level of specificity in Defendants' use of the word &#x201C;stable.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>b. Plaintiffs' Purchase Agreements Foreclose Reliance on Defendants' Allegedly Fraudulent Representations</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p70" level="1">Defendants further contend that the purchase agreements Plaintiffs signed prevent Plaintiffs from relying reasonably on the statements Plaintiffs now allege are fraudulent.<footnote.reference ID="fr10" refid="f10" style="percent_n">10</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f10"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN10.</label.designator><paratext ID="p71">&#8195;Insofar as some of the allegedly fraudulent representations are contained in the purchase agreements themselves, the Court questions whether Defendants' alleged failure to make good on them gives rise to a fraud claim at all (rather than a breach of contract claim). <underscore>See Garza v. Gruma Corp.</underscore>, No. C 07-02092 JW, 2009 WL 2136930, at *6 (N.D. Cal. July 16, 2009) (&#x201C;A claim that is based on a promise made in a contractual agreement is actionable as a breach of contract, not as a claim for fraud.&#x201D;) (citing <underscore>Stop Loss Ins. Brokers, Inc. v. Brown &#38; Toland Med. Group</underscore>, 143 Cal. App. 4th 1036, 1041 (2006)).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p72" level="1">For instance, Plaintiff James Dodaro signed an &#x201C;Occupancy Agreement&#x201D; requiring him to occupy his new house as his primary residence for a year, fortifying his understanding that other houses in the neighborhood would be owner-occupied. (<underscore>See</underscore> Dodaro SAC &#182; 60.) Defendant Standard Pacific Corp. filed a copy of a &#x201C;Use and Occupancy Addendum&#x201D; signed by Mr. Dodaro, in which he agreed to use his house as his principal residence, and for one year from the close of escrow, not to (among other things) sell or rent his house to someone else. (See Ex. B to Dodaro MTD (Case No. 09-1666, Doc. No. 78-3).)<footnote.reference ID="fr11" refid="f11" style="percent_n">11</footnote.reference> If Mr. Dodaro breached that agreement, Standard Pacific would be entitled to damages, including &#x201C;the amount of the appreciation&#x201D; of Mr. Dodaro's house between the time Mr. Dodaro purchased the house and the time he sold it (assuming the breach was a sale). (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Crucially, the agreement contains a disclaimer of third-party beneficiaries: &#x201C;[t]here are no third party beneficiaries to this Use and Occupancy Addendum.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f11"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN11.</label.designator><paratext ID="p73">&#8195;The Court takes judicial notice of Plaintiffs' purchase documents, as their Second Amended Complaints refer to, and rely on, them. <underscore>Swartz v. KPMG LLP</underscore>, 476 F.3d 756, 763 (9th Cir. 2007).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p74" level="1">With the Use and Occupancy Addendum, Mr. Dodaro, and every other buyer who signed the same addendum, made a promise to Standard Pacific to live in his or her house for a year. But all the buyers also agreed that none was the beneficiary of another's agreement. Thus, no buyer had a remedy against another buyer for selling his house less than a year after buying it, and none was in a position to sue Standard Pacific over another buyer's breach of the agreement.<footnote.reference ID="fr12" refid="f12" style="percent_n">12</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f12"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN12.</label.designator><paratext ID="p75">&#8195;Even if a third-party beneficiary relationship existed, a suit against Standard Pacific would be an unusual outcome. In the arrangement created by the Use and Occupancy Addendum, a buyer is the promisor, Standard Pacific the promisee, and other buyers are the putative third-party beneficiaries. A third-party beneficiary may enforce the agreement of which he is the beneficiary against a promisor (<underscore>i.e.</underscore>, another buyer), not a promisee (<underscore>i.e.</underscore>, Standard Pacific). <underscore>Souza v. Westlands Water Dist.</underscore>, 135 Cal. App. 4th 879, 893 (2006).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p76" level="1">Likewise, Defendant Lennar Corp. submitted agreements signed by Plaintiff Stella Stephens and Plaintiff Timothy Young, both of whom promised Lennar they would occupy their houses for one year. (<underscore>See</underscore> Exs. A-D to Request for Judicial Notice (&#x201C;RJN&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1668, Doc. No. 76).) Both also agreed that Lennar could offer different terms to other buyers, however, presumably including a term relieving the other buyers from occupancy requirements, which in any event, by the contract's terms, &#x201C;may be required&#x201D; (and therefore may also not be required). (<underscore>See</underscore> Ex. B to RJN at 38, 46-47.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p77" level="1">Lennar also points to portions of the agreements signed by Ms. Stephens and Mr. Young in which they &#x201C;acknowledge[d] that at no time has [Lennar] or any of its sales associates, employees, or representatives made any representation or warranties regarding tax benefits, value, price appreciation or depreciation, or future pricing adjustments,&#x201D; and further, &#x201C;that the California real estate market reacts to economic and other conditions that may cause the price of housing to fluctuate. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> At the sole discretion of [Lennar], and without notice to [Plaintiffs], the purchase price [and] terms of purchase <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> are subject to change from time to time.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> at 46-47.) Most critically, Lennar disclaims any representation that it &#x201C;will refrain from any pricing program, product design program, development strategy or marketing plan which in any manner adversely affects the value of the Property.&#x201D; (Ex. A to RJN at 10.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p78" level="1">Another Defendant, D.R. Horton, Inc., filed an agreement executed by Plaintiff Remedios Martinez, which stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p79" first-line="2" turnover="1">As Seller may have previously disclosed to you, even when the Occupancy Addendum was in use, Seller could not guarantee that the Project would be entirely owner-occupied. In addition, Seller had no obligation to enforce the Occupancy Addendum.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p80" first-line="2" turnover="1">Seller has now elected to discontinue using the Addendum. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> Because Seller will no longer ask buyers to make these representations, there is a possibility that there may be fewer owner-occupied residences within the Community.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p81" contd-flag="y">(Ex. 2 to Martinez MTD.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p82" level="1">Additionally, Defendants' agreements were fully integrated, containing clauses to the effect of &#x201C;[a]ll prior statements and representations, whether oral or written, are hereby superseded by this Purchase Agreement <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> this Purchase Agreement shall constitute the complete and exclusive statement of its terms.&#x201D; (Ex. 1 to Martinez MTD at 10.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p83" level="1">From this foundation, Defendants argue that Plaintiffs simply could not have relied reasonably on representations made outside the four corners of the agreements, particularly where those representations are either contradicted or disclaimed by the agreements.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p84" level="1">Plaintiffs argue in response that Defendants' disclaimers are insufficient to make their reliance on Defendants' alleged misrepresentations unreasonable. (<underscore>See</underscore> Opp'n (&#x201C;Nielsen Opp'n&#x201D;) (Case No. 09-1673, Doc. No. 65) at 17-18).) Plaintiffs point to <underscore>Broberg v. Guardian Life Ins. Co. of Am.</underscore>, 171 Cal. App. 4th 912 (2009), in which the court of appeal discussed the effectiveness of disclaimers. The court noted &#x201C;[a] plaintiff will be denied recovery only if his conduct is manifestly unreasonable in the light of his own intelligence or information. It must appear that he put faith in representations that were preposterous or shown by facts within his observation to be so patently and obviously false that he must have closed his eyes to avoid discovery of the truth.&#x201D; <underscore>Broberg</underscore>, 171 Cal. App. 4th at 921-22 (brackets in original, internal quotations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p85" level="1">In <underscore>Broberg</underscore>, a Dr. Powell relied on the representations of an insurance salesman that a life insurance policy would generate earnings sufficient to cover the policy's premiums by the policy's 12th year. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 915. Those statements were echoed in the marketing materials for the policy; the policy itself had &#x201C;inconsistent language&#x201D; on the point. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 916. When it turned out that the policy did not generate earnings sufficient to cover its premiums, the trustees of Dr. Powell's trust sued; the defendant, Guardian Life Insurance Co., argued among other things that it disclaimed effectively the representation that the policy would pay for itself after 11 years. The court of appeal held that where the defendant buried disclaimers and issued a policy illustration &#x201C;contain[ing] deceptive language and figures indicating Powell's out-of-pocket payments will &#x2018;vanish,&#x2019;&#x201D; a court could not find the disclaimers effective as a matter of law. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 922.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p86" level="1">While <underscore>Broberg</underscore>'s analysis is relevant to this matter, the facts in the present case do not compel <underscore>Broberg</underscore>'s conclusion. Here, most of the representations that Plaintiffs took to mean, implicitly, that they were buying houses in &#x201C;stable&#x201D; communities, surrounded by &#x201C;qualified&#x201D; buyers, appear in the same documents as the disclaimers. There is no deceptive language, nor are there deceptive pictures. Instead, Plaintiffs allege to have been given a deceptive impression of the nature of their neighborhoods based on the straightforward terms of their purchase agreements. And unlike in <underscore>Broberg</underscore>, there are no allegations &#8211; or at least, no allegations that satisfy Rule 9(b) &#8211; that Plaintiffs were cajoled by oral representations into seeing more in their purchase agreements than what is actually there.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p87" level="1">Consequently, the Court concludes that even if Defendants made actionable representations, rather than merely puffing, Defendants disclaimed those representations effectively, sometimes in the very same documents where the representations themselves appeared. The Court therefore finds that Plaintiffs fail to state fraud claims based on false representations.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>c. Defendants Had No Duty to Disclose the Presence or Concentration of &#x201C;Unqualified&#x201D; Purchasers</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p88" level="1">In California, &#x201C;[a] seller of real property has a common law duty to disclose &#x2018;where the seller knows of facts materially affecting the value or desirability of the property which are known or accessible only to him and also knows that such facts are not known to, or within the reach of the diligent attention and observation of the buyer. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Alfaro v. Cmty. Housing Improvement Sys. &#38; Planning Ass'n</underscore>, 171 Cal. App. 4th 1356, 1382 (2009) (quoting <underscore>Lingsch v. Savage</underscore>, 213 Cal. App. 2d 729, 735 (1963)). Plaintiffs allege Defendants therefore owed them a duty to disclose that they were selling houses to &#x201C;unqualified&#x201D; buyers, as the presence of such buyers &#8211; or the wave of foreclosures following in their wake &#8211; diminished the value of Plaintiffs' property. The Court disagrees with Plaintiffs.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p89" level="1">Plaintiffs depict themselves as people &#x201C;who did everything right,&#x201D; in juxtaposition with &#x201C;unqualified and high-foreclosure-risk buyers.&#x201D; (Dodaro SAC &#182; 45.) From this premise, Plaintiffs argue Defendants had a duty to warn them of the presence of feckless debtors, as sure as they would have been obligated to warn of a neighbor who creates a nuisance by, for example, regularly pouring motor oil all over the roof of his house. <underscore>See Alexander v. McKnight</underscore>, 7 Cal. App. 4th 973, 976 (1992) (affirming the trial court's conclusion that the plaintiffs had a duty, on selling their house, to inform the buyer that their neighbors are nuisances).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p90" level="1">The Court declines to analogize an indebted neighbor to one who creates a noxious nuisance on his or her property. Whatever risk one's neighbors' insolvency may pose to real property values, their debts do not besmirch them in the eyes of the law; &#x201C;[i]nsolvency is often, maybe most often, simply the result of bad luck, and our society closed its debtors' prisons long ago.&#x201D; <underscore>Chapin v. Knight-Ridder, Inc.</underscore>, 993 F.2d 1087, 1094 (4th Cir. 1993). As the Court observed previously, subprime mortgages went generally to people who were cash-poor but house-rich (or became house-rich, if they got purchase-money mortgages). Those borrowers, and their lenders, took a permissible risk, in a skyrocketing housing market, even if it appears with the benefit of hindsight the creditors' (and debtors') profligacy was enormously misguided.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p91" level="1">Even if, as Plaintiffs argue, the presence of certain buyers (in this case, highly leveraged debtors) in a neighborhood materially affects the value or desirability of all the property therein, the Court's analysis does not change.<footnote.reference ID="fr13" refid="f13" style="percent_n">13</footnote.reference> At what point does the presence or concentration of such buyers mandate disclosure? As Defendants observe, Plaintiffs have yet to define adequately whose presence Defendants were required to make known, and what level of detail regarding those buyers (or would-be buyers) Defendants should have disclosed. Plaintiffs respond that Defendants need not have disclosed any particular person's financial information, but instead that they &#x201C;were obligated to disclose their practice of selling homes to high-foreclosure risk buyers, including subprime buyers, their expectation as to how many of the homes would be sold to such buyers, and the percentage of homes in the development neighborhoods which were sold to such buyers,&#x201D; as those sales &#x201C;fraudulently <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> maintain[ed] high prices in neighborhoods that, based on the buyers to whom [Defendants] were selling, did not warrant those prices.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr14" refid="f14" style="percent_n">14</footnote.reference> (Nielsen Opp'n at 8, 11.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f13"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN13.</label.designator><paratext ID="p92">&#8195;Given the basis for Plaintiffs' claims &#8211; that Defendants had a duty to disclose sales to certain people, <underscore>i.e.</underscore>, subprime mortgagors &#8211; Plaintiffs' discussion of the duty to disclose &#x201C;nuisances or other conditions of nearby <underscore>properties</underscore>&#x201D; (Nielsen Opp'n at 4) (emphasis added), is inapposite. Subprime mortgagors are neither a nuisance nor a condition of real property.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f14"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN14.</label.designator><paratext ID="p93">&#8195;That the presence of many subprime mortgagors allegedly buoyed prices raises the question whether one must disclose hidden facts that <underscore>increase</underscore> the value of property. Unsurprisingly, there appears to be no case law on this issue, because few people sue when the value of their property unexpectedly goes up.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p94" level="1">In the absence of any authority imposing such a duty on sellers to disclose whether they are selling to &#x201C;high-foreclosure risk buyers,&#x201D; the Court declines to create one here, particularly without any meaningful criteria delineating precisely who those buyers are. Moreover, such a duty would only apply, realistically, at the time of a house's first sale in a neighborhood owned entirely by one developer, with knowledge of how all the other houses were being financed, because once houses are placed for sale on the secondary market (or if their original buyers encumber them with additional mortgages), the developer has no way of knowing how many houses in its development are owned by &#x201C;high-foreclosure risk buyers.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr15" refid="f15" style="percent_n">15</footnote.reference> And such a duty, if it applied to sellers, could impose a vast burden &#8211; unlike, for example, the duty to disclose that a murder occurred in a house, the sort of uncommon event a seller is required to disclose under <underscore>Reed v. King</underscore>, 145 Cal. App. 3d 261 (1983). <underscore>See Reed</underscore> 145 Cal. App. 3d at 267 (finding that &#x201C;[m]urder is not such a common occurrence that <underscore>buyers</underscore> should be charged with anticipating and discovering this disquieting possibility,&#x201D; and thereby charging sellers with a duty to disclose it) (emphasis in original).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f15"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN15.</label.designator><paratext ID="p95">&#8195;That is, no way other than that equally available to the buyer: searching for recorded deeds of trust.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p96" level="1">Given these considerations, and beginning from the premise that &#x201C;[c]oncepts of real property are deeply rooted in state traditions, customs, habits, and laws,&#x201D; <underscore>Reconstr. Fin. Corp. v. Beaver Cnty.</underscore>, 328 U.S. 204, 209 (1946), the Court will leave the imposition of a duty to disclose the presence and concentration of &#x201C;high-foreclosure risk buyers&#x201D; to the California State Legislature.<footnote.reference ID="fr16" refid="f16" style="percent_n">16</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f16"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN16.</label.designator><paratext ID="p97">&#8195;Plaintiffs also argue that Defendants must disclose the presence of &#x201C;high foreclosure-risk buyers&#x201D; to rehabilitate the misrepresentations they allegedly made about the stability of Plaintiffs' neighborhoods. (<underscore>See</underscore> Nielsen Opp'n at 11-12.) As the Court concludes Defendants made no misrepresentations about stability, Plaintiffs' argument fails.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>D. Plaintiffs Fail to State a Claim for Negligent Misrepresentation</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p98" level="1">A claim for negligent misrepresentation, like a claim for fraud, requires &#x201C;the misrepresentation of a past or existing material fact&#x201D; on which a plaintiff justifiably relied. <underscore>Wells Fargo Bank, N.A. v. FSI, Fin. Solutions, Inc.</underscore>, 196 Cal. App. 4th 1559, 1573 (2011) (internal quotation omitted). As the Court concludes Plaintiffs fail to allege both misrepresentations and justifiable reliance, their claims for negligent misrepresentation fail.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>E. Plaintiffs Fail to State Claims for False Advertising Under California Business and Professions Code &#167;&#167; 17500, <underscore>et seq.</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p99" level="1">Plaintiffs' claims for false advertising under California Business and Professions Code &#167;&#167; 17500, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>, fail for the same reason their claims of fraud based on affirmative misrepresentations fail: Defendants' allegedly misleading assertions, <underscore>e.g.</underscore>, of &#x201C;stability,&#x201D; or family-orientation, are too vague to be actionable under Section 17500. <underscore>See, e.g., Williams v. Gerber Prods. Co.</underscore>, 552 F.3d 934, 939 n.3 (9th Cir. 2008) (positing the statement that fruit snacks are &#x201C;nutritious&#x201D; could constitute puffery, &#x201C;since nutriousness can be difficult to measure concretely&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>F. Plaintiffs Also Fail to State Claims for Unfair Competition under California Business and Professions Code &#167;&#167; 17200, <underscore>et seq.</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p100" level="1">California's Unfair Competition Law (&#x201C;UCL&#x201D;), Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167;&#167; 17200, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>, establishes three varieties of unfair competition: engaging in acts that are unlawful, engaging in acts that are unfair, and engaging in acts that are fraudulent. <underscore>Cel-Tech Commc'ns, Inc. v. L.A. Cellular Tel. Co.</underscore>, 20 Cal. 4th 163, 180 (1999). Plaintiffs allege Defendants engaged in all three varieties of violations. Defendants allegedly engaged in unlawful activity by violating California Civil Code &#167; 1709; allegedly engaged in fraudulent activity by failing &#x201C;to disclose material facts about the communities in which [Plaintiffs'] home[s] would be located, and misrepresent[ing] the nature of those communities&#x201D;; and allegedly engaged in unfair activity by &#x201C;process[ing] loans for buyers that falsified and inflated unverified income.&#x201D; (Dodaro SAC &#182; 104.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p101" level="1">The unlawful activity in which Defendants allegedly engaged, <underscore>i.e.</underscore>, violations of California Civil Code &#167; 1709, consists of &#x201C;willfully deceiv[ing] another with intent to induce him to alter his position to his injury or risk,&#x201D; Cal. Civ. Code &#167; 1709 &#8211; in other words, committing fraud. <underscore>See Express, LLC v. Fetish Group, Inc.</underscore>, 464 F. Supp. 2d 965, 971-72 (C.D. Cal. 2006) (setting forth the elements of &#x201C;fraudulent deceit&#x201D; under Section 1709; they are the elements of common-law fraud). Given the Court's conclusion that Plaintiffs fail to state claims for fraud, their UCL-unlawful activity claims, premised on fraud, fail.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p102" level="1">The fraudulent activity in which Plaintiffs allege Defendants engaged is run-of-the-mill fraud; however, Plaintiffs can show a violation of the UCL without satisfying all of the elements ordinarily necessary to prove fraud. Fraudulent activity under the UCL, &#x201C;&#x2018;unlike common law fraud, can be shown even if no one was actually deceived, relied upon the fraudulent practice, or sustained any damage.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>StreamCast Networks, Inc. v. IBIS LLC</underscore>, No. CV 05-04239 MMM (Ex), 2006 WL 5720345, at *11 (C.D. Cal. May 2, 2006) (quoting <underscore>Prata v. Sup. Ct.</underscore>, 91 Cal. App. 4th 1128, 1146 (2001)). Instead, a plaintiff &#x201C;need only show that &#x2018;members of the public are likely to be deceived.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Searle v. Wyndham Int'l, Inc.</underscore>, 102 Cal. App. 4th 1327, 1333 (2002) (internal citation omitted). Thus, rather than asking whether a person's reliance on Defendants' alleged representations was reasonable, the Court now asks whether a reasonable member of the public is likely to be deceived by Defendants' representations. <underscore>See Williams</underscore>, 552 F.3d at 938 (observing that the reasonable consumer standard applies to claims under the UCL). The Court concludes that a reasonable member of the public would not be deceived by Defendants' puffery, for the same reason that Plaintiffs' reliance on that puffery would be unjustified: the allegedly deceptive statements are so subjective as to be almost entirely devoid of meaning.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p103" level="1">Lastly, the unfair activity Plaintiffs allege is Defendants' improper verification of the income of various other borrowers, in violation of the policy set forth in 66 Fed. Reg. 65601. Plaintiffs' unfair activity claim is misplaced, as the California courts interpret the &#x201C;unfair activity&#x201D; prong of the UCL to address &#x201C;unfair methods of competition&#x201D;; that is, &#x201C;action[s] by a competitor&#x201D; in a case where the plaintiff is &#x201C;alleging anticompetitive practices.&#x201D; <underscore>Cal-Tech Commc'ns</underscore>, 20 Cal. 4th at 186-87 &#38; n.12. Consumers, like Plaintiffs, are limited to actions &#x201C;alleging other kinds of violations of the unfair competition law such as &#x2018;fraudulent&#x2019; or &#x2018;unlawful&#x2019; business practices or &#x2018;unfair, deceptive, untrue or misleading advertising.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore>, at 187 n.12. Further, as discussed in note 8, <underscore>supra</underscore>, the policy set forth in 66 Fed. Reg. 65601 does not apply to purchase-money mortgages; consequently, it does not apply to the loans Defendants were making.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p104" level="1">The Court therefore concludes Plaintiffs fail to state a claim under the UCL.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>G. On Plaintiffs' Facts, There is No Breach of the Covenant of Good Faith and Fair Dealing</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p105" level="1">Lastly, Plaintiffs raise a claim for breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing. An implied &#x201C;covenant of good faith is read into contracts in order to protect the express covenants or promises of the contract, not to protect some general public policy interest not directly tied to the contract's purpose.&#x201D; <underscore>Foley v. Interactive Data Corp.</underscore>, 47 Cal. 3d 654, 690 (1988). &#x201C;&#x2018;[T]he covenant is implied as a <underscore>supplement</underscore> to the express contractual covenants, to prevent a contracting party from engaging in conduct which (while not technically transgressing the express covenants) frustrates the other party's rights to the benefits of the contract.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Racine &#38; Laramie, Ltd. v. Dep't of Parks &#38; Rec.</underscore>, 11 Cal. App. 4th 1026, 1031-32 (1992) (quoting <underscore>Love v. Fire Ins. Exch.</underscore>, 221 Cal. App. 3d 1136, 1153 (1990)) (emphasis in original). While the covenant of good faith and fair dealing supplements express contractual covenants, it remains tethered to them; it &#x201C;is limited to assuring compliance with the <underscore>express terms</underscore> of the contract, and cannot be extended to create obligations not contemplated by the contract.&#x201D; <underscore>Pasadena Live, LLC v. City of Pasadena</underscore>, 114 Cal. App. 4th 1089, 1094 (2004) (emphasis in original).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p106" level="1">Here, Plaintiffs attempt to divert the covenant of good faith and fair dealing from its purposes, thereby saddling Defendants with obligations they bargained expressly not to undertake. Plaintiffs allege their purchase agreements with Defendants obligated Defendants to &#x201C;build and sell to [a Homeowner] a home in the community identified in the agreement&#x201D; (Dodaro SAC &#182; 129), but Defendants sullied the communities by &#x201C;selling houses to subprime borrowers and investors&#x201D; (Dodaro SAC &#182; 131). Indeed, Plaintiffs allege, even if the houses they received were &#x201C;not yet in a community materially worse than represented, the community [Defendants] ultimately delivered was worse than represented.&#x201D; (Dodaro SAC &#182; 133.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p107" level="1">Plaintiffs recognize, as they must, that Defendants reserved expressly the rights to, <underscore>e.g.</underscore>, implement &#x201C;a pricing program, product design program, development strategy or marketing plan which in any manner adversely affects the value of the Property.&#x201D; (Ex. A to RJN at 10.) Defendants promised Plaintiffs a wide variety of amenities while reserving this right, and there is no allegation that Defendants failed to deliver on any contractual items that were promised explicitly. Instead, Plaintiffs allege that Defendants exercised the discretion reserved to them in bad faith by selling houses to investors and subprime mortgagors. Accepting that argument, however, swallows an express provision of the contract for which Defendants bargained: that they could sell houses to whomever they wanted, at whatever price they wanted, even if such sales affected the values of Plaintiffs' houses adversely. On Plaintiffs' allegations, the Court thus can find no breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p108" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court finds as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p109" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">1. Plaintiffs allege causation sufficiently to establish standing to bring claims for damages stemming from the diminished value of their houses;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p110" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">2. Plaintiffs allege some fraudulent acts with the degree of specificity required under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 9(b);</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p111" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">3. Plaintiffs' claims for fraud, negligent misrepresentation, and false advertising are time-barred;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p112" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">4. Plaintiffs shall not have leave to amend those claims, as they fail on their merits;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p113" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">5. Plaintiffs' claims for violations of the UCL and for breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing also fail;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p114" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">6. Plaintiffs' Second Amended Complaints are therefore DISMISSED without leave to amend;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p115" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">7. Defendants' Motions to Strike are DENIED as MOOT.</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p116" level="1">Dated: <underscore>March 26, 2012</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>