<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>UNTIED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>EASTERN DISTRICT OF MICHIGAN</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>SOUTHERN DIVISION</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>BRANDON CASPER and ANGELA CASPER, Plaintiffs,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment> NATIONSTAR MORTGAGE LLC, et al., Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>CASE NO. 2:14-cv-14251</docket.line>
<docket.number>2:14-cv-14251</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:14-cv-14251-MOB-DRG Doc</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 06/02/2015</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>OPINION AND ORDER GRANTING DEFENDANTS' MOTION TO DISMISS</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1"> HON. MARIANNE O. BATTANI</judge.line>
<judge.line first-line="1">MARIANNE O. BATTANI United States District Judge</judge.line>
<judge.line first-line="1"><underscore>s/ Kay Doaks</underscore> Case Manager</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. INTRODUCTION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">This matter is before the Court on Defendants' Motion to Dismiss pursuant to Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(b)(6). (Doc. 13.) Plaintiff has brought an eleven-count complaint alleging claims ranging from violations of Michigan's loan modification statute to fraud to violations of the Truth in Lending Act. (Compl.) For the following reasons, the Court <bold>GRANTS</bold> Defendants' Motion to Dismiss.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. STATEMENT OF FACTS</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On January 29, 2004, Plaintiffs, Brandon and Angela Casper, executed a loan agreement in the amount of $203,000 (the &#x201C;Note&#x201D;), payable to David Piccinini, Inc. (&#x201C;Piccinini&#x201D;). Plaintiffs also granted a mortgage on property located at 52849 Turnberry Drive, Chesterfield, Michigan (&#x201C;the Property&#x201D;) to Mortgage Electronic Registration Systems, Inc. (&#x201C;MERS&#x201D;). (Doc. 13, Exs. A, B.) On May 27, 2011, MERS assigned the mortgage to Deutsche Bank National Trust Company (&#x201C;Deutsche Bank&#x201D;), and the assignment was recorded on June 2, 2011, with the Macomb County Register of Deeds. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> at Ex. C.) Likewise, the Note was also sold by Piccinini to Deutsche Bank sometime between 2004 and 2008. (<underscore>See</underscore> Compl. &#182;&#182; 13-14.) Beginning in 2008, the loan was serviced by Bank of America, N.A. (&#x201C;BANA&#x201D;), but these servicing rights were later transferred to Nationstar Mortgage, LLC, (&#x201C;Nationstar&#x201D;) in July 2013.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">In 2008, Plaintiffs allege that they suffered an economic hardship and contacted BANA to request a loan modification. BANA purportedly informed Plaintiffs that the only way they could qualify for a loan modification would be to fall behind in their payments. Consequently, Plaintiffs stopped making mortgage payments and continued to pursue a loan modification. Plaintiffs allege that the loan modification process was essentially a sham intended to force Plaintiffs into default and their home into foreclosure. The complaint advances the familiar concept of &#x201C;Paperwork Hell&#x201D; wherein BANA is alleged to have continuously represented that they had not received all necessary paperwork to evaluate Plaintiffs' eligibility for a loan modification. (Compl. &#182;&#182; 50-51.) BANA ultimately determined that Plaintiffs failed to qualify for a modification and denied their application. (Compl. &#182; 56.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">At some unspecified time, BANA began foreclosure by advertisement proceedings. (Compl. &#182; 58-59.) In early 2012, Plaintiffs were provided with another opportunity to apply for a modification. (Compl. &#182; 72.) Once again, Plaintiffs were found not to qualify, which they attribute to a gross miscalculation of their monthly income. (Compl. &#182; 75.) In September 2012, Plaintiffs filed their first lawsuit against BANA and Deutsche Bank, which was dismissed without prejudice to allow for further modification negotiations. (Compl. &#182;&#182; 84-85.) Because Plaintiffs were determined for a third time not to qualify for a modification, Nationstar initiated foreclosure by advertisement proceedings and scheduled a sheriff's sale for August 1, 2014.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Plaintiffs filed the present lawsuit on July 28, 2014, just prior to the sheriff's sale, in Macomb County Circuit Court. On July 28, 2014, a state court judge granted an Ex Parte Motion for Temporary Restraining Order enjoining the sheriff's sale on the Property and scheduling a show cause hearing for July 30, 2014. It is unclear whether this hearing took place. Presently, the Property has yet to be sold at a sheriff's sale. On November 5, 2014, Defendants removed the suit to this Court. The eleven-count complaint advances the following claims: (1) violation of Mich. Comp. Laws &#167;&#167; 600.3204(1) and (3); (2) violation of Mich. Comp. Laws &#167;&#167; 600.3204(4), 600.3205a, and 600.3205c; (3) violation of Truth in Lending Act relating to a forged assignment; (4) breach of contract; (5) intentional fraud; (6) constructive fraud; (7) violation of the Truth in Lending Act: Regulation Z; (8) violation of the Michigan Collection Practices Act; (9) violation of Michigan's Occupational Code; (10) violation of the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act; and (11) violation of the Mortgage Brokers, Lenders, and Servicers Licensing Act.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">On December 12, 2014, Defendants filed the instant motion to dismiss. Since the filing of that motion, Plaintiffs' attorney withdrew himself as counsel. Plaintiffs have no replacement counsel and have not filed a response to Defendants' motion.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. STANDARD OF REVIEW</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">In order to survive a motion to dismiss pursuant to Rule 12(b)(6), a complaint must &#x201C;contain sufficient factual matter, accepted as true, to state a claim to relief that is plausible on its face.&#x201D; <underscore>Ashcroft v. Iqbal</underscore>, 556 U.S. 662, 678 (2009) (quoting <underscore>Bell Atl. Corp. v. Twombly</underscore>, 550 U.S., 544, 570 (2007)). A claim that is plausible &#x201C;pleads factual content that allows the court to draw the reasonable inference&#x201D; and demonstrates &#x201C;more than a sheer possibility&#x201D; that the plaintiff's claim has merit. <underscore>Id.</underscore> A complaint that offers &#x201C;&#x2018;labels and conclusions&#x2019; or a &#x2018;formulaic recitation of the elements of a cause of action will not do.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> While a court must accept as true all factual allegations set forth in a plaintiff's complaint, it is not bound to accept as true a legal conclusion or a legal conclusion couched as a factual allegation. <underscore>Id.</underscore> All legal conclusions must be supported by the factual allegations. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 679.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">In deciding a motion to dismiss, &#x201C;courts must consider the complaint in its entirety, as well as other sources courts ordinarily examine when ruling on Rule 12(b)(6) motions to dismiss, in particular, documents incorporated into the complaint by reference, and matters of which a court may take judicial notice.&#x201D; <underscore>Tellabs, Inc. v. Makor Issues &#38; Rights, Ltd.</underscore>, 551 U.S. 308, 322 (2007). Further, the Sixth Circuit has found that courts may consider documents not formally incorporated by reference but that are referred to in the complaint and are central to the plaintiff's claim. <underscore>See Greenberg v. Life Ins. Co.</underscore>, 177 F.3d 507, 514 (6th Cir. 1999).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Count I &#8211; Foreclosure in Violation of Mich. Comp. Laws &#167; 600.3204</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">This count challenges both the record chain of title to the Note and the validity of the assignment of the Note. Plaintiffs, as nonparties to the assignment, lack standing to challenge any aspect of the assignment unless they can show a risk that they will be subject to double liability on their debt. <underscore>See Livonia Props. Holdings, LLC v. 12840-12976 Farmington Rd. Holdings, LLC</underscore>, 399 F. App'x 97, 102 (6th Cir. 2010) (&#x201C;[E]ven if there were a flaw in the assignment, [plaintiff] does not have standing to raise that flaw to challenge [defendant's] chain of title. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> [T]here is ample authority to support the proposition that &#x2018;a litigant who is not a party to an assignment lacks standing to challenge that assignment.&#x2019;&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Further, to the extent Plaintiffs attempt to invalidate the foreclosure proceedings on the theory that the promissory note was severed from the mortgage, this position lacks merit. Michigan law is quite clear that there is no requirement that the record title holder of the mortgage also possess the underlying Note in order to proceed with foreclosure. <underscore>See Residential Funding Co. LLC v. Saurman</underscore>, 490 Mich. 909, 910 (2011) (&#x201C;&#x2018;It has never been necessary that the mortgage should be given directly to the beneficiaries. The security is always made in trust to secure obligations, and the trust and the beneficial interest need not be in the same hands. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> The choice of a mortgagee is a matter of convenience.&#x2019;&#x201D;) (quoting <underscore>Adams v. Niemann</underscore>, 46 Mich. 135, 137 (Mich. 1881)). Accordingly, Plaintiffs' challenges to the chain of title and assignments of the mortgage must fail.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Count II &#8211; Violation of the Michigan Loan Modification Statute</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Count II of the complaint sets forth a claim alleging Defendants' failure to comply with Michigan's loan modification statutes, namely Mich. Comp. Laws &#167;&#167; 600.3204(4), 600.3205a, and 600.3205c. These provisions generally compelled lenders, before commencing foreclosure by advertisement proceedings, to give borrowers notice of the option to request a loan modification and to determine whether the borrower qualified for a loan modification. However, each of these statutory provisions has been repealed &#8211; while repeal of section 3204(4) became effective June 19, 2014, repeal of sections 3205a through 3205d became effective June 30, 2013. <underscore>See</underscore> Mich. Comp. Laws &#167; 600.3205e (2012); 2014 Mich. Leg. Serv. P.A. 125 (H.B. 5277). In the present case, no foreclosure sale has yet taken place. The foreclosure proceedings have been pending since June 2014, after the repeal of sections 3205a through 3205d. Consequently, Defendants are not compelled to comply with the loan modification framework set forth by those provisions.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">As for Plaintiffs' claim arising under section 3204(4), it is unclear whether foreclosure proceedings were commenced before or after repeal of this provision. Plaintiff does not specify in what manner section 3204(4) was violated and cites only to section 3204(4)(g), which provides that a party shall not commence foreclosure proceedings on a property claimed as a principal residence if &#x201C;[c]alculations under section 3205c(1) show that the mortgagor is eligible for a loan modification and foreclosure under this chapter is not allowed under section 3205c(7).&#x201D; As discussed above, however, at the time foreclosure proceedings were initiated in June 2014, section 3205c had been repealed. Therefore, Defendants were not required to comply with section 3204(4)(g), and the Count II claims must fail.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>C. Counts III and VII &#8211; Violation of the Truth in Lending Act (&#x201C;TILA&#x201D;), 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1641(g) and Regulation Z, 12 C.F.R. &#167; 226.39</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Both of these claims relate to Defendants' alleged failure to notify Plaintiffs of the assignments of the mortgage and loan. The assignment of the Plaintiffs' mortgage took place on May 27, 2011, while the assignment of the interest in the Note took place sometime between 2004, when the loan agreement was executed, and 2008, when Piccinini went out of business. (<underscore>See</underscore> Compl. &#182;&#182; 13-15.) Both of these claims are therefore time-barred by TILA's one-year statute of limitations. <underscore>See</underscore> 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1640(e) (&#x201C;[A]ny action under this section may be brought in any United States district court, or in any other court of competent jurisdiction, within one year from the date of the occurrence of the violation.&#x201D;). To the extent that Plaintiffs allege that the statute of limitations should be equitably tolled based on Defendants' fraudulent concealment of the transfers, the complaint is utterly devoid of pleadings supporting an assertion of fraudulent concealment. A statute of limitations can be equitably tolled only where the plaintiff alleges: &#x201C;(1) the defendant took affirmative steps to conceal the plaintiff's cause of action; and (2) the plaintiff could not have discovered the cause of action despite exercising due diligence.&#x201D; <underscore>Jarrett v. Kassel</underscore>, 872 F.2d 1415, 1423 (6th Cir. 1992). No facts have been asserted here demonstrating what steps Defendants took to conceal a publicly recorded transfer or why Plaintiffs were unable to discover the transfer in spite of due diligence. Accordingly, Counts III and VII must be dismissed as barred by the statute of limitations.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>D. Count IV &#8211; Breach of Contract</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Plaintiffs allege that Defendants breached the mortgage contract by misallocating funds paid by Plaintiffs during the loan modification review process and during a trial period. Instead of crediting Plaintiffs' account for payments made, the funds were instead placed into a &#x201C;suspense account,&#x201D; thereby resulting in an inflated reinstatement quote. It is further alleged that Defendants breached the contract by failing to send Plaintiffs the required notice of the transfer of the servicing rights from BANA to Nationstar. To state a claim of breach of contract under Michigan law, a plaintiff must establish: &#x201C;(1) that there was a contract, (2) that the other party breached the contract and, (3) that the party asserting breach of contract suffered damages as a result of the breach.&#x201D; <underscore>Dunn v. Bennett</underscore>, 303 Mich. App. 767, 774 (Mich. Ct. App. 2014). Additionally, in Michigan, one who initially breaches a contract cannot maintain an action against the other contracting party for a subsequent breach. <underscore>Michaels v. Amway Corp.</underscore>, 206 Mich. App. 644, 650 (Mich. Ct. App. 1994).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Assuming Plaintiffs' allegations to be true, they claim that Defendants breached the contract during the loan modification review process. By Plaintiffs' own admission in their complaint, Defendants did not begin the loan modification process until Plaintiffs defaulted on their payments. (Compl. &#182;&#182; 44-45.) Likewise, Nationstar did not become the mortgage servicer until 2013, well after Plaintiffs defaulted. Therefore, Plaintiffs were the first parties to breach the contract, and, consequently, cannot maintain an action for breach of contract against the Defendants. <underscore>See Michaels</underscore>, 206 Mich. App. at 650. Accordingly, the breach of contract claim should be dismissed.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>E. Counts V and VI &#8211; Intentional and Constructive Fraud</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">In order to set forth an actionable case of fraud under Michigan law, a plaintiff must plead the following facts:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p17" first-line="1" turnover="1">(1) That defendant made a material representation; (2) that it was false; (3) that when he made it he knew that it was false, or made it recklessly, without any knowledge of its truth and as a positive assertion; (4) that he made it with the intention that it should be acted upon by plaintiff; (5) that plaintiff acted in reliance upon it; and (6) that he thereby suffered injury. Each of these facts must be proved with a reasonable degree of certainty, and all of them must be found to exist; the absence of any one of them is fatal to a recovery.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p18" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Hi-Way Motor Co. v. Int'l Harvester Co.</underscore>, 398 Mich. 330, 336 (1976) (internal quotations omitted). Further, Fed. R. Civ. P. 9(b) requires that the circumstances surrounding an alleged fraud be pleaded with particularity.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Plaintiffs allege that Defendants falsely informed them that their loan modification application paperwork was incomplete. However, the pleadings do not plausibly allege how Plaintiffs were injured in acting in reliance upon these representations. Plaintiffs argue that the representations prolonged the modification process such that they became mired so deeply in debt that they were foreclosed from reinstating the original mortgage and from exploring other options. However, as discussed above, they do not allege that they would have been able to reinstate the original mortgage absent any misrepresentations &#8211; after all, Plaintiffs could have resumed making their original payments in order to decrease the overall amount in default.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">The remaining claims of fraud concern Defendants' representation to Plaintiffs that if they defaulted on their mortgage payments and applied for a modification, Defendants would not foreclose and would instead grant them a modification to a lower payment. In reality, Plaintiffs allege that Defendants had no intention of offering a modification. Firstly, it is well-settled that &#x201C;an action for fraudulent misrepresentation must be predicated upon a statement relating to a past or an existing fact. Future promises are contractual and do not constitute fraud.&#x201D; <underscore>Hi-Way Motor Co.</underscore>, 398 Mich. at 336. Defendants' future promises to modify the loan therefore do not constitute actionable fraud. Secondly, Michigan's statute of frauds requires that any agreement by a financial institution to modify a loan agreement or refrain from initiating foreclosure proceedings be made in writing and be signed by an authorized agent of the financial institution. <underscore>See</underscore> Mich. Comp. Laws &#167; 566.132. The statute provides in pertinent part:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p21" first-line="1" turnover="1">(2) An action shall not be brought against a financial institution to enforce any of the following promises or commitments of the financial institution unless the promise or commitment is in writing and signed with an authorized signature by the financial institution:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" first-line="2" turnover="2">(a) A promise or commitment to lend money, grant or extend credit, or make any other financial accommodation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" first-line="2" turnover="2">(b) A promise or commitment to renew, extend, modify, or permit a delay in repayment or performance of a loan, extension of credit, or other financial accommodation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" first-line="2" turnover="2">(c) A promise or commitment to waive a provision of a loan, extension of credit, or other financial accommodation.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p25" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Id.</underscore> Case law has strictly applied the statute of frauds as a bar against any claim against a financial institution seeking to enforce an oral representation unsupported by a written document. <underscore>See Crown Tech. Park v. D&#38;N Bank, FSB</underscore>, 242 Mich. App. 538, 550 (Mich. Ct. App. 2000) (&#x201C;This language is unambiguous. It plainly states that a party is precluded from bringing a claim &#8211; no matter its label &#8211; against a financial institution to enforce the terms of an oral promise to waive a loan provision.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">In a case presenting a similar theory of fraud, a plaintiff claimed that a representative of the defendant loan servicer recommended he stop making his mortgage payments and reapply for a modification after his first missed payment. <underscore>Loeffler v. BAC Home Loans Servicing, L.P.</underscore>, No. 11-cv-13711, 2012 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 26604 at *2 (E.D. Mich. Feb. 29, 2012). The plaintiff alleged that after defaulting and while his modification application was being processed, defendants initiated foreclosure proceedings on his property. <underscore>Id.</underscore> The court ultimately rejected plaintiff's fraud and misrepresentation claims because the statute of fraud bars claims based on oral agreements. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at *5.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">In the present case, Plaintiffs do not allege the existence of any written and signed agreement promising to modify their loan. Therefore, Counts V and VI must fail.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>F. Count VIII &#8211; Violation of Michigan Collection Practices Act (&#x201C;MCPA&#x201D;), Mich. Comp. Laws &#167; 445.251 et seq.</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Plaintiffs assert their MCPA claim only against Nationstar, the current loan servicer &#8211; the complaint alleges that Nationstar &#x201C;masqueraded&#x201D; as Plaintiffs' mortgagee when it is merely the servicer and that it inappropriately and continuously contacted Plaintiffs directly. The MCPA applies only to &#x201C;regulated persons,&#x201D; defined as &#x201C;a person whose collection activities are confined and are directly related to the operation of a business other than that of a collection agency including <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> [a] state or federally chartered bank when collecting its own claim.&#x201D; Mich. Comp. Laws &#167; 445.251(g)(ii). Because Nationstar is a mortgage-loan servicer appointed to collect Deutsche Bank's claim and not its own, the MCPA does not apply. <underscore>See Botsford v. Bank of Am., N.A.</underscore>, No. 13-13379, 2014 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 137612 at *32 (E.D. Mich. Sept. 30, 2014) (finding the MCPA inapplicable to a loan servicer because it was not collecting its own claim). Accordingly, this claim must be dismissed.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>G. Count IX &#8211; Violation of Michigan's Occupational Code</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Plaintiffs assert their claim under the Michigan Occupational Code only against Nationstar. They allege that Nationstar, as a collection agency, violated the Occupational Code by communicating with Plaintiffs directly after being notified that they were represented by counsel. However, this claim fails for the same reason as articulated in Section F of this opinion. According to the Occupational Code, a state or federally chartered bank is a &#x201C;collection agency&#x201D; regulated by the Code only &#x201C;when collecting its own claim.&#x201D; <underscore>See</underscore> Mich. Comp. Laws &#167; 339.901(b)(ii). Because Nationstar, as a mortgage-loan servicer, was collecting another lender's claim, it does not classify as a &#x201C;collection agency.&#x201D; <underscore>See McDonald v. Green Tree Servicing, LLC</underscore>, No. 13-12993, 2014 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 40749 at *22 (E.D. Mich. Mar. 27, 2014) (&#x201C;The Occupational Code is not applicable to a bank's actions as owner of the indebtedness and in the operation of its own business as a loan servicer.&#x201D;). The Occupational Code does not apply to the present claim, and Count IX must be dismissed.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>H. Count X &#8211; Violation of Real Estate Settlement and Procedures Act (&#x201C;RESPA&#x201D;), 12 U.S.C. &#167; 2601 et seq.</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">The RESPA claims advanced in the complaint allege that BANA and Nationstar violated 12 U.S.C. &#167; 2605(k) by &#x201C;fail[ing] to take timely action to respond to [Plaintiffs'] requests to correct errors relating to allocation of payments, final balances for purposes of paying off the loan, or avoiding foreclosure, or other standard servicer's duties.&#x201D; Defendants are correct that the pleadings are inadequate to state a claim. Plaintiffs have not alleged that they requested either BANA or Nationstar to correct any particular errors. Moreover, as Defendants have noted, it is unclear what &#x201C;errors&#x201D; required correction. Given that Plaintiffs have failed to plead their RESPA claim sufficiently, Count X must be dismissed.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. Count XI &#8211; Violation of Michigan Brokers, Lenders and Servicers Licensing Act</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Plaintiffs' final claim is brought against Nationstar and alleges violation of Mich. Comp. Laws &#167; 445.1672 based on the fraudulent misrepresentations that Nationstar had not received all documents necessary to process Plaintiffs' modification application. This claim is therefore similar to the fraud claims advanced in Counts V and VI and must fail for the same reasons articulated in Section E above.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>V. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">For the reasons discussed above, the Court <bold>GRANTS</bold> Defendants' Motion to Dismiss and <bold>DISMISSES</bold> the present case.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Date: June 2, 2015</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>CERTIFICATE OF SERVICE</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">The undersigned certifies that the foregoing Order was served upon counsel of record via the Court's ECF System to their respective email addresses or First Class U.S. mail to the non-ECF participants on June 2, 2015.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>