<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>EASTERN DISTRICT OF MICHIGAN</venue.name>
<venue.name>SOUTHERN DIVISION</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>SAMMY COLANGELO and SHIRLEY COLANGELO, Plaintiffs,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment> THE HUNTINGTON NATIONAL BANK, Defendant.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. 2:15-cv-11722-GAD-RSW</docket.line>
<docket.number>2:15-cv-11722-GAD-RSW</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:15-cv-11722-GAD-RSW</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 07/29/2015</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>ORDER GRANTING DEFENDANT'S MOTION TO DISMISS [#5] AND CANCELLING HEARING</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1"> Honorable Gershwin A. Drain</judge.line>
<judge.line first-line="1">GERSHWIN A. DRAIN UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
<judge.line first-line="1"><underscore>/s/ Felicia Moses for Tanya Bankston</underscore> Case Manager</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1"><bold>I. INTRODUCTION</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On April 22, 2015, Plaintiffs filed the present action in the state court raising the following claims: wrongful foreclosure, Count I; breach of contract, Count II; fraudulent misrepresentation, Count III; slander of title, Count IV; declaratory relief foreclosure barred by unclean hands, Count V; preliminary injunction, Count VI; equitable mortgage, Count VII. Defendants was served with the Summons and Complaint on April 29, 2015, and removed the action to this Court on May 14, 2015 based on 28 U.S.C. &#167;&#167; 1331 and 1441.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Presently before the Court is the Defendant's Motion to Dismiss. Plaintiff has failed to file a response. Local Rule 7.1(c)(1) states that &#x201C;[a] respondent opposing a motion must file a response, including a brief and supporting documents then available.&#x201D; E.D. Mich. L.R. 7.1(c)(1). Responses to dispositive motions &#x201C;must be filed within 21 days after service of the motion.&#x201D; E.D. Mich. L.R. 7.1(e)(1)(B). Accordingly, the response to Defendant's present motion was due no later than July 10, 2015. <ital>Id.</ital>; <ital>see also</ital> Fed. R. Civ. P. 6(a) and 6(d). Since no response has been filed, the present motion is unopposed.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Upon review of the present unopposed motion, the Court concludes that oral argument is unnecessary. Accordingly, the Court will resolve the present motion on the submitted brief. <ital>See</ital> E.D. Mich. L.R. 7.1(f)(2). For the reasons that follow, the Court grants the Defendant's Motion to Dismiss.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. FACTUAL BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">This matter involves real property located at 39627 Dorian in Sterling Heights, Michigan (the &#x201C;Property&#x201D;). On January 9, 2006, the Plaintiffs obtained a loan to finance the purchase of the Property in the amount of $213,750.00 through non-party, Shore Mortgage, represented by a promissory note. The repayment of the note was secured by a mortgage. On January 9, 2006, the mortgage was subsequently assigned to Mortgage Electronic Registration Systems, Inc. as nominee for Shore Mortgage. On October 17, 2012, the mortgage was assigned to the Defendant, which began servicing the mortgage thereafter.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">The Plaintiffs defaulted under the terms of the mortgage and note by failing to make payments, and the Defendant began foreclosure by advertisement proceedings. An initial foreclosure was first published on April 16, 2014 with posting of the notice of foreclosure occurring on April 21, 2014.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">On May 13, 2014, Plaintiff, Sammy Colangelo, filed a Chapter 13 bankruptcy petition in the Eastern District of Michigan, case number 14-48275, which stayed the pending foreclosure proceedings. Plaintiff's bankruptcy schedules acknowledged that the Defendant was the holder of the mortgage, listed a total claim of $183,971.00 and noted that the law firm of Trott &#38; Trott was then representing the Defendant. The Plaintiff failed to mark the Defendant's claim as disputed in the bankruptcy case. The Defendant's claim was not objected to by the Plaintiff. The Bankruptcy case was subsequently dismissed on September 6, 2014, by order of the Bankruptcy Court.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">After dismissal of the bankruptcy proceedings, a notice of default was mailed to the Plaintiffs on September 17, 2014. Plaintiffs allege that the Defendant never sent a &#x201C;Notice of Default,&#x201D; and that the Plaintiffs &#x201C;watched diligently for any and all notices with respect to the Mortgage in the mail <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> and by the telephone.&#x201D; Compl., &#182;&#182; 15 and 16. Defendant again commenced foreclosure proceedings on or about September 23, 2014 and published the notice of sale on that date, as well as on September 30, October 7, and October 14 in the Macomb County Legal News.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">The Defendant purchased the property at a sheriff's sale on October 24, 2014. Thus, the statutory redemption period expired on April 24, 2015. The Plaintiffs filed their action in the Macomb County Circuit Court on April 23, 2015, a day before the expiration of the redemption period. They obtained a Temporary Restraining Order which ordered the Defendant to appear for a show cause hearing but did not toll or stay the redemption period as the suggested language was deleted by the Macomb County Circuit Court. Thereafter, Defendant removed the action to this Court and filed the present Motion to Dismiss [#5].</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. LAW AND ANALYSIS</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Standard of Review</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6) allows the court to make an assessment as to whether the plaintiff has stated a claim upon which relief can be granted. <ital>See</ital> Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(b)(6). &#x201C;Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 8(a)(2) requires only &#x2018;a short and plain statement of the claim showing that the pleader is entitled to relief,&#x201D; in order to &#x2018;give the defendant fair notice of what the <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> claim is and the grounds upon which it rests.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Bell Atlantic Corp. v. Twombly</ital>, 555 U.S. 544, 555 (2007) (citing <ital>Conley v. Gibson</ital>, 335 U.S. 41, 47 (1975)). Although the complaint does not need to contain &#x201C;detailed&#x201D; factual allegations, its &#x201C;factual allegations must be enough to raise a right to relief above the speculative level on the assumption that all of the allegations in the complaint are true.&#x201D; <ital>Ass'n of Cleveland Fire Fighters v. City of Cleveland</ital>, 502 F.3d 545, 548 (6th Cir. 2007)(quoting <ital>Bell Atlantic</ital>, 550 U.S. at 555).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">The court must consider the complaint in the light most favorable to the plaintiff, accept allegations as true, and determine whether plaintiff's factual allegations present plausible claims. In order to survive a 12(b)(6) motion to dismiss, plaintiff's pleadings for relief must provide &#x201C;more than labels and conclusions, and a formulaic recitation of the elements of a cause of action will not do.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> (citations and quotations omitted). &#x201C;[T]he tenant that a court must accept as true all of the allegations contained in a complaint is inapplicable to legal conclusions.&#x201D; <ital>Ashcroft v. Iqbal</ital>, 556 U.S. 662, 668 (2009). &#x201C;Nor does a complaint suffice if it tenders &#x2018;naked assertion[s]&#x2019; devoid of &#x2018;further factual enhancement.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> &#x201C;[A] complaint must contain sufficient factual matter, accepted as true, to &#x2018;state a claim to relief that is plausible on its face.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> The plausibility standard requires &#x201C;more than a sheer possibility that a defendant has acted unlawfully.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> &#x201C;[W]here the well-pleaded facts do not permit the court to infer more than the mere possibility of misconduct, the complaint has alleged-but it has not &#x2018;show[n]&#x2019; &#8211; &#x2018;that the pleader is entitled to relief.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">The district court generally reviews only the allegations set forth in the complaint in determining whether to grant a Rule 12(b)(6) motion to dismiss, however &#x201C;matters of public record, orders, items appearing in the record of the case, and exhibits attached to the complaint, also may be taken into account. <ital>Amini v. Oberlin College</ital>, 259 F. 3d 493, 502 (6th Cir. 2001). Documents attached to a defendant's &#x201C;motion to dismiss are considered part of the pleadings if they are referred to in the plaintiff's complaint and are central to her claim.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Defendant's Motion to Dismiss</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>1. Wrongful Foreclosure</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Plaintiffs allege various bases in support for their wrongful foreclosure claim. First, Plaintiffs allege that the foreclosure violated <csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 600.3208, which states:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p14" first-line="1" turnover="1">Notice that the mortgage will be foreclosed by sale of the mortgaged premises, or some part of them, shall be given by publishing the same for 4 successive weeks at least once in each week, in a newspaper published in the county where the premises included in the mortgage and intended to be sold, or some part of them is situated. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> In every case within 15 days after the first publication of the notice, a true copy shall be posted in a conspicuous place upon any part of the premises[.]</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p15" contd-flag="y"><csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 600.3208.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Plaintiffs allege that they were not provided with proper notice of the foreclosure sale. Plaintiffs' arguments are belied by the exhibits Plaintiffs attach to their Complaint, including the Affidavit of Publication which states that the notice of foreclosure proceedings was &#x201C;published in [the] Macomb County Legal News[,] a newspaper circulated in Macomb County on September 23, September 30, October 7, [and] October 14, 2014.&#x201D; Compl., Ex. 5.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Furthermore, Defendants provide the Evidence of Sale form which states in relevant part:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p18" first-line="1" turnover="1">[O]n the 24th day of September, 2014 <csc>A</csc>.<csc>D</csc>, he/she posted a notice, a true copy of which is annexed hereto, in a conspicuous place upon the premises described in said notice by attaching the same in a secure manner to 39627 Dorian Dr[.], Sterling Heights, <csc>MI</csc> 48310</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p19" contd-flag="y">Dkt. No. 5, Ex. <csc>E</csc>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">Plaintiffs also attached the initial Evidence of Sale form to their Complaint which states in relevant part:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p21" first-line="1" turnover="1">[O]n the 21st day of April, 2014 A.D, he/she posted a notice, a true copy of which is annexed hereto, in a conspicuous place upon the premises described in said notice by attaching the same in a secure manner to 39627 Dorian Dr[.], Sterling Heights, MI 48310</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p22" contd-flag="y">Compl., Ex. 5.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p23">&#8195;The initial foreclosure was stayed because the Plaintiff Sammy Colangelo filed for bankruptcy. In addition, the initial Evidence of Sale attached by the Plaintiffs was also attached with the Sherriff's Deed on Mortgage Sale which shows a sale date of October 24, 2014.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Under Michigan law, these affidavits serve as &#x201C;presumptive evidence&#x201D; that notice was in fact given. MICH. COMP. LAWS &#167; 600.3264 (&#x201C;Such affidavits shall be recorded <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> [and] shall be presumptive evidence of the facts therein contained.&#x201D;); <ital>Marshall v. Nationstar Mortgage</ital>, LLC, No. 1:12-cv-852, 2015 U.S. Dis. LEXIS 288868, *15-16 (W.D. Mich. Mar. 10, 2015).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Plaintiffs allege that they &#x201C;never saw any Notice of Sale posted on their property within 15 days of the alleged first publication date of September 23, 2014.&#x201D; Compl. &#182; 27. Plaintiffs also claim they never saw the Notice of Sale that the Defendant published in the Macomb County Legal News. Compl. &#182; 25. These allegations concerning lack of proper notice are implausible and do not state a claim upon which relief may be granted. <ital>Ashcroft</ital>, 556 U.S. at 668.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">Next, Plaintiffs assert that the foreclosure was wrongful because the Defendant failed to provide the Notice of Default under Section 22 of the Mortgage. However, Defendant attaches the Notice of Default that was sent to Plaintiff Sammy Colangelo at 39627 Dorian Dr., Sterling Heights, MI 48310-2314 dated September 17, 2014 by the Trott &#38; Trott, the firm that represents the Defendant. The letter states &#x201C;[t]his office represents The Huntington National Bank. This matter was referred to this office to foreclose the mortgage.&#x201D; Dkt. No 5, Ex. D. The letter then goes on to state the Defendant's plan to accelerate the total indebtedness, the total amount of the indebtedness, identifies the creditor, and provides a deadline for any possible action to be taken by the Plaintiffs. <ital>Id.</ital> Thus, the letter refutes the claim that Plaintiffs did not receive the Notice of Default and their allegations supporting the wrongful foreclosure claim based on purported lack of notice pursuant to the mortgage fail to withstand Rule 12(b)(6) scrutiny.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">The Plaintiffs further allege that the Defendant &#x201C;unlawfully caused a foreclosure proceeding to commence and continue when Plaintiffs were being considered for foreclosure alternatives prior to the publication of the notice of sale and holding of the foreclosure sale.&#x201D; Compl. &#182; 60. Plaintiffs also maintain the Defendant did not respect 12 C.F.R. 1024.41 (&#x201C;Regulation X&#x201D;) and failed to make any &#x201C;live contact with Plaintiffs within 36 days of the alleged delinquency of their mortgage,&#x201D; and that Defendant failed to provide Plaintiffs with &#x201C;notice that they were not eligible with any of the loss mitigation options that may be available.&#x201D; Compl. &#182;&#182; 66-67. However, Plaintiffs undercut their own argument that Defendant failed to respect Plaintiffs' foreclosure alternatives by their reliance on 12 C.F.R. &#167; 1024.41, which states:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p28" first-line="1" turnover="1">A borrower may enforce the provisions of this section pursuant to section 6(f) of RESPA (12 U.S.C. 2605(f)). Nothing in &#167; 1024.41 imposes a duty on a servicer to provide any borrower with any specific loss mitigation option. Nothing in &#167; 1024.41 should be construed to create a right for a borrower to enforce the terms of any agreement between a servicer and the owner or assignee of a mortgage loan, including with respect to the evaluation for, or offer of, any loss mitigation option or to eliminate any such right that may exist pursuant to applicable law</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p29" contd-flag="y">12 C.F.R. &#167; 1024.41(a).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">In light of the regulation's language, Defendant was not required to provide Plaintiffs with any specific loss mitigation option, nor should 12 C.F.R. &#167; 1024.41 be construed to create a right for the borrower, i.e. the Plaintiffs, to enforce the terms of an agreement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Furthermore, &#x201C;dual tracking violations relate to the loan modification process rather than the foreclosure process.&#x201D; <ital>Elezaj v. US Bank, Nat'l Ass'n</ital>, No. 14-10485, 2014 U.S. Dis. LEXIS 140739 (E.D. Mich. Oct. 3, 2014) (quoting <ital>Kloss v. RBS Citizens, N.A.</ital>, 996 F. Supp. 2d 574, 585 (E.D. Mich. 2014)). &#x201C;[E]ven if the Defendant engaged in dual tracking, as the Plaintiffs allege, this practice does not constitute fraud or irregularity in the foreclosure proceeding itself.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">In addition, this Court has noted that declaratory and injunctive relief by a Plaintiff is not available under 12 C.F.R. &#167; 1024.41 or &#x201C;Regulation X&#x201D; because the only available remedy is &#x201C;actual damages to the borrower as a result of the failure&#x201D; and &#x201C;any additional damages, as the court may allow, in the case of a pattern or practice of noncompliance with the requirements of this section, in an amount not to exceed $2,000.&#x201D; <ital>Brunning v. Nationstar Mortg. LLC</ital>, No. 15-cv-10587, 2015 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 92418, *8 (E.D. Mich. Jul. 16, 2015). Plaintiffs' allegations regarding &#x201C;Regulation X&#x201D; fail to state a claim for wrongful foreclosure.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">The Plaintiffs next allege that Defendant violated The Truth in Lending Act (&#x201C;TILA&#x201D; or &#x201C;Regulation Z&#x201D;), specifically 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1641(d)(1) and &#167; 1641(g)(1) because they were not notified that the Loan and/or Mortgage was sold or transferred. Compl. &#182; 80. However, Plaintiffs attach the Assignment of Mortgage, dated October 17, 2012, as Exhibit 3 to their Complaint, which refutes their argument that they had no notice of the transfer. For similar reasons, Plaintiffs argument that Defendant failed to notify the Plaintiffs in writing of the assignment, sale, or transfer of the loan to another person was a violation of 12 U.S.C. &#167; 2605(b)(1) is without merit. <ital>See</ital> Compl. &#182; 83.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Plaintiffs also seek damages in the amount of $4000.00 under 15 C.F.R. &#167; 1640(a)(1) and 15 C.F.R. &#167; 1640(a)(2)(A)(iv). However, 15 C.F.R. &#167; 1640(e) imposes a statute of limitations of 1 year from the &#x201C;date of occurrence of the violation.&#x201D; Therefore, even if Plaintiffs allegations were true, they are barred from bringing the claim as a matter of law because the statute of limitations has run out. For the foregoing reasons, Plaintiffs' wrongful foreclosure claim fails to state a claim upon which relief can be granted.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>2. Breach of Contract</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">Plaintiffs allege that Defendant &#x201C;breached the contract as well as the implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing&#x201D; by:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p36" first-line="1" turnover="1">(a) Failing to send Plaintiffs a notice containing all the components of Paragraph 22 of the Mortgage;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p37" first-line="1" turnover="1">(b) Disingenuously negotiating loss mitigation assistance with the Plaintiffs; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" first-line="1" turnover="1">(c) Misleading Plaintiffs about approval and extension of loss mitigation assistance as an alternative to foreclosure</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p39" contd-flag="y">Compl. &#182; 92 (a-c).</paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">As an initial matter, to the extent Plaintiffs are attempting to raise a claim that Defendant breached the covenant of good faith and fair dealing, Michigan &#x201C;does not recognize a cause of action for breach of the implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing.&#x201D; <ital>Fodale v. Waste Management of Michigan, Inc.</ital>, 271 Mich.App. 11, 35; 718 N.W.2d 827 (2006).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">In order to survive a breach of contract claim, Plaintiffs must establish: (1) that the parties entered into a valid enforceable contract that include the terms and conditions claimed by the Plaintiffs; (2) that the Defendant breached the contract; and (3) that the Defendant's breach caused a loss to the Plaintiff. <ital>Plastis v. E.F. Hutton &#38; Co.</ital>, 642 F. Supp. 1277 (W.D. Mich. 1986); <ital>Pittsburgh Tube Co. v. Tri-Blend, Inc.</ital>, 185 Mich. App. 581 (1990). However, even if Plaintiffs' allegations are true, Michigan courts have held that generally &#x201C;a party who breaches a contract cannot sue the other party for breach of contract.&#x201D; <ital>Pletos v. Lake in the Woods Homeowners Ass'n</ital>, No. 319087, 2015 Mich.App. LEXIS 715, *46 (Mich. Ct. App. Apr. 14, 2015) (quoting <ital>Flamm v. Scherer</ital>, 40 Mich.App. 1, 8-9; 198 N.W.2d 702 (1972)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">Here, Plaintiffs substantially breached the contract first by failing to pay the mortgage as required under the contract. Plaintiffs allege no facts showing they performed under the contract at the time of Defendant's purported breach. In any event, Plaintiffs' default gave Defendant the contractual right to proceed with foreclosure pursuant to the terms of the mortgage. <ital>See</ital> Compl. Ex. 2.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">Moreover, the record shows that Defendant sent the Notice of Default and Foreclosure to Plaintiff Sammy D. Colangelo at 39627 Dorian Dr. Sterling Heights, MI 48310 on September 17, 2014. Accordingly, there are no plausible factual allegations for this Court to infer a violation of Paragraph 22 of the Mortgage occurred. <ital>See Brunning</ital>, 2015 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 92418, at *11. Plaintiffs' breach of contract claim must therefore be dismissed for failure to state a claim upon which relief can be granted.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>3. Fraudulent Misrepresentation</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">Plaintiffs' fraudulent misrepresentation claim also cannot withstand Rule 12(b)(6) scrutiny. Plaintiffs allege that Defendant &#x201C;made representations to Plaintiffs <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> that it would not begin foreclosure proceedings while the parties were actively pursuing loan modification or other financial assistance options.&#x201D; Compl., &#182; 94.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">In order to state a claim for fraudulent misrepresentation, Plaintiffs must allege: (1) that the Defendant made a material representation, (2) that was false, (3) that Defendant knew was false, or that was made recklessly, without any knowledge of its truth, (4) that Defendant made it with the intention that Plaintiff would act upon it, and (5) that the Plaintiff acted in reliance upon it, and (6) suffered damages. <ital>See Hi-Way Motor Co. v. Internat'l Harvester Co.</ital>, 398 Mich. 330, 336; 247 N.W. 2d 813 (1976). The Plaintiffs' pleadings do not contain any factual allegations concerning the who, when, or any specific details surrounding the allegedly fraudulent statements. <ital>See</ital> Fed. <csc>R</csc>. Civ. <csc>P</csc>. 9(b) (&#x201C;[i]n allegations of fraud or mistake, a party must state with particularity the circumstances constituting fraud or mistake.&#x201D;) Therefore, Plaintiffs' fraudulent misrepresentation claim fails as a matter of law.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>4. Slander of Title</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">Plaintiffs make a claim of slander of title under <csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 565.108 and common law. Michigan Compiled Laws &#167; 565.108 states:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p47" first-line="1" turnover="1">No person shall use the privilege of filing notices hereunder for the purposes of slandering the title to land, and in any action brought for the purpose of quieting title to land, if the court shall find that any person has filed a claim for that reason only, he shall award the plaintiff all the costs of such action, including such attorney fees as the court may allow to the plaintiff, and in addition, shall decree that the defendant asserting such claim shall pay to the plaintiff all damages that plaintiff may have sustained as the result of such notice of claim been so filed for record.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p48" contd-flag="y"><csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 565.108.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">In order to prove slander of title under <csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 565.108 and at common law, &#x201C;a claimant &#x2018;must show falsity, malice, and special damages, i.e., that the defendant maliciously published false statements that disparaged a plaintiff's right in property causing special damages.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Fannie Mae v. Villa Del Lago Condo. Ass'n &#38; Lori Gilbert</ital>, No. 315459, 2014 Mich.App. <csc>LEXIS</csc> 1400, *9, 2014 <csc>WL</csc> 3747607 (Mich. Ct. App. Jul. 29, 2014) (quoting <ital>Fannie Mae v. Lagoons Forest Condominium Ass'n</ital>, 305 Mich.App. 258, 270 (2014)). &#x201C;Malice may not be inferred simply from the filing of an invalid lien; plaintiffs must show that defendants knowingly filed an invalid lien with the intent to cause plaintiffs injury.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> (quoting <ital>Sullivan v. Thomas Org</ital>, 88 Mich. App. 77, 86; N.W.2d 522, 526 (1979) (internal citation omitted)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">Plaintiffs fail to show any malicious intent on the part of the Defendant that would constitute a violation of <csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 565.108 or common law slander of title. &#x201C;The crucial element is malice.&#x201D; <ital>Gehrke v. Janowitz</ital>, 55 Mich. App. 643, 648; 223 N.W.2d 107 (1974). In this case, the Plaintiffs have failed to allege any malice.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p51" level="1">The Court notes that Defendant argues the Plaintiffs lack standing to bring a claim under slander of title and <csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 565.108 the redemption period has expired under <csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 600.3236. Thus, Defendant maintains Plaintiffs no longer have any interest in the subject Property. The Michigan Court of Appeals has recently held that by failing to redeem the property during the redemption period, a borrower loses standing to bring a claim challenging the foreclosure. <ital>Bryan v. JPMorgan Chase Bank</ital>, 304 Mich.App. 708, 713-14 (2014). The Plaintiffs failed to redeem their property during the redemption period which expired on April 24, 2015, and they no longer hold an interest in the property. <ital>Id.</ital>; <csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 600.3236. For this additional reason, Plaintiffs' arguments are without merit and fail as a matter of law.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>5. Declaratory Relief &#8211; Foreclosure Barred by Unclean Hands</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p52" level="1">The Plaintiffs argue that although the Defendant seeks the equitable relief of a foreclosure, Defendant is barred from doing so because it cannot make a showing of clean hands. Compl. &#182; 108. &#x201C;Defendant's above-referenced conduct constitutes multiple instances of bad faith negotiations with Plaintiffs, as well as bad faith processing of their mortgage loan and/or request for modification.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at &#182; 107.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p53" level="1">The doctrine of &#x201C;unclean hands <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> does not state a cause of action. Rather, it is a defense that &#x2018;depends upon the connection between the complainant's iniquitous acts and the defendant's conduct which the complainant relies upon as establishing his cause of action.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Soto v. Wells Fargo Bank N.A.</ital>, No. 11-14064, 2012 U.S. Dis. LEXIS 4195, *13, 2012 WL 113534 (E.D. Mich. Jan. 13, 2012) (quoting <ital>Wuliger v. Manufacturers Life Ins. Co.</ital>, 567 F.3d 787, 797 (6th Cir. 2009)). Furthermore, the Sixth Circuit has held that a bank's reasonable attempt to mitigate its own losses &#x201C;does not establish the bad faith or unfairness that would be necessary to invoke the doctrine of unclean hands.&#x201D; <ital>Flagstar Bank v. Premier Lending Corp.</ital>, No. 295211, 2011 Mich. App. LEXIS 579, *13, 2011 WL 1086558 (Mich. Ct. App. Mar. 24, 2011). &#x201C;The clean hands maxim is a self-imposed ordinance that closes the doors of a court of equity to one tainted with inequitableness or bad faith relative to the matter in which he seeks relief, however improper may have been the behavior of the defendant.&#x201D; <ital>Lupas v. U.S. Bank, NA</ital>, No. 11-14584, 2012 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 123917, *23, 2012 WL 3758037 (E.D. Mich. Aug. 30, 2012) (quoting <ital>McFerren v. B&#38;B Inv. Grp.</ital>, 253 Mich.App. 517, 655 N.W.2d 779, 783 (Mich. Ct. App. 2002). Based on the foregoing authority, Plaintiffs cannot assert a claim for unclean hands, which is an equitable defense. Moreover, even if unclean hands was a viable claim, Plaintiffs are barred from bringing such a claim because they no longer have any rights to the Property having failed to redeem during the available statutory period. Plaintiffs' unclean hands claim fails to state a claim upon which relief can be granted.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>6. Preliminary Injunction</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p54" level="1">Plaintiffs also argue that they will likely have success on the merits of their claims, thus they seek a preliminary injunction to enjoin the expiration of the redemption period. Compl. &#182;&#182; 111-12.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p55" level="1">When considering a request for preliminary injunction, the Court must balance four factors. The four factors include: (1) the likelihood of the plaintiff's success on the merits; (2) whether the plaintiff will suffer irreparable injury without the injunction; (3) the harm to others which will occur if the injunction is granted; and (4) whether the injunction would serve the public interest. <ital>In re Delorean Motor Co.</ital>, 755 F.2d 1223, 1228 (6th Cir. 1985); <ital>In re Eagle-Pitcher Industries, Inc.</ital>, 963 F.2d 855, 858 (6th Cir. 1992); and <ital>N.A.A.C.P. v. City of Mansfield, Ohio</ital>, 866 F.2d 162, 166 (6th Cir. 1989).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p56" level="1">The Court has concluded that none of Plaintiffs' allegations plausibly allege entitlement to relief. As such, Plaintiffs cannot show a likelihood of success on the merits of their claims and they are not entitled to a preliminary injunction.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>7. Equitable Mortgage</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p57" level="1">Lastly, Plaintiffs argue that the Court should impose an equitable mortgage on the parties. Plaintiffs argue they no longer have recourse under <csc>Mich</csc>. <csc>Comp</csc>. <csc>Laws</csc> &#167; 600.3205(c) because it was repealed and no comparable statute has been adopted. Compl. &#182; 127. Equitable mortgages &#x201C;are generally found when what appears to be an absolute conveyance on its face was actually intended as a mortgage.&#x201D; <ital>Burkhardt v. Bailey</ital>, 260 Mich.App. 636, 660; 680 N.W.2d 453 (2004) (citing <ital>Townsend v. Chase Manhattan Mtg. Corp.</ital>, 245 Mich.App. 133, 138; 657 N.W.2d 741 (2002)). &#x201C;An equitable mortgage places the substance of the parties intent over form.&#x201D; <ital>Bailey</ital>, 260 Mich.App. at 660 (citing <ital>Hess v. Haas</ital>, 230 Mich. 646, 651-652; 203 <csc>N</csc>.<csc>W</csc>. 471 (1925). &#x201C;Michigan law is clear that equitable mortgages are appropriate in circumstances where the underlying mortgage is void, particularly when one party received the benefits of the mortgage.&#x201D; <ital>Sutter v. U.S. Nat'l Bank</ital>, 665 F.3d 722, 728 (6th Cir. 2012).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p58" level="1">Plaintiff recognizes that equitable mortgage is typically a remedy for creditors. Compl. &#182; 127. This Court has found no cases that have allowed borrowers, such as the Plaintiffs, recourse under an equitable mortgage remedy. Upon review of Michigan law, it is beyond dispute that an equitable mortgage is inappropriate under the circumstances. Plaintiffs defaulted on their mortgage obligations and failed to redeem the Property during the redemption period. Moreover, Plaintiffs provide no supporting authority for their equitable mortgage argument. Therefore, Plaintiffs are not entitled to an equitable mortgage.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p59" level="1">For the reasons set forth above, Defendant's Motion to Dismiss [#5] is GRANTED. This cause of action is dismissed.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p60" level="1">SO ORDERED. Dated:</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>CERTIFICATE OF SERVICE</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p61" level="1">Copies of this Order were served upon attorneys of record by electronic and/or ordinary mail.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>