<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>NORTHERN DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>MESA UNDERWRITERS SPECIALTY INSURANCE CO., Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>PARADISE SKATE, INC., Defendant.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. <underscore>15-cv-01253-YGR</underscore> (JSC)</docket.line>
<docket.number><underscore>15-cv-01253-YGR</underscore> (JSC)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">4:15-cv-01253-YGR</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 04/11/2016</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>REPORT AND RECOMMENDATION RE: DEFAULT JUDGMENT</bold> Re: Dkt. No. 52</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">JACQUELINE SCOTT CORLEY United States Magistrate Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">This is an insurance coverage dispute arising from a state-court action. Plaintiff Mesa Underwriters Specialty Insurance Company (&#x201C;MUSIC&#x201D;) contends that it has no duty to defend its insured, Defendant Paradise Skate, Inc. (&#x201C;Paradise&#x201D;), in the underlying action, and that Paradise owes MUSIC reimbursement for costs incurred in defending Paradise in that action. (Dkt. No. 1.) After Paradise failed to appear in this action, default was entered and MUSIC now moves for default judgment in the form of declaratory relief and damages. (Dkt. No. 52.) The motion for default judgment was referred to the undersigned magistrate judge for a report and recommendation. The Court recommends that the district court GRANT the motion for default judgment as set forth below.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. Factual Background</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Insurance Policy</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">MUSIC is an insurance company incorporated under New Jersey's laws with headquarters in Arizona. (Dkt. No. 1 at &#182; 1.) Paradise is a corporation incorporated under California's laws with headquarters in California. (<ital>Id.</ital> at &#182; 2.) At the time of the events giving rise to this action, Paradise operated a roller skating rink in Antioch, California, that it leased from the 23rd District Agricultural Association (the &#x201C;Agricultural Association&#x201D;). (<ital>Id.</ital> at &#182; 11.) According to the complaint, MUSIC issued a Commercial General Liability policy (the &#x201C;Policy&#x201D;) to Paradise with a policy period running from January 1, 2013, to January 1, 2014. (<ital>Id.</ital> at &#182; 18.) The Policy included the following provision regarding injuries and property damage arising from assault and battery (the &#x201C;Assault and Battery Exclusion&#x201D;):</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p3" first-line="1" turnover="1">This policy does not apply to &#x201C;bodily injury&#x201D;, &#x201C;personal injury&#x201D; or &#x201C;property damage&#x201D; arising out of assault and/or battery or out of any act or omission in connection with the prevention or suppression of such acts, including the failure to warn, train or supervise, whether caused by or at the instigation or direction of the insured, his employees, patrons or any other person.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p4" contd-flag="y">(Dkt. No. 1 at &#182; 20; Dkt. No. 52-3 at 1.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference>) The Policy defines &#x201C;bodily injury&#x201D; as &#x201C;bodily injury, sickness, or disease sustained by a person, including death resulting from any of these at any time.&#x201D; (Dkt. No. 1 at &#182; 21.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p5">&#8195;Record citations are to material in the Electronic Case File (&#x201C;ECF&#x201D;); pinpoint citations are to the ECF-generated page numbers at the top of the documents.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. <ital>Horace</ital> Action</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">On September 8, 2013, Amber Abagnan was shot in the Paradise parking lot; she later died from her injuries. (Dkt. No. 52 at 3; Dkt. No. 52-2 at &#182; 15.) A year later, in November 2014, Amber Abagnan's minor daughter, Kennedy H., by and through her guardian ad litem, Paul Horace, filed an action against several defendants, including Paradise, in Contra Costa County Superior Court (the <ital>&#x201C;Horace</ital> action&#x201D;).<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> (Dkt. No. 1 at &#182; 13; Dkt. No. 52-2.) The complaint asserted causes of action for negligence, premises liability, and wrongful death, and alleged that Paradise's negligence &#x201C;cause[d] a violent assault and battery to be committed against Ms. Abagnan[,]&#x201D; who &#x201C;was killed as a result of the assault and battery.&#x201D; (Dkt. No. 52-2 at &#182;&#182; 13-31.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p7">&#8195;The other defendants named in the <ital>Horace</ital> action include: (1) the Agricultural Association; (2) the California Fair Services Authority (&#x201C;CFSA&#x201D;), a joint powers authority that provides insurance to the Agricultural Association; (3) Sharon Abagnan, one of Amber Abagnan's heirs; and (4) Tyler Woods, another of Amber Abagnan's heirs. (Dkt. No. 52-2; Dkt. No. 1; Dkt. No. 28 at &#182; 4.)</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Paradise tendered defense of the <ital>Horace</ital> action to MUSIC. (Dkt. No. 1 at &#182; 22.) MUSIC initially declined the tender on the ground that Amber Abagnan's shooting death was a battery, and therefore the Assault and Battery Exclusion precluded coverage for the <ital>Horace</ital> action claims. (Dkt. No. 52-4 at 5.) However, Paradise insisted that the Policy did in fact provide coverage, so about two months later, while maintaining that the Policy precluded coverage, MUSIC agreed to provide Paradise a courtesy defense under a reservation of rights. (Dkt. No. 52-5 at 1-2.) Specifically, MUSIC reserved its rights to seek reimbursement from Paradise for any legal fees and expenses it paid to defend against the uncovered claims, to withdraw its defense at any time, and to seek reimbursement of any indemnity and/or settlement payments it made on an insured's behalf. (<ital>Id.</ital> at 6-7.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">On August 15, 2015, following the entry of default against Paradise in this action, the <ital>Horace</ital> plaintiffs filed a FAC that only asserted causes of action for wrongful death and dangerous condition of public property. (Dkt. No. 52 at 5; Dkt. No. 52-6.) The <ital>Horace</ital> plaintiffs did not bring the dangerous condition cause of action against Paradise, and Paradise did not tender the FAC to MUSIC. (Dkt. No. 52 at 5-6.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. Procedural Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">On March 17, 2015, MUSIC filed the original complaint in this action against all parties to the <ital>Horace</ital> action: the Agricultural Association, CFSA, Paul Horace, Kennedy H., Sharon Abagnan, and Tyler Woods (collectively, the &#x201C;responding Defendants&#x201D;), as well as Paradise. (Dkt. No. 1.) The complaint asserts two state-law claims. (<ital>Id.</ital>) The first seeks a judicial declaration that MUSIC does not, and did not at any time, have a duty to defend or indemnify Paradise, the Agricultural Association, or CFSA in the <ital>Horace</ital> action. (<ital>Id.</ital> at &#182;&#182; 26-28.) The second claim seeks reimbursement from Paradise for the expenses MUSIC had incurred and continues to incur defending Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action. (<ital>Id.</ital> at &#182;&#182; 29-33.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">MUSIC properly served the complaint on Paradise on April 1, 2015, and on April 17, 2015, MUSIC and Paradise filed a joint stipulation extending Paradise's time to file a responsive pleading. (Dkt. No. 14 at 2; Dkt. No. 8.) However, Paradise never filed its responsive pleading or otherwise appeared; indeed, when MUSIC'S counsel emailed Paradise's counsel noting that the stipulated deadline had come and gone, Paradise's counsel replied that it did not intend to file a responsive pleading. (Dkt. No. 24-2.) The clerk entered default as to Paradise on May 21, 2015. (Dkt. No. 25.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">On February 29, 2016, MUSIC and the responding Defendants filed a stipulation to dismiss the responding Defendants with prejudice, which the court granted, leaving Paradise as the sole defendant in this action. (Dkt. No. 51; Dkt. No. 54.) The same day, MUSIC also filed the underlying motion for default judgment against Paradise. (Dkt. No. 52.) In its motion, MUSIC seeks judgment on its declaratory relief and reimbursement claims, as well as post-judgment interest on any damages awarded and costs of suit incurred in the instant action. (<ital>Id.</ital> at 1-2.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. Jurisdiction And Service Of Process</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">A court considering whether to enter a default judgment has &#x201C;an affirmative duty to look into its jurisdiction over both the subject matter and the parties.&#x201D; <ital>In re Tuli</ital>, 172 F.3d 707, 712 (9th Cir. 1999). Here, the court has original jurisdiction under 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1332 because it is a civil action between citizens of different states and the amount in controversy exceeds $75,000. (See Dkt. No. 1.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">A court must also &#x201C;assess the adequacy of the service of process on the party against whom default is requested.&#x201D; <ital>Penpower Tech. Ltd. v. S.P.C. Tech.</ital>, 627 F. Supp. 2d 1083, 1088 (N.D. Cal. 2008) (internal quotation marks and citation omitted). Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 4(e) provides that service in accordance with California law is proper. Under California law, &#x201C;[a] summons may be served by personal delivery of a copy of the summons and of the complaint to the person to be served.&#x201D; Cal. Code Civ. Proc. &#167; 415.10. Here, MUSIC has filed a declaration from a process server indicating that Paradise was personally served with the summons and complaint on April 1, 2015. (Dkt. No. 14 at 2.) Service of process was proper.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. MUSIC Is Entitled To Default Judgment Based On <ital>Eitel</ital> Factors</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">After entry of default, a court may grant default judgment on the merits of the case. <ital>See</ital> Fed. R. Civ. P. 55. &#x201C;The district court's decision whether to enter a default judgment is a discretionary one.&#x201D; <ital>Aldabe v. Aldabe</ital>, 616 F.2d 1089, 1092 (9th Cir. 1980). Courts consider the following factors in determining whether to enter default judgment:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="2" turnover="2">(1) the possibility of prejudice to the plaintiff, (2) the merits of plaintiff's substantive claim, (3) the sufficiency of the complaint, (4) the sum of money at stake in the action[,] (5) the possibility of a dispute concerning material facts[,] (6) whether the default was due to excusable neglect, and (7) the strong policy underlying the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure favoring decisions on the merits.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p17" contd-flag="y"><ital>Eitel v. McCool</ital>, 782 F.2d 1470, 1471-72 (9th Cir. 1986). Upon entry of default, the court deems the complaint's factual allegations related to liability to be true. <ital>TeleVideo Sys., Inc. v. Heidenthal</ital>, 826 F.2d 915, 917-18 (9th Cir. 1987) (citation omitted). However, the court does not deem allegations regarding damages to be true; to that end, the court has the discretion to consider competent evidence and other papers submitted with a default judgment motion to determine damages. <ital>Shanghai Automation Instrument Co., Ltd. v. Kuei</ital>, 194 F. Supp. 2d 995, 1000, 1010 (N.D. Cal. 2001) (citing <ital>Tele Video Sys., Inc.</ital>, 826 F.2d at 917).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The majority of the <ital>Eitel</ital> factors support default judgment in this case.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A. <ital>Possibility Of Prejudice</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">The first <ital>Eitel</ital> factor considers whether the plaintiff will suffer prejudice if a default judgment is not entered. <ital>Craigslist, Inc. v. Naturemarket, Inc.</ital>, 694 F. Supp. 2d 1039, 1054 (N.D. Cal. 2010). Here, MUSIC faces potential prejudice if the court does not enter default. There is potential prejudice where denying default judgment would deny an insurer a judicial determination as to whether it has a duty to indemnify and defend the defendant and whether it is entitled to reimbursement of the defense costs in the underlying action. <ital>Burlington Ins. Co. v. Diamond Partners, Inc.</ital>, No. 1:10-CV-00100-LJO, 2011 WL 284490, at *3 (E.D. Cal. Jan. 25, 2011) <ital>report and recommendation adopted</ital>, No. 1:10-CV-00100-LJO, 2011 WL 587108 (E.D. Cal. Feb. 9, 2011); <ital>see also Axis Reinsurance Co. v. Telekenex, Inc.</ital>, No. 12-2979 SC, 2014 WL 644950, at *4 (N.D. Cal. Feb. 19, 2014) (finding that where an insurer may have been without recourse for recovery if the court denied default judgment, the first <ital>Eitel</ital> factor favored default judgment). Moreover, an insurer's continued exposure to liability in an underlying lawsuit amounts to potential prejudice that weighs in favor of default judgment. <ital>Aspen Ins. UK Ltd. v. Killarney Const. Co.</ital>, No. C 11-1294 RS, 2012 WL 1831498, at *2 (N.D. Cal. May 18, 2012).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">In <ital>Diamond</ital>, a bar patron sued the defendant-insured Diamond Partners, Inc. (&#x201C;Diamond&#x201D;) in state court for negligence when the patron allegedly suffered injuries arising from an assault in the bar that Diamond operated. <ital>Diamond</ital>, 2011 WL 284490, at *1. Diamond had a commercial general liability policy with the plaintiff-insurer Burlington Insurance Co. (&#x201C;Burlington&#x201D;), but the policy included an assault and battery exclusion stating that coverage did not apply &#x201C;to bodily injury arising out of assault and battery, or out of any act or omission in connection with the prevention or suppression of an assault or battery.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> (internal quotations marks and alterations omitted). Burlington agreed to defend Diamond in the lawsuit, but reserved its rights to seek a judicial declaration that it had no duty to defend because of the assault and battery exclusion and to seek reimbursement of any expenses it incurred in defending Diamond. <ital>Id.</ital> Burlington then filed a federal-court action seeking declaratory relief and reimbursement. <ital>Id.</ital> Diamond failed to respond to the complaint and the clerk entered default. <ital>Id.</ital> at *2. The court found that the prejudice Burlington might suffer if Diamond never filed a responsive pleading, and if the court therefore never determined the case's merits, weighed in favor of default judgment. <ital>Id.</ital> at *3.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Similarly, in <ital>Aspen</ital>, the plaintiff- and intervenor-insurers sought declaratory relief regarding their duty to defend the defendant-insured in an underlying state-court action where the respective insurance policies did not provide coverage. <ital>Aspen</ital>, 2012 WL 1831498, at *l-2. The court found that without default judgment, the insurers &#x201C;would be continuously exposed to liability in the underlying construction dispute&#x201D; and &#x201C;would also be prejudiced in that they would be denied the right to judicial resolution of the claims.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at *2. The court thus concluded that the first <ital>Eitel</ital> factor favored default judgment. <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">The rationales <ital>of Diamond</ital> and <ital>Aspen</ital> apply equally here. As in <ital>Diamond</ital>, MUSIC faces potential prejudice, and as in <ital>Aspen</ital>, without a judgment MUSIC faces potential liability should it discontinue its defense of Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action. This factor thus favors default judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">B. <ital>Merits And Sufficiency Of Claims</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Factors two and three&#8212;the merits of MUSIC's substantive claims and the sufficiency of the complaint&#8212;also favor default judgment. The Court considers these factors simultaneously because of the inquiries' relatedness. <ital>See, e.g., Craigslist, Inc. v. 3taps, Inc.</ital>, No. 3:12-CV-03816-CRB, 2015 WL 5921212, at *3 (N.D. Cal. Oct. 11, 2015). In particular, the Court must determine whether the allegations in the complaint are sufficient to state a claim that supports the relief sought. <ital>See Danning v. Lavine</ital>, 572 F.2d 1386, 1388 (9th Cir. 1978); <ital>PepsiCo, Inc. v. Cal. Sec. Cans.</ital>, 238 F. Supp. 2d 1172, 1177 (CD. Cal. 2002). Following entry of default, the Court takes the complaint's well-pleaded allegations regarding liability as true, but not allegations regarding the amount of damages. <ital>Fair Housing of Marin v. Combs</ital>, 285 F.3d 899, 906 (9th Cir. 2002). Furthermore, &#x201C;necessary facts not contained in the pleadings, and claims which are legally insufficient, are not established by default.&#x201D; <ital>Cripps v. Life Ins. Co. of N. Am.</ital>, 980 F.2d 1261, 1267 (9th Cir. 1992). For that reason, default does not automatically entitle a plaintiff to judgment. Instead, default may be inappropriate under the second <ital>Eitel</ital> factor where a court determines that a plaintiff has not alleged a justifiable claim. <ital>Draper v. Coombs</ital>, 792 F.2d 915, 924 (9th Cir. 1986). To determine if a plaintiff has pleaded the elements of common law claims sufficiently to state a claim for relief, district courts look to state law. <ital>Kearns v. Ford Motor Co.</ital>, 567 F.3d 1120, 1126 (9th Cir. 2009) (citation omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">MUSIC has properly pleaded claims for declaratory relief and reimbursement, and the complaint's allegations adequately support both claims. As such, factors two and three favor default judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">1. <underscore>Merits And Sufficiency Of Declaratory Relief Claim</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">In its complaint, MUSIC contends that it has no duty to defend Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action pursuant to the Assault and Battery Exclusion and its default judgment motion seeks a judicial declaration to that effect.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">California law requires that a claim for declaratory relief demonstrate (1) a proper subject of declaratory relief and (2) an actual controversy involving justiciable questions relating to the rights or obligations of a party. <ital>Brownfield v. Daniel Freeman Marina Hosp.</ital>, 208 Cal. App. 3d 405, 410 (Cal. Ct. App. 1989). Proper subjects of declaratory relief include the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p27" first-line="2" turnover="2">Any person interested under a written instrument <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> or under a contract, or who desires a declaration of his or her rights or duties with respect to another <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> may, in cases of actual controversy relating to the legal rights and duties of the respective parties, bring an original action or cross-complaint in the superior court for a declaration of his or her rights and duties in the premises, including a determination of any question of construction or validity arising under the instrument or contract.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p28" contd-flag="y">Cal. Code Civ. P. &#167; 1060; <ital>see also Diamond</ital>, 2011 WL 284490, at *4. The &#x201C;actual controversy&#x201D; requirement turns on &#x201C;the existence of a <ital>present</ital> controversy relating to the legal rights and duties of the respective parties pursuant to the contract.&#x201D; <ital>Diamond</ital>, 2011 WL 284490, at *4 (quoting <ital>Brownfield</ital>, 208 Cal. App. 3d at 410) (internal quotation marks omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">California and federal courts have held that declaratory relief is appropriate to negate an insurer's duty to defend. <ital>See Essex Ins. Co. v. Yi</ital>, 795 F. Supp. 319, 322 (N.D. Cal. 1992) (collecting cases). &#x201C;The determination whether the insurer owes a duty to defend usually is made in the first instance by comparing the allegations of the complaint with the terms of the policy.&#x201D; <ital>Horace Mann Ins. Co. v. Barbara B.</ital>, 4 Cal. 4th 1076, 1081 (Cal. 1993), <ital>as modified on denial of reh g</ital> (May 13, 1993). More specifically, &#x201C;an insurer's duty to defend is determined by those facts known by the insurer at the inception of a third party lawsuit&#x201D; and &#x201C;from the facts and inferences known to an insurer from the pleadings, available information and its own investigations at the time of the tender of defense[.]&#x201D; <ital>Storek v. Fid. &#38; Guar. Ins. Underwriters, Inc.</ital>, 504 F. Supp. 2d 803, 812 (N.D. Cal. 2007) <ital>aff'd</ital>, 320 F. App'x 508 (9th Cir. 2009) (internal quotation marks, alterations, and citations omitted). In declaratory judgment actions based on diversity jurisdiction, district courts interpret and apply policy language according to California law. <ital>St. Paul Mercury Ins. Co v. Ralee Eng'g Co.</ital>, 804 F.2d 520, 522 (9th Cir. 1986). If contractual language is clear and explicit, it governs, and a provision is ambiguous <ital>&#x201C;only</ital> if it is susceptible to two or more reasonable constructions despite the plain meaning of its terms within the context of the policy as a whole.&#x201D; <ital>Sony Computer Entm't Am. Inc. v. Am. Home Assurance Co.</ital>, 532 F.3d 1007, 1012 (9th Cir. 2008) (internal quotation marks and citations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">In <ital>Burlington Ins. Co. v. Alan</ital>, No. C 12-03372 SI, 2013 WL 1819996, at *1 (N.D. Cal. Apr. 30, 2013), the court considered the merits of a similar claim for declaratory relief based on an insurer's duty to defend. There, a man was shot and killed outside of a nightclub. <ital>Alan</ital>, 2013 WL 1819996, at *1. The defendant-insured owned the building where the nightclub operated, but his insurance policy with the plaintiff-insurer excluded&#8212;broadly, unambiguously, and in plain language&#8212;coverage for injuries &#x201C;[a]rising in whole or in part out of any &#x2018;assault&#x2019; or &#x2018;battery&#x2019; committed or attempted by any person&#x201D; or &#x201C;[a]rising in whole or in part out of any attempt by any person to avoid, prevent, suppress, or halt any actual or threatened &#x2018;assault&#x2019; or &#x2018;battery.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at *l-2. The deceased's survivors sued the insured in state court for negligence and wrongful death, and the insurer agreed to defend the insured under a reservation of rights. <ital>Id.</ital> The insurer then brought a federal action seeking a declaration that it had no duty to defend and reimbursement of expenses incurred defending the insured in the underlying action. <ital>Id.</ital> at *2. The court held that &#x201C;because the crux of the [underlying] action arises &#x2018;in whole or in part&#x2019; from an incident in which [the deceased] &#x2018;was shot during a skirmish among patrons&#x2019;&#8212;a battery&#8212;the Assault or Battery Exclusion to the insurance policy applie[d,]&#x201D; and the insurer had no duty to defend. <ital>Id.</ital> at *3; <ital>see also Diamond</ital>, 2011 WL 284490, at *4 (concluding that the plaintiff-insurer (1) demonstrated a proper subject of declaratory relief by alleging the existence of an insurance policy and a complaint in an underlying lawsuit, and (2) demonstrated an actual controversy by alleging that the policy's assault and battery exclusion negated the insurer's duty to defend in the underlying action and that it had provided a defense under a reservation of rights).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Here, MUSIC has sufficiently alleged both a proper subject of declaratory relief&#8212;the existence of the Policy and the <ital>Horace</ital> complaint&#8212;and an actual controversy&#8212;specifically, MUSIC'S contention that the Assault and Battery Exclusion precludes coverage in the <ital>Horace</ital> action and that MUSIC provided Paradise a defense under a reservation of rights.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">Moreover, MUSIC'S factual allegations support its declaratory relief claim. The original <ital>Horace</ital> complaint asserted causes of action for negligence, premises liability, and wrongful death, and alleged that Paradise's negligence &#x201C;cause[d] a violent assault and battery to be committed against Ms. Abagnan[,]&#x201D; who &#x201C;was killed as a result of the assault and battery.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> (Dkt. No. 52-2 at &#182;&#182; 13-31.) Additionally, MUSIC'S investigation of the <ital>Horace</ital> allegations revealed that Amber Abagnan was shot in Paradise's parking lot following an altercation inside the rink. (Dkt. No. 52-1 at 3.) By all accounts, a common-law battery gave rise to the <ital>Horace</ital> action. The Assault and Battery Exclusion here provides that the Policy</paratext>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p33">&#8195;That the <ital>Horace</ital> FAC&#8212;which was filed after the entry of default in this action&#8212;only asserted one cause of action against Paradise for wrongful death, thereby eliminating the negligence and premises liability claims, does not change this analysis as the wrongful death claim remains.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p34" first-line="2" turnover="2">does not apply to &#x201C;bodily injury&#x201D;, &#x201C;personal injury&#x201D; or &#x201C;property damage&#x201D; arising out of assault and/or battery or out of any act or omission in connection with the prevention or suppression of such acts, including the failure to warn, train or supervise, whether caused by or at the instigation or direction of the insured, his employees, patrons or any other person.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p35" contd-flag="y">(<ital>Id.</ital> at 4; Dkt. No. 52-3 at 1.) The Policy defines &#x201C;bodily injury&#x201D; as &#x201C;bodily injury, sickness, or disease sustained by a person, including death resulting from any of these at any time.&#x201D; (Dkt. No. 1 at &#182; 21.) The Court interprets &#x201C;battery&#x201D; consistent with its common-law definition and a shooting is a battery. <ital>See Mount Vernon Fire Ins. Corp. v. OxnardHosp. Enter., Inc.</ital>, 219 Cal. App. 4th 876, 882-84 (Cal. Ct. App. 2013); <ital>see also People v. Trujillo</ital>, 181 Cal. App. 4th 1344, 1357 (Cal. Ct. App. 2010) (noting that jurors could reasonably find that &#x201C;a person with actual knowledge that he is shooting indiscriminately at a moving vehicle would realize that his conduct would directly, naturally, and probably <ital>result in a battery</ital> to anyone and everyone inside&#x201D; the car) (emphasis added); <ital>People v. Williams</ital>, 26 Cal. 4th 779, 790 (Cal. 2001) (finding that the defendant &#x201C;undoubtedly knew those facts establishing that his act by its nature would directly, naturally and probably <ital>result in a battery&#x201D;</ital> where the defendant fired his gun at a truck knowing that another person was in the truck's near vicinity) (emphasis added).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Where an insurance policy's plain language excludes coverage for injuries and property damage arising from assault and battery and a complaint's allegations against an insured all arise from a shooting, the insurer has no duty to defend. <ital>See Burlington Ins. Co. v. Alan</ital>, No. C 12-03372 SI, 2013 WL 1819996, at *4 (N.D. Cal. Apr. 30, 2013). Comparing the <ital>Horace</ital> complaint's allegations and MUSIC'S investigation results with the Policy, the Assault and Battery Exclusion obviates MUSIC'S duty to defend Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action. Declaratory relief is therefore appropriate.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">2. <underscore>Merits And Sufficiency Of Reimbursement Claim</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">MUSIC also contends that it is entitled to money damages in the amount that it has expended defending Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action. (Dkt. No. 52 at 2.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">In California, an insurer that properly reserves its rights has a right to seek reimbursement of costs it incurs defending its insured against claims that the relevant policy does not potentially cover, but not for defending claims that are covered or potentially covered. <ital>Buss v. Super. Ct.</ital>, 16 Cal. 4th 25, 50 (Cal. 1997); <ital>Scottsdale Inc. Co. v. MV Transp.</ital>, 36 Cal. 4th 643, 656 (Cal. 2005). In a &#x201C;mixed action,&#x201D; where the relevant policy potentially covers some of the claims against the insured but not others, an insurer has a duty to defend the entire action, but, &#x201C;having reserved its rights, [the insurer] may recover its costs of defense attributable to the claims for which there was no potential coverage.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> <ital>Scottsdale</ital>, 36 Cal. 4th at 658 (citation omitted). The reasoning behind allowing reimbursement is &#x201C;rooted in basic contract principles. The insured pays for, and can reasonably expect, a defense against third party claims that are potentially covered by its policy, but no more.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 659 (citation omitted). Thus, when an insured is sued, an &#x201C;insurer may unilaterally condition its proffer of a defense upon its reservation of a right later to seek reimbursement of costs advanced to defend claims that are not, and never were, potentially covered by the relevant policy.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 656. An insurer makes an adequate and proper reservation by expressly reserving its right to seek reimbursement of defense costs for claims raising no potential for coverage. <ital>See id.</ital> at 655 (citation omitted). &#x201C;Such an announcement by the insurer permits the insured to decide whether to accept the insurer's terms for providing a defense, or instead to assume and control its own defense.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 656 (citation and footnote omitted). Further, &#x201C;[a] reservation of rights to recover defense costs is effective even when an insured objects to the reservation but accepts the defense.&#x201D; <ital>Burlington Ins. Co. v. Devdhara</ital>, No. C 09-00421 SBA, 2010 WL 3749301, at *6 (N.D. Cal. Sept. 23, 2010) (citing <ital>Blue Ridge Ins. Co. v. Jacobsen</ital>, 25 Cal. 4th 489, 498 (Cal. 2001)).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p39">&#8195;&#x201C;This is so, <ital>Buss</ital> explained, because the contractual duty to defend the potentially covered claims immediately and meaningfully implies the prophylactic duty to defend &#x2018;entirely,&#x2019; without pausing to parse among potentially covered and clearly uncovered claims.&#x201D; <ital>Scottsdale</ital>, 36 Cal. 4th at 658 (citation omitted).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">Here, MUSIC has submitted evidence that it determined it had no duty to defend Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action and therefore initially declined Paradise's tender of the defense. (Dkt. No. 52-1 at 3; Dkt. No. 52-4.) However, MUSIC ultimately agreed to provide a courtesy defense while opining in detail that the Policy did not provide coverage for the <ital>Horace</ital> claims and expressly reserving &#x201C;its right to seek reimbursement from the insured for any legal fees and expenses MUSIC paid and/or may pay on behalf of the insured related to the defense of the claims not potentially covered by the Policy.&#x201D; (Dkt. No. 52-5.) MUSIC'S express reservation, even given Paradise's objection, adequately and properly reserved MUSIC'S right to seek reimbursement for expenses it incurred defending against non-covered claims. <ital>See Scottsdale</ital>, 36 Cal. 4th at 658; <ital>Devdhara</ital>, 2010 WL 3749301, at *6. Because the Policy provided no potential coverage in the <ital>Horace</ital> action, MUSIC has adequately supported its claim for reimbursement.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">C. <ital>Sum Of Money At Stake</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">The fourth <ital>Eitel</ital> factor also favors default judgment. This factor balances the amount of money at stake in the claim with the seriousness of the defendant's conduct. <ital>Eitel</ital>, 782 F.2d at 1471-72; <ital>Axis Reinsurance Co. v. Telekenex, Inc.</ital>, No. 12-2979 SC, 2014 WL 644950, at *5 (N.D. Cal. Feb. 19, 2014). A court considers a &#x201C;[p]laintiff's declarations, calculations, and other documentation of damages in determining if the amount at stake is reasonable.&#x201D; <ital>Axis</ital>, 2014 WL 644950, at *5 (citation omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">For instance, in <ital>Axis</ital>, the plaintiff-insurer sought reimbursement for approximately $39,000 it had advanced to defend a defaulting party in an underlying action. <ital>Id.</ital> at *4-5. The plaintiff submitted a declaration by one of its assistant vice presidents supporting the amount of money it sought. <ital>Id.</ital> at *5. After finding that reimbursement was merited because the relevant insurance policy did not cover the claims in the underlying action, the court found that this factor favored default judgment because the plaintiff sought &#x201C;only&#x201D; $39,000, and sought reimbursement only from a party whose defense costs it had advanced. <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">Here, MUSIC seeks reimbursement of $32,085.41, which represents the costs it incurred defending Paradise through January 28, 2016, in addition to reimbursement in an unspecified amount for expenses that it has continued to incur in defending Paradise. (Dkt. No. 52 at 2.) Further, MUSIC only seeks reimbursement for defending against claims that the Policy does not cover and only seeks reimbursement from Paradise, a defaulting party whose defense costs it advanced. (Dkt. No. 52.) Accordingly, this factor favors default judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">D. <ital>Possibility Of Dispute Concerning Material Facts</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">The fifth <ital>Eitel</ital> factor, which considers the possibility that material facts may be in dispute, also favors default judgment here. <ital>Eitel</ital>, 782 F.2d at 1471-72. Courts have found that a dispute concerning material facts is unlikely and that factor five therefore favors default judgment where defendants make no effort to challenge a complaint by filing a responsive pleading or otherwise appearing in a case. <ital>See, e.g., Evans v. Creditor's Specialty Serv. Inc.</ital>, No. 15-CV-03355-BLF, 2016 WL 730277, at *2 (N.D. Cal. Feb. 24, 2016); <ital>Atain Specialty Ins. Co. v. N. Bay Waterproofing, Inc.</ital>, No. 14-CV-04056-RMW, 2015 WL 428161, at *4 (N.D. Cal. Jan. 30, 2015), <ital>appeal dismissed</ital> (June 10, 2015).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">For instance, in <ital>Atain</ital>, the plaintiff-insurer brought an action seeking a judicial declaration that it had no duty to defend the defendant-insureds in an underlying state-court action because the claims in the underlying action were either outside the scope of the relevant insurance policy or subject to coverage exclusions. <ital>Atain</ital>, 2015 WL 428161, at *l-2. The plaintiff personally served the defendants, but neither defendant filed a responsive pleading and the clerk entered default as to both. <ital>Id.</ital> at *2. The court found that the defendants might have disputed the factual allegations had they appeared in the case, but &#x201C;the reality [was] defendants failed to do so,&#x201D; and thus they had &#x201C;waived their opportunity to dispute [those] facts.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at *4.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">Here, despite receiving personal service of the summons and complaint, and even filing a joint stipulation with MUSIC to extend its time to answer the complaint, Paradise did not file a responsive pleading or otherwise challenge the complaint. Thus, while Paradise might have disputed the factual allegations had it appeared, that it did not means that this factor favors default judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">E. <ital>Whether The Default Was Due To Excusable Neglect</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p47" level="1">The sixth <ital>Eitel</ital> factor considers whether the defendant's default may have been due to excusable neglect. <ital>Eitel</ital>, 782 F.2d at 1471-72. &#x201C;Excusable neglect is an equitable concept and takes account of factors such as prejudice, the length of the delay and impact on judicial proceedings, the reason for the delay, including whether it was within the reasonable control of the defendant, and whether the defendant acted in good faith.&#x201D; <ital>Triumph Furniture Processing-Exp. Joint Stock Co. v. Everest Furniture Co.</ital>, No. 13-CV-01729 NC, 2013 WL 9600372, at *4 (N.D. Cal. Aug. 29, 2013) <ital>report and recommendation adopted</ital>, No. C 13-1729 SI, 2014 WL 4211076 (N.D. Cal. Aug. 25, 2014) (internal quotation marks, alterations, and citation omitted). Where a defendant has been properly served with a complaint and a default judgment motion, courts find it unlikely that default is due to excusable neglect. <ital>See, e.g., McMillan Data Commc &#x2018;ns, Inc. v. AmeriCom Automation Servs., Inc.</ital>, No. 14-CV-03127-JD, 2015 WL 4380965, at *11 (N.D. Cal. July 16, 2015); <ital>W. States Insulators &#38; Allied Workers Pension Plan v. Jenco Mech. Insulation, Inc.</ital>, No. C-l 1-0175 EMC, 2012 WL 1123229, at *2-3 (N.D. Cal. Apr. 3, 2012). Excusable neglect is particularly unlikely where a defaulting defendant enters into a stipulation for additional time to respond to a complaint and then fails to respond. <ital>See Xerox Corp. v. Zablocki Corp.</ital>, No. C 12-00819 LB, 2012 WL 3778968, at *3 (N.D. Cal. July 19, 2012) <ital>report and recommendation adopted</ital>, No. C 12-00819 RS, 2012 WL 3779024 (N.D. Cal. Aug. 30, 2012).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p48" level="1">Here, MUSIC properly served Paradise with the summons and complaint and Paradise entered into a stipulation for additional time to answer the complaint, but Paradise failed to answer the complaint and the clerk entered default. (Dkt. No. 14 at 2; Dkt. No. 8; Dkt. No. 25.) Further, MUSIC properly served Paradise with the default judgment motion (Dkt. No. 52-10), but Paradise has not responded. As such, it is unlikely that Paradise's default is due to excusable neglect, and therefore this factor favors default judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">F. <ital>Strong Policy Underlying The Federal Rules Of Civil Procedure Favoring Decisions On The Merits</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">Finally, the seventh <ital>Eitel</ital> factor reflects the policy that generally disfavors default judgments because &#x201C;cases should be decided upon their merits whenever reasonably possible.&#x201D; <ital>Eitel</ital>, 782 F.2d at 1472. Despite this general policy, &#x201C;because a discretionary standard is applied, default judgments are more often granted than denied.&#x201D; <ital>Webb v. Indigenous Global Dev. Corp.</ital>, C-04-3174 MJJ, 2005 WL 1200203, at *5 (N.D. Cal. May 16, 2005) (internal quotation marks and citation omitted). Although this factor weighs against default, it is not alone dispositive nor does it weigh substantially against granting default given the impossibility of deciding a case on its merits when a defendant fails to answer. <ital>See Willamette Green Innovation Ctr., LLC v. Quartis Capital Partners</ital>, No. 13-CV-00848-JCS, 2014 WL 5281039, at *13 (N.D. Cal. Jan. 21, 2014) <ital>report and recommendation adopted</ital>, No. 13-CV-00848-WHO, 2014 WL 5260921 (N.D. Cal. Apr. 10, 2014) (citation omitted).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>* * *</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">In sum, a majority of the <ital>Eitel</ital> factors favor default judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. Relief</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p51" level="1">Because the Court recommends granting default judgment, it next turns to the matter of the relief to which MUSIC is entitled. In its motion, MUSIC seeks (1) the court's declaration that it does not, and did not at any time, have a duty to defend or indemnify Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action because the Policy provides no potential coverage of the claims in that action; (2) reimbursement for defending Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action; (3) post-judgment interest on any damages award; and (4) costs incurred in this action. (Dkt. No. 52 at 1-2.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A. <ital>Declaratory Relief</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p52" level="1">For the reasons discussed above, MUSIC is entitled to declaratory relief.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">B. <ital>Money Damages</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p53" level="1">MUSIC seeks $32,085.41 in money damages for defense expenses it incurred in the <ital>Horace</ital> action through January 28, 2016. (Dkt. No. 52 at 1-2.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p54" level="1">The moving party has the burden to &#x201C;prove up&#x201D; the amount of damages. <ital>United States v. Sundberg</ital>, No. C-09-4085 EMC, 2011 WL 3667458, at *6 (N.D. Cal. Aug. 22, 2011) (citation omitted). Where the amount of damages &#x201C;is liquid or capable of ascertainment from definite figures contained in documentary evidence or detailed affidavits, the [c]ourt may enter default judgment without a hearing on damages.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> (internal quotation marks and citation omitted); <ital>see also Pope v. United States</ital>, 323 U.S. 1, 12 (1944) (&#x201C;It is a familiar practice and an exercise of judicial power for a court upon default, by taking evidence when necessary or by computation from facts of record, to fix the amount which the plaintiff is entitled to recover and to give judgment accordingly.&#x201D;). Similarly, if the plaintiff can meet its burden of proving an amount of damages &#x201C;capable of mathematical calculation&#x201D; through evidence, testimony, or written affidavit, there is no need for an evidentiary hearing on damages. <ital>See Davis v. Fendler</ital>, 650 F.2d 1154, 1161 (9th Cir. 1981); <ital>Bd. of Trs. of the Boilermaker Vacation Trust v. Shelly, Inc.</ital>, 389 F. Supp. 2d 1222, 1226 (N.D. Cal. 2005).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p55" level="1">Under similar circumstances in <ital>Axis</ital>, the plaintiff &#x201C;proved up&#x201D; its requested damages by submitting a declaration specifying the amount it had paid to defend the defaulting defendant against non-covered claims in the underlying action. <ital>Axis</ital>, 2014 WL 644950, at *5. Here too, MUSIC has submitted a declaration showing that it incurred $32,085.41 in expenses defending Paradise against non-covered claims through January 28, 2016. (Dkt. No. 52-7; Dkt. No. 52-8.) This declaration is sufficient to prove that MUSIC is entitled to money damages in the amount of $32,085.41.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p56" level="1">MUSIC also appears to seek money damages for the costs it has continued to incur in defending Paradise since January 2016 (Dkt. No. 52 at 2), but has provided neither a sum certain nor any evidence supporting its request. Thus, any such amount cannot be included in the judgment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">C. <ital>Post-judgment Interest On Damages Award</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p57" level="1">MUSIC also seeks post-judgment interest on any damages award. (Dkt. No. 52 at 1-2.) Federal law determines post-judgment interest awards in diversity cases. <ital>Northrop Corp. v. Triad Int'lMktg., S.A.</ital>, 842 F.2d 1154, 1155 (9th Cir. 1988) (citations omitted); <ital>Lucasfilm, Ltd. v. Canal Toys</ital>, No. C 11-01639 WHA, 2012 WL 685415, at *4 (N.D. Cal. Mar. 2, 2012). &#x201C;Such interest shall be calculated from the date of the entry of the judgment, at a rate equal to the weekly average 1-year constant maturity Treasury yield, as published by the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, for the calendar week preceding[] the date of the judgment.&#x201D; 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1961(a) (footnote omitted). A post-judgment interest award is mandatory and recoverable on all aspects of a judgment, including amounts awarded for damages, pre-judgment interest, attorneys' fees, and costs. <ital>Lucasfilm</ital>, 2012 WL 685415, at *4 (citing <ital>Air Separation, Inc. v. Underwriters at Lloyd's of London</ital>, 45 F.3d 288, 290-91 (9th Cir. 1995)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p58" level="1">The Court thus recommends awarding MUSIC post-judgment interest on the entire amount awarded in MUSIC's favor, to begin accruing at the applicable statutory rate on the date such judgment is entered. 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1961(a) (footnote omitted); <ital>Lucasfilm</ital>, 2012 WL 685415, at *4 (citation omitted).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">D. <ital>Costs Incurred In The Instant Action</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p59" level="1">Finally, MUSIC seeks costs in this action. (Dkt. No. 52 at 1-2.) Because MUSIC seeks to obtain judgment only as to state-law claims, the Court must apply California law to assess the availability of costs of suit. <ital>Kona Enters., Inc. v. Estate of Bishop</ital>, 229 F.3d 877, 883 (9th Cir. 2000). Under California law, &#x201C;a prevailing party is entitled as a matter of right to recover costs in any action or proceeding.&#x201D; Cal. Code Civ. P. &#167; 1032(b). MUSIC is entitled to costs of suit as set forth in Cal. Code Civ. P. Section 1033.5. However, MUSIC has not requested a specific amount of costs, nor has counsel submitted any documentation of costs. Accordingly, no costs shall be awarded.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p60" level="1">For the reasons stated above, the Court RECOMMENDS that the district court GRANT MUSIC's motion for default judgment and thereby declare that MUSIC had and has no duty to defend Paradise in the <ital>Horace</ital> action and award MUSIC $32,085.41 in damages plus post-judgment interest. The Court further RECOMMENDS that MUSIC'S request for costs be DENIED in light of the failure to request a specific amount or offer any evidence in support of a cost award.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p61" level="1">Any party may file objections to this Report and Recommendation with the district judge within fourteen days after being served with a copy. <ital>See</ital> 28 U.S.C. &#167; 636(b)(1); Fed. R. Civ. P. 72(b); N.D. Cal. Civ. L.R. 72. Failure to file an objection may waive the right to review of the issue in the district court.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p62" level="1">The Court ORDERS MUSIC to serve a copy of this report and recommendation on Paradise.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p63" level="1">Dated: April 11, 2016</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>