<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF OKLAHOMA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>F. STEPHEN ALLEN, Plaintiff</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>MEETME, INC., Defendant.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. 15-CV-210-GKF-TLW</docket.line>
<docket.number>15-CV-210-GKF-TLW</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">4:15-cv-00210-GKF-TLW</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed in USDC ND/OK on 12/14/2015</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head>
<headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>ORDER</bold></underscore></headtext>
</head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">GREORY K. FRIZZELL, CHIEF JUDGE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Before the court are the Motion for Judgment on the Pleadings filed by defendant MeetMe, Inc. (&#x201C;MeetMe&#x201D;), [Dkt. #20], and the Motion to Amend Complaint filed by plaintiff F. Stephen Allen (&#x201C;Allen&#x201D;). [Dkt. #22]. For the reasons stated below, MeetMe's motion is granted and Allen's motion is denied.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">In the complaint, Allen alleges he invested in Quepasa Corporation (&#x201C;Quepasa&#x201D;), a predecessor to MeetMe. In exchange for the funds he invested, Allen alleges he received three warrants to buy a total of 1,500,000 shares of Quepasa stock. A warrant is like an option to buy stock, except that it is issued by the company itself and not by a stock exchange. Allen alleges Quepasa and he entered into a &#x201C;Registration Rights Agreement&#x201D; (&#x201C;the Agreement&#x201D;), under which Quepasa was required to &#x201C;use its best efforts to&#x201D; register the new shares of stock with the Securities and Exchange Commission (&#x201C;SEC&#x201D;), and thereafter maintain their registration, so that Allen could resell to the public any shares he had purchased by exercising the warrants. [Dkt. #1, p. 3]. Allen alleges Quepasa violated the Agreement by allowing the registration statement it had filed with the SEC to lapse&#8212;and by failing to give Allen timely notice of the registration statement's lapse as required in the Agreement&#8212;such that Allen was unable to resell some of that stock when he wanted to in July and August 2011. Allen alleges Quepasa filed a post-effective amendment to the registration statement, but the amendment was not declared effective by the SEC until September 2011. At that time, Allen alleges, the value of the stock no longer incentivized the sales he had contemplated in July and early August. As a result, Allen alleges Quepasa's breach of the Agreement damaged him in the amount of no less than $4 million. In the alternative, Allen asserts claims for reformation and equitable estoppel to extend the term of the Agreement to offer him additional time to exercise his rights thereunder.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">MeetMe moves to dismiss Allen's claims for reformation and equitable estoppel, arguing those claims were not adequately stated. MeetMe notes that the Agreement provides that it &#x201C;shall be governed by, and construed and enforced in accordance with, the laws of the state of Nevada. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; [Dkt. #20-1, p. 8, &#167; 4.2].<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Allen did not object to the use of Nevada law in his response to MeetMe's motion. Allen separately moves to amend the complaint to provide additional support for his reformation claim. [Dkt. #22].</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p4">&#8195;Because the Agreement was attached to MeetMe's Motion for Judgment on the Pleadings, is referred to in the Complaint, is central to Allen's claims, and because Allen has not objected to its authenticity, the court may consider it. <ital>See Prager v. LaFaver</ital>, 180 F.3d 1185, 1189 (10th Cir. 1999).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">A motion for judgment on the pleadings under Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(c) is subject to the same standard applicable to a motion under Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(b)(6). <ital>Corder v. Lewis Palmer Sch. Dist. No. 38</ital>, 566 F.3d 1219, 1223 (10th Cir. 2009). To survive a Rule 12(c) motion, the complaint &#x201C;must contain sufficient factual matter, accepted as true, to &#x2018;state a claim to relief that is plausible on its face.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Ashcroft v. Iqbal</ital>, 556 U.S. 662, 678 (2009) (quoting <ital>Bell Atl. Corp. v. Twombly</ital>, 550 U.S. 544, 570 (2007)). &#x201C;[M]ere labels and conclusions, and a formulaic recitation of the elements of a cause of action will not suffice; a plaintiff must offer specific factual allegations to support each claim.&#x201D; <ital>Kan. Penn Gaming, LLC v. Collins</ital>, 656 F.3d 1210, 1214 (10th Cir. 2011) (internal quotation marks omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">Leave to amend should be freely given &#x201C;when justice so requires,&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 15(a)(2), but may be denied when the proposed amendment would be futile because it would be subject to dismissal. <ital>See Lind v. Aetna Health, Inc.</ital>, 466 F.3d 1195, 1199 (10th Cir. 2006).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">Under Nevada law, reformation is &#x201C;available as an equitable remedy to a party seeking to alter a written instrument which, because of a mutual mistake of fact, fails to conform to the parties' previous agreement or understanding.&#x201D; <ital>Helms Constr. &#38; Dev. Co. v. Nevada</ital>, 634 P.2d 1224, 1225 (Nev. 1981). MeetMe argues Allen has failed to allege any previous agreement or understanding to which the written Agreement fails to conform. Allen does allege that the parties &#x201C;believed the Registration Statement would be effective throughout the entire period&#x201D; of the Agreement. [Dkt. #1, p. 6]. Allen thus alleges a prior understanding of the parties.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">However, Allen does not make specific factual allegations supporting his claim that the Agreement failed to conform to that understanding. The Agreement clearly contemplated the registration statement might lapse by providing obligations triggered by such a lapse. [<ital>See</ital> Dkt. #20-1, p. 2 (&#x201C;If the [registration statement] ceases to be effective for any reason at any time during the Effectiveness Period. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;)]. A general understanding between two parties that a <ital>possible</ital> future event will not occur&#8212;<ital>e.g.</ital>, the roof will not leak&#8212;is not inconsistent with an agreement containing obligations conditioned on that possible future event&#8212;<ital>e.g.</ital>, if the roof leaks, the event planner will move the party to another room. For such conditional obligations to be inconsistent with the parties' understanding, Allen would have to allege the parties understood that a lapse of the registration statement would completely nullify or breach the Agreement. Allen does not allege such an understanding and alleges no specific facts supporting his claim that the Agreement fails to conform to a prior understanding of the parties. Allen's complaint thus fails to state a claim for equitable estoppel.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Allen's proposed amended complaint takes a slightly different approach, but similarly fails to allege the Agreement did not conform to a prior understanding of the parties. Allen again alleges the parties believed the registration statement would not lapse, but adds the allegation that the parties believed &#x201C;Allen or a similarly situated warrant holder would be able to exercise his warrants.&#x201D; [Dkt. #22, p. 8]. This does not materially alter the parties' alleged understanding as described in Allen's complaint. The alleged understanding that the registration statement would not lapse implies that Allen, or another warrant holder, would be able to exercise his warrants. Allen does not allege the parties also understood that no other conditions would impair the exercise of the warrant holders' rights.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Allen's proposed amended complaint alleges the Agreement failed to conform to the parties' prior understanding because it did not provide for the extension of the period of effectiveness <ital>of the warrants</ital> in the event the registration statement lapsed. In support, Allen cites to a provision of the Agreement extending the period of effectiveness of <ital>the registration statement itself</ital> by the amount of time spent on amendments to or supplementation of the registration statement. [<ital>See</ital> Dkt. #22, p. 8]. Allen argues the Agreement failed to conform to the parties' understanding because it did not similarly provide &#x201C;for an express extension of the expiration date of the Warrants. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; [<ital>Id.</ital>].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">However, Allen does not allege the parties specifically understood that the warrants' period of effectiveness would be extended by the period during which the registration statement was ineffective or being amended or supplemented. Rather, he alleges the parties generally believed the registration statement would remain effective and that warrant holders would be able to exercise their rights. As noted above, the Agreement expressly contemplated that the exercise of the warrant holder's rights might be interrupted if the registration statement became ineffective. In the Agreement, the parties provided conditional terms for that scenario. The particular terms selected are not inconsistent with Allen's proposed prior understanding. The parties did not provide for the extension of the warrants&#8212;which authorize the warrant holder to <ital>buy</ital> the shares of stock&#8212;but did provide for the extension of the registration statement&#8212;which enables the warrant holder to thereafter <ital>sell</ital> the shares of stock. While there may have been good reasons to extend both the registration statements and the warrants, Allen does not allege the parties had a <ital>specific</ital> understanding that the Agreement would do so. Furthermore, an agreement extending only the registration statement would not fail to conform to a <ital>general</ital> understanding that &#x201C;the Registration Statement would be effective throughout the entire period from February 12, 2007 through March 21, 2016, and Allen or a similarly situated warrant holder would be able to exercise his warrants.&#x201D; [Dkt. #22, p. 8].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">In sum, Allen's proposed amended complaint does not allege a more specific understanding to which the Agreement does not conform. Thus, the proposed amended complaint fails to state a claim for reformation. The proposed amendment would be futile.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">In Nevada, equitable estoppel has four elements:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p14" first-line="1" turnover="1">(1) the party to be estopped must be appraised of the true facts;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" first-line="1" turnover="1">(2) the party to be estopped must intend that his conduct shall be acted upon, or</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="1" turnover="1">must so act that the party asserting estoppel has the right to believe it was so intended;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" first-line="1" turnover="1">(3) the party asserting the estoppel must be ignorant of the true state of facts;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" first-line="1" turnover="1">(4) the party asserting estoppel must have relied to his detriment on the conduct of the party to be estopped.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p19" contd-flag="y"><ital>See Hermanson v. Hermanson</ital>, 887 P.2d 1241, 1245 (Nev. 1994) (quoting <ital>Southern Nev. Mem. Hosp. v. State</ital>, 101 Nev. 387, 391, 705 P.2d 139, 142 (1985)). Allen states his claim for equitable estoppel by reference to the facts alleged in earlier in the complaint, adding only a single sentence. [Dkt. #1, p. 6 (&#x201C;[MeetMe] should be equitably estopped from enforcing the Expiration Date of March 21, 2016, for the number of days after such date that the Court determines the Registration Statement was not effective.&#x201D;)]. MeetMe argues Allen has not alleged any facts of which it was aware, but of which Allen was not. In response, Allen argues he alleged Quepasa knew that it had allowed the registration statement to lapse, and that he was not aware of the lapse until he attempted to exercise the warrants. In the complaint, Allen indeed alleges he was not aware of the lapsed registration statement. Allen also alleges that he relied on Quepasa's conduct&#8212; <ital>i.e.</ital>, that because Quepasa had not notified him otherwise, as required by the Agreement, he did not take steps to ensure the registration statement was effective before attempting a series of sales in July and August 2011. However, Allen does not allege Quepasa was aware of the lapse prior to the date on which Quepasa sent Allen a letter notifying him of the lapse. Allen also does not allege Quepasa intended him to rely on his mistaken understanding that the registration statement was still effective.</paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">In sum, because Allen does not allege that Quepasa was aware of the registration lapse prior to notifying him or that Quepasa intended him to rely on its conduct, Allen's complaint fails to state a claim for equitable estoppel. Allen's proposed amended complaint contains no changes to the equitable estoppel allegations in the complaint.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, MeetMe's Motion for Judgment on the Pleadings [Dkt. #20] is granted and Allen's claims for reformation and equitable estoppel are dismissed. Allen's Motion to Amend Complaint [Dkt. #22] is denied.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">ENTERED this 14th day of December, 2015.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>