<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>NORTHERN DISTRICT OF OKLAHOMA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>STUART C. IRBY COMPANY, Plaintiff</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>WIRE NUTS ELECTRIC, INC., an Oklahoma Corporation; CHRISTY McGILL; WILLIAM SMITH; and JANET SMITH, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No.12-CV-617-CVE-FHM</docket.line>
<docket.number>12-CV-617-CVE-FHM</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">4:12-cv-00617-CVE-FHM</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed in USDC ND/OK on 07/19/2013</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head>
<headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>REPORT AND RECOMMENDATION</bold></underscore></headtext>
</head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">FRANK H. MCCARTHY UNITED STATES MAGISTRATE JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Plaintiff's Motion for Attorneys' Fees and Costs, [Dkt. 30], has been referred to the undersigned United States Magistrate Judge for report and recommendation. The undersigned RECOMMENDS that the motion be GRANTED in part and DENIED in part.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">In this action Plaintiff sought to recover monetary damages in the amount of $179,682.36, plus a monthly service charge against Defendant Wire Nuts on the basis that Wire Nuts failed to pay for materials and equipment Plaintiff sold to Wire Nuts pursuant to terms and conditions of sale. Plaintiff also sought to recover the attorneys' fees, costs, and expenses Plaintiff incurred to collect the amount Wire Nuts owed. [Dkt. 2]. Default judgment was entered in Plaintiff's favor against Defendant Wire Nuts. [Dkt. 29]. Plaintiff now seeks an award of $34,142.23 in attorney fees and costs as permitted by the terms and conditions of sale. [Dkt. 2, &#182;013; Dkt. 2-3, &#182; 4].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">The undersigned has reviewed Plaintiff's billing statements to determine whether the number of hours and rate are reasonable and well supported as required by Tenth Circuit authority. <ital>Case v. Unified School District No. 233, Johnson County, Kansas</ital>, 157 F.3d 1243,1250 (10th Cir. 1998) citing <ital>Ramos v. Lamm</ital>, 713 F.2d 546, 552 (10th Cir. 1983) (The number of hours requested must be proven &#x201C;by submitting meticulous, contemporaneous time records that reveal, for each lawyer for whom fees are sought, all hours for which compensation is requested and how those hours were allotted to specific tasks&#x201D;); <ital>Ellis v. University of Kansas Medical Center</ital>, 163 F.3d 1186, 1202 (10th Cir. 1998) (the application for a fee award should reflect the exercise of &#x201C;billing judgment&#x201D; with respect to the number of hours claimed, excluding from the fee request hours that are redundant, excessive, or otherwise unnecessary);<ital>Malloy v. Monahan</ital>, 73 F.3d 1012, 1018 (10th Cir. 1996) (citing <ital>Blum v. Stenson</ital>, 465 U.S. 886, 895, 104 S.Ct. 1541, 79 L.Ed.2d 891 (1084))(&#x201C;[a] reasonable rate is the prevailing market rate in the relevant community&#x201D;); <ital>Beard v. Teska</ital>, 31 F.3d 942, 956 (10th Cir. 1994) (the relevant market value is not necessarily the price a party's lawyer charged to prosecute the case, but &#x201C;the price that is customarily paid in the community for services like those involved in the case at hand&#x201D;). The undersigned makes the following recommendation applying the foregoing standards.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Plaintiff's billing statements and fee request include fees incurred in the prosecution of a state court action in Blaine County Oklahoma against Oscar J. Boldt Construction, et al. Plaintiff represents that it seeks recovery from other defendants for the same sales to Wire Nuts that are at issue in this action. Plaintiff represents that the Blaine County action is still pending. [Dkt. 30, pp. 2-3]. Plaintiff has offered no authority which would permit this court to award attorney fees incurred in a state court action which has not been removed to federal court and, in fact, is still pending in state court. Given that Plaintiff bears the burden of establishing the reasonableness of each dollar and each hour in the attorney fee request above zero, <ital>Mares v. Credit Bureau of Raton</ital>, 801 F.2d 1197, 1210 (10th Cir. 1986), the undersigned recommends that the court decline to award any fees incurred in prosecution of the state court action.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">The undersigned has reviewed the billing statements and has reduced the number of hours for entries which clearly relate to the state action.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Further, since the party seeking fees is required to submit meticulous, contemporaneous time records that reveal, for each lawyer for whom fees are sought, all hours for which compensation is requested and how those hours were allotted to specific tasks, the undersigned has reduced the number of hours for entries which are redacted to the extent the undersigned cannot discern what work was performed. The undersigned has also reduced the number of hours for performance of purely clerical tasks and where multiple time keepers billed for conferring with each other or where multiple timekeepers logged significant time to accomplish a straightforward task such as the request for extension of time for service.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p6">&#8195;This reduction generally includes those entries related to out of state attorney registration, the motion for summary judgment, discovery, settlement negotiations, and all references to Boldt.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p7">&#8195;The Tenth Circuit has recognized that it may be unreasonable and practically impossible for the district court to identify hours reasonably expended by billing entry or litigation activity. <ital>Case v. Unified School District No 223</ital>, 157 F.3d 1243, 1250 (10th Cir. 1998). &#x201C;There is no requirement <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> that district courts identify and justify each disallowed hour. Nor is there any requirement that district courts announce what hours are permitted for each legal task. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> A general reduction of hours claimed in order to achieve what the court determines to be a reasonable number is not an erroneous method, so long as there is sufficient reason for its use.&#x201D; <ital>Mares v. Credit Bureau of Raton</ital>, 801 F.2d 1197, 1202 (10th Cir. 1986) (citations omitted).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Reductions for the foregoing categories of time result in the following hours for the identified timekeepers: BCK 15.75 hours; LWO 19.5 hours; MSG 2.25 hours; JCF 1.75 hours; MKC 4.0 hours.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p9">&#8195;Hours allowed generally include time after October 2012 in which the activity relates to drafting the complaint and related spreadsheets, admission pro hac vice, service of process, and default.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Generally an hourly rate for an attorney fee award is determined by what attorneys of comparable skill and experience practicing in the area where the litigation occurs charge for their time. The rates for paralegals and interns are determined in the same way. Apart from the affidavit of Brian Kimball, who states that the requested rates are those consistently charged for the services of the timekeepers in Oklahoma and elsewhere, [Dkt. 30-1], Plaintiff has offered no support for the requested hourly rates.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">The undersigned is familiar with the prevailing rates for the Tulsa community. <ital>See D.G. v. Yarbrough</ital>, 08-CV-74-GKF-FHM, [Dkt. 846, pp. 9-11], 2012 WL 7829602 (N.D. Okla.)(finding the prevailing hourly rate for attorneys who had been practicing law from two to thirty years was from $165 to $300 per hour for performing plaintiff's work in a civil rights case). The rate of $300 per hour does not represent the prevailing market rate for all federal litigation in the Northern District of Oklahoma. In the <ital>DG</ital> case the rate of $300 per hour was awarded for the most experienced attorneys engaged in that complicated civil rights litigation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">The work in this case was not legally or factually complicated. Ths case is a collection matter for amounts owing on sales invoices made pursuant to uncomplicated contractual provisions. Default judgment has been rendered against Defendant Wire Nuts. The undersigned finds that the rate of $250 per hour for attorney Brian C. Kimball (BCK) is on the high end for this type of work. However, it is not outside the range of prevailing hourly rates in the community of Tulsa, Oklahoma. At $170 per hour, the hourly rate for Lauren W. Oaks is within the range of prevailing hourly rates for Tulsa, Oklahoma. The undersigned recommends that Plaintiff be awarded its attorney fees based on those rates.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">The rate of $110 per hour is requested for paralegal work. Plaintiff provided no information about the qualifications, skill level, and experience of the paralegals to justify a rate of $110 per hour. The undersigned has recently recommended an award of $70 per hour for paralegal time. <ital>See D.G. v. Yarbrough</ital>, 08-CV-74-GKF-FHM, [Dkt. 846, p. 12], 2012 WL 7829602 (N.D. Okla.). Since nothing has been presented to justify a higher rate, the undersigned recommends that paralegal time be paid at $70 per hour.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">The fee award resulting from the foregoing hours and rates is $7,812.50. (15.75 hours at $250 for time billed by BCK; 19.5 hours at $170 for time billed by LWO; 2.25 hours billed at $70 for time billed by MSG; 1.75 hours at $70 for time billed by JCF; and 4.0 hours billed at $70 for time billed by MKC).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">The undersigned recommends that no award be made for the expenses Plaintiff claims to have incurred. Plaintiff has offered no explanation or justification of the necessity for the expenses appearing on the billing statements. The undersigned has reviewed these statements and has determined that some Westlaw charges do not have a corresponding billing entry, and for some the undersigned cannot determine the nature of the research due to redaction of the billing entries. Some expenses were listed for registration with the Oklahoma Bar Association, and for certificates of good standing from the Supreme Court of Mississippi in connection therewith. No justification is offered for these expenses. The docket sheet reflects two charges for $75 for the fees attendant to motions for admission pro hac vice in this district, but Plaintiff has not requested reimbursement for those expenses. The billing statements contain expenses for &#x201C;Consulting Services&#x201D; from Andrews Davis. No explanation is offered for the necessity or purpose of those expenses. Through review of the Applications for Admission Pro Hac Vice filed in this case, [Dkt. 10, 11], and through review of the later filed request for fees against Defendants William Smith and Janet Smith, [Dkt. 42], the undersigned has determined that Andrews Davis is the law firm engaged as local counsel. Fees for local counsel must be proven by &#x201C;submitting meticulous, contemporaneous time records that reveal, for each lawyer for whom fees are sought, all hours for which compensation is requested and how those hours were allotted to specific tasks.&#x201D; <ital>Ramos v. Lamm</ital>, 713 F.2d 546, 552 (10th Cir. 1983). Listing local counsel's bills as an expense for &#x201C;consulting services&#x201D; does not meet this standard. Finally, the affidavit of attorney Brian Kimball informs the court that the fee request includes &#x201C;$5,325.59 in invoices that have not been billed to Irby on this matter yet.&#x201D; [Dkt. 30-1]. That statement does not establish the reasonableness of each dollar in the request above zero.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">It may be that Plaintiff has incurred recoverable expenses, but the undersigned cannot discern what expenses Plaintiff is attempting to recover, whether the expenses are reasonable, or whether they were incurred in the state court action. In a similar situation the District Court of Kansas stated &#x201C;[d]umping billing statements on the court is not an adequate means of supporting the expenses component of an attorney fee request.&#x201D; <ital>United Phosphorus, Ltd., v. Midland Fumigant, Inc.</ital>, 21 F.Supp.2d 1255, 1262 (D. Kan. 1998). In the <ital>United Phosphorus</ital> case, the court attempted to distill the invoices and calculate totals for each category of expenditures in the plaintiff's fee application, noting that &#x201C;plaintiffs have only themselves to blame&#x201D; for any omission or computational error by the court. <ital>Id.</ital> Such is the case here.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">The undersigned United States Magistrate Judge RECOMMENDS that Plaintiff's Motion for Attorneys' Fees and Costs, [Dkt. 30], be GRANTED in part and DENIED in part and that Plaintiff be awarded the amount of $7,812.50.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">In accordance with 28 U.S.C. &#167;636(b) and Fed. R. Civ. P. 72(b)(2), a party may file specific written objections to this report and recommendation. Such specific written objections must be filed with the Clerk of the District Court for the Northern District of Oklahoma on or before August 2, 2013.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">If specific written objections are timely filed, Fed.R.Civ.P. 72(b)(3) directs the district judge to:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p20" first-line="2" turnover="2">determine de novo any part of the magistrate judge's disposition that has been properly objected to. The district judge may accept, reject, or modify the recommended disposition; receive further evidence; or return the matter to the magistrate judge with instructions.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p21" contd-flag="y">See also 28 U.S.C. &#167; 636(b)(1).</paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">The Tenth Circuit has adopted a &#x201C;firm waiver rule&#x201D; which &#x201C;provides that the failure to make timely objections to the magistrate's findings or recommendations waives appellate review of factual and legal questions.&#x201D; <ital>United States v. One Parcel of Real Property</ital>, 73 F.3d 1057, 1059 (10th Cir. 1996) (quoting <ital>Moore v. United States</ital>, 950 F.2d 656, 659 (10th Cir. 1991)). Only a timely specific objection will preserve an issue for de novo review by the district court or for appellate review.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">DATED this 19th day of July, 2013.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>