<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF OKLAHOMA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>THE RICHARDS GROUP, INC., Plaintiff</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>DECISIONPOINT SYSTEMS, INC., Defendant.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. 14-cv-575-TCK-TLW</docket.line>
<docket.number>14-cv-575-TCK-TLW</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">4:14-cv-00575-TCK-TLW</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed in USDC ND/OK on 01/13/2016</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head>
<headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>REPORT AND RECOMMENDATION</bold></underscore></headtext>
</head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">T. Lane Wilson United States Magistrate Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Before the undersigned United States Magistrate Judge for a report and recommendation is plaintiff The Richards Group, Inc.'s Motion for Attorney Fees. (Dkt. 17). Plaintiff filed this motion for attorney fees in conjunction with a motion for default judgment under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 55(b). (Dkt. 16). The District Court granted the motion for default judgment and referred the issue of attorney fees to the undersigned. (Dkt. 18).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>BACKGROUND INFORMATION<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p2">&#8195;All facts contained in the Background Information section are derived from the Complaint and the affidavits attached to the Motion for Attorney Fees.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Plaintiff is an advertising agency located in Dallas, Texas. (Dkt. 2). Plaintiff contracted with restaurant chain TGIFriday's, Inc. (&#x201C;TGIFriday's&#x201D;) in July 2011 to develop a &#x201C;mobile marketing program&#x201D; that included a mobile app, and again in December 2011 to provide &#x201C;advertising, media, and digital services.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> In January 2012, plaintiff contracted with a company called MacroSolve to develop the mobile app for TGIFriday's. <underscore>Id.</underscore> MacroSolve developed the initial version of the mobile app, which launched in April 2012, and later developed a second version that integrated TGIFriday's rewards program. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">In July 2012, defendant DecisionPoint Systems, Inc. (&#x201C;DecisionPoint&#x201D;) bought MacroSolve and assumed MacroSolve's contracts and liabilities. <underscore>Id.</underscore> DecisionPoint continued to use MacroSolve's End User License Agreement (&#x201C;EULA&#x201D;), which governed the use of the mobile app and the parties' rights and responsibilities. <underscore>Id.</underscore> DecisionPoint developed the third phase of the TGIFriday's mobile app in September 2012. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Plaintiff and DecisionPoint entered into their own agreement in January 2013. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Under the terms of this new contract, DecisionPoint agreed &#x201C;to provide continued hosting and platform licensing&#x201D; for one year for a monthly fee. <underscore>Id.</underscore> The parties entered into another yearly agreement in January 2014. <underscore>Id.</underscore> In addition to hosting the mobile app, DecisionPoint also made multiple updates and added &#x201C;new creative material&#x201D; to the app itself. <underscore>Id.</underscore> The original EULA applied to these annual contracts. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">Under the terms of the EULA, DecisionPoint retained ownership of all technology used to develop the mobile app. (Dkt. 16-2). The EULA also contained a &#x201C;Mutual Indemnification&#x201D; provision. <underscore>Id.</underscore> DecisionPoint agreed to</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p7" first-line="1" turnover="1">indemnify and hold You and Your parent organizations, subsidiaries, affiliates, officers, directors, employees, attorneys and agents harmless from and against any and all claims, costs, damages, losses, liabilities and expenses (including attorneys' fees and costs) arising out of or in connection with: (i) a claim alleging that the Service directly infringes a copyright, a U.S. patent issued as of the Effective Date, or a trademark of a third party; (ii) a claim, which if true, would constitute a violation by Us of Our representations or warranties; or (iii) a claim arising from breach of this Agreement by Us; provided that You (a) promptly give written notice of the claim to Us; (b) give Us sole control of the defense and settlement of the claim (provided that We may not settle or defend any claim unless it unconditionally releases You of all liability); (c) provide to Us all available information and assistance; and (d) have not compromised or settled such claim. We shall have no indemnification obligation, and You shall indemnify Us pursuant to this Agreement, for claims arising from any infringement arising from the combination of the Service with any of Your products, service, hardware or business process(s).</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p8" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Id.</underscore> The EULA defines &#x201C;Service&#x201D; as &#x201C;the online and mobile products, services and platforms, including billing, data analysis, or other services identified during the ordering process, developed, operated, and maintained by us. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">In August 2013, TGIFriday's received a letter from a company named Cascades, &#x201C;alleging that the &#x2018;Service&#x2019; and &#x2018;Technology&#x2019;&#x201D; DecisionPoint licensed to plaintiff for use in the TGIFriday's mobile app infringed on three patents belonging to Cascades. (Dkt. 2). Cascades demanded that TGIFriday's pay a $250,000.00 licensing fee to resolve the issue. <underscore>Id.</underscore> TGIFriday's tendered the letter to plaintiff with a demand that plaintiff defend and indemnify TGIFriday's. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Plaintiff agreed to defend and indemnify. IcL Plaintiff then &#x201C;promptly&#x201D; notified DecisionPoint of Cascades' claim of patent infringement and demanded that DecisionPoint defend the claim, as required by the EULA. <underscore>Id.</underscore> DecisionPoint refused. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">After DecisionPoint refused to defend the claim, plaintiff continued to defend TGIFriday's, incurring attorney fees and costs as a result. <underscore>Id.</underscore> DecisionPoint was non-responsive to plaintiff's continued attempts to have DecisionPoint honor the indemnification provisions of the EULA, prompting plaintiff to file the Complaint in September 2014, alleging breach of contract. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>MOTION FOR DEFAULT JUDGMENT AND ATTORNEY FEES</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">In May 2015, with only the Complaint on the docket, the District Court issued a show cause order to plaintiff. (Dkt. 10). Plaintiff responded with proof of service on DecisionPoint. (Dkt. 12). Plaintiff also requested sixty days in which to file a motion for default judgment, stating that it was currently finalizing a settlement agreement with Cascades on the underlying patent infringement claim. <underscore>Id.</underscore> The District Court granted the request. (Dkt. 13).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Plaintiff filed a Motion for Entry of Default by Clerk in June 2015. (Dkt. 14). The Clerk entered a default judgment the following day. (Dkt. 15). Plaintiff then filed the motion for default judgment, including the request for attorney fees, on July 6, 2015. (Dkt. 16). The District Court granted the motion, awarding plaintiff $75,000.00 in damages for the breach of contract claim. (Dkt. 18). The District Court referred the application for attorney fees and costs to the undersigned for a report and recommendation. (Dkt. 18).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ANALYSIS</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Plaintiff seeks attorney fees under the terms of the EULA and <csc>Okla. Stat.</csc> tit. 12, &#167; 936. (Dkt. 17). Plaintiff seeks $67,368.42 in fees and costs for defending and settling the patent infringement suit and $23,027.55 in fees and costs associated with the instant breach of contract claim. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Plaintiff also requests $15,000.00 in fees for the anticipated cost of collecting the judgment. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>Eligibility for Attorney Fees</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">The EULA's indemnification clause provides for recovery of the attorney fees incurred in defending and settling the patent infringement case. (Dkt. 16-2 at 12). The EULA does not address indemnification in the event of a lawsuit to address a breach of the EULA contract itself. <underscore>Id.</underscore> However, the EULA contains a choice of law provision stating that, &#x201C;[w]ith respect to U.S. customers, this Agreement shall be governed by Oklahoma law and controlling United States federal law, without regard to the choice or conflicts of law provisions of any jurisdiction. <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 15. Therefore, Oklahoma law governs plaintiff's ability to recover attorney fees associated with DecisionPoint's failure to indemnify plaintiff in the patent infringement suit.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Plaintiff contends that it is entitled to recover those fees under <csc>Okla. Stat.</csc> tit. 12, &#167; 936. (Dkt. 17). That statute provides,</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="1" turnover="1">In any civil action to recover for labor or services rendered, or on an open account, a statement of account, account stated, not bill, negotiable instrument, or contract relating to the purchase or sale of goods, wares, or merchandise, unless otherwise provided by law or the contract which is the subject of the action, the prevailing party shall be allowed a reasonable attorney fee to be set by the court, to be taxed and collected as costs.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p17" contd-flag="y"><csc>Okla. Stat.</csc> tit. 12, &#167; 936. The Oklahoma Supreme Court narrowly construes this provision, holding that fees should only be awarded in &#x201C;actions for the collection of monetary consideration promised as payment for the receipt of property, labor or services.&#x201D; <underscore>Kay v. Venezuelan Sun Oil Co.</underscore>, 806 P.2d 648, 650-52, 651 n.12 (Okla. 1991) (outlining previous cases in which the Oklahoma Supreme Court rejected a &#x201C;liberal interpretation of &#167; 936&#x201D; and instead limited recovery of attorney fees to &#x201C;actions for money judgments for debts created by the contracts enumerated in the statute.&#x201D;). More specifically, in <underscore>Russell v. Flanagan</underscore>, 544 P.2d 510, 512 (Okla. 1975), the Oklahoma Supreme Court determined that the phrase &#x201C;relating to&#x201D; in the statute modifies the phrase &#x201C;the purchase or sale of goods, wares, or merchandise&#x201D; as opposed to the phrase &#x201C;for labor or services.&#x201D; The Tenth Circuit has noted this strict interpretation of &#167; 936, holding that attorney fees are not recoverable in cases where the &#x201C;claim relates to the performance of labor or services.&#x201D; <underscore>Merrick v. Northern Natural Gas. Co., Div. of Enron Corp.</underscore>, 911 F.2d 426, 434 (10th Cir. 1990) (quoting <underscore>Burrows Constr. Co. v. Independent Sch. Dist. No. 2 of Stephens County</underscore>, 704 P.2d 1136, 1138 (Okla. 1985); see <underscore>also Specialty Beverages, L.L.C. v. Pabst Brewing Co.</underscore>, 537 F.3d 1165, 1184 (10th Cir. 2008).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">In this case, plaintiff's Complaint sought a declaratory judgment interpreting the indemnification clause in the EULA and damages for breach of contract relating to the indemnification clause. Accordingly, plaintiff was not, through its claims, seeking to recover payment for labor or services rendered. Therefore, plaintiff is not entitled to attorney fees under <csc>Okla. Stat.</csc> tit. 12, &#167; 936.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> As noted, however, the EULA does permit recovery of attorney fees for plaintiff's defense of the patent infringement claim.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p19">&#8195;Lackey Hershman and Conner &#38; Winters represent plaintiff in this action. Although their billing records indicate that the attorneys in these firms communicated with plaintiff and with counsel in the patent infringement case to discuss timing of settlement and strategy, the undersigned finds that most of these entries were intended to further this litigation rather than to provide services in the patent infringement case. The limited entries that do relate directly to work performed on the settlement agreement are discussed in the calculation of fees, <ital>infra.</ital></paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Reasonableness of Fees Incurred Defending the Patent Infringement Claim</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">The Oklahoma Supreme Court has outlined a two-step procedure for arriving at a reasonable attorney fee: (1) determine the lodestar fee, which is the reasonable hourly compensation on an &#x201C;hours times rate basis,&#x201D; and (2) enhance or reduce the lodestar fee, if warranted, by adding or subtracting an amount arrived at by applying the factors set forth in <underscore>Burk v. City of Oklahoma City</underscore>, 598 P.2d 659 (Okla. 1979). The twelve factors cited for consideration of an award above or below the lodestar amount, if the circumstances so warrant, are as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p21" first-line="1" turnover="1">1. Time and labor required. 2. The novelty and difficulty of the questions. 3. The skill requisite to perform the legal service properly. 4. The preclusion of other employment by the attorney due to acceptance of the case. 5. The customary fee. 6. Whether the fee is fixed or contingent. 7. Time limitations imposed by the client or the circumstances. 8. The amount involved and the results obtained. 9. The experience, reputation and ability of the attorneys. 10. The &#x2018;undesirability&#x2019; of the case. 11. The nature and length of the professional relationship with the client. 12. Awards in similar cases.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p22" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Id.</underscore> at 661.</paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">The applicant &#x201C;bears the burden of establishing entitlement to an award and documenting the appropriate hours expended and hourly rates. The applicant should exercise &#x2018;billing judgment&#x2019; with respect to hours worked [] and should maintain billing time records in a manner that will enable a reviewing court to identify distinct claims.&#x201D; <underscore>Hensley v. Eckerhart</underscore>, 461 U.S. 424, 437, 103 S.Ct. 1933, 76 L.Ed.2d 40 (1983) (internal citation omitted). Finally, &#x201C;[t]he product of reasonable hours times a reasonable rate does not end the inquiry.&#x201D; <underscore>Hensley</underscore>, 461 U.S. at 434. A reviewing court must also consider &#x201C;the important factor of the &#x2018;results obtained.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> &#x201C;Work on an unsuccessful claim&#x201D; cannot be included in the calculation for a reasonable fee. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 435.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Hunton &#38; Williams represented plaintiff against the patent infringement claim. The undersigned has reviewed the timesheets from Hunton &#38; Williams and finds that the time reflected is reasonable; however, some of the hourly rates are not.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Timesheets from Hunton and Williams indicate that five people &#8212; identified as J.R. Holzgraefe, E.J. Hanson, B.W. Grout, M. Dye, and W.J. Ross &#8211; performed services for plaintiff. (Dkt. 16-1 at 59-118). The timesheets do not identify the timekeepers as attorneys, and a search of the professionals section at Hunton &#38; Williams website identified only two of the five timekeepers: Holzgraefe as a partner in Dallas specializing in business transactions, and Hanson, a partner in Atlanta specializing in intellectual property and patent law. <underscore>See www.hunton.com</underscore> (last visited on January 8, 2016). Based on the hourly rates and the work performed, the undersigned has concluded that Grout and Ross are also attorneys. The time entry by Grout on April 29, 2014, identifies Dye as a &#x201C;research specialist.&#x201D; (Dkt. 16-1 at 86). The undersigned equates this title with that of a paralegal.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">The hourly fees<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> sought are as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p27" first-line="2" turnover="2">J.R. Holzgraefe: $666.00 per hour;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" first-line="2" turnover="2">E.J. Hanson: $541.00 per hour;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" first-line="2" turnover="2">B.W. Grout: $551.00 per hour;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" first-line="2" turnover="2">W.J. Ross: $270.00 per hour; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" first-line="2" turnover="2">M. Dye: $200.00 per hour.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p32" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Id.</underscore> at 59-118. An affidavit from Lackey Hershman attorney Jamie R. Welton provides the only support for the reasonableness of the hourly rates. (Dkt. 16-1 at 1-6). In that affidavit, Mr. Welton states, &#x201C;I oversaw the resolution of the Patent Infringement Claim, have personally reviewed Hunton &#38; Williams' invoices, and in my opinion the legal services rendered and costs incurred were reasonable and necessary.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 4.</paratext>
</para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p33">&#8195;These hourly rates are based on the undersigned's calculations, as the timesheets do not list hourly rates.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">The Tenth Circuit defines a reasonable hourly rate as &#x201C;the prevailing market rate in the relevant community.&#x201D; <underscore>Malloy v. Monahan</underscore>, 73 F.3d 1012, 1018 (10th Cir. 1996) (citing <underscore>Blum v. Stenson</underscore>, 465 U.S. 886, 895, 104 S.Ct. 1541, 79 L.Ed.2d 891 (1984)). The relevant community in this case is the Northern District of Oklahoma. Based on the undersigned's experience on other fee matters in this district and a review of recent case law in Oklahoma's federal courts, the undersigned finds that the hourly rates charged by Holzgraefe, Hanson, and Grout are not reasonable in this community, regardless of the attorneys' skill or experience. See, <underscore>e.g., OuikTrip Corp. v. Jahaver et al.</underscore>, 2015 WL 7103558 (N.D.Okla. November 13, 2015) (holding that a $340.00 hourly rate was reasonable for work on an ERISA appeal); <underscore>Sundance Energy Oklahoma, LLC v. Dan P. Drilling Corp.</underscore>, 2015 WL 3849409 (W.D.Okla. June 22, 2015) (reducing the hourly rate from $375.00 to $300.00); and <underscore>Bishop v. Smith</underscore>, 2015 WL 4086356 (N.D.Okla. May 1, 2015) (finding a $400.00 hourly rate reasonable in a case involving issues of constitutional law).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">After reviewing the website profiles for Holzgraefe<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> and Hanson<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference>, the undersigned finds that an hourly rate of $400.00 for Holzgraefe and $380.00 for Hanson is consistent with the local market and reflective of the skill and expertise of these attorneys. The undersigned was not able to find any information regarding the experience of attorneys Grout and Ross<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference>; therefore, the undersigned has assigned a lower hourly rate of $300.00 and $200.00, respectively, for the work performed by these attorneys. Likewise, $200.00 is an excessive hourly rate for paralegal work in this district, and the undersigned recommends a reduced rate of $100.00 for the work performed by Dye. See, e.g., <underscore>Seifried v. Portfolio Recovery Associates, LLC</underscore>, 2014 WL 2916757 (E.D.Okla. June 26, 2014) (approving an $85.00 hourly rate for paralegal work); <underscore>EQ-Environmental Quality Co. v. FMRI, Inc.</underscore>, 2014 WL 1774490 (E.D. Okla. April 29, 2014) (permitting a $125.00 hourly rate for paralegal work).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p36">&#8195;Holzgraefe has been practicing since 1980 and specializes in mergers and acquisitions and transactional law involving private equity firms. <underscore>See https://www.hunton.com/John_Holzgraefe/</underscore> (last visited January 8, 2016). He also has experience in intellectual property, including the acquisition and licensing of IP rights. <underscore>See id.</underscore></paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p37">&#8195;Hanson is a registered patent attorney who has practiced law since 1998. <underscore>See https://www.hunton.com/Eric_Hanson/</underscore> (last visited on January 8, 2016). He exclusively practices in the area of intellectual property. <underscore>See id.</underscore></paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p38">&#8195;Even though the undersigned was unable to ascertain the skill level and expertise of these attorneys, based on the scale of the fees in this case, the undersigned presumes that Grout was an experienced attorney and that Ross was likely a younger associate attorney. While Ross's hourly rate of $270.00 is not out of line with the prevailing market rates in Tulsa, Oklahoma, it is at the higher end and, therefore, would not be an appropriate hourly rate for a less experienced attorney.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p39">&#8195;Those time entries are dated April 8-22, 2015, and May 2, 14, and 15, 2015. (Dkt. 16-1 at 41-44).</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">Attorney Walton with Lackey Hershman also performed some work on the patent infringement claim, related solely to the drafting and revision of the settlement agreement in April and May 2015.<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference> (Dkt. 16-1 at 41-46). Mr. Walton charged an hourly fee of $425.00. <underscore>Id.</underscore> That rate is higher than the prevailing market rate in Tulsa, Oklahoma. Based on Mr. Walton's experience (15 years as a commercial litigator), as outlined in his affidavit (dkt. 16-1 at 1-2), the undersigned recommends a reduction in Mr. Walton's hourly rate from $425.00 to $325.00.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">After calculating the number of hours worked, the resulting fee is as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p42" first-line="2" turnover="2">Holzgraefe: 33.8 hours X $400.00 = $13,520.00</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" first-line="2" turnover="2">Hanson: 67.3 hours X $380.00 = $25,574.00</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p44" first-line="2" turnover="2">Grout: 7.6 hours X $300.00 = $2,280.00</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" first-line="2" turnover="2">Ross: 2.0 hours X $200.00 = $400.00</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p46" first-line="2" turnover="2">Dye: 2.8 hours X $100.00 = $280.00</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p47" first-line="2" turnover="2">Walton: 4.8 hours X $325.00 = $1,560.00</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p48" contd-flag="y">for a total fee award of $43,614.00.</paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">The timesheets also indicate that Hunton &#38; Williams incurred $59.62 in expenses associated with delivery services and research. Those expenses are reasonable and should be awarded.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>RECOMMENDATION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">For these reasons, the undersigned recommends that the District Court <bold>GRANT IN PART</bold> plaintiff's motion for attorney fees (dkt. 17) in the amount of $43,614.00, to be distributed as set forth in the Report and Recommendation.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>OBJECTION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p51" level="1">In accordance with 28 U.S.C. &#167; 636(b) and Fed. R. Civ. P. 72(b)(2), a party may file specific written objections to this report and recommendation. Such specific written objections must be filed with the Clerk of the District Court for the Northern District of Oklahoma by January 27, 2016.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p52" level="1">If specific written objections are timely filed, Fed. R. Civ. P. 72(b)(3) directs the district judge to:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p53" first-line="1" turnover="1">determine <ital>de novo</ital> any part of the magistrate judge's disposition that has been properly objected to. The district judge may accept, reject, or modify the recommended disposition; receive further evidence; or return the matter to the magistrate judge with instructions.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p54" contd-flag="y">See also 28 U.S.C. &#167; 636(b)(1).</paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p55" level="1">The Tenth Circuit has adopted a &#x201C;firm waiver rule&#x201D; which &#x201C;provides that the failure to make timely objections to the magistrate's findings or recommendations waives appellate review of factual and legal questions.&#x201D; <underscore>United States v. One Parcel of Real Property</underscore>, 73 F.3d 1057, 1059 (10th Cir. 1996) (quoting <underscore>Moore v. United States</underscore>, 950 F.2d 656, 659 (10th Cir. 1991)). Only a timely specific objection will preserve an issue for <ital>de novo</ital> review by the district court or for appellate review.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p56" level="1">Submitted this 13th day of January, 2016.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>