<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>NORTHERN DISTRICT OF OKLAHOMA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment><bold>STUART C. IRBY COMPANY, Plaintiff</bold></title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment><bold>WIRE NUTS ELECTRIC, INC., CHRISTY MCGILL, WILLIAM SMITH, and JANET SMITH, Defendants.</bold></title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line><bold>Case No. 12-CV-0617-CVE-FHM</bold></docket.line>
<docket.number><bold>12-CV-0617-CVE-FHM</bold></docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">4:12-cv-00617-CVE-FHM</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed in USDC ND/OK on 08/06/2013</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head>
<headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>ORDER</bold></underscore></headtext>
</head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">CLAIRE V. EAGAN UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">On July 19, 2013, Magistrate Judge Frank H. McCarthy entered a Report and Recommendation (Dkt. # 47) recommending that Plaintiff Stuart C. Irby Company's Motion for Attorney's Fees and Costs (Dkt. # 30) be granted in part and denied in part. On March 26, 2013, the Court entered default judgment in favor of plaintiff and against defendant Wire Nuts Electric, Inc. (Wire Nuts) in the amount of $179,682.36, plus accrued service charges of $80,120.54. Plaintiff requests attorney fees in the amount of $34,142.23 under the terms and conditions of sale incorporated to the Application for Credit completed by Wire Nuts. The magistrate judge reviewed plaintiff's motion, and he stated that the number of hours billed by plaintiff's counsel was excessive and that the hourly rate billed for attorney work did not represent the prevailing market rate. He recommended that the Court award attorney fees in the amount of $7,812.50. Plaintiff has not filed an objection to the report and recommendation. The Court has independently reviewed the report and recommendation, and finds no reason to modify or reject it. Plaintiff has served its motion for attorney fees and costs on Wire Nuts, and Wire Nuts has not filed a response. In addition, Wire Nuts has not filed an objection to the magistrate judge's report and recommendation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1"><bold>IT IS THEREFORE ORDERED</bold> that the Report and Recommendation (Dkt. # 47) is <bold>accepted</bold>, and Plaintiff Stuart C. Irby Company's Motion for Attorney's Fees and Costs (Dkt. # 30) is <bold>granted in part</bold> and <bold>denied in part</bold>. A separate judgment awarding attorney fees and costs to plaintiff in the amount of $7,812.50 is entered herewith.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1"><bold>DATED</bold> this 6th day of August, 2013.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>