<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>NORTHERN DISTRICT OF WEST VIRGINIA</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>MARTINSBURG</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment><bold>EDWARD LANG and GEORGIANA LANG</bold>, Plaintiffs</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment><bold>WELLS FARGO HOME MORTGAGE, INC., a division of WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A., and HSBC BANK USA, N.A.</bold>, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line><bold>Civil Action No. 3:13-CV-60 (BAILEY)</bold></docket.line>
<docket.number><bold>3:13-CV-60 (BAILEY)</bold></docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">3:13-cv-00060-JPB-JES</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 09/23/2013</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head>
<headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>ORDER DENYING PLAINTIFFS' MOTION TO REMAND</bold></underscore></headtext>
</head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">JOHN PRESTON BAILEY CHIEF UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Currently pending before this Court is the plaintiffs' Motion to Remand [Doc. 9], filed July 11, 2013. The defendants filed a response in opposition on July 25, 2013 [Doc. 12], and the plaintiffs replied on August 1, 2013 [Doc. 14]. The Court has reviewed the record and the arguments of the parties and, for the reasons set out below, concludes that the motion should be <bold>DENIED</bold>.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>BACKGROUND</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">I. <underscore>Factual Allegations</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">According to the Complaint, the action &#x201C;arises out of the practice known as predatory lending, whereby regulated lenders solicit unsophisticated borrowers and fraudulently persuade them into unwise and illegal home equity loans.&#x201D; [Doc. 1-1 at &#182; 1] (internal citations omitted). In this case, the plaintiffs allege that defendant Wells Fargo closed two loans with the plaintiffs in the amount of $200,000 and $37,500 [Id. at &#182;&#182; 8, 9]. The plaintiffs claim that the loans' provisions were unreasonable [Id. at &#182; 7]. They also claim that the defendant promised it would provide refinancing after two years, but later refused to provide them with a consolidated loan with a lower interest rate [Id. at &#182; 11].</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. <underscore>Procedural History</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">On May 2, 2013, the plaintiffs filed suit against, <ital>inter alia</ital>, Wells Fargo in the Circuit Court of Jefferson County, West Virginia [Doc. 1-1]. In Count I of the Complaint, the plaintiffs assert a claim of unconscionable inducement against Wells Fargo [Id. at &#182;&#182; 15&#8211;21]. As relief, the plaintiffs request the following: &#x201C;(a) The Court order the Defendant to pay the holder of the loan; (b) Actual damages plus civil penalties; (c) Reasonable attorney's fees <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> and (d) Such other relief as the Court may deem equitable and just.&#x201D; [Id. at 12]. Count II of the claim asserts a contract defense of fraud and seeks equitable relief and attorney's fees. [Id. at &#182;&#182; 22&#8211;28]. Count III claims illegal debt collection and the plaintiffs seek actual damages and civil penalties and attorney's fees and costs [Id. at &#182;&#182; 29&#8211;31]. The plaintiffs' complaint does not stipulate that alleged damages are no greater than $75,000.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">On May 31, 2013, Wells Fargo removed the above-styled matter to this Court pursuant to 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1446 [Doc. 1]. Wells Fargo bases federal jurisdiction upon diversity jurisdiction pursuant to 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1332, under which federal district courts have original jurisdiction if the case involves citizens of different states and the amount in controversy exceeds $75,000.00, exclusive of interest and costs [Id. at 3]. Wells Fargo argues that the amount in controversy requirement is met for three reasons. First, because the plaintiffs argue that the loans are unenforceable, the defendant claims that the collective value of those instruments, $235,000, should be included in determining the amount in controversy [Id. at 5]. Second, the defendant contends that the value of the equitable relief the plaintiffs seek, a Court order prohibiting the defendant from foreclosing or otherwise enforcing the terms of the Deeds of Trust, exceeds $75,000 [Id. at 6]. Third, the defendant argues that the plaintiffs' request for costs and attorneys' fees incurred in the litigation, taken together, satisfy the amount in controversy requirement [Id.].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">On July 11, 2013, the plaintiffs filed the instant Motion to Remand [Doc. 9], contending that the defendants have failed to establish that the pecuniary impact of the relief requested by the plaintiffs exceeds $75,000. The plaintiffs contest the defendant's assertion that the plaintiffs seek to declare the loan contracts null and void [Doc. 9-1 at 6]. The plaintiffs assert that they do not seek to declare the loan unenforceable, and could not because the West Virginia Consumer Credit and Protection Act does not allow a Court to cancel a debt obligation [Id.]. The plaintiffs contend that they are seeking actual damages and civil penalties, fees and costs, equitable relief, and for the Court to order the defendant to pay the holder of the loan [Id]. The plaintiffs also contest the defendant's equitable relief calculations. The plaintiffs state that they do not seek a Court order prohibiting the defendants from foreclosing on the home, and the defendants would not be able to seek foreclosure, because the plaintiffs are current on their payments. The plaintiffs further claim that they make no allegations in the Complaint which would give rise to a permanent injunction against enforcing the loan agreement [Id. at 8]. The plaintiffs construe their complaint as seeking a loan modification &#x201C;to reasonable terms&#x201D; and aver that the defendants provide no evidence that such relief exceeds the amount in controversy requirement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">On July 25, 2013, Wells Fargo filed its Response [Doc. 12], arguing first that the plaintiffs' motion mischaracterizes the relief sought in the Complaint and the relevant case law, and second that the plaintiffs' failure to stipulate that their damages do not exceed $75,000 is evidence that the amount in controversy is met in this case [Id. at 3&#8211;9]. With respect to the first argument, the defendant claims the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p7" first-line="2" turnover="1">1) The language of the Complaint requests the &#x201C;Court [to] order the Defendant to pay the holder of the loan&#x201D; [Id. at 3]. According to the defendant, this claim, if successful, would require the defendant to tender at least the outstanding principal balance of the $200,000 loan and therefore the amount in controversy requirement is satisfied [Id.].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" first-line="2" turnover="1">2) If the loans were determined to be unenforceable, the defendants would stand to lose the outstanding balance of the loans, which exceed $75,000. The Customer Service Record, Wells Fargo emphasizes, shows that the unpaid principal balance as of the filing of the Notice of Removal was $199,233.45 on the first loan [Id. at 7].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" first-line="2" turnover="1">3) The plaintiffs are seeking, but should not be permitted, to remold their allegations to seek a loan modification as opposed to an order rendering the debt unenforceable [Id. at 7]. The defendants claim that the Complaint makes no mention of loan modifications and therefore should be ignored.</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">With respect to the failure to stipulate that damages do not exceed $75,000, the defendant claims that the election to not file such a stipulation is evidence that the threshold is met in this action [Id. at 8&#8211;9].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">On August 1, 2013, the plaintiffs filed their Reply [Doc. 14], reiterating their previous argument that the defendants failed to meet their burden of establishing the relief sought by the plaintiffs exceeds the amount in controversy. Specifically, the plaintiffs reiterate that they do not seek to declare the mortgage loans unenforceable, but only that certain aspects are unenforceable because certain terms are unconscionable [Id. at 2]. The plaintiffs claim that the West Virginia Consumer Credit and Protection Act would allow the Court to limit the application of unconscionable terms, such as high interest rates and the provisions which states that payments are not applied toward the principle balance [Id. at 2&#8211;3]. Further, the plaintiffs claim that any estimate of the relief available in the form of a loan modification or partial loan forgiveness cannot be determined with any certainty at this stage of the litigation [Id. at 4]. Finally, the plaintiffs contest the defendant's assertion that the absence of a stipulation acts as evidence in the defendant's attempt to meet their evidentiary burden [Id. at 4&#8211;5].</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>DISCUSSION</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">I. <underscore>Applicable Standard</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">In a removal action in which federal jurisdiction is premised upon 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1332, the defendant bears the burden of proving that the plaintiffs' claim exceeds the jurisdictional amount. <ital><bold>Landmark Corp. v. Apogee Coal Co.</bold></ital>, 945 F. Supp. 932, 935 (S.D. W.Va. 1996). Often, this burden is settled without argument because a plaintiff's good-faith claim for specific monetary damages in the complaint binds the defendant. <ital><bold>St. Paul Mercury Indem. Co. v. Red Cab Co.</bold></ital>, 303 U.S. 283, 288 (1938); <ital>see also <bold>Horton v. Liberty Mut. Ins. Co.</bold></ital>, 367 U.S. 348, 353 (1961) (stating that general federal rule is that complaint determines the amount in controversy and, consequently, federal jurisdiction). However, when the complaint's <ital>ad damnum</ital> clause does not specifically state the amount in controversy, several courts require the removing defendant to prove by a preponderance of the evidence that the value of the matter in controversy exceeds the jurisdictional amount. <ital>See, e.g., <bold>Tapscott v. MS Dealer Serv. Corp.</bold></ital>, 77 F.3d 1353, 1357 (11th Cir. 1996).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">In order to meet the preponderance of the evidence standard and to establish jurisdiction upon removal, a defendant must show that it is more likely than not that the amount in controversy exceeds the jurisdictional amount. <ital><bold>Landmark Corp.</bold></ital>, 945 F. Supp. at 935 (citing <ital><bold>Tapscott</bold></ital>, 77 F.3d at 1357). To satisfy this burden, a defendant must offer more than a bare allegation that the amount in controversy exceeds $75,000.00. <ital>See <bold>Gaus v. Miles, Inc.</bold></ital>, 980 F.2d 564, 567 (9th Cir. 1992). Instead, a defendant seeking removal must &#x201C;supply evidence to support his claim regarding the amount at issue in the case.&#x201D; <ital><bold>Sayre v. Potts</bold></ital>, 32 F. Supp. 2d 881, 886 (S.D. W.Va. 1999).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Specifically, the amount in controversy is determined by &#x201C;considering the judgment that would be entered if the plaintiff prevailed on the merits of his case as it stands at the time of removal.&#x201D; <ital><bold>Id.</bold></ital> (citing <ital><bold>Landmark Corp.</bold></ital>, 945 F.Supp. at 636&#8211;37). To calculate this amount, a court must consider the entire record and make an independent evaluation of whether the amount in controversy has been satisfied. <ital><bold>Weddington v. Ford Motor Credit Co.</bold></ital>, 59 F. Supp. 2d 578, 584 (S.D. W.Va. 1999); <ital>see also <bold>Mullins v. Harry's Mobile Homes</bold></ital>, 861 F. Supp. 22, 24 (S.D. W.Va. 1994) (specifically stating that court may consider complaint, removal petition, and &#x201C;other relevant matters in the file&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Finally, the Fourth Circuit &#x201C;ascertain[s] the value of an injunction for amount in controversy purposes by reference to the larger of two figures: the injunction worth to the plaintiff or its cost to the defendant.&#x201D; <ital><bold>JTH Tax, Inc. v. Frashier</bold></ital>, 624 F.3d 635, 639 (4th Cir. 2010); <ital>see also <bold>Lee v. Citimortgage, Inc.</bold></ital>, 2010 WL 3632771, *5 (E.D. Va. 2010) (acknowledging that most courts use &#x201C;plaintiff approach,&#x201D; but held that Fourth Circuit utilizes &#x201C;either party approach&#x201D;). Similarly, when a plaintiff asks a court to declare a contract null and void, the focus of the amount in controversy inquiry is the value of the contract to either party. <ital>See <bold>Dixon v. Edwards</bold></ital>, 290 F.3d 699, 710&#8211;11 (4th Cir. 2002). <bold>II. <underscore>Analysis</underscore></bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">There is no question that diversity of citizenship exists between the plaintiffs and the defendants. The sole issue presented by the instant motion is whether this action involves the requisite amount in controversy. The Court finds that the $75,000 threshold is met because the plaintiffs' Complaint seeks to declare the contract null and void and therefore the full amount of the plaintiffs' loan should be considered in determining the amount in controversy.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">As outlined above, when a plaintiff seeks to declare an installment contract null and void, a Court should consider the total value of the contract to either party when determining the amount in controversy. <ital>See <bold>Dixon</bold></ital>, 290 F.3d at 710&#8211;11; <ital><bold>Davis</bold></ital>, 94 F.2d at 443. As partial relief for the unconscionable inducement claim, the plaintiffs request that the Court &#x201C;order the Defendant to pay the holder of the loan.&#x201D; [Doc. 1-1 at &#182; 12]. The plaintiffs claim that &#x201C;[t]he two loan agreements <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> were unconscionable, under all circumstances alleged, at the time they were made and/or were induced by unconscionable conduct, and therefore were unenforceable under West Virginia Code &#167; 46S-2-121&#x201D; [Id.].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The defendants assert that the claim seeks to have the Court declare the contract null and void and, therefore, the collective value of the two loans should be included in determining the amount in controversy. The plaintiffs counter that they do not seek to cancel the two loans because under the West Virginia Credit and Consumer Protection Act, such relief is unavailable contend in their motion that they do not seek the cancellation of their debt obligations.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">This Court agrees with the defendant that the plaintiffs' Complaint seeks not a loan modification but that the Court declare the loans void and unenforceable. As such, the total of the payments that the plaintiffs would make to Wells Fargo over the course of their loans will be considered. Given that the value of the two loans is $235,000, this amount satisfies the amount in controversy requirement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">The Court is not persuaded by the plaintiffs' contention that they seek a loan modification. Nowhere in the Complaint do the plaintiffs make mention of a loan modification. Diversity jurisdiction is determined as of the date the suit is filed. <ital>See, e.g., <bold>Porsche Cars N. Am., Inc. v. Porsche.Net</bold></ital>, 302 F.3d 248, 255&#8211;56 (4th Cir. 2002) (holding that diversity determinations are unaffected by later &#x201C;changes in originally crucial facts such as the <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> amount in controversy&#x201D;) (internal citations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Diversity jurisdiction existed when the action was filed and removed to this court; the plaintiffs' later claims that would reduce any damages provide no basis for remanding this case.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Insofar as the value of the plaintiffs' loans exceeds $75,000.00, the Court finds that Wells Fargo has met its burden of showing by a preponderance of the evidence that this case meets the amount in controversy requirement associated with diversity jurisdiction. Accordingly, this Court has original jurisdiction and removal was appropriate.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>CONCLUSION</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">For the reasons stated above, this Court finds that the plaintiff's Motion to Remand <bold>[Doc. 9]</bold> should be, and hereby is, <bold>DENIED</bold>. It is so <bold>ORDERED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">The Clerk is directed to transmit copies of this Order to all counsel of record herein.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1"><bold>DATED</bold>: September 23, 2013.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>