<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF WEST VIRGINIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>FRASIER HEALTHCARE CONSULTING, INC., Plaintiff</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>GRANT MEMORIAL HOSPITAL REGIONAL HEALTHCARE CENTER, Defendant.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Civil Action No. 2:12-cv-87</docket.line>
<docket.number>2:12-cv-87</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:12-cv-00087-JPB-JES</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 01/09/2014</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head>
<headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>ORDER GRANTING PLAINTIFF'S MOTION TO COMPEL</bold></underscore></headtext>
</head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">JAMES E. SEIBERT UNITED STATES MAGISTRATE JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">On December 6, 2013, came the above named Plaintiff, by Christopher Sears, Esq., in person, and Defendant Grant Memorial Hospital (&#x201C;Defendant&#x201D;), by William Galeota, Esq. And William O'Brien, Esq., in person, for an evidentiary hearing and argument on Plaintiff's Motion to Compel Defendant's Response to Request for Production of Documents. Plaintiff offered the testimony of Robert Frasier and Daren Bush, and Defendant offered the testimony of Joe Allen Barnes. Additionally, both parties offered exhibits into evidence.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. INTRODUCTION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><ital>A. Background</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">Plaintiff provides billing and collection services to healthcare facilities. In 2011, Plaintiff and Defendant entered into a written contract whereby Plaintiff was to provide billing and collection support to Defendant. Under the contract, Defendant was required to assign certain categories of overdue patient accounts to Plaintiff, and Plaintiff was to receive compensation for its collection services on a sliding pricing scale based on the age of the assigned delinquent accounts. In order to track the accounts, Defendant was required to provide Plaintiff with weekly payment reports. According to Plaintiff, Defendant initially provided it with so-called &#x201C;sequel reports&#x201D; which showed all cash posted on all accounts. However, Plaintiff alleges that at some point during the course of the contract, Defendant &#x201C;changed or implemented reporting procedures for late postings that caused Plaintiff to not earn commissions&#x201D; and refused to provide Plaintiff with the aforementioned sequel reports.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">On December 13, 2012, Plaintiff filed this action alleging that Defendant breached the terms of that contract by failing to provide timely and accurate payment records which caused Plaintiff to miss payments to which it claims it was entitled under the contract. On January 15, 2013, Plaintiff served Defendant with a summons and the Complaint, as well as Plaintiff's First Set of Interrogatories and Requests for Production of Documents. On February 5, 2013, the parties filed a joint stipulation,<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> which acknowledged that Plaintiff's discovery requests were premature under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26. The parties also stipulated that &#x201C;counsel for the parties have conferred and agreed that additional time and a stay of these proceedings for the purpose of informally exchanging additional information, pursuing further negotiations and possibly conducting a non-binding mediation would mutually serve all interests.&#x201D; The parties agreed to file a status report with the Court on or before March 29, 2013. The Court stayed the proceedings by Stipulation and Order dated February 5, 2013.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p4">&#8195;Dkt. No. 9.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p5">&#8195;Dkt. No. 10.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">On March 28, 2013, the parties filed a joint status report with the Court in which they advised the Court that the action should proceed and moved the Court to lift the stay.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> The parties further stipulated that they had conferred pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(f), and that they agreed that Defendant's responses to Plaintiff's previously served discovery requests would be due on or before April 5, 2013. On April 2, 2013, the Court lifted the stay.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> Pursuant to the parties' agreement, Defendant served its Responses to Plaintiff's First Set of Interrogatories and Request for Production of Documents on April 4, 2013. Plaintiff filed the instant Motion to Compel<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> on November 8, 2013, and Defendant filed a Response in Opposition<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference> on November 22, 2013. The Court held an evidentiary hearing and argument on Plaintiff's Motion to Compel on November 27, 2013. However, at that hearing, the undersigned noted that there was a direct conflict in argument regarding whether the requested discovery was actually in existence, but neither party produced any additional testimony or evidence in support of its claims. Accordingly, the Court rescheduled the hearing and ordered both parties to produce all necessary witnesses with personal knowledge of the accounts receivable reports on which this Motion is based. The rescheduled hearing was held on December 6, 2013.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p7">&#8195;Dkt. No. 11.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p8">&#8195;Dkt. No. 12.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p9">&#8195;Dkt. No. 23.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p10">&#8195;Dkt. No. 27.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><ital><bold>B. The Motions</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">1. Plaintiff's Motion to Compel Defendant's Response to Request for Production of Documents.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><ital><bold>C. Decision</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Plaintiff's Motion to Compel is <bold>GRANTED</bold> because the requested sequel reports are discoverable electronically stored information (&#x201C;ESI&#x201D;) in Defendant's possession, custody, or control. Additionally, cost-shift is not appropriate because producing the reports will not result in an undue burden to Defendant.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. PLAINTIFF'S MOTION TO COMPEL DISCOVERY</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold><ital>A. Contentions of the Parties</ital></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Plaintiff seeks an order compelling Defendant to produce monthly sequel reports in response to Requests for Production of Documents 1, 2, 3, and 4. The discovery requests and Defendant's responses are as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p14" first-line="2" turnover="2"><bold>Request for Production 1</bold>: Please produce the monthly sequel reports on all self-pay patient accounts in the accounts receivable of Grant Memorial Hospital Trust Foundation, Incorporated from September 1, 2011 to June 30, 2012.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" first-line="2" turnover="2"><bold>Request for Production 2</bold>: Please produce the monthly sequel reports on all patient accounts aged 120 days or more in the accounts receivable of Grant Memorial Hospital Trust Foundation, Incorporated from September 1, 2011 to June 30, 2012.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="2" turnover="2"><bold>Request for Production 3</bold>: Please produce the monthly sequel reports on all HMS self-pay patient accounts of Grant Memorial Hospital Trust Foundation, Incorporated from September 1, 2011 to June 30, 2012.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" first-line="2" turnover="2"><bold>Request for Production 4</bold>: Please produce the monthly sequel reports on all HMS patient accounts aged 120 days or more of Grant Memorial Hospital Trust Foundation, Incorporated from September 1, 2011 to June 30, 2012.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" first-line="2" turnover="2"><bold>Defendant's Response</bold>: GMH objects to this request as going beyond the scope of discovery and being unduly burdensome. The &#x201C;sequel reports&#x201D; requested, as GMH understands the term, do not exist, but would have to be created, likely with the assistance of an outside vendor. GMH is under no obligation to create or generate reports, documents or summaries of information as part of litigation discovery. Without waiving the objection, GMH states that it made available to Frasier all accounts received reports to which Frasier was entitled in the course of their contractual relationship.</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Defendant raises two arguments in opposition to Plaintiff's motion. First, Defendant asserts that Plaintiff waived its right to compel discovery responses because the motion to compel is untimely under Local Rule of Civil Procedure 37.02(b). Substantively, Defendant contends that the requested sequel reports are outside the scope of allowable discovery because the reports do not actually exist, but would have to be created by Defendant with the assistance of a third-party vender, and therefore they are not in Defendant's possession, custody, or control as required by Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(b)(1). Plaintiff argues that it received these sequel reports from Defendant in the past, and that even if Defendant no longer maintains copies of the reports, &#x201C;the information is deemed to be within its control since they own the information and have simply chosen to outsource the collection and reporting of the same to an outside vendor.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><ital><bold>B. Discussion</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><ital>1. Timeliness of Plaintiff's Motion to Compel</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">Pursuant to Fed. R. Civ. P. 37(a), a party may move for an order to compel discovery or disclosure from an opposing party where the opposing party fails to respond or where the party's response is evasive or incomplete. Local Rule 37.02 states that &#x201C;[a] motion to compel<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> is deemed waived if it is not filed within thirty (30) days after the discovery response or disclosure requirement sought was due, which date is determined in accordance with a rule or by mutual agreement among the parties, unless such failure to file the motion was caused by excusable neglect or by some action of the non-moving party.&#x201D; L.R. Civ. P. 37.02(b). However, the Court has discretion to examine the circumstances surrounding an untimely motion to compel in order &#x201C;to avoid what may constitute overly &#x2018;technical&#x2019; applications of the Rule.&#x201D; <ital>Ayers v. Continental Cas. Co.</ital>, 250 F.R.D. 216, 225 (N.D.W.V. 2007).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Here, the parties stipulated that Defendant's discovery responses would be due on April 5, 2013, and Defendant served its responses on April 4, 2013. By letter dated May 13, 2013, Plaintiff requested that Defendant supplement its responses by providing the requested sequel reports. Defendant responded by letter dated May 17, 2013, and reiterated its refusal to provide the sequel reports. Thereafter, the parties communicated regarding a proposed protective order, but Plaintiff apparently did not raise the issue of the sequel reports again until October 1, 2013&#8211;nearly five months later. On October 2, 2013, Defendant again stated that it would not produce the sequel reports, and Plaintiff filed the instant motion to compel on November 8, 2013.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Thus, at first glance, it appears that Plaintiff waived its right to file a motion to compel by waiting more than thirty days after responses were due. However, digging deeper, it appears to the Court that the parties remained in communication regarding the production of payment reports responsive to Requests for Production 1, 2, 3, and 4. First, the parties did not agree on a protective order until October 11, 2013,<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference> and this Court did not enter the protective order until October 15, 2013.<footnote.reference ID="fr8" refid="f8" style="percent_n">8</footnote.reference> The record shows that both parties contemplated that full discovery responses would not be produced in this case until the protective order was entered. On September 4, 2013, counsel for Defendant advised Plaintiff's counsel that &#x201C;we cannot provide documents which include protected health information or other confidential or protected material without an appropriate protective order in place.&#x201D; Additionally, Plaintiff's counsel averred at the first evidentiary hearing on November 27, 2013, that he did not actually receive the many of Defendant's responses until a few days before the hearing, and that for some time prior to the protective order being entered, he was led to believe that additional payment records would be produced containing the information sought in the sequel reports.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p23">&#8195;Dkt. No. 21.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<footnote ID="f8"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN8.</label.designator><paratext ID="p24">&#8195;Dkt. No. 22.</paratext></para>
</footnote.body>
</footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">The Court acknowledges that this is a close call. However, in the interest of judicial economy, the Court believes that the best use of its resources is to decide this Motion on its merits. Accordingly, the Court finds that Plaintiff anticipated that Defendant's post-protective order disclosures would contain the payment records it sought, and it was only after Plaintiff realized that no such payment records would be forthcoming that Plaintiff resorted to a Motion to Compel. Thus, Plaintiff's Motion is not untimely, and the Court will turn to the merits of the Motion and Defendant's Response. <ital>2. Requests for Production of Electronically Stored Information</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 34 provides for the discovery of &#x201C;documents or electronically stored information&#8211;including writings, drawings, graphs, charts, photographs, sound recordings, images, and other data or data compilations&#8211;stored in any medium from which information can be obtained either directly or, if necessary, after translation by the responding party into a reasonably usable form.&#x201D; Fed.R.Civ.P. 34(a)(1)(A). &#x201C;Rule 34 applies to information that is fixed in a tangible form and to information that is stored in a medium from which it can be retrieved and examined.&#x201D; Advisory Comm. Notes to the 2006 Amendment of Rule 34.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Here, Plaintiff seeks a very specific compilation of data regarding payments posted to different categories of accounts during specific time periods. In its response brief, Defendant acknowledges that the data sought by Plaintiff is clearly discoverable under Rule 34 when it asserts that Plaintiff &#x201C;could also have sought discovery of the basic information it sought, instead of demanding that it be provided with specific reports that were nonexistent and unduly burdensome for GMH to have created.&#x201D; Thus, there is no question that the payment data sought by Plaintiff is discoverable ESI. The three issues before the Court, then, are (1) whether this data is in Defendant's possession, custody, or control; (2) whether requiring Defendant to produce the data in the form of a sequel report is tantamount to the creation of new information; and (3) whether Plaintiff should bear all or some of the cost of producing the sequel reports. The Court will address each in turn. <underscore>a. The Data Sought by Plaintiff Is within the Possession, Custody, or Control of Defendant</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 34, a party may seek discovery of documents or ESI in the responding party's possession, custody, or control. Fed.R.Civ.P. 34(a)(1). The term &#x201C;control&#x201D; is liberally construed, and &#x201C;the applicable test under Rule 34 is whether the litigant has the ability to obtain documents upon reasonable request, either as a matter of law or as a matter of practical fact.&#x201D; <ital>Automated Merchandising Systems Inc. v. Crane Co.</ital>, 279 F.R.D. 366, 374 (N.D.W.V. 2011). Thus, actual possession of responsive information is not required, and a party may be compelled to produce information in the possession of a third-party vendor &#x201C;if that party has a legal right to obtain the document or has control over the entity who is in possession of the document.&#x201D; <ital>Soto v. City of Concord</ital>, 162 F.R.D. 603, 619 (N.D.Cal.1995); <ital>see also Kiser v. Pride Commc'ns, Inc.</ital>, 2011 WL 5080162 (D. Nev. Oct. 26, 2011) (finding it &#x201C;inconceivable&#x201D; that defendants lacked the ability to obtain payroll records from a third-party vendor where defendants &#x201C;requested and ordered the third-party payroll vendor, Southwest Payroll Service, Inc., to perform the acts of processing and maintaining the payroll and the accompanying records&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Here, the record clearly shows that Defendant has the ability to obtain the sequel reports from HMS, its third-party vendor. Joe Barnes, Defendant's Chief Financial Officer, testified that the sequel application is similar to a word processing application, like Excel or Adobe; but, while Defendant's computers are equipped with the sequel application, Defendant cannot actually produce the sequel reports because no one at the hospital has the technical know-how to use the software. However, the evidence clearly shows that Defendant produced the report at least once in the past. Additionally, Mr. Barnes testified that HMS can easily produce the reports for the requested time periods, albeit at a cost of approximately $5000. Moreover, Defendant actually owns the data underlying the sequel reports and only contracts with HMS for its processing and management. Accordingly, the Court finds that the requested information is clearly within Defendant's possession, custody, or control because Defendant has the ability to obtain the information from HMS upon request.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><underscore>b. Requiring the Production of the Data Is Not the Same as Requiring the Creation of New Data or Documents</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">In general, Rule 34 only requires a party to produce documents and information already in existence. Thus, &#x201C;a party cannot be compelled to create or cause to be created new documents solely for their production.&#x201D; <ital>Paramount Pictures Corp. v. Replay TV</ital>, 2002 WL 32151632 at *2 (C.D.Cal. 2002). Defendant contends that because hard-copy sequel reports do not exist, requiring it to produce them would be tantamount to requiring it to create new documents in response to Plaintiff's requests. However, in making this argument, Defendant takes too narrow a view of Plaintiff's discovery requests. Plaintiff is not seeking production of the hard-copy sequel report that may have existed for each month in question. Plaintiff is seeking production of the data contained in the sequel report. Defendant's argument that Plaintiff should have requested the underlying data, rather than specific reports that do not exist, lacks merit. It is clear from the record that Defendant was apprised often and early of Plaintiff's desire for the data underlying the sequel reports.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Additionally, there is a distinct difference between requiring a party to create new data that does not currently exist and requiring a party to produce already existing data in a reasonably usable form. Two cases from the Central District of California are instructive. First, in <ital>Paramount Pictures Corp. v. Replay TV</ital>, 2002 WL 32151632 (C.D.Cal. 2002), the Court reversed a Magistrate Judge's Order compelling production of customer information because &#x201C;it impermissibly require[d] defendants to create new data which does not now exist.&#x201D; In <ital>Paramount</ital>, the Magistrate Judge ordered defendants to use their broadband connections with customers to gather information about their customers' viewing habits. <ital>Id.</ital> at *1. In order for defendants to comply with the order, they &#x201C;would be required to undertake a major software development effort, incur substantial expense, and spend approximately four months doing so.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at *3. The Court found that the defendants had never collected the requested information, so the information &#x201C;is not now and never has been in existence.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> However, the Court also noted that information currently being collected by defendants was discoverable under Rule 34 because it was already in existence. <ital>Id.</ital> at n.2.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">In contrast, the Court in <ital>Columbia Pictures Industries v. Bunnell</ital>, 2007 WL 2080419 (C.D.Cal. 2007) held that where the requested data already exists and is controlled by the responding party, requiring production of that data &#x201C;is not tantamount to ordering the creation of new data.&#x201D; In <ital>Columbia Pictures</ital>, the plaintiffs sought server log data which defendants did not actually keep, but which defendants stored on a third-party vendors website. <ital>Id.</ital> at *1. Defendants, relying on <ital>Paramount</ital>, argued that because their website never recorded or stored the requested server log data, an order requiring them to retain and produce such information would be tantamount to requiring them to create a new record solely for its production. <ital>Id.</ital> at *6. The Court distinguished <ital>Paramount</ital> from the instant case &#x201C;because the Server Log Data already exists, is temporarily stored in RAM, and is controlled by defendants.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">The Court finds that this case is similar to <ital>Columbia Pictures</ital> because the data in question is already in existence. Defendant is not being asked to create new data. It is simply being asked to access its existing database in order to produce the information requested by Plaintiff. <ital>See Burkybile v. Mitsubishi Motors Corp.</ital>, 2006 WL 3191541, at *5 (N.D.Ill. Oct.17, 2006) (holding that where the data previously used to prepare requested reports still exists in a database, &#x201C;[i]t is no matter that the original printouts are no longer available&#x201D; as long as the &#x201C;data compilation used to prepare the reports is accessible&#x201D;); <ital>Jinks-Umstead v. England</ital>, 227 F.R.D. 143, 147-48 (D.D.C.2005) (requiring the responding party &#x201C;to formulate queries and recover information&#x201D; from a database where the evidenced indicated &#x201C;that additional information can be retrieved from the system if specific data queries are formulated&#x201D;). Defendant has not argued that the data itself is nonexistent. In fact, both Plaintiff's independent consultant and an employee of HMS verified that the requested information is relatively easily accessible from existing data. Thus, because the data exists and is clearly accessible by Defendant, it must be produced in a reasonably usable format. <underscore>c. Cost-Shifting Is Not Appropriate Because Production Will Not Cause an Undue Burden</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">At the evidentiary hearing, Defendant asserted that Plaintiff should be required to bear some of the $5,000 cost of producing the reports. In general, the presumption is that the responding party bears the expense of complying with discovery requests. <ital>Oppenheimer Fund, Inc. v. Sanders</ital>, 437 U.S. 340 (1978). However, if the discovery of electronically stored information is &#x201C;not reasonably accessible because of undue burden or cost,&#x201D; the Court retains the discretion to shift some or all of the cost of the discovery to the requesting party. Fed.R.Civ.P. 26(b)(2)(B); <ital>Zubulake v. UBS Warburg LLC</ital>, 217 F.R.D. 309, 318 (S.D.N.Y. 2003) (&#x201C;[C]ost-shifting should be considered only when electronic discovery imposes an &#x201C;undue burden or expense&#x201D; on the responding party.&#x201D;). &#x201C;The burden or expense of discovery is, in turn, undue when it outweighs its likely benefit, taking into account the needs of the case, the amount in controversy, the parties' resources, the importance of the issues at stake in the litigation, and the importance of the proposed discovery in resolving the issues.&#x201D; <ital>Zubulake</ital>, at 318 (internal quotations omitted); <ital>see also</ital> Fed.R.Civ.P. 26(b)(2)(C)(iii).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">Here, the burden of producing the reports is small because the record shows that HMS can quickly and easily generate the reports using a simple query. Moreover, while the reports will cost $5,000 to produce, the Court finds that this expense does not outweigh the likely benefit of the reports. The reports are likely to contain extremely relevant information, and the information contained in the reports directly bears on dispositive issues in the case. Additionally, Mr. Barnes testified that Defendant has a positive cash flow such that $5,000 is a minor amount compared to Defendant's resources. Thus, the production of the reports by Defendant will not impose an <ital>undue</ital> burden or expense, and cost-shifting is not appropriate in this case.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>VII. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Plaintiff's Motion to Compel is <bold>GRANTED</bold>. Defendant is <bold>ORDERED</bold> to produce the sequel reports, as directed by this Order, within seven (7) days of the date of this Order.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">Filing of objections does not stay this Order.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">Any party may, within fourteen [14] days of this Order, file with the Clerk of the Court written objections identifying the portions of the Order to which objection is made, and the basis for such objection. A copy of such objections should also be submitted to the District Court Judge of Record. Failure to timely file objections to the Order set forth above will result in waiver of the right to appeal from a judgment of this Court based upon such order.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">The Clerk of the Court is directed to transmit a copy of this Order to parties who appear <ital>pro se</ital> and any counsel of record, as applicable.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">DATED: January 9, 2014</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>