<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF WEST VIRGINIA</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>Wheeling</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment><bold>LORI L. ARCHBOLD, INDIVIDUALLY, AND ON BEHALF OF A CLASS OF SIMILARLY SITUATED PERSONS, Plaintiffs</bold></title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment><bold>WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A., Defendant.</bold></title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line><bold>Civil Action No. 5:13-CV-83 (BAILEY)</bold></docket.line>
<docket.number><bold>5:13-CV-83 (BAILEY)</bold></docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">5:13-cv-00083-JPB</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 10/02/2013</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head>
<headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>ORDER DENYING PLAINTIFF'S MOTION TO REMAND</bold></underscore></headtext>
</head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">JOHN PRESTON BAILEY CHIEF UNITED STATED DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Pending before this Court is Plaintiff's Motion to Remand [Doc. 15], which was filed on August 2, 2013. Defendant Wells Fargo Bank, N.A. (&#x201C;Wells Fargo&#x201D;) filed its Response in Opposition [Doc. 19] on August 19, 2013. Plaintiff filed her Reply Brief [Doc. 22] on August 28, 2013. Having been fully briefed, the Motion is ripe for disposition. For the reasons that follow, the Motion is <bold>DENIED</bold>.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">This case was originally filed in the Circuit Court of Ohio County, West Virginia, on May 30, 2013. In her Complaint, plaintiff alleges and seeks to represent a class of &#x201C;[a]ll West Virginia citizens at the time of the filing of this action who, within the applicable statute of limitations preceding the filing of this action through the date of class certification, had or have loans serviced by the Defendant.&#x201D; [Doc. 1-1, &#182; 12].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Plaintiff asserts claims for: Count I &#8211; Assessment of attorneys' fees and other unlawful default charges; Count II &#8211; Failure to credit payments against amounts due; Count III &#8211; False representation of amount of claim; and Count IV &#8211; Assessment of multiple late fees for a single late payment &#8211; which are brought as both class and individual claims. Count V, Illegal Debt Collection, is brought solely as an individual claim, and alleges that Wells Fargo contacted the plaintiff directly despite knowledge that she was represented by an attorney, in violation of W. Va. Code &#167; 46A-2-128(e) [Doc. 1-1, &#182;&#182; 17-33].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">On July 3, 2013, defendant Wells Fargo removed this case to this Court under the Class Action Fairness Act (&#x201C;CAFA&#x201D;), 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1332(d)(2) [Doc. 1]. The plaintiff timely filed the pending Motion to Remand [Doc. 15].</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Discussion</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">CAFA provides in relevant part that &#x201C;[t]he district courts shall have original jurisdiction of any civil action in which the matter in controversy exceeds the sum or value of $5,000,000, exclusive of interest and costs, and is a class action in which &#8211; any member of a class of plaintiffs is a citizen of a State different from any defendant.&#x201D; 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1332(d)(2)(A). The proposed class must also include at least 100 members. 28 U.S.C. &#167;1332(d)(5)(B).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">In this case, there is no dispute that the requisite minimal diversity is present. Rather, the dispute centers upon whether the class includes at least 100 members and whether the amount in controversy requirement has been met.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">&#x201C;We begin with the undergirding principle that federal courts, unlike most state courts, are courts of limited jurisdiction, created by Congress with specified jurisdictional requirements and limitations. Accordingly, a party seeking to adjudicate a matter in federal court must allege and, when challenged, must demonstrate the federal court's jurisdiction over the matter. If a plaintiff files suit in state court and the defendant seeks to adjudicate the matter in federal court through removal, it is the defendant who carries the burden of alleging in his notice of removal and, if challenged, demonstrating the court's jurisdiction over the matter.&#x201D; <ital><bold>Strawn v. AT &#38; T Mobility</bold></ital>, 530 F.3d 293, 296 (4th Cir. 2008) (citations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Federal courts &#x201C;&#x2018;are obliged to construe removal jurisdiction strictly because of the significant federalism concerns implicated&#x2019; and that &#x2018;if federal jurisdiction is doubtful, a remand to state court is necessary.&#x2019; <ital><bold>Md. Stadium Auth. v. Ellerbe Becket Inc.</bold></ital>, 407 F.3d 255, 260 (4th Cir. 2005) (internal quotation marks, citations, and alterations omitted); <ital>see also <bold>Shamrock Oil</bold></ital>[<ital><bold>&#38; Gas Co. v. Sheets</bold></ital>], 313 U.S. at 109 (&#x2018;Due regard for the rightful independence of state governments, which should actuate federal courts, requires that they scrupulously confine their own jurisdiction to the precise limits which the statute has defined.&#x2019; (internal quotation marks omitted)).&#x201D; <ital><bold>Palisades Collections LLC v. Shorts</bold></ital>, 552 F.3d 327, 333-34 (4th Cir. 2008).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">&#x201C;Defendants seeking removal bear the burden of demonstrating that jurisdiction is proper. <ital>See <bold>Strawn v. AT &#38; T Mobility LLC</bold></ital>, 530 F.3d 293, 296-97 (4th Cir. 2008). This is true even in the context of removals pursuant to CAFA. In <ital><bold>Strawn</bold></ital>, this Court found that, while CAFA was intended to open the doors of the federal courts to class action litigants, its statutory language did nothing to reverse the long-settled principle that a defendant seeking to invoke a federal court's removal jurisdiction bears the burden of demonstrating that jurisdiction would be proper. <ital><bold>Id</bold>.</ital> at 297.&#x201D; <ital><bold>Bartnikowski v. NVR, Inc.</bold></ital>, 307 Fed.Appx. 730, 734 (4th Cir. 2009).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">&#x201C;While a defendant filing a notice of removal under 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1446(a) need only <ital>allege</ital> federal jurisdiction with a short plain statement &#8211; just as federal jurisdiction is pleaded in a complaint &#8211; when removal is challenged, the removing party bears the burden of <ital>demonstrating</ital> that removal jurisdiction is proper.&#x201D; <ital><bold>Strawn</bold>, supra</ital> at 297, citing <ital><bold>Ellenburg v. Spartan Motors Chassis, Inc.</bold></ital>, 519 F.3d 192, 200 (4th Cir. 2008).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">&#x201C;The question then becomes how that burden is to be satisfied. Generally, the amount specified in the complaint will determine whether the jurisdictional amount is satisfied for purposes of removal. <ital>See <bold>Wiggins v. North Am. Equitable Life Assurance Co.</bold></ital>, 644 F.2d 1014, 1016 (4th Cir. 1981). Determining the amount in controversy becomes more difficult, however, where, as here, Plaintiffs have left damages unspecified in their complaint. In this case, both parties agree that the defendant's burden in these circumstances is to establish the jurisdictional amount by a preponderance of the evidence.&#x201D; <ital><bold>Bartnikowski</bold>, supra</ital> at 734 (footnote omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">In this case, the defendant appended to its Notice of Removal a Declaration of Lori Dahl [Doc. 1-2]. In her Declaration, Ms. Dahl states:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">1. That she is employed as Vice-President of Wells Fargo;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">2. That she has knowledge of Wells Fargo's computer systems and customer data stored therein;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">3. That for the period of July 1, 2012 through July 1, 2013, Wells Fargo serviced at least 4,099 loans for West Virginia consumers who were in default and had actually incurred at least one default charge; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">4. That the balances on these 4,099 loans collectively exceed $5,000,000.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Using this data in its Notice of Removal, the defendants multiply the 4,099 loans times the approximately $4,725.05 maximum inflation-adjusted statutory penalty under W.Va. Code &#167;&#167; 46A-5-101(1) &#38; 106, resulting in potential liability of at least $19,267,979.95, assuming only one violation per prospective class member [Doc. 1].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The plaintiff contends that Ms. Dahl's declaration is deficient because it fails to provide evidence that each of the 4,099 loans were actually assessed <ital>unlawful</ital> default charges [Doc. 16]. This Court finds, however, that Wells Fargo has more than adequately provided the universe of potential class members as specifically defined in the plaintiff's Complaint. Indeed, while the Complaint has defined the prospective class as &#x201C;[a]ll West Virginia citizens <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> who <charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> had or have loans serviced by the Defendant,&#x201D; which Wells Fargo asserts includes 23,537 loans, Wells Fargo has narrowed the number of loans to those West Virginia consumers who were in default and had actually incurred at least one default charge, i.e. 4,099.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">In <ital><bold>Bartnikowski v. NVR, Inc.</bold></ital>, 307 Fed.Appx. 730 (4th Cir. 2009), the Fourth Circuit found similar portions of a removing party's affidavit to be sufficient. It was only the unsupported assumption that class members worked five hours of overtime per week that led to the affirmation of the remand of the case. In <ital><bold>Bartnikowski</bold></ital>, the Court found that multiplying th number of months by the expected monthly amount of overtime would yield a <ital>reasonable estimate</ital> of the unpaid wages at stake.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">The plaintiff contends that the affidavit is over inclusive and does not assert that the default payments were actually unlawful. However, in <ital><bold>Raskas v. Johnson &#38; Johnson</bold></ital>, 719 F.3d 884, 888 (8th Cir. 2013), the Eighth Circuit held that &#x201C;Defendants are not required to provide a &#x2018;formula or methodology for calculating the potential damages&#x2019; more accurately, as the district court held. We have specifically rejected the need for this kind of formula or methodology, as it would require a defendant to &#x2018;confess liability&#x2019; for the entire jurisdictional amount. <ital><bold>Hartis v. Chicago Title Ins. Co.</bold></ital>, 694 F.3d 935, 945 (8th Cir. 2012) (quoting <ital><bold>Spivey</bold></ital> [<ital><bold>v. Vertrue, Inc.</bold></ital>], 528 F.3d at 986 [7th Cir. 2008]); <ital>see also <bold>Lewis</bold></ital> [<ital><bold>v. Verizon Commc'ns, Inc.</bold></ital>, 627 F.3d at 400 [9th Cir. 2010](&#x2018;To establish the jurisdictional amount, [the defendant] need not concede liability for the entire amount, which is what the district court was in essence demanding by effectively asking [the defendant] to admit that at least $5 million of the billings were &#x201C;unauthorized&#x201D; within the meaning of the complaint.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">In reviewing such affidavits, one must bear in mind that the issue is &#x201C;&#x2018;not what damages the plaintiff will recover, but what amount is &#x2018;in controversy&#x2019; between the parties. That the plaintiff may fail in its proof, and the judgment be less than the threshold (indeed, a good chance that the plaintiff will fail and the judgment will be zero) does not prevent removal.&#x2019;&#x201D;). <ital><bold>Martin v. State Farm Mut. Auto. Ins. Co.</bold></ital>, 2010 WL 3259418, *5 (S.D. W.Va. August 18, 2010) (Chambers, J), quoting <ital><bold>Brill v. Countrywide Home Loans, Inc.</bold></ital>, 427 F.3d 446, 448-49 (7th Cir. 2005). <ital>Accord, <bold>Raskas</bold>, supra</ital> at 887 (&#x201C;the question &#x2018;is not whether the damages <ital>are</ital> greater than the requisite amount, but whether a fact finder <ital>might</ital> legally conclude that they are.&#x2019;&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">In addition, &#x201C;multiplying the individual damage amounts pled in the complaint by the number of persons in an alleged class is a reasonable method for determining the amount in controversy.&#x201D; <ital><bold>Martin</bold>, supra</ital> at *5. <ital>See also <bold>Cowit v. Citimortgage, Inc.</bold></ital>, 2013 WL 142893 (S.D. Ohio January 11, 2013) (&#x201C;Courts routinely rely on such basic multiplication to determine whether the aggregate claims of a putative class likely exceed CAFA's threshold.&#x201D;)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">In <ital><bold>Cowit</bold></ital>, the Court considered the Eighth Circuit's decision in <ital><bold>Hartis v. Chicago Title Ins. Co.</bold></ital>, 694 F.3d 935 (8th Cir. 2012). The Court stated:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">For example, in <ital><bold>Hartis v. Chicago Title Ins. Co.</bold></ital>, 694 F.3d 935, 939 (8th Cir. 2012), the</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p25" first-line="1" turnover="1">Eighth Circuit affirmed the denial of a remand motion in a putative class action where the plaintiff alleged that a title insurer had retained excess recording fees in real estate closings in 17 states. The complaint alleged that the insurer had collected a recording fee from Missouri residents along with more than 71,000 transactions, which multiplied by 17 (the total number of states) yielded 1,207,000 transactions. <ital><bold>Id</bold>.</ital> As a conservative estimate, the court multiplied half of this number by $12, the average of the putative class representatives' overcharges, which yielded $7,242,000. <ital>Id.</ital> at 946. The court found that CAFA's threshold was &#x201C;easily satisfied.&#x201D; <bold>Id</bold>.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p26" contd-flag="y">2013 WL at *6.</paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">This Court finds that the same holds true in this case. The pleadings and declaration filed in this case are sufficient to demonstrate that the amount in controversy exceeds $5,000,000.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">In addition, Courts have considered whether the party seeking remand has provided no contrary evidence. In <ital><bold>Ray v. Wells Fargo Bank, N.A.</bold></ital>, 2011 WL 1790123 (C.D. Cal. May 9, 2011), the Court noted that there was no contrary evidence and no allegation that the plaintiff seeks less than $5,000,000. 2011 WL 1790123 at *7, quoting <ital><bold>Lewis v. Verizon</bold></ital>, 627 F.3d 395, 397 (9th Cir. 2010).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">In <ital><bold>Strawn</bold>, supra</ital>, the Fourth Circuit, in denying remand, noted that &#x201C;the plaintiffs have offered nothing to suggest that the 58,800-customer figure is not an accurate number. 530 F.3d at 299.</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p30" first-line="1" turnover="1">In <ital><bold>Bartnikowski</bold>, supra</ital>, Judge Wilkinson, in his dissent, stated: The party seeking removal in a CAFA case has the burden of alleging federal jurisdiction and establishing it if challenged. <ital><bold>Strawn</bold></ital>, 530 F.3d at 298. But once petitioner has set forth a prima facie case establishing jurisdiction, the onus is on respondent to offer something of its own. <ital>See <bold>id</bold>.</ital> at 298-99. <ital><bold>Strawn</bold></ital> held that the petitioner in that case had met its burden by identifying the number of class members (based on the terms of the respondent's complaint) and by calculating the minimum statutory damages due each member of the class, where the respondent &#x201C;offered nothing to suggest that the [figure put forth by the petitioner] is not an accurate number.&#x201D; <ital><bold>Id</bold>.</ital> The court thus held for the petitioner based on the petitioner's calculations and the facts presented in the complaint, even though respondent's counsel even went so far as to stipulate that they would not accept an award over $5 million. <ital>See <bold>id</bold>.</ital> at 295, 299.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p31" contd-flag="y">307 Fed.Appx. at 740.</paratext>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">As previously stated, Wells Fargo has more than sufficiently established CAFA jurisdiction using the Complaint's broad class definition, and plaintiff has failed to offer anything other than its own conjecture and speculation that the 4,099 loans were not unlawfully charged default fees.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">Having found the defendant has established this Court's jurisdiction pursuant to CAFA, this Court finds it unnecessary to address the arguments concerning injunctive relief or plaintiff's attempt to invoke and deny this Court's jurisdiction &#x201C;in the same breath.&#x201D; For the reasons stated above, Plaintiff's Motion to Remand [<bold>Doc. 15</bold>] is <bold>DENIED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">It is so <bold>ORDERED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">The Clerk is directed to transmit copies of this Order to counsel of record herein.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1"><bold>DATED:</bold> October 2, 2013.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>