<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN" "C:\Documents and Settings\riyaz.EXETERPM\Desktop\archiveJats-interchange-dtd-1.1\JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<?release-delay 0|0?>
<article article-type="letter" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bull</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Bulletin of the Royal College of Surgeons of England</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1473-6357</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1478-7075</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Royal College of Surgeons</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/rcsbull.2017.145</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2017.145</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Letters</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="rcs-spec">
<compound-subject>
<compound-subject-part content-type="code">pub</compound-subject-part>
<compound-subject-part content-type="label">Public health</compound-subject-part>
</compound-subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Letters to the Editor</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>04</month><year>2017</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><month>04</month><year>2017</year></pub-date>
<volume>99</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>145</fpage>
<lpage>146</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2017 Royal College of Surgeons</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="rcsbull.2017.145.pdf" content-type="pdf"></self-uri>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec><title>Project 2020</title>
<p>Sir,</p>
<p>On 17 January 2017 Westminster Council approved, with minor caveats, the planning application for Project 2020 despite some serious objections on architectural grounds from The Victorian Society, the Twentieth Century Society and the Georgian Group. However, before Council and the Board of Trustees make a final decision to proceed with the extensive and costly rebuild that Project 2020 entails, we would urge them to compare it with a more modest staged renovation of the Barry building &#x2013; to be accomplished as funds are available and without requiring the disposal of the Nuffield accommodation, which was built with a major benefaction from Lord Nuffield.</p>
<p>This would preserve those parts on the Ground Floor that have architectural merit and remain functional &#x2013; such as the entrance hall, stair case, Council room, Lumley Hall and lecture theatres, as well as the Library and fourth-floor Education Centre &#x2013; while leaving the recently upgraded Hunterian Museum where it is. However, the plans would also be commissioned to propose better use of space in other parts of the building and the modernisation of services and facilities where necessary.</p>
<p>Such a scheme has been referred to previously but never properly commissioned and costed. It would, however, inevitably be much cheaper than Project 2020, the latest estimate for which is &#xA3;89 million. This leaves a funding gap of &#xA3;34 million to be serviced by fundraising and loans after the lease of the Nuffield for &#xA3;55 million. Retaining the latter would also have the important advantage of preserving accommodation for RCS fellows, the Faculty of Dental Surgery, the Clinical Effectiveness Unit and the specialist associations. In addition, better use of the Nuffield could be developed so that it became more of an income generator, as the Edinburgh College has done so successfully with its hotel facilities.</p>
<p>We believe Council and the Board of Trustees would be more likely to arrive at a wise decision if they had two such different plans to compare for cost-effectiveness and the future needs of the RCS before finally embarking on improving our site at Lincoln&#x2019;s Inn Fields.</p>
<p><bold>Sir Terence English</bold></p>
<p><italic>Past-President of the RCS (1989&#x2013;1992)</italic></p>
<p><bold>Sir Peter Morris</bold></p>
<p><italic>Past-President of the RCS (2001&#x2013;2004</italic>)</p>
<p><bold>John Black</bold></p>
<p><italic>Past-President of the RCS (2008&#x2013;2011)</italic></p>
</sec>
<sec><title>Redevelopment of Royal College of Surgeons</title>
<p>Sir,</p>
<p>As the committee representing The Senior Fellows Society (SFS), we wish to express our views relating to the development plans for the RCS. There is growing concern not only among the membership of the SFS but also, we understand, from the membership at large, the Faculty of Dental Surgery (FDS) and the specialty associations as the details, risks and cost of the project are becoming more widely known. </p>
<p>Although Westminster Council gave planning permission for the development of the Barry building, there was significant opposition to this from conservation groups and from members of the RCS.</p>
<p>We do not consider it justified to sacrifice most of our iconic headquarters for an alternative building that provides much less amenity space. For generations, the RCS buildings in Lincoln&#x2019;s Inn Fields have demonstrated that the integrated Nuffield and Barry buildings are essential in adapting to the huge changes in surgical practice, both nationally and internationally, as well as providing a major source of income. There is no evidence that we could manage future change in the rebuilt Barry building.</p>
<p>Westminster Council are not concerned that the project will cost around &#xA3;90 million and will require the sale of the Nuffield on a very long-term lease, as well as major borrowing and further charitable donations. In uncertain economic and political times this scenario must surely expose the RCS to serious medium- and long-term risk, which might threaten its existence as the voice of surgery in England and Wales.</p>
<p>It is our unanimous and considered opinion that the Board and Council should be presented with an alternative and costed business case for a programme of staged refurbishment whereby we would retain the ground floor (entrance hall, Lumley and Webb-Johnson, Council and Committee rooms, lecture theatres and members&#x2019; lounge), Hunterian Museum, the FDS, specialty associations, hotel accommodation, fourth-floor educational facilities and President&#x2019;s lodge. Development should be concentrated on parts of the RCS that need upgrading and might be exploited as sources of additional income. An example is the Edinburgh College&#x2019;s success with their hotel facility. A similar plan in the Nuffield would be particularly welcomed by provincial members who otherwise might feel further distanced from the RCS by lack of on-site accommodation.</p>
<p><bold>David Jones (Chair)</bold></p>
<p><bold>Roger Watson</bold></p>
<p><bold>Irving Taylor</bold></p>
<p><bold>David Webster Andrew Brown</bold></p>
<p><bold>Richard Welfare</bold></p>
<p><italic>Senior Fellows Society Committee</italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>