<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN" "C:\Documents and Settings\riyaz.EXETERPM\Desktop\archiveJats-interchange-dtd-1.1\JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<?release-delay 0|0?>
<article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bull</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Bulletin of the Royal College of Surgeons of England</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1473-6357</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1478-7075</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Royal College of Surgeons</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/rcsbull.2017.258</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2017.258</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Rcs Member Benefits</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="rcs-spec">
<compound-subject>
<compound-subject-part content-type="code">adm</compound-subject-part>
<compound-subject-part content-type="label">Hospital administration</compound-subject-part>
</compound-subject>
<compound-subject>
<compound-subject-part content-type="code">emg</compound-subject-part>
<compound-subject-part content-type="label">Emergency care</compound-subject-part>
</compound-subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>RCS Current Awareness Updates</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>McEwan</surname>
<given-names>Amy</given-names>
</string-name>
<role>RCS Senior Information Specialist</role>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>07</month><year>2017</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><month>07</month><year>2017</year></pub-date>
<volume>99</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>133</fpage>
<lpage>136</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2017 Royal College of Surgeons</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="rcsbull.2017.258.pdf" content-type="pdf"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>RCS members will receive email summaries of relevant papers in their specialty every other month. Here&#x2019;s what fellows and members can expect from the service, and how to contribute.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>

<p><bold>T</bold> he Current Awareness Service was launched by the RCS Library in 2012 as a response to indications from fellows and members that they wanted more support in keeping up to date with the latest scientific advancements. After its inception, the service expanded quickly and was delivering specialty bulletins to eight specialties by the end of its pilot in 2016.</p>
<p>Following further feedback, we have been working hard behind the scenes and are now ready to relaunch with some exciting changes. The bulletins have been rebranded as <italic>Updates </italic>and will cover all ten surgical specialties by summer 2018, meaning that this valued membership benefit will be available to all current fellows and members within the next year. Patient safety content, which had been sent in a separate bulletin, will now be embedded into each <italic>Update</italic>, ensuring that surgeons only receive the information most relevant to them.</p>
<p>Sent directly to your inbox every two months, the <italic>Updates </italic>are concise email summaries of the latest evidence compiled by qualified Information Specialists with support from a panel of specialist advisors. Information is selected from a variety of sources, with a strong focus on the highest levels of evidence, guidelines, policy and new technology. Presented in an easy-to-use format sorted by topic, the <italic>Updates </italic>allow highly specialised consultants to easily focus on their chosen subspecialty. Citations include a brief summary and link directly to the full text of the article, where possible, which will make reading for continuing professional development (CPD) easier and less time-consuming.</p>

<sec1>
<title>WHEN WILL I START TO RECEIVE UPDATES?</title>

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Cardiothoracic &#x2013; May 2017</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Plastic and Reconstructive &#x2013; May 2017</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Trauma and Orthopaedics &#x2013; May 2017</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Emergency General Surgery &#x2013; July 2017</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Urology &#x2013; July 2017</p></list-item>
</list>

<p>Further details on launch dates for the following specialties will be available soon:

<list list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>Colorectal</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Vascular</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Paediatric Surgery</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Neurosurgery</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Otolaryngology.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec1>

<sec1>
<title>BECOME A SPECIALIST ADVISOR</title>
<p>We are currently looking to recruit fellows and members to be specialist advisors for the <italic>Updates</italic>. The role is suitable for certification as a formal professional development activity and certificates will be awarded to those panel members that actively work to fulfil the responsibilities and functions of the post.</p>

<p>The specialist advisor&#x2019;s main role will be to:

<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>provide clarity about the suitability of content for specific specialties and subspecialties</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>review the <italic>Updates </italic>before they are distributed more widely</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>highlight important content to the Information Specialists.</p></list-item>
</list>
</p>

<p>This work will require a time commitment of beween one and two hours every two months.</p>
<p>&#x2018;I have thoroughly enjoyed contributing to the plastic [and reconstructive] current awareness bulletin since its inception. It keeps me up to date with my reading across the specialty. This makes me a better surgeon and academic&#x2019; &#x2013; Matthew Gardiner, Honorary Clinical Lecturer in Plastic Surgery and specialty trainee.</p>
<p>If you would like to get involved please visit the Current Awareness page (www.rcseng.ac.uk/library-and-publica-tions/library/guide-to-services/cas/) on the RCS website to see which specialties we are currently recruiting for. The page contains more information, including a full role description and expression of interest forms that can be downloaded and sent to updates&#x0040;rcseng.ac.uk.</p>
</sec1>
</body>
</article>
