
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN" "C:\Documents and Settings\riyaz.EXETERPM\Desktop\archiveJats-interchange-dtd-1.1\JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<?release-delay 0|0?>
<article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bull</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>The Bulletin of the Royal College of Surgeons of England</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1473-6357</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1478-7075</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Royal College of Surgeons</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/rcsbull.2017.283</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2017.283</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject></subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="rcs-spec">
<compound-subject>
<compound-subject-part content-type="code">adm</compound-subject-part>
<compound-subject-part content-type="label">Hospital administration</compound-subject-part>
</compound-subject>
<compound-subject>
<compound-subject-part content-type="code">emg</compound-subject-part>
<compound-subject-part content-type="label">Emergency care</compound-subject-part>
</compound-subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Slop and decrepitude</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<string-name>
<collab>Mr Slop FRCS (Eng)</collab>
</string-name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>07</month><year>2017</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><month>07</month><year>2017</year></pub-date>
<volume>99</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>283</fpage>
<lpage>283</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2017 Royal College of Surgeons</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
<license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:href="rcsbull.2017.283.pdf" content-type="pdf"></self-uri>
<abstract>
<p>Our tired scribe finds the Fountain of Youth and tries not to spill the beans&#x2026; or the wine.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>

<p><BOLD>M</BOLD>r Slop FRCS felt slightly bewildered as he noticed the changes at The Royal College of Surgeons of England. There seemed to have been a lot of objects ripped up since the Hunterian Museum closed and the Nuffield was filled with refugees from the Barry Building. As he tripped up the stairs to the Esteemed Editor-in-Chief&#x2019;s new temporary office, he hoped the familiar face of his tormentor would at least re-orient his befuddled brain into some kind of order.</p>
<p>Slop, who was quite breathless after climbing three flights of stairs, knocked with trepidation on the large Victorian door of the Editor&#x2019;s office.</p>
<p>&#x2018;Come in!&#x2019; shouted his boss as he looked up from his iPad while staring absent-mindedly straight at Slop, who began the traverse across the thick-knotted pile carpet.</p>
<p>&#x2018;Ah Slop. You are limping and out of breath, old man! Take a seat and have a glass of Highland Spring&#x00AE;.&#x2019;</p>
<p>Slop almost collapsed on the <italic>chaise longue </italic>by the window.</p>
<p>&#x2018;Yes, Sir! It&#x2019;s true I am a bit puffed and my right knee has an effusion and is very painful around the medial meniscus area.&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x2018;How did you do that? Or is it just the effects <italic>of anno domini </italic>in an old curmudgeon like yourself?&#x2019;</p>
<p>With that, the Esteemed Editor-in-Chief roared with laughter and started to roll back on his chair, barely able to contain himself. Slop felt highly awkward and rather humiliated.</p>
<p>&#x2018;Well,&#x2019; continued Slop. &#x2018;A week&#x2019;s skiing in Zermatt with the family started the problem and then it was not helped by a 58-mile walk on the Pembrokeshire Coastal Path.&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x2018;All completely self-inflicted, Slop! Only yourself to blame if you attempt such activities at your age. That&#x2019;s it, Slop! The perfect subject for your next article &#x2013; <italic>Ageing, Decrepitude and Surgery</italic>.&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x2018;But Sir, I think I&#x2019;d rather write about...&#x2019;</p>
<p>&#x2018;Nonsense, Slop! Have it on my desk by Friday! That will be all.&#x2019;</p>
<p>Slop heaved himself painfully off the <italic>chaise longue </italic>and began the long hobble to Holborn tube station and the train back to Midhampton. As he journeyed north, he knew how sobering any account of the kind the Editor was proposing would be for his readers. However, it might help Slop face the reality that he was not the surgeon &#x2013; let alone the man &#x2013; he once was.</p>
<p>When Slop first arrived at Midhampton General Hospital more than a quarter of a century ago, he had run two full day-lists each week as well as endoscopy, outpatients and ward rounds. He would think nothing of operating until eight o&#x2019;clock each evening and, in those far-off days, no one much tried to stop him. Of course, he would feel a tad sore in the foot department by the end of the long day but he would be up at six o&#x2019;clock the next morning none the worse for wear and chomping at the bit to get going again.</p>
<p>Nowadays his routine would have quite a different texture to it. After swallowing his felodipine and statin, Slop would sit on his toilet looking out at the copper beech tree swaying in the breeze while trying not to strain too hard. If he did, his piles &#x2013; despite liberal application of AnusolHC&#x00AE; &#x2013; would create merry hell for the rest of the morning and interfere with his day-care list. By midday his dyspepsia would require a gulp of Gaviscon&#x00AE; and his left acromio-clavicular joint would need an urgent massage after performing a laparoscopic hernia repair.</p>
<p>By lunchtime, all four of his malleoli would be hidden under a light covering of spongy oedema and the anaesthetic gases would have irritated his chronic bronchitis enough for him to be suffering from bouts of gentle coughing. During the afternoon colonoscopy list, Slop&#x2019;s right wrist would become sore enough from the constant torque required to negotiate the colon that he would be forced to rub it hard to improve the circulation. By the evening, as he strolled slowly to his car, he would notice that his neck would be stiff and his gait uneven as the arthritis of his right hip began to make its presence known to him.</p>
<p>It is true, of course, that an hour in the gym would normally solve most of these problems. However, Mr Slop knew what the real remedy for his ageing was, even though the Nursing Sister might have different ideas on the subject. A couple of glasses of Merlot followed by a nightly tot of Famous Grouse&#x00AE;!</p>
<p>Slop recalled, with some unpleasantness, his meeting with the Editor-in-Chief the two weeks before but, after much reflection, finally realised the solution to his health problems. Just start the Merlot at breakfast time!</p>
</body>
</article>
