<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>WESTERN DIVISION</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>KENNETH JOHN LODGE, JUDSON LERTZMAN, BARBARA GALARO AND MICHAEL HOPKINS, individually and on behalf of all others similarly situated, Plaintiffs,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>U.S. REMODELERS, INC., a corporation, U.S. HOME SYSTEMS, INC., a corporation, and DOES 1 through 75, inclusive, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>CASE NO.:CV07-05409 CAS (AJWx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV07-05409 CAS (AJWx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:07-cv-05409-CAS-AJW</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 08/24/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<procedural.history xml:lang="en">
<appeal>
<appeal.text>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">[<ital>Honorable Judge Christina A. Snyder</ital>]</paratext></para>
</appeal.text>
</appeal>
</procedural.history>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER GRANTING MOTION FOR ORDER: (1) GRANTING PRELIMINARY APPROVAL TO PROPOSED CLASS ACTION SETTLEMENT; (2) CONDITIONALLY CERTIFYING SETTLEMENT CLASS; (3) APPROVING CLASS NOTICE; (4) APPOINTING CLASS COUNSEL;AND (5) SCHEDULING FINAL APPROVAL HEARING DATE AND RELATED DATES</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">HONORABLE CHRISTINA A. SNYDER UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<head><headtext align="center"><underscore><bold>ORDER</bold></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">Having considered Plaintiffs' MOTION FOR ORDER: (1) GRANTING PRELIMINARY APPROVAL TO PROPOSED CLASS ACTION SETTLEMENT; (2) CONDITIONALLY CERTIFYING SETTLEMENT CLASS; (3) APPROVING CLASS NOTICE; (4) APPOINTING CLASS COUNSEL;AND (5) SCHEDULING FINAL APPROVAL HEARING DATE AND RELATED DATES, and finding good cause:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="0">NOW, THEREFORE, IT IS HEREBY ORDERED:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">1. This Order incorporates by reference the definitions in the parties' Stipulation And Settlement Agreement (hereinafter &#x201C;Stipulation&#x201D;) attached to the Declaration of Andrew H. Friedman In Support of Motion for Preliminary Approval as Exhibit &#x201C;A&#x201D;, and all terms defined therein shall have the same meaning in this Order as set forth in the Stipulation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">2. The Court hereby conditionally certifies the Class for settlement purposes only. The Class is defined as: (1) Class No. 1 (Commission Subclass): any Class Member who was paid or should have been paid any commission for any contract or job sold anywhere in California from July 3, 2003 up to and including the date preliminary approval of this settlement is granted; and (2) Class No. 2 (Expenses Subclass): any Class Member who claims to have incurred any expenses related to or in connection with the selling of contracts or jobs because the Class Members purchased items necessary to discharge the duties of the job or because she or he was told, instructed, directed, recommended, suggested, or advised to purchase any item to do his or her job by anyone acting on behalf of the Defendants as an agent, employee, officer, supervisor, or manager from July 3, 2003 up to and including the date preliminary approval of this settlement is granted. Should for whatever reason the Settlement not become final, the fact that the Parties were willing to stipulate to class certification as part of the Settlement shall have no bearing on, nor be admissible in connection with, the issue of whether of a class should be certified in a nonsettlement context.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">3. Named Plaintiffs Kenneth John Lodge, Judson Lertzman, Barbara Galaro, And Michael Hopkins (&#x201C;Named Plaintiffs&#x201D;) are hereby appointed and designated, for all purposes, as the representatives of the Class, and Andrew H. Friedman and Gregory D. Helmer of Helmer Friedman LLP are hereby appointed and designated as counsel for the Named Plaintiffs and the Class (&#x201C;Class Counsel&#x201D;): Class Counsel is authorized to act on behalf of Class Members with respect to all acts or consents required by, or which may be given pursuant to, the Settlement, and such other acts reasonably necessary to consummate the Settlement. Any Class Member may enter an appearance through counsel of such Class Member's own choosing and at such Class Member's own expense. Any Class Member who does not enter an appearance or appear on his or her wn will be represented by Class Counsel.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">4. The Court hereby preliminarily approves the Stipulation and the settlement contained therein. The Court finds on a preliminary basis that the Stipulation appears to be within the range of reasonableness of a settlement that could ultimately be given final approval by this Court. The Court has reviewed the monetary recovery that is being granted as part of the Settlement and recognizes the significant value to the Class of that monetary recovery. It appears to the Court on a preliminary basis that the settlement amount and allocation of that amount between the class, class counsel as attorneys' fees and costs (and potentially to cover claims administration expenses in excess of $10,000.00) and the class representatives as incentive payments is fair, adequate and reasonable when balanced against the probable outcome of further litigation relating to liability and damages issues. It further appears that extensive and costly investigation and research, discovery, and litigation have been conducted such that counsel for the Parties at this time are able to reasonably evaluate their respective positions. It further appears to the Court that settlement at this time will avoid substantial additional costs by all Parties, as well as avoid the delay and risks that would be presented by the further prosecution of the Actions. It further appears that the Settlement has been reached as the result of intensive, serious, and non-collusive arms-length negotiations.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">5. A final approval hearing (the &#x201C;Settlement Hearing&#x201D;) shall be held before this Court on November 30, 2009 at 10:00 a.m., or as soon thereafter as the matter may be heard, in Courtroom 5 of The United States District Court For The Central District Of California &#8212; Western Division &#8212; Located At 312 N. Spring Street, Los Angeles, CA 90012 (The Honorable Christina A. Snyder Presiding), to determine all necessary matters concerning the Settlement, including: whether the proposed settlement of the Actions on the terms and conditions provided for in the Stipulation is fair, adequate and reasonable and should be finally approved by the Court; whether a Judgment, as provided in the Stipulation, should be entered herein; whether the plan of allocation contained in the Stipulation should be approved as fair, adequate and reasonable to the Class Members; and to finally approve Class Counsel's Fees Award, the Named Plaintiffs' Incentive Awards, and the claims administration expenses.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">6. The Court hereby approves, as to form and content, the Notice and Claim Form attached as Exhibits &#x201C;B&#x201D; and &#x201C;C&#x201D; to the Declaration of Andrew H. Friedman. The Court finds that the content and distribution of the Notice and Claim Form substantially in the manner and form set forth in the Stipulation and this Order meets the requirements of due process, is the best notice practicable under the circumstances, and shall constitute due and sufficient notice to all persons entitled thereto.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">7. The Court hereby appoints CPT Group, Inc., 16630 Aston Street Irvine, CA 92606, Toll Free: (800) 542-0900, Tel: (949) 852-8240, Fax: (949) 852-9340, as Claims Administrator and hereby directs the Claims Administrator to mail or cause to be mailed to Plaintiffs the Notice and Claim Form by first class mail within thirty (30) days after the entry of this Preliminary Approval Order (the &#x201C;Notice Date&#x201D;) using the procedures set forth in the Stipulation. Plaintiffs who wish to participate in the settlement provided for by the Stipulation (&#x201C;Settlement Class Members&#x201D;) must complete and return the Claim Form pursuant to the instructions contained therein within the time period provided for in the Stipulation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">8. Any Plaintiff may choose to opt out of and be excluded from the Class as provided in the Notice by following the instructions for requesting exclusion from the Class that are set forth in the Notice. All requests for exclusion must be submitted as provided in the Notice. Any such person who chooses to opt out of and be excluded from the Class will not be entitled to any recovery under the Settlement and will not be bound by the Settlement or have any right to object, appeal or comment thereon. Any written request to opt out must be signed by each such person opting out. Class Members who have not requested exclusion shall be bound by all determinations of the Court and the Stipulation and Judgment.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">9. Any Class Member may appear at the Final Approval Hearing and may object or express the Class Member's views regarding the Settlement, and may present evidence and file briefs or other papers (according to the briefing schedule set forth herein), that may be proper and relevant to the issues to be heard and determined by the Court as provided in the Notice. However, no Class Member or any other person shall be heard or entitled to object, and no papers or briefs submitted by any such person shall be received or considered by the Court, unless that person has timely served by hand or by first class mail written objections, copies of any papers and briefs in support of their position, and verification of their membership in the Class upon: Gregory D. Helmer and Andrew H. Friedman of HELMER &#183; FRIEDMAN, LLP, 723 Ocean Front Walk Venice, California 90291, and filed the objections, papers and briefs with the Clerk of this Court. Any Class Member who does not make his or her objection in the manner provided for in the Stipulation shall be deemed to have waived such objection and shall forever be foreclosed from making any objection to the Settlement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">10. All papers filed by any person or party in support of or opposition to Final Approval shall be filed with the Court and served on all of the Parties' Counsel no later than fourteen (14) Court days before the Final Approval Hearing. Any papers not filed via the United States District Court, Central District of California's Case Management/Electronic Case Filing System (&#x201C;CM/ECF&#x201D;) must be personally served on all parties.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">11. Any reply/supplemental papers filed by the parties in support of Motion For Final Approval, if any, shall be filed with the Court and served on all of the Parties' Counsel no later than five (5) Court days before the Final Approval Hearing.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">12. The following schedule sets forth relevant dates:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1"><underscore><bold>Timing</bold></underscore>, Within 15 days after August 24, 2009, (15 days after preliminary approval of settlement)., Within 30 days after August 24, 2009 (30 days after preliminary approval of settlement)., On the 30<super style="percent_r">th</super> day after the provision of notice to the class members., Within 45 days after provision of notice to the class members., November 16, 2009 (14 days before final approval hearing)., November 25, 2009, November 30, 2009</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1"><underscore><bold>Event</bold></underscore>, Defendants provide Claims, Administrator with contact information for class members., Claims administrator provides notice to class members., Claims administrator provides a reminder postcard to class members. Deadline for class members to submit Exclusion Form or Objections., Deadline for class members to submit Claims Form., Plaintiffs file Motion For Final Approval of Class Action Settlement. Anyone opposing the Motion For Final approval file opposition., Parties file reply/supplemental papers in support of Motion For Final Approval, if any., Final Approval Hearing.</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">13. All claims administration expenses shall be paid as follows: (1) the first $10,000.00 by Defendants; and (2) the remainder, if any, by Class Counsel.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">14. The Settlement is not a concession or admission, and shall not be used against Defendants or any of the Released Parties as an admission or indication with respect to any claim of any fault or omission by Defendants or any of the Released Parties. Whether or not the Settlement is finally approved, neither the Settlement, nor any document, statement, proceeding or conduct related to the Settlement, nor any reports or accounts thereof, shall in any event be: a. Construed as, offered or admitted in evidence as, received as or deemed to be evidence for any purpose adverse to the Released Parties, including, but not limited to, evidence of a presumption, concession, indication or admission by Defendants or any of the Released Parties of any liability, fault, wrongdoing, omission, concession or damage; or b. Disclosed, referred to, or offered or received in evidence against any of the Released Parties in any further proceeding in the Actions, or in any other civil, criminal or administrative action or proceeding, except for purposes of settling the Actions pursuant to the Stipulation or enforcing the terms of the Stipulation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">15. As of the date this Order is signed, all dates and deadlines associated with this litigation shall be stayed, other than those related to the administration of the Settlement of the Actions.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">16. In the event the Settlement does not become effective in accordance with the terms of the Stipulation, or the Settlement is not finally approved, or is terminated, canceled or fails to become effective for the reasons specified in the Stipulation, this Order shall be rendered null and void and shall be vacated, and the Parties shall revert to their respective positions existing immediately prior to the date they entered into the Stipulation.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">17. The Court reserves the right to adjourn or continue the date of the Final Approval Hearing and all dates provided for in the Stipulation without further notice to Class Members, and retains jurisdiction to consider all further applications arising out of or connected with the proposed Settlement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="0">Dated: August 24, 2009</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>