<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>XPays, INC., Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>INTERNET COMMERCE GROUP, INC., an Arizona corporation; SK INTERTAINMENT, INC., an Illinois corporation; ADULT PROFIT, a Danish business entity of unknown form; LUCINA S.L., a Spanish business entity of unknown form; WEB TRAFFIC, INC.,an Australian corporation; TARASANT, a Singaporean business entity of unknown form; et al. Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 06-05688 DDP (FFMx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 06-05688 DDP (FFMx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:06-cv-05688-DDP-VBK</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 01/14/2008</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER DENYING MOTION FOR SUMMARY JUDGMENT</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center">[Motion filed on December 11, 2007]</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">DEAN D. PREGERSON United States District Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">This matter comes before the Court on Defendant and counterclaimant Internet Commerce Group, Inc.'s (&#x201C;ICG&#x201D;) motion for summary judgment. After reviewing the papers submitted by the parties and motion and adopts the following order.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="0">///</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I.</bold> considering the arguments therein, the Court denies the <bold>BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">This case concerns copyright, trademark, and unfair competition claims arising from a company's use of the Paris Hilton sex video (&#x201C;Video&#x201D;), entitled &#x201C;One Night in Paris.&#x201D; Plaintiff XPays claims a license to the internet usage of the Video, and alleges that Defendant ICG unlawfully used content from the Video on its website, www.celebrityhardcore.com.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">XPays is a California internet company. XPays operates a number of websites that offer affiliate programs for the Video. The parties dispute whether XPays' rights to use the Video were exclusive or nonexclusive at times relevant to this action. Evan Horowitz is a co-owner of XPays. Both are plaintiffs in the action against ICG, and defendants to ICG's counterclaim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Defendant ICG operates several websites featuring sexually explicit content, including www.celebrityhardcore.com and www.xxxcash.com. Through the XXXCash site, ICG runs an &#x201C;affiliate program&#x201D;, the purpose of which is to enter into agreements with third-parties who receive referral fees from XXX Cash for directing customers to ICG websites, including the Celebrity Hardcore site. At all times relevant to this action, CWIE, L.L.C., an Arizona company doing business as CCBILL, has hosted and provided credit card payment processing for ICG's Celebrity Hardcore website.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">On November 30, 2005, ICG entered into an agreement with Red Light District Video (&#x201C;RLDV&#x201D;), the authorized manufacturer of the Video in DVD format, to purchase DVD copies of the Video for sale on its websites, including the Celebrity Hardcore site. ICG designed a marketing page for the Video, which included six thumbnail images and six clips of the Video that were each less than 31 seconds. While ICG claims the page was intended to generate consumer interest in purchasing its lawfully obtained copies of the DVD, XPays asserts that the marketing page was aimed at attracting consumers to subscribe as members to ICG's website through its use of the Video. (<underscore>Compare</underscore> Declaration of Bob Gibson &#182; 10, Ex. H <underscore>with</underscore> Declaration of Evan Horowitz &#182; 5; Declaration of Paul Berra, Ex. B-D.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">In December 2005, ICG attempted to obtain Rick Salomon's permission for the marketing page by contacting David Joseph, President of RLDV, who in turn contacted Rick Salomon. In an email, David Joseph reported to ICG's Bob Gibson that Rick Salomon had said of the marketing page, &#x201C;it is OK.&#x201D; The parties dispute, however, whether Rick Salomon agreed to a page that contained only an image of the Video's box cover or the marketing page used by ICG, which contained clips and images of the Video itself.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">In April 2006, XPays claims to have discovered infringing use of the Video on ICG's Celebrity Hardcore website. A potential customer that went to the Celebrity Hardcore website would find an image of the Video along with the statement &#x201C;Secret Hollywood Sex Tapes they didn't want out!,&#x201D; and a list of celebrities with sex tapes that included the name &#x201C;Paris.&#x201D; XPays argues that one could access the aforementioned page with clips and images of the Video after becoming a member of the site.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">At that time, Horowitz sent notice to CCBill, and to ICG personnel, pursuant to the Digital Millennium Copyright Act, notifying of the alleged infringement and stating the following: &#x201C;Please cease billing this THIEVING copyright infringer (repeat infringer) within 48 hours per the terms of the [DMCA] which requires hosts to cease providing services to copyright violators.&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> Gingras Decl., Ex. A.) Subsequently, CCBill temporarily shutdown the entire Celebrity Hardcore website and disabled bill processing for ICG customers.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A. <underscore>Legal Standard on Motion for Summary Judgment</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Summary judgment is appropriate if there is no genuine issue as to any material fact and a party is entitled to judgment as a matter of law. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c). The moving party bears the initial burden of demonstrating the absence of a genuine issue of material fact. <underscore>Celotex Corp. v. Catrett</underscore>, 477 U.S. 317, 323 (1986). Summary judgment cannot be granted where a genuine dispute exists as to any material fact. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c). A &#x201C;material&#x201D; fact is one which might affect the outcome of the case under the applicable law. <underscore>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc.</underscore>, 477 U.S. 242, 248 (1986). A dispute about a material fact is genuine if a reasonable jury could return a verdict for the non-moving party. <underscore>Id.</underscore> When the moving party has the burden of persuasion at trial, it must be shown that there is no material fact on the elements of a claim or defense. <underscore>S. Cal. Gas Co. v. City of Santa Ana</underscore>, 336 F.3d 885, 888 (9th Cir. 2003).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">In deciding a motion for summary judgment, the evidence is viewed in the light most favorable to the non-moving party, and all justifiable inferences are to be drawn in its favor. <underscore>Anderson</underscore>, 477 U.S. at 255. Moreover, &#x201C;credibility determinations, the weighing of the evidence, and the drawing of legitimate inferences from the facts are jury functions, not those of a judge [when] he is ruling on a motion for summary judgment.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">B. <underscore>Copyright Infringement</underscore></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center">1. <underscore>ICG's Nonexclusive License Defense</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">&#x201C;To establish [copyright] infringement, two elements must be proven: (1) ownership of a valid copyright and (2) copying of constituent elements of the work that are original.&#x201D; <underscore>Feist Publications, Inc. v. Rural Telephone Service Co.</underscore>, 499 U.S. 340, 361 (1991). An alleged infringer that obtains a license from the copyright owner has an affirmative defense to copyright infringement. <underscore>Worldwide Church of God v. Philadelphia Church of God</underscore>, 227 F.3d 1110 (9th Cir. 2000); <underscore>Michaels v. Internet Entertainment Group, Inc.</underscore>, 5 F. Supp.2d 823 (C.D. Cal. 1998).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">The following facts are undisputed. In late 2005, ICG and RLDV reached an agreement for ICG's purchase of copies of the Video for sale on some of its websites. In December 2005, Bob Gibson of ICG sent an e-mail to RLDV that provided a link to a webpage containing &#x201C;promo stuff for the Paris Hilton Video&#x201D; and stated the following: &#x201C;[D]ue to issues regarding this DVD in the past, Sal wants you to take a look at what's [sic] we've setup and confirm it's ok.&#x201D; (Def.'s Ex. E.) In response, David Joseph of RLDV wrote, &#x201C;Looks good to me, I forwarded to Rick Solomon [sic] and as soon as I hear back from him I will confirm that everything is Ok.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) On the same day, Joseph sent another e-mail to Gibson that stated, &#x201C;I received an e-mail from Rick and it is OK.&#x201D; XPays does not dispute that RLDV was an agent of Rick Salomon.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">ICG argues that these facts establish it obtained permission from Rick Salomon, through RLDV, for its use of the Video on the &#x201C;Marketing Page.&#x201D; (Def.'s Ex. F.) XPays raises two counterarguments: (1) Rick Salomon was unable to give ICG a nonexclusive license because he had already assigned the exclusive rights for use of the Video to Jim Salomon, and then those rights were transferred to Merlin and XPays in partnership; and (2) Even if Rick Salomon was able to give a nonexclusive license, he did not authorize ICG's use of images and clips of the Video. ICG counters that XPays did not have an exclusive license, or alternatively, that any such license did not allow XPays to prohibit any and all display of the Video. ICG raises additional arguments challenging the lack of a contemporaneous writing transferring an exclusive license to XPays. The Court will address these many issues in turn.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">a. <underscore>Section 204(a) Writing Requirement</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">The Court first addresses ICG's argument related to the writing requirement for transferring an exclusive license. ICG acknowledges that the Court has discussed this issue at length in connection with SK Intertainment, Inc.'s motion to dismiss for lack of standing. The Court follows its earlier opinion on this issue, and briefly reiterates the basis for finding that ICG, like SK, is not entitled to summary judgment on this issue.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">&#x201C;A prior oral grant that is confirmed by a later writing becomes valid as of the time of the oral grant, even if the writing is subsequent to the initiation of litigation on the copyright infringement.&#x201D; <underscore>Magnuson v. Video Yesteryear</underscore>, 85 F.3d 1424, 1428 (9th Cir. 1996) (citations omitted).<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> XPays may maintain this action so long as it was assigned the necessary rights prior to this action. The &#x201C;Copyright Assignment&#x201D; could still be a valid writing, even if the writing occurred after the filing of the complaint. <underscore>See Magnuson</underscore>, 85 F.3d at 1428. While ICG is entitled to make the argument that XPays was not a copyright owner or exclusive licensee at the time the alleged infringement occurred, it cannot rely on the lack of a writing for that argument.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p17">&#8195;<underscore>Magnuson</underscore> notes that the Ninth Circuit's opinion in <underscore>Konigsberg Int'l, Inc. v. Rice</underscore>, 16 F.3d 355 (9th Cir. 1994) which is cited here by ICG, suggested the requirement of a contemporaneous writing. However, the Ninth Circuit in <underscore>Magnuson</underscore> found that language in <underscore>Konigsberg</underscore> to be confined to its facts or dicta. <underscore>See Magnuson</underscore>, 85 F.3d at 1429 n.1.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">b. <underscore>Rick Salomon's Right to Grant a Nonexclusive License to ICG</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The next issue is whether Rick Salomon had a right to grant a nonexclusive license to ICG, or whether he granted an exclusive license to Jim Salomon that prevented him from giving ICG a nonexclusive license. Neither party adequately addresses this question, or even offers any case law or argument that is on point. ICG does not address this question in its opening brief. XPays merely asserts that Rick Salomon could not give a nonexclusive license. For the first time in its reply brief, ICG argues that its nonexclusive license was not inconsistent with XPays rights to the Video. This argument is misplaced because the relevant question is whether Jim Salomon was transferred an exclusive license such that Rick Salomon no longer had the right to give ICG the nonexclusive license that it claims to have received from him. The Court finds genuine issues of material fact whether Rick Salomon could grant a nonexclusive license.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">c. <underscore>Whether Rick Salomon Granted ICG a Nonexclusive License</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Even if the previous question were resolved in ICG's favor, there are triable issues of fact regarding whether Rick Salomon granted ICG a nonexclusive license. More to the point, whether Rick Salomon authorized the &#x201C;Marketing Page&#x201D; with clips and images, or authorized some other page that did not include the clips and images is a triable issue. While it is undisputed that Rick Salomon authorized ICG to make some use of the Video on a webpage,<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> XPays offers evidence supporting a reasonable inference that he never authorized ICG to use images and clips in the manner in which ICG did so. (<underscore>See</underscore> Declaration of Rick Salomon &#182; 2; Declaration of Paul Berra, Ex. D.) The deposition testimony of Salomon and Joseph at least suggests that the marketing page was never approved, and permission was limited to display of the box cover or another more limited use. A finder of fact will have to determine the credibility of the witnesses and weigh the evidence to resolve this issue.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p20">&#8195;At oral argument, XPays asserted that the the Salomon statement approving of use of the Video, which was contained in the Joseph e-mail, is inadmissible hearsay. However, the Court notes that XPays never raised any evidentiary objections in connection to ICG's presentation of this evidence.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">d. <underscore>17 U.S.C. &#167; 205(e) Priority Between Conflicting Transfer of Ownership and Nonexclusive License</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">17 U.S.C. &#167; 205(e) provides that a nonexclusive licensee prevails over a conflicting transfer of copyright ownership if the license is granted in writing by the owner or the owner's agent and if &#x201C;(1) the license was taken before execution of the transfer; or (2) the license was taken in good faith before recordation of the transfer and without notice of it.&#x201D; Since the Court finds triable issues of fact whether Rick Salomon could grant a nonexclusive license, and if he could whether he in fact did so, there is also an issue of fact whether 17 U.S.C. &#167; 205(e) is applicable; it applies only if ICG had a nonexclusive license.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">2. <underscore>ICG's Fair Use Defense</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Fair use is an affirmative defense to copyright infringement that &#x201C;permits the use of copyrighted works without the copyright owner's consent under certain situations.&#x201D; <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc. v. Amazon.com, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d 701, 719 (9th Cir. 2007). &#x201C;[T]he fair use of a copyrighted work<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> for purposes such as criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching,<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> scholarship, or research<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> is not an infringement of copyright.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 107.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Whether a defendant has made a &#x201C;fair use&#x201D; of a copyright is a mixed question of law and fact. <underscore>Kelly v. Arriba Soft Corp.</underscore>, 336 F.3d 811, 816 (9th Cir. 2003). &#x201C;If there are no genuine issues of material fact, or if, even after resolving all issues in favor of the opposing party, a reasonable trier of fact can reach only one conclusion, a court may conclude as a matter of law whether the challenged use qualifies as a fair use of the copyrighted work.&#x201D; <underscore>Hustler Magazine, Inc. v. Moral Majority, Inc.</underscore>, 796 F.2d 1148, 1151 (9th Cir. 1996).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">The Copyright Act sets forth a four-factor test to determine whether a particular use of a copyrighted work was fair use. A court is to consider:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p25" first-line="1" turnover="1">(1) the purpose and character of the use, including whether such use is of a commercial nature or is for nonprofit educational purposes;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" first-line="1" turnover="1">(2) the nature of the copyrighted work;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" first-line="1" turnover="1">(3) the amount and substantiality of the portion used in relation to the copyrighted work as a whole; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" first-line="1" turnover="1">(4) the effect of the use upon the potential market for or value of the copyrighted work.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p29" contd-flag="y">17 U.S.C. &#167; 107.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">While SK bears the burden of proving fair use, it need not prove that all of the &#167; 107 factors support a finding of fair use. See <underscore>Sega Enters. Ltd. v. Accolade, Inc.</underscore>, 977 F.2d 1510, 1522 (9th Cir. 1992). After consideration of each factor, a court must balance the factors &#x201C;in light of the purposes of copyright.&#x201D; <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 725, <underscore>citing Campbell v. Acuff-Rose Music, Inc.</underscore>, 510 U.S. 569, 590 (1994).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">a. <underscore>Purpose and Character of the Use</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">The Court first considers &#x201C;the purpose and character of the use, including whether such use is of a commercial nature or is for nonprofit educational purposes.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 107(1). This factor concentrates inquiry on whether the defendant engages in a &#x201C;transformative&#x201D; use that adds &#x201C;something new, with a further purpose or different character, altering the [original] with new expression, meaning, or message,&#x201D; and does not &#x201C;merely supersede the objects of the original creation.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 579.; <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 720-21 (internal citations and quotations omitted). A commercial purpose absent any transformative use, although it does not render use presumptively unfair, weighs against finding fair use. <underscore>See Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 585.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">ICG concedes that its use of the Video was for a commercial purpose, not a transformative use. ICG argues that the Court should still weigh this factor in its favor, however, because a defendant should be able to make &#x201C;limited commercial use of a work for the purpose of truthfully and accurately describing the work and advertising sales of lawfully acquired copies of the work itself.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> (Def.'s Mot. 9.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p33">&#8195;The Court considers ICG's reliance on <underscore>New Kids on the Block v. News America Publ., Inc.</underscore>, 971 F.2d 302 (9th Cir. 1992) inapposite, where that case concerned the &#x201C;nominative use&#x201D; doctrine under trademark law.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Under these circumstances, a reasonable factfinder may view the facts contrary to ICG's characterization, and infer that ICG offered images and clips of the Video to profit off memberships. Also, it could be found that ICG's use supersedes the original by using highlights of the Video, <underscore>see Los Angeles News Service v. Tullo</underscore>, 973 F.2d 791, 798 (9th Cir. 1992), and thereby undermining interest in purchasing the Video. ICG essentially provides its consumers with a compilation of several images and clips without any additional transformative use. A reasonable fact-finder could find that there was not fair use.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">b. <underscore>Nature of the Copyrighted Work</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">A creative work is &#x201C;closer to the core of intended copyright protection than are more fact-based works.&#x201D; <underscore>Perfect 10</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 723, <underscore>citing Kelly v. Arriba Soft Corp.</underscore>, 336 F.3d 811, 820 (9th Cir. 2003). The Video, like a news broadcast, is clearly a work of a factual nature. <underscore>See Feist Publications, Inc.</underscore>, 499 U.S. at 359 (contrasting a film with a news broadcast, finding the latter to receive a lesser degree of copyright protection). Use of such factual works are more likely considered fair. <underscore>Sony Corp. v. Universal City Studios, Inc.</underscore>, 464 U.S. 417, 455 n.40 (1984). Moreover, at the time of ICG's use, the Video was available in DVD and on the Internet, and thus was &#x201C;no longer entitled to the enhanced protection available for an unpublished work.&#x201D; <underscore>See Perfect 10</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 723. Thus, the Court finds that any reasonable factfinder will weigh this factor in ICG's favor.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">c. <underscore>Amount and Substantiality of Use of Copyrighted Work</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">&#x201C;The third factor asks whether the amount and substantiality of the portion used in relation to the copyrighted work as a whole<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> are reasonable in relation to the purpose of the copying.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 586.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="0">It is undisputed that ICG used six clips of the Video, all less than 31 seconds. Quantitatively, three minutes of a sixty-two minute adult film is not excessive in the abstract, but this factor &#x201C;calls for thought not only about the quantity of the materials used, but about their quality and importance, too.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 587.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">Here, ICG asserts that its commercial use was for the purpose of lawfully selling DVD copies of the Video. A reasonable factfinder could reach more than one conclusion whether ICG appropriated the &#x201C;heart&#x201D; of the work in those clips, or whether it was reasonable in relation to its commercial objective. <underscore>Compare LANS v. KCAL-TV Channel 9</underscore>, 108 F.3d 1119, 1121 (9th Cir. 1997) <underscore>with Kelly v. Arriba Soft Corp.</underscore>, 336 F.3d 811, 820-21 (9th Cir. 2003). Accordingly, the Court finds that this factor could be weighed in either party's favor.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">d. <underscore>Effect of the Use on the Market or Value of Copyrighted Work</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">The fourth factor is &#x201C;the effect of the use upon the potential market for or value of the copyrighted work.&#x201D; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 107(4); <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 724. This factor requires the Court to consider &#x201C;the extent of market harm caused by the particular actions of the alleged infringer, but also whether unrestricted and widespread conduct of the sort engaged in by the defendant<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> would result in a substantially adverse impact on the potential market for the original.&#x201D; <underscore>Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 589. This factor has been considered in terms of market substitution; copying original material such that the new use becomes a &#x201C;market replacement&#x201D; creates a higher probability of market harm. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 591.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">As stated already, it is reasonable inference that consumers that paid for the opportunity to see clips and images of the Video at ICG's websites would forgo purchasing the Video from XPays. The Court notes that ICG offers evidence showing similar XPays' sales in the weeks before, during, and after ICG's use, and argues that this evidence shows no market harm. (Declaration of David Gingras, Ex. A.) The Court does not believe that this is the only inference that could be drawn from the sales figures. A reasonable factfinder may conclude, based in part on the strength of the other factors, that XPays' sales during the entire period were harmed by ICG's use and similar uses by others. <underscore>See Campbell</underscore>, 51 U.S. 590-91. It is plausible that unrestricted conduct of the kind engaged in by ICG, if engaged in by other internet pornographic sites, could have a significant effect on the marketability of the Video in its entirety.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">e. <underscore>Conclusion on Fair Use</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">Ultimately, a court must weigh all factors together &#x201C;in light of the purposes of copyright.&#x201D; <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc.</underscore>, 487 F.3d at 725, <underscore>citing Campbell</underscore>, 510 U.S. at 578. The purposes of copyright law are to promote sciences and the arts, and to advance the public welfare. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 720.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">ICG's use was unquestionably commercial in nature, and lacked any transformative quality. This weighs against fair use, especially where ICG is XPays' competitor and may have replaced demand for the Video by offering clips and images to consumers. ICG expresses significant disagreement with XPays' characterization that &#x201C;[i]t is undisputed that ICG used images and clips for commercial gain, namely to convince web surfers to pay a membership fee of $29.95 for an opportunity to watch the Video<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> Pl.'s Opp'n 12.) While the Court agrees that this is not undisputed, there remains a genuine issue of fact whether ICG's use was fair in light of its exclusively commercial purpose, the amount and substantiality of its use, and potential market harm.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">3. <underscore>ICG's Copyright Misuse Defense</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">Copyright misuse is an affirmative defense to copyright infringement. <underscore>Practice Mgmt. Info. Corp. v. American Medical Ass'n</underscore>, 121 F.3d 516, 520 (9th Cir. 1997) (adopting the rule articulated in <underscore>Lasercomb Am., Inc. v. Reynolds</underscore>, 911 F.2d 970, 977-79 (4th Cir. 1990)). The misuse inquiry focuses on &#x201C;whether the copyright is being used in a manner violative of the public policy embodied in the grant of a copyright.&#x201D; <underscore>Lasercomb Am., Inc.</underscore>, 911 F.2d at 978; <underscore>see also MGM Studios, Inc. v. Grokster, Ltd.</underscore>, 454 F. Supp. 2d 966, 994 (C.D. Cal. 2006). The defense of copyright misuse forbids a copyright holder from &#x201C;securing an exclusive right or limited monopoly not granted by the Copyright Office.&#x201D; <underscore>Lasercomb Am., Inc.</underscore>, 911 F.2d at 977-79, (quoted and followed in <underscore>Practice Mgmt. Info. Corp.</underscore>, 121 F.3d at 520).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">Soon after learning that clips and images of the Video were on ICG's CelebrityHardcore.com website, on April 13, 2006, Evan Horowitz e-mailed CCBill a notice pursuant to the Digital Millenium Copyright Act (&#x201C;DMCA&#x201D;), 17 U.S.C. &#167; 512, asking that CCBill take action with respect to ICG's infringing activity. That e-mail was also sent to ICG's Becky Adams. In that notice, Horowitz wrote: &#x201C;Please cease billing this THIEVING copyright infringer (repeat infringer) within 48 hours per the terms of the [DMCA] which requires hosts to cease providing services to copyright violators.&#x201D; (Gingras Decl., Ex. A.) CCBill attempted to notify ICG of the infringement claim.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> When the content had not been removed by April 14, 2006, CCBilL shutdown the entire CelebrityHardcore.com website and disabled the billing feature that allowed CCBill to process payments from ICG customers. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>, Ex. K.) ICG then sent a DMCA counter-notice to CCBill.<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> (<underscore>Id.</underscore>, Ex. M.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p45">&#8195;ICG claims it did not learn of CCBill's e-mail until the website was shutdown because the message was sent to a general email address. However, XPays notes that ICG was copied on the original DMCA notice e-mail sent to CCBill, and ICG does not seem to dispute this fact.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p46">&#8195;Some of the subsequent events are disputed. ICG states that Horowitz refused to review the website to ensure that only infringing material was removed, while Horowitz contends that he did review the website and informed CCBill that the infringing content remained on the website.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p47" level="1">ICG contends that XPays and Horowitz engaged in copyright misuse by deliberately failing to comply with the DMCA's notice provisions in its e-mail to CCBill, by misrepresenting to CCBill that its DMCA obligations required shutting off the website and billing services entirely, and by refusing to comply with the DMCA upon being informed by ICG of defects in its infringement notice.<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference> ICG concludes that XPays' copyright misuse prohibits its claim of copyright infringement.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p48">&#8195;For reasons discussed in II.B.1 <underscore>supra</underscore>, the Court does not address ICG's argument that XPays misrepresented to CCBill its rights in the Video.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">Under the circumstances of this case, the Court finds that copyright misuse is unavailable as a defense to infringement. &#x201C;Copyright misuse does not invalidate a copyright, but precludes its enforcement during the period of misuse.&#x201D; <underscore>Practice Mgmt. Info. Corp.</underscore>, 121 F.3d at 520 (citing <underscore>Lasercomb</underscore>, 911 F.2d at 979 n.22). Here, the alleged misuse occurred when Horowitz sent the DMCA notice, and the period immediately following the notice when ICG's website was shutdown and billing was disabled. As it is undisputed that the period of misuse has ceased, ICG cannot raise this defense. <underscore>See MGM Studios, Inc.</underscore>, 454 F. Supp. 2d at 994-95 (quoting <underscore>In re Napster, Inc. Copyright Litigation</underscore>, 191 F. Supp. 2d 1087, 1102 (N.D. Cal. 2002)) (&#x201C;The [misuse] doctrine does not prevent plaintiffs from ultimately recovering for acts of infringement that occur during the period of misuse.&#x201D;)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">Additionally, the Court notes that the facts surrounding the DMCA notice are substantially different from situations where the misuse doctrine was found applicable. ICG was not subject to a restrictive licensing scheme, <underscore>see A&#38;M Records v. Napster, Inc.</underscore>, 239 F.3d 1004, 1027 n.8 (agreeing with a district court that &#x201C;&#x2018;most of the cases&#x2019; that recognize the affirmative defense of copyright misuse involve unduly restrictive licensing schemes&#x201D;), nor did Defendants' conduct subject it to &#x201C;restraints on inventive or creative activity.&#x201D; <underscore>MGM Studios, Inc.</underscore>, 454 F. Supp. 2d at 995 (noting that misuse doctrine has been applied to conduct that undermines the purposes of copyright law).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p51" level="1">The Court, therefore, holds that ICG is not entitled to a copyright misuse defense. The Defendants' conduct with respect to the DMCA notice, however, remains the subject of ICG's counterclaim for intentional interference with contractual relations.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">C. <underscore>XPays' Lanham Act and Unfair Competition Claims</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p52" level="1">The Court has addressed this issue at length in a previous summary judgment motion in this case (<underscore>See</underscore> Order. There, the Court found that the Supreme Court's decision in <underscore>Dastar Corp. v. Twentieth Century Fox Film Corp.</underscore>, 539 U.S. 23, 28-38 (2003), does not foreclose an initial interest confusion claim of trademark infringement. Similarly here, XPays' Lanham Act and unfair competition claims are distinct from its copyright claim, alleging that ICG aimed to lead consumers to believe that it had the full Video available for viewing at its website.<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference> Accordingly, the Lanham Act and unfair competition claims are not preempted.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p53">&#8195;XPays offers as evidence a page on the front of its CelebrityHardcore.com website indicating that the website had &#x201C;Secret Hollywood Sex Tapes they didn't want out!&#x201D; and mentioned the name of &#x201C;Paris&#x201D; among a list of celebrities.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">D. <underscore>ICG's Counterclaim and Third-Party Claim for Intentional Interference With Contractual Relations</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p54" level="1">ICG seeks summary judgment on its intentional inference with contractual relations claim against XPays and Horowitz. The elements of this claim, as set forth in &#167; 2201 of the California Civil Jury Instructions, are (1) the existence of a contract; (2) knowledge of the contract; (3) intent to disrupt the performance of the contract; (4) conduct that prevented performance or made performance expensive or difficult; (5) harm caused; and (6) conduct that was a substantial factor in causing the harm. ICG concedes issues of fact with respect to the amount of damages.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p55" level="1">Viewing the evidence in the light most favorable to XPays and Horowitz, the Court finds that ICG's counterclaim raises genuine issues of material fact. A reasonable factfinder may conclude that the Defendants did not intend to disrupt business relations by its representations and conduct with respect to the DMCA notice, but rather, sought to prevent the presence of infringing material on ICG's website. Further, CCBill's conduct in actually shutting down the website and bill processing was an intervening cause that raises issues of fact whether the Defendants were a substantial factor in causing ICG harm.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p56" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court DENIES ICG's motion for summary judgment.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p57" level="0">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p58" level="0">Dated: January 14, 2008</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>