<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><bold><underscore>CIVIL MINUTES &#8211; GENERAL</underscore></bold></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>VETRA PERRY-ROMAN, individually, and on behalf of all others similarly situated,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>AIG RETIREMENT SERVICES, INC. et al.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 09-02287 DOC (RNBx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-02287 DOC (RNBx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-02287-DOC-RNB</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 06/10/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Kristee Hopkins, Courtroom Clerk, ATTORNEYS PRESENT FOR PLAINTIFFS: NONE PRESENT</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">None Present, Court Reporter, ATTORNEYS PRESENT FOR DEFENDANTS: NONE PRESENT</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">DOCKET ENTRY</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">[I hereby certify that this document was served by first class mail or Government messenger service, postage prepaid, to all counsel (or parties) at their respective most recent address of record in this action on this date.]</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Date:____________ Deputy Clerk: _______________</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">PROCEEDING (IN CHAMBERS): ORDER GRANTING IN PART AND DENYING IN PART MOTIONS TO STRIKE AND DISMISS</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1"><underscore>THE HONORABLE DAVID O. CARTER, JUDGE</underscore></judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Before the Court is Defendants AIG Retirement Advisors, Inc. (&#x201C;AIGRA&#x201D;) and The Variable Annuity Life Insurance Company's (&#x201C;VALIC&#x201D;) (collectively, &#x201C;Defendants&#x201D;) Motion to Strike Portions of the First Amended Complaint (&#x201C;FAC&#x201D;) Pursuant to Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(f). Also before the Court is Defendants' Motion to Dismiss the Fourth Claim for Relief Pursuant to Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(b)(6). The Court considers the matters jointly as they raise interrelated legal issues. In addition, the Court finds the matters appropriate for decision without oral argument. Fed. R. Civ. P. 78; Local R. 7-15. After considering the moving, opposing, and replying papers, and for the reasons stated below, the Court hereby GRANTS IN PART and DENIES IN PART the Motions.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">Plaintiff Vetra Perry-Roman brings suit on behalf of herself and others similarly situated &#x201C;who are, or have been, employed as Financial Advisors by defendants [AIGRA] and [VALIC], in any position to sell or market (or to assist in selling or marketing) securities and other financial products to the public on its behalf within the applicable statutory period.&#x201D; FAC, &#182; 2. Plaintiff asserts several claims against Defendants for violations of California wage and hour laws, including unlawful failure to pay all wages due (Claim 1), failure to provide meal and rest periods (Claim 2), and failure to provide accurate itemized wage statements (Claim 3). In addition, Plaintiff's Fourth Claim for Relief asserts that Defendants violated California's Unfair Competition Laws (&#x201C;UCL&#x201D;) in that Defendants' knowing violation of California wage and hour laws constitutes impermissible business practices under that code. On May 18, 2009, Defendants filed the instant motions to strike portions of the FAC and to dismiss the Fourth Claim for Relief.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. Legal Standard</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>a. Motion to Strike</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(f) provides that a court &#x201C;may order stricken from any pleading any insufficient defense or any redundant, immaterial, impertinent, or scandalous matter.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(f). Motions to strike are disfavored and &#x201C;are generally not granted unless it is clear that the matter to be stricken could have no possible bearing on the subject matter of the litigation.&#x201D; <ital>LeDuc v. Ky. Cent. Life Ins. Co.</ital>, 814 F. Supp. 820, 830 (N.D. Cal. 1992). The Ninth Circuit has defined &#x201C;immaterial&#x201D; matter as &#x201C;that which has no essential or important relationship to the claim for relief or the defenses being pleaded.&#x201D; <ital>Fantasy, Inc. v. Fogerty</ital>, 984 F.2d 1524, 1527 (9th Cir. 1993) (internal quotation marks and citation omitted), <ital>rev'd on other grounds</ital>, 510 U.S. 517, 114 S. Ct. 1023 (1994).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>b. Motion to Dismiss</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6), a complaint must be dismissed when a plaintiff's allegations fail to state a claim upon which relief can be granted. Once it has adequately stated a claim, a plaintiff may support the allegations in its complaint with any set of facts consistent with those allegations. <ital>Bell Atlantic Corp. v. Twombly</ital>, 127 S. Ct. 1955, 1969 (2007). Dismissal for failure to state a claim does not require the appearance, beyond a doubt, that the plaintiff can prove &#x201C;no set of facts&#x201D; in support of its claim that would entitle it to relief. <ital>Bell Atlantic</ital>, 127 S. Ct. at 1968 (abrogating <ital>Conley v. Gibson</ital>, 355 U.S. 41, 45-46, 78 S. Ct. 99 (1957)). However, if the complaint &#x201C;lacks a cognizable legal theory&#x201D; or &#x201C;sufficient facts alleged under a cognizable legal theory,&#x201D; it must be dismissed. <ital>Balistreri v. Pacifica Police Dep't</ital>, 901 F.2d 696, 699 (9th Cir. 1990).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Under 12(b)(6) motion analysis, the Court must accept as true all factual allegations in the complaint and must draw all reasonable inferences from those allegations, construing the complaint in the light most favorable to the plaintiff. <ital>Guerrero v. Gates</ital>, 442 F.3d 697, 703 (9th Cir. 2006); <ital>Balistreri</ital>, 901 F.2d at 699. Dismissal without leave to amend is appropriate only when the Court is satisfied that the deficiencies in the complaint could not possibly be cured by amendment. <ital>Jackson v. Carey</ital>, 353 F.3d 750, 758 (9th Cir. 2003) (citing <ital>Chang v. Chen</ital>, 80 F.3d 1293, 1296 (9th Cir. 1996)); <ital>Lopez v. Smith</ital>, 203 F.3d 1122, 1127 (9th Cir. 2000).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. Discussion</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">By their Motion to Strike and Motion to Dismiss, Defendants raise a number of arguments regarding the insufficiency of Plaintiff's pleadings. The Court proceeds to address each matter in turn.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>a. Standing to Pursue Injunctive Relief</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">Defendants argue that Plaintiff does not have standing to seek injunctive relief. To have standing in order to bring a claim for injunctive relief, Plaintiff must show: (1) she has suffered an injury; (2) that injury was caused by Defendants; and (3) the injury will likely be redressed by the relief sought. <ital>See Thinket Ink Info. Res., Inc. v. Sun Microsystems, Inc.</ital>, 368 F.3d 1053, 1057 (9th Cir. 2004). Defendants properly note that the Ninth Circuit has held that a former employee lacks standing to seek an injunction against a former employer because the plaintiff's status as a former employee demonstrates that he or she will not benefit from the requested relief. Therefore, the third prong of the standing requirement is not met. <ital>See Walsh v. Nevada Dept. of Human Resources</ital>, 471 F.3d 1033, 1036-37 (9th Cir. 2006).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">However, <ital>Walsh</ital> did not deal with the class action context. When evaluating standing, the Court must look at the facts as they existed at the time the complaint was filed. <ital>Amer. Civil Liberties Union v. Lomax</ital>, 471 F.3d 1010, 1015 (9th Cir. 2006). Thus, in response to Defendants' argument, Plaintiff first avers that she was still employed by Defendants as of the filing of her FAC on February 6, 2009; indeed, she contends that her employment was not terminated until February 11, 2009. Further, she also points out that as a representative of a class including <ital>current</ital> employees of Defendants, she can assert injunctive relief.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">The Court agrees with Plaintiff. Ninth Circuit precedent confirms that in the class action context, where putative class members remain employed by the defendant employers, injunctive relief may still be sought. <ital>See Dukes v. Wal-Mart, Inc.</ital>, 509 F.3d 1168, 1189 (9th Cir. 2007). Further, this Court finds persuasive the reasoning in <ital>Johnson v. GMRI, Inc.</ital>, No. CV F 07-0283 LJO DLB, 2007 WL 2462101, *1 (E.D. Cal. Aug. 27, 2007), addressing the wage and hour class context. In that matter, former employees sought injunctive relief against defendant employers, and the employers moved to strike claims for injunctive relief based on lack of standing arguments. <ital>Id.</ital> at *1. The court reasoned that a former employee may still be an adequate representative of a class that includes current employees; and with current employees members of the putative class, the requirements of standing were met at that point. In addition, the court recognized that &#x201C;public policy purposes dissuade striking injunctive relief at this early stage. Disqualifying plaintiffs to seek injunctive relief would unfairly advantage defendants and rob potential class members of a remedy. The circumstances here raise at least an inference that current employees may be resistant to champion the claims of potential class members.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at *4-5. Despite Defendants' argument to the contrary, the FAC makes clear that Plaintiff is attempting to represent a class that includes <ital>current</ital> Financial Advisors employed by Defendants. See FAC, &#182; 2 (identifying class members as those individuals &#x201C;<ital>who are</ital>, or have been, employed as Financial Advisors&#x201D; by Defendants (emphasis added)). With current employees members of the putative class, the Court sees no reason not to allow injunctive relief claims to proceed. The Court agrees that public policy considerations, including fear of retaliation by current employees, support the pursuit of injunctive relief here even where the class representative is a former employee. Thus, at this early stage in the litigation, the Court denies Defendants' Motion to Strike Plaintiff's claims for injunctive relief based on lack of standing.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">While the above reasoning demonstrates that the Court need not rely on the date of Plaintiff's termination to allow the injunctive relief claims to go forward, the Court acknowledges that Defendants argue the Court cannot consider such facts as they are not contained within the four corners of the FAC. However, even if this amounted to a deficiency in the pleadings, such an inadequacy can clearly be remedied by amendment. As a result, the Court grants Plaintiff leave to amend the FAC to represent the facts related to her employment termination date.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>b. Punitive Damages</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Defendants argue that punitive damages are not available for Plaintiff's wage and hour claims. Defendants raise two arguments regarding why punitive damages are unavailable. First, Defendants argue that wage and hour claims are &#x201C;contractual&#x201D; in nature and not subject to punitive damages. Second, Defendants argue that the California Labor Code sets forth the exclusive remedies for Plaintiff's claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Under California law, punitive damages are available &#x201C;[i]n an action for the breach of an <ital>obligation not arising from contract</ital>, where it is proven by clear and convincing evidence that the defendant has been guilty of oppression, fraud, or malice<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; Cal. Civ. Code &#167; 3294(a) (emphasis added).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Plaintiff seeks punitive damages for Defendant's alleged Labor Code violations. As a general rule, when a statute creates new rights and obligations that did not exist at common law, the express statutory remedy is deemed to be the exclusive remedy for statutory violations, unless the remedies are inadequate. <ital>Turnbull &#38; Turnbull v. ARA Transp. Inc.</ital>, 219 Cal. App. 3d 811 (1990); <ital>De Anza Santa Cruz Mobile Estates Homeowners Ass'n v. De Anza Santa Cruz Mobile Estates</ital>, 94 Cal. App. 4th 890, 912 (2001). Here, the statutory claims Plaintiff asserts under the Labor Code do not appear to have existed at common law. <ital>See Aubry v. Goldhor</ital>, 201 Cal. App. 3d 399, 404 (1988). In particular, &#x201C;the duty to pay overtime is a duty created by statute rather than one that existed at common law.&#x201D; <ital>Green v. Party City Corp.</ital>, No. 01-9681, 2002 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7750, at *13 (C.D. Cal. Apr. 9, 2002); <ital>see also Brewer v. Premier Golf Properties</ital>, 168 Cal. App. 4th 1243, 1256 (2008) (holding punitive damages not available for violations of Labor Code provisions governing meal and rest breaks, minimum wages/unpaid wages, and accurate pay stubs). Moreover, there is no indication that the remedies provided by the Labor Code do not adequately compensate employees for the alleged violations, though Plaintiff makes a conclusory argument to the contrary. Nor does Plaintiff provide the Court with any authority suggesting that the Labor Code provisions at issue relate to duties that existed at common law.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Furthermore, it is widely accepted that when a statute provides for a specific penalty, it can be inferred that the Legislature intended to exclude other penalties. <ital>De Anza</ital>, 94 Cal. App. 4th at 912. In particular, courts have concluded that &#x201C;[t]he Legislature's provision of such statutory penalties [in Labor Code Section 203] precludes an award of punitive damages.&#x201D; <ital>Czechowski v. Tandy Corp.</ital>, 731 F. Supp. 406, 410 (N.D. Cal. 1990); <ital>see also Green</ital>, 2002 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 7750, at *13-14 (holding that plaintiff could not assert conversion claim, but rather was limited to statutory remedies for defendant's alleged failure to pay overtime and thus, the amount in controversy requirement was not satisfied because punitive damages were not available for the statutory Labor Code claims).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Moreover, Plaintiffs' request for punitive damages suffers from an additional defect &#8211; they have not alleged a single tort claim. <ital>De Anza</ital>, 94 Cal. App. 4th at 895 (&#x201C;Punitive damages would be available upon a proper showing in a tort action, and a plaintiff may elect to recover either punitive damages on a tort cause of action or statutory penalties on a cause of action for violating the statute.&#x201D;). &#x201C;However, a plaintiff proceeding only on a statutory violation is limited to the statutory remedies.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> Thus, because Plaintiff has only alleged statutory violations, the statutory remedies in the Labor Code are the exclusive remedies for Plaintiff's causes of action. Indeed, Plaintiff has not even countered Defendants' argument that Plaintiff's claims arise from the employee-employer relationship and are fundamentally contractual in nature, thus barring punitive damages. <ital>See Bell v. Farmers Ins. Exch.</ital>, 135 Cal. App. 4th 1138, 1146-47 (2006) (recognizing the principle that &#x201C;the employment relationship is itself &#x2018;fundamentally contractual&#x2019;&#x201D; (quoting <ital>Guz v. Bechtel National, Inc.</ital>, 24 Cal. 4th 317, 335 (2000))).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Defendants also argue that Plaintiff cannot seek to recover punitive damages for Defendants' alleged violation of California's Unfair Competition Laws (&#x201C;UCL&#x201D; or &#x201C;Section 17200&#x201D;), Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167;&#167; 17200 <ital>et seq.</ital> Defendants are correct that punitive damages are not recoverable for UCL violations. <ital>Southwest Marine, Inc. v. Triple A Mach. Shop, Inc.</ital>, 720 F. Supp. 805, 810 (N.D. Cal. 1989) (only equitable relief is available under Section 17200, not penalties such as punitive damages); <ital>Newport Components v. NEC Home Elecs.</ital>, 671 F. Supp. 1525, 1550-51 (C.D. Cal. 1987) (punitive damages are not available under Section 17200). Thus, the request for punitive damages pursuant to Section 17200 violations is stricken.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>c. Attorneys' Fees in Connection with a Labor Code Section 203 Claim</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Defendants also argue that Plaintiff cannot pursue attorneys' fees in conjunction with her claim for waiting time penalties under California Labor Code &#167; 203. <ital>See</ital> FAC, &#182; 30 (&#x201C;As a consequence of Defendants' willful conduct in not paying compensation for all hours worked, certain class members are entitled to 30 days wages, as a penalty under California Labor Code &#167; 203, together with attorneys' fees and costs.&#x201D;). Defendants argue that there is no statutory basis to award Plaintiff attorneys' fees for a violation of Section 203.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">Plaintiff counters by arguing that she may be entitled to fees pursuant to California Code of Civil Procedure &#167; 1021.5, providing in pertinent part that:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p19" first-line="2" turnover="1">[A] court may award attorneys' fees to a successful party against one ore more opposing parties in any action which has resulted in the enforcement of an important right affecting the public interest if: (a) a significant benefit, whether pecuniary or nonpecuniary, has been conferred on the general public or a large class of persons, (b) the necessity and financial burden of private enforcement, or of enforcement by one public entity against another public entity are such as to make the award appropriate, and (c) such fees should not in the interest of justice be paid out of the recovery, if any.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p20" contd-flag="y">Cal. Code Civ. Proc. &#167; 1021.5. Plaintiff thus argues that by proceeding through class certification and ultimately trial, she will prove that Defendants systemically misclassified and continue to misclassify a large class of its California Financial Advisors, entitling each putative class member to significant penalties under Section 203 for failure to pay wages due and satisfying the requirements of Cal. Code Civ. Proc. &#167; 1021.5.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Despite Defendants' argument to the contrary, Plaintiff may be able to satisfy the requirements of Cal. Code Civ. Proc. &#167; 1021.5. Defendants would have this Court believe that Plaintiff is primarily acting out of her own self-interest and does not mean to confer a significant benefit on others. However, Defendants' argument does not stand, especially in light of Plaintiff's representation that she seeks to represent a class. <ital>See Estrada v. FedEx Ground Package System, Inc.</ital>, 154 Cal. App. 4th 1, 16-17 (2007) (finding that plaintiff's &#x201C;personal motivation [did] not diminish the fact the he pursued this public class action not only for himself but on behalf of a class comprised of FedEx's past and present drivers and ultimately obtained awards [for reimbursement of work-related expenses] for 209 drivers&#x201D; and ruling that &#x201C;[n]o more is required to satisfy the &#x2018;significant benefit,&#x2019; &#x2018;public interest,&#x2019; and &#x2018;large class of persons&#x2019; requirements of section 1021.5&#x201D;). The Court here is not making an ultimate determination that Plaintiff will be awarded attorneys' fees pursuant to Cal. Code Civ. Proc. &#167; 1021.5 if she is successful on her Section 203 claim in the context of a class action suit. Instead, the Court in its discretion at the close of litigation will have to consider all the facts before it to determine if the elements of Cal. Code Civ. Proc. &#167; 1021.5 are in fact met. However, the Court finds that such request for fees need not be stricken at this early stage in the litigation.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>d. Unlawful Deductions</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Defendants point out that while the FAC does not expressly assert claims for unlawful deductions under California Labor Code &#167;&#167; 221 or 224, the FAC nonetheless contains repeated references to Defendants allegedly taking unlawful deductions from Plaintiff and the putative class members' pay. <ital>See, e.g.</ital>, FAC, &#182; 7 (&#x201C;Moreover, during the class period, Defendants unlawfully deducted and/or retained monies from commission paychecks issued to Representative Plaintiff and class members, in violation of California labor law.&#x201D;); see also <ital>Id.</ital> at &#182;&#182; 4 and 23. Because none of the claims for relief cite to the relevant labor code sections, Defendants argue that these factual assertions related to improper deductions have no bearing on any legal issues to be decided and, as a result, should be stricken from the FAC. <ital>See Fantasy, Inc. v. Fogerty</ital>, 984 F.2d 1524, 1527 (9th Cir. 1993), <ital>rev'd on other grounds, Fogerty v. Fantasy, Inc.</ital>, 510 U.S. 517 (1994) (recognizing that &#x201C;impertinent&#x201D; matters are those that have no bearing on issues to be decided and defining &#x201C;immaterial&#x201D; matters as those that have no essential relationship to a claim for relief).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">However, the Court reiterates that motions to strike &#x201C;are generally not granted unless it is clear that the matter to be stricken could have <ital>no possible bearing</ital> on the subject matter of the litigation.&#x201D; <ital>LeDuc</ital>, 814 F. Supp. at 830 (emphasis added). While the First Claim for Relief does not expressly refer to a California Labor Code section for unlawful deductions, Plaintiff does in fact cite to Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 221 in the Preliminary Statement section of the FAC. <ital>See</ital> FAC at &#182; 1. Further, in the First Claim for Relief, Plaintiff asserts that &#x201C;Defendants withheld amounts accrued and owing on commissions earned by Representative Plaintiff and class members.&#x201D; FAC, &#182; 34. Thus, Plaintiff seems to clearly assert that unlawful deductions are another form of earned but unpaid wages to which Plaintiff and the putative class members are entitled under the First Claim for Relief. As a result, Defendants' argument that Plaintiff's reference to unlawful deductions has &#x201C;no possible bearing on the subject matter of the litigation&#x201D; is without merit. However, the Court agrees with the argument raised in Defendants' reply that Plaintiff has provided an insufficient factual basis for her claim of unlawful deductions pursuant to <ital>Bell Atlantic Corp v. Twombly, supra</ital>. Instead, her allegation is rather conclusory. Thus, Plaintiff is given leave to amend in order to provide at least a minimal factual basis for her assertion that Defendants made some type of unlawful deductions from the wages of Plaintiff and putative class members.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>e. Section 17200</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Defendants move to strike or, alternatively, move to dismiss Plaintiff's Section 17200 claim.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Section 17200 prohibits unfair competition, including unlawful, unfair, and fraudulent business acts. <ital>See</ital> Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167;&#167; 17200 <ital>et seq.</ital> &#x201C;Section 17200 &#x2018;borrows&#x2019; violations from other laws by making them independently actionable as unfair competitive practices.&#x201D; <ital>Korea Supply Co. v. Lockheed Martin Corp.</ital>, 29 Cal. 4th 1134, 1143 (2003) (quoting <ital>Cal-Tech Commc'ns, Inc. v. Los Angeles Cellular Telephone Co.</ital>, 20 Cal. 4th 163, 180 (1999)). In bringing her Section 17200 claim, Plaintiff &#x201C;seek[s] equitable, injunctive and statutory relief to stop the misconduct of Defendants<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> and seek[s] restitution from Defendants through the unfair, unlawful and fraudulent business practices described herein.&#x201D; FAC, &#182; 57.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p25">&#8195;The arguments raised by the motion to strike and motion to dismiss are virtually identical, so the Court addresses them simultaneously.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">Injunctive relief enjoining a defendant from engaging in the acts constituting unfair competition is available under Section 17200. Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167; 17203. However, &#x201C;restitution is the only monetary remedy expressly authorized by Section 17203.&#x201D; <ital>Korea Supply.</ital>, 29 Cal. 4th at 1146. An order for restitution is an order &#x201C;compelling a UCL defendant to return money obtained through an unfair business practice to those persons in interest from whom the property was taken.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 1144 (quoting <ital>Kraus v. Trinity Mgmt. Servs., Inc.</ital>, 23 Cal. 4th 116, 126-27 (2000)). In other words, the purpose of restitution is &#x201C;to restore the status quo by returning to the plaintiff funds in which he or she has an ownership interest.&#x201D; <ital>Korea Supply</ital>, 29 Cal. 4th at 1149; <ital>see also Kraus</ital>, 23 Cal. 4th at 126 (relief under Section 17200 is available to &#x201C;restore to the parties in interest money or property taken by means of unfair competition&#x201D;). Accordingly, California Business and Professions Code Section 17200 does not authorize a monetary remedy where a plaintiff does not have any ownership interest in the money sought. For example, disgorgement of profits, which are &#x201C;neither money taken from a plaintiff nor funds in which the plaintiff has an ownership interest,&#x201D; is &#x201C;not an authorized remedy in an individual action under the UCL.&#x201D; <ital>Korea Supply</ital>, 29 Cal. 4th at 1140.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Defendants essentially raise two arguments in favor of dismissing the Section 17200 claim. First, they reiterate their argument that Plaintiff has no standing to pursue injunctive relief enjoining Defendants from engaging in the allegedly ongoing, unlawful conduct. However, as this Court already noted, in this class action context, injunctive relief may still be sought. To the extent Plaintiff is unsuccessful in certifying this matter as a class action and proceeds on her claims solely as an individual, she will then not be able to pursue such injunctive relief due to her status as a former employee. However, at this early stage and with the representation that Plaintiff seeks to represent a putative class including current employees, the Court finds it premature to strike requests for injunctive relief from the FAC. Thus, Plaintiff can proceed on her Section 17200 claim seeking to enjoin the Defendants from engaging in particular conduct.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Second, Defendants argue that none of the underlying violations entitle Plaintiff to restitution. Thus, to the extent she is barred from seeking injunctive relief as a former employee, she also cannot argue, as an individual, that she is properly seeking restitution under the UCL. Instead, they argue that such violations, at most, entitle her to monetary damages that do not constitute equitable relief under Section 17200. As a result, Defendants contend Plaintiff's first three claims for relief based on various labor code violations cannot form the basis for her UCL claim. The Court examines each cause of action in turn.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>1. First Claim for Relief</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">With respect to Plaintiff's First Claim for Relief, Plaintiff avers that Defendants have unlawfully failed to pay all wages due, including overtime compensation, under a series of California wage orders and various labor codes. For example, Plaintiff contends that she and members of the putative class often worked &#x201C;in excess of eight hours in a workday and/or forty hours in a workweek,&#x201D; FAC, &#182; 34, when such employees were improperly classified.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">Defendants do not expressly argue that the relief sought under the First Claim for Relief is not restitutionary in nature. Instead, they argue that the oft-cited California Supreme Court case allowing for the recoupment of improperly withheld wages under Section 17200 requires that the alleged unpaid wages be readily quantifiable. <ital>See</ital> Defs.'s Mot. to Dismiss, 5, and <ital>generally Cortez v. Purolator Air Filtration Prod. Co.</ital>, 23 Cal. 4th 163 (2000). In that case, a former employee brought suit against her employer for failure to pay overtime wages. More specifically, plaintiff's employer switched her working schedule from five eight-hour days to four ten-hour days but failed to pay overtime wages for those hours worked over eight hours in one day. <ital>Id.</ital> at 169-70. The California Supreme Court held that Section 17023 of the UCL authorized an order compelling the defendant employer to pay unlawfully withheld wages as a restitutionary remedy under Section 17200. The court reasoned that &#x201C;[o]nce earned, those unpaid wages became property to which the employees were entitled. Failure to promptly pay those wages was unlawful and thus an unfair practice.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 168.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Defendants argue that the subsequent California Supreme Court decision in <ital>Korea Supply</ital> further clarified that a restitutionary remedy must be readily quantifiable and aver that Plaintiff cannot prove up a specific amount of restitution owed. However, the import of <ital>Korea Supply</ital> is that the court confirmed that <ital>nonrestitutionary</ital> disgorgment is not an available remedy under the UCL and that a plaintiff must demonstrate a vested interest in the property sought to be restored, rather than a contingent expectancy. <ital>Korea Supply</ital>, 29 Cal. 4th at 149-50, 1152. Thus, the <ital>Korea Supply</ital> Court did not distinguish <ital>Cortez</ital> based on the fact that <ital>Cortez</ital> involved a quantifiable sum and the sum at issue in <ital>Korea Supply</ital> was not quantifiable. Instead, <ital>Korea Supply</ital> did not involve an alleged earned but unpaid wage sought by the plaintiff employee from the defendant employer. Further, while Defendants contend that Plaintiff will not be able to prove the number of hours worked by Plaintiff and class members that remain unpaid, at the 12(b)(6) stage, the Court cannot assume that such a showing is an impossibility or take Defendants' assertions as final proof on the matter. Relatedly, neither <ital>Cortez</ital> nor <ital>Korea Supply</ital> imply that a plaintiff seeking to obtain alleged earned but unpaid wages must plead the exact amount of those wages in order to survive a Rule 12(b)(6) dismissal.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">Thus, to the extent the First Claim for Relief seeks to return to Plaintiff and putative class members wages that have been earned but remain unpaid, it can form a basis for her UCL claim.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>2. Second Claim for Relief</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">As to Plaintiff's Second Claim for Relief, Plaintiff alleges that Defendants failed to provide Plaintiff and putative class members with required meal and rest periods in violation of California Labor Code &#167;&#167; 226.7 and 512. Under Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 2267(b), &#x201C;[i]f the employer fails to provide an employee a meal period or rest period in accordance with an applicable order of the Industrial Welfare Commission, the employer shall pay the employee one additional hour of pay at the employee's regular rate of compensation for each work day that the meal or rest period is not provided.&#x201D; In addition, Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 512 identifies the relevant rest breaks required to be provided by employers to nonexempt employees.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Defendants argue that the one-hour premium pay available under Cal. Labor Code &#167; 226.7 cannot constitute restitution for purposes of monetary relief under Section 17200. Defendants concede that the California Supreme Court has deemed such premium pay as &#x201C;wages&#x201D; to compensate employees for working through required breaks rather than as a &#x201C;penalty&#x201D; to the employer. <ital>See Murphy v. Kenneth Cole Prod. Inc.</ital>, 40 Cal. 4th 1094, 1114 (2007). However, unlike the unpaid, overtime wages that could constitute restitution in <ital>Cortez</ital>, Defendants aver that the premium payment under Section 226.7, while constituting a wage, is not an <ital>already earned</ital> wage. However, the Court finds this a distinction without merit. After a nonexempt employee works through a mandated rest or meal break, that one-hour of premium pay is a wage which he are she has earned, just as an overtime rate is a wage earned once the nonexempt employee works past the eighth hour in a single day. In other words, the extra one-hour of pay is a premium wage just like overtime pay constitutes a premium wage, an analogy acknowledged by the <ital>Murphy</ital> Court. <ital>Id.</ital> at 1109-10. Thus, if unpaid overtime premium wages can constitute restitution for purposes of the UCL, the Court cannot see why unpaid premium wages for working through a legally required rest break also would not constitute restitutionary relief, despite Defendants unpersuasive arguments to the contrary. Thus, the premium payments sought in Plaintiff's Second Claim for Relief can form the basis for her UCL claim.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>3. Third Claim for Relief</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">By her Third Claim for Relief, Plaintiff alleges that Defendants failed to provide employees with accurate itemized wage statements pursuant to California Labor Code &#167;&#167; 226 and 1174. Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 226(a) provides that an employer shall provide its employees either &#x201C;semimonthly, or at the time of each payment of wages&#x201D; with &#x201C;an itemized wage statement&#x201D; that includes certain required information. For violation of this code section, an employee who has &#x201C;suffer[ed] injury as a result of a knowing and intentional failure by an employer to comply with subdivision (a) is entitled to recover the greater of all actual damages or fifty dollar ($50) for the initial pay period in which a violation occurs and one hundred dollars ($100) per employee for each violation in a subsequent pay period, not exceeding an aggregate penalty of four thousand dollars ($4,000)<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; Cal. Lab. Code &#167; 226(e).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Plaintiff avers that Defendants &#x201C;failed to provide timely, accurate itemized wage statements&#x201D; to her and putative class members and as a result, &#x201C;seek[s] to recover penalties, in amounts to be established<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> at trial.&#x201D; FAC, &#182;&#182; 54-55. As Defendants point out, no money that Plaintiff already has an ownership interest in has been inequitably retained by Defendants that must now be disgorged. Thus, Plaintiff has no argument that the monetary penalties she seeks pursuant to a Section 226(a) violation are restitutionary in nature. Indeed, the alleged violation in no way indicates that Defendants retained funds that are owed to and already earned by Plaintiffs; instead, the violation implicates improper wage statements. Thus, the monetary penalties sought by Plaintiff under her third claim for relief do not implicate the applicable &#x201C;restore&#x201D; prong of the UCL. <ital>See Korea Supply</ital>, 29 Cal. 4th at 1147 (&#x201C;A court cannot, under the equitable powers of section 17203, award whatever form of monetary relief it believes might deter unfair practices. The fact that the &#x2018;restore&#x2019; prong of section 17203 is the only reference to monetary penalties in this section indicates that the Legislature intended to limit the available monetary remedies under the act.&#x201D;) As a result, Plaintiff can only proceed on her UCL claim as to the Third Claim for Relief to the extent she seeks (and ultimately can seek pending class certification) injunctive relief requiring Defendants to comply with the requirements of Section 226.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>f. Reference to a Statute That Does Not Exist</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">Defendants lastly argue that California Civil Code &#167; 1021.5 does not exist. As a result, Defendants argue that references to such statute in paragraphs 31 and 16 of the &#x201C;Relief Sought&#x201D; section of the FAC must be stricken. However, Plaintiff clearly meant to refer to California Code of Civil Procedure &#167; 1021.5. Thus, she is given leave to amend such deficiencies.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. Disposition</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court hereby ORDERS as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p39" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">&#8226; Defendants' Motion to Strike and/or Dismiss Plaintiff's claims for injunctive relief due to lack of standing is DENIED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">&#8226; Defendants' Motion to Strike Plaintiff's request for punitive damages is GRANTED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">&#8226; Defendants' Motion to Strike Plaintiff's request for attorneys' fees in conjunction with her Cal. Labor Code &#167; 203 claim is DENIED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">&#8226; Defendants' Motion to Strike Plaintiff's reference to unlawful deductions is DENIED. However, Plaintiff must provide a more concrete factual basis for her claim and is given leave to amend in accordance with this order.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">&#8226; Defendants' Motion to Strike and/or Dismiss Plaintiff's Fourth Claim for Relief is DENIED. However, Plaintiff cannot seek restitutionary, monetary relief under Section 17200 based on her Third Claim for Relief.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p44" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">&#8226; Plaintiff is given 30 days leave to amend those portions of the FAC that improperly cite Cal. Code of Civ. Proc. &#167; 1021.5</paratext></para>
</para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">The Clerk shall serve this minute order on all parties to the action.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>