<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><underscore>CIVIL MINUTES &#8212; GENERAL</underscore></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>CHO MARY SABOL</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>ALLSTATE INSURANCE COMPANY; SHIRLEY KOMURA; and Does 1-100, inclusive</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. EDCV 09-1318-VAP (OPx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>EDCV 09-1318-VAP (OPx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">5:09-cv-01318-VAP-OP</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 09/28/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Marva Dillard, Courtroom Deputy, ATTORNEYS PRESENT FOR PLAINTIFFS: None</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">None Present, Court Reporter, ATTORNEYS PRESENT FOR DEFENDANTS: None</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">PROCEEDINGS: MINUTE ORDER REMANDING TO SUPERIOR COURT FOR THE COUNTY OF SAN BERNARDINO (IN CHAMBERS)</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">HONORABLE VIRGINIA A. PHILLIPS, U.S. DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Defendants' Motion to Remand (&#x201C;Motion&#x201D;) came before the Court for hearing on September 14, 2009. After reviewing and considering all papers filed in support of, and in opposition to, the Motion, the Court GRANTS the Motion to Remand.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On April 9, 2009, plaintiff Cho Mary Sabol (&#x201C;Plaintiff&#x201D;) filed a lawsuit against defendants Allstate Insurance Company (&#x201C;Allstate&#x201D;), Shirley Komura (&#x201C;Komura&#x201D;), and Does 1 through 100 (collectively &#x201C;Defendants&#x201D;) in the Superior Court of the State of California, County of San Bernardino. Plaintiff alleges the following five causes of action under California law: (1) breach of contract; (2) negligent misrepresentation; (3) breach of the implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing; (4) intentional infliction of emotional distress (&#x201C;IIED&#x201D;); and (5) violation of California Business &#38; Professions Code &#167; 17200 <underscore>et seq.</underscore> Plaintiff only alleges an IIED claim against defendant Komura, an adjuster for Allstate. (Complaint &#182; 3.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Plaintiff's action arises from an automobile accident on April 7, 2002, where Plaintiff was a passenger in a vehicle which was rear-ended by an underinsured motorist. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 8.) As a result of the accident, Plaintiff sustained serious injuries and incurred approximately $194,000 in medical bills. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Plaintiff had an automobile insurance policy with Allstate covering her 1987 Chevrolet Caprice. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 6.) In May 2003, Plaintiff submitted an underinsured motorist claim to defendant Allstate. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 11.) Allstate paid $11,255.40 in medical payments to Plaintiff. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 13.) Plaintiff filed a petition for bankruptcy protection on February 13, 2003; the bankruptcy case closed on March 16, 2007. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 14.) On June 26, 2008, Allstate advised Plaintiff that it would not pay her claim. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 15.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">In Plaintiff's IIED claim, she asserts that Allstate and Komura &#x201C;knew that [she] had sustained serious physical injuries and incurred significant medical expenses as a result of her injuries&#x201D; and &#x201C;knew that [her] claims for medical expenses and underinsured motorist benefits exceeded her policy limits.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 39.) Plaintiff alleges that despite this knowledge, Allstate and Kumara &#x201C;refused to pay [her] medical payments claim and underinsured motorist claim.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) She further alleges that &#x201C;Defendants' conduct was intentional and malicious and done for the purpose of causing [her] to suffer humiliation, mental anguish, and emotional and physical distress.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 40.) Moreover, she alleges that Defendants' conduct &#x201C;was done with knowledge that [her] emotional and physical distress would thereby increase, and was done with a wanton and reckless disregard of the consequences to [P]laintiff.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">As to causation, Plaintiff alleges that &#x201C;[a]s a proximate result of [these] acts, [she] suffered humiliation, mental anguish, and emotional and physical distress, and has been injured in mind and body.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 41.) She further alleges that Defendants' acts &#x201C;were willful, wanton, malicious and oppressive.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 42.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">Plaintiff served the complaint on Komura on April 27, 2009 and on Allstate on April 29, 2009. On May 28, 2009, Komura served special interrogatories on Plaintiff. (Zhordania Decl. &#182; 3.) Komura received Plaintiff's responses to the interrogatories on July 2, 2009. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 4.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Interrogatory No. 1 requested Plaintiff &#x201C;[s]tate all facts that support [her] claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress against Ms. Komura.&#x201D; (Zhordania Decl., Ex. 1 at 2.) In response to Interrogatory No. 1, Plaintiff stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p9" first-line="1" turnover="1">Shirley Komura was employed as an adjuster by Allstate and was the adjuster handling Responding Party's underinsured motorist and medical payments claims arising from the accident on April 7, 2002. As the adjuster handling Responding Party's claim, Ms. Komura was in a position to make decisions regarding payment of Responding Party's claim. Ms. Komura knew that Responding Party had suffered serious physical injuries and incurred significant medical expenses as a result of her injuries, and that Responding Party's claims for medical expenses and underinsured motorist benefits exceeded her policy limits. Despite said knowledge, Ms. Komura abused her position as an adjuster and refused to pay Responding Party's underinsured motorist claim and medical payments claim knowing that Responding Party is susceptible to injuries through mental distress, since Responding Party underwent multiple surgeries and continued to have significant pain and suffering from the injuries she sustained in the subject accident.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p10" contd-flag="y">(<underscore>Id.</underscore> at 2-3.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Interrogatory No. 4 requested Plaintiff to state all facts that support her contention that she suffered humiliation, mental anguish, and/or emotional distress as a result of something Ms. Komura did or did not do. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> at 4.) In response to Interrogatory No. 4, Plaintiff stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p12" first-line="1" turnover="1">As a direct and proximate result of Ms. Komura's outrageous and unreasonable denial of Sabol's underinsured and medical payments claim, Responding Party has suffered, and continued to suffer, severe, substantial and enduring emotional distress, to include but not limited to stress, anxiety, difficult concentrating and focusing on tasks, and difficult sleeping.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p13" contd-flag="y">(<underscore>Id.</underscore> at 4.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">On July 13, 2009, eight days after receiving Plaintiff's answers to the interrogatories, Defendants filed a notice of removal under 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1441 based on diversity jurisdiction. (Zhordania Decl. &#182; 5.) Defendants' basis for removal was that complete diversity existed because defendant Komura had been fraudulently joined.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Legal Standard</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">An action is removable to a federal court only if it might have been brought there originally. 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1441(a). The removal statute is &#x201C;strictly construed, and federal jurisdiction must be rejected if there is any doubt as to the right of removal in the first instance.&#x201D; <underscore>Duncan v. Stuetzle</underscore>, 76 F.3d 1480, 1485 (9th Cir. 1996) (internal citations and quotation marks omitted).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>i. Timely Removal</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Section 1446 of Title 28 of the United States Code governs the procedures for removing a case from state court to the United States District Court. The statute requires that the defendant file a notice of removal of a civil action within 30 days after the receipt of the complaint. 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1446(b). In the event that &#x201C;the case stated by the initial pleading is not removable,&#x201D; the defendant must file a notice of removal within 30 days after receipt of &#x201C;an amended pleading, motion, order or other paper from which it may first be ascertained that the case is one which is or has become removable<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">The time limit under 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1446(b) is mandatory and a timely objection to a late petition will defeat removal. <underscore>Fristoe v. Reynolds Metals Co.</underscore>, 615 F.2d 1209, 1212 (9th Cir. 1980).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">Nevertheless, some courts have ignored the 30 day limit in &#167; 1446(b) when removal is sought on the ground that some defendants have been joined fraudulently to prevent removal. <underscore>See United Computer Sys. v. AT&#38;T Info. Sys.</underscore>, 298 F.3d 756, 762 (9th Cir. 2002), citing 14C Charles Alan Wright, Arthur R. Miller &#38; Edward H. Cooper, Federal Practice and Procedure &#167; 3732 (3d ed. 1998) (collecting cases). Other courts have held that where fraudulent joinder can be ascertained on the face of the complaint, the defendant must remove within 30 days in order to be timely. <underscore>See Simpson v. Union Pac. R.R. Co.</underscore>, 282 F. Supp. 2d 1151, 1154 (N.D. Cal. 2003).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>ii. Fraudulent Joinder</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Fraudulent joinder is an exception to the requirement of complete diversity. <underscore>Simpson</underscore>, 282 F. Supp. 2d at 1154, citing <underscore>Wecker v. National Enameling &#38; Stamping Co.</underscore>, 204 U.S. 176, 185-86 (1907). Under the fraudulent joinder doctrine, &#x201C;[a] defendant may remove a civil action on the basis of diversity jurisdiction and seek to persuade the district court that a non-diverse defendant was fraudulently joined.&#x201D; <underscore>Charlin v. Allstate Ins. Co.</underscore>, 19 F. Supp. 2d 1137, 1139-40 (C.D. Cal. 1998), citing <underscore>McCabe v. General Food Corp.</underscore>, 811 F.2d 1336, 1339 (9th Cir. 1987). If the court determines there was fraudulent joinder, &#x201C;the court may disregard the joinder and retain jurisdiction.&#x201D; <underscore>Lewis v. Time Inc.</underscore>, 83 F.R.D. 455, 460 (E.D. Cal. 1979), <underscore>aff'd</underscore>, 710 F.2d 549 (9th Cir. 1983).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">&#x201C;The defendant seeking removal to the federal court is entitled to present the facts showing the joinder to be fraudulent.&#x201D; <underscore>McCabe</underscore>, 811 F.2d at 1339. A court reviewing a claim of fraudulent joinder may look beyond the pleadings, consider the entire record, and determine the basis of joinder by any means available. <underscore>Charlin</underscore>, 19 F. Supp. 2d at 1140. &#x201C;The district court, however, must resolve all disputed questions of fact in favor of the non-moving party.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">The test for fraudulent joinder is &#x201C;whether on the face of the removed complaint there is any possibility plaintiff could prevail.&#x201D; <underscore>Simpson</underscore>, 282 F. Supp. 2d at 1155, citing <underscore>Morris v. Princess Cruises, Inc.</underscore>, 236 F.3d 1061, 1068 (9th Cir. 2001). In other words, &#x201C;the joinder of a resident defendant is fraudulent<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> if the plaintiff fails to state a cause of action against a resident defendant, and the failure is obvious according to the settled rules of the state.&#x201D; <underscore>McCabe</underscore>, 811 F.2d at 1339. &#x201C;A &#x2018;colorable&#x2019; claim against a non-diverse defendant bars removal under the fraudulent joinder doctrine.&#x201D; <underscore>Charlin</underscore>, 19 F. Supp. 2d at 1140.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>iii. Intentional Infliction of Emotional Distress</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">The elements of a prima facie case of intentional infliction of emotional distress in California are:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p23" first-line="1" turnover="1">(1) extreme and outrageous conduct by the defendant with the intention of causing, or reckless disregard of the probability of causing, emotional distress; (2) the plaintiff's suffering severe or extreme emotional distress; and (3) actual and proximate causation of the emotional distress by the defendant's outrageous conduct.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p24" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Corales v. Bennett</underscore>, 567 F.3d 554, 571 (9th Cir. 2009). &#x201C;The complaint must plead specific facts that establish severe emotional distress resulting from defendant's conduct.&#x201D; <underscore>Michaelian v. State Comp. Ins. Fund</underscore>, 50 Cal. App. 4th 1093, 1114 (1996).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">&#x201C;Outrageous&#x201D; conduct is that which is &#x201C;so extreme as to exceed all bounds of that usually tolerated in a civilized community.&#x201D; <underscore>Corales</underscore>, 567 F.3d at 571. The &#x201C;extreme and outrageous character of the conduct may arise from the actor's knowledge that the other is peculiarly susceptible to emotional distress, by reason of some physical or mental condition or peculiarity. The conduct may become heartless, flagrant, and outrageous when the actor proceeds in the face of such knowledge, where it would not be so if he did not know.&#x201D; <underscore>Hailey v. California Physicians' Service</underscore>, 158 Cal. App. 4th 452, 474 (2007). &#x201C;While the outrageousness of a defendant's conduct normally presents an issue of fact to be determined by the trier of fact, the court may determine in the first instance, whether the defendant's conduct may reasonably be regarded as so extreme and outrageous as to permit recovery.&#x201D; <underscore>Trerice v. Blue Cross of Cal.</underscore>, 209 Cal. App. 3d 878, 883 (1989) (internal citations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">In the insurance context, &#x201C;the insured must plead and prove acts by the insurer so extreme as to exceed all bounds usually tolerated in a civilized community.&#x201D; <underscore>Michaelian</underscore>, 50 Cal. App. 4th at 1114. The violation of statutory duties under California Insurance Code &#167; 790.03<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> does not itself constitute the type of outrageous conduct which will support a cause of action for IIED. <underscore>Schlauch v. Hartford Accident &#38; Indem. Co.</underscore> 146 Cal. App. 3d 926, 936 (1983). Moreover, alleging that a worker's compensation insurance carrier and its two employees &#x201C;intentionally, willfully, knowingly and maliciously refused to properly investigate, process and communicate with plaintiff concerning his [worker's compensation] claim for wrongfully terminating [the carrier's] continuing obligation to furnish medical care in the future to plaintiff for his chronic injury&#x201D; does not state an IIED claim. <underscore>Ricard v. Pacific Indemnity Co.</underscore>, 132 Cal. App. 3d 886, 890, 895 (1983).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p27">&#8195;California Insurance Code &#167; 790.03 describes prohibited unfair or deceptive acts or practices.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Unless a defendant can show on a fraudulent joinder theory that there is no possibility a plaintiff can state an IIED claim, a district court addressing a sham defendant claim will remand. For example, in <underscore>Burris v. AT&#38;T Wireless, Inc.</underscore>, the district court remanded the plaintiff employee's case after the defendant employer removed to federal court on the theory of fraudulent joinder of the plaintiff's supervisor. 2006 WL 2038040 (N.D. Cal. July 19, 2006). The defendants did not argue that the plaintiff could not bring an IIED claim against his former supervisor as a matter of law, but instead contended that the plaintiff failed to allege any extreme or outrageous conduct. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at *2. Rejecting this argument, the court reasoned that while the complaint failed to allege extreme or outrageous conduct, the defendants failed to show that &#x201C;under California law, [the plaintiff] would not be afforded leave to amend his complaint to cure this purported deficiency.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore>; <underscore>see also Barsell v. Urban Outfitters, Inc.</underscore>, 2009 WL 1916495, *6-*9 (C.D. Cal. July 1, 2009) (holding that there was a &#x201C;non-fanciful possibility a state court would conclude that [the plaintiff employee's complaint] states a claim against her supervisor&#x201D; especially given the supervisor's knowledge of the plaintiff's depressive disorder); <underscore>Dagley v. Target Corp., Inc.</underscore>, 2009 WL 910558, *3 (C.D. Cal. Mar. 31, 2009) (holding that &#x201C;a reasonable jury could find that [the supervisor] denied Plaintiff's right to medical leave in a deceptive manner by terminating her&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Analysis</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>i. Timely Removal</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Defendants have failed to remove timely pursuant to 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1446(b). Defendant Komura was served on April 27, 2009, but the removal notice was not filed until July 13, 2009. The lapse of time between receipt of the complaint and filing the removal notice exceeds the 30 day deadline imposed by 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1446(b). Although Defendants argue they needed Plaintiff's answers to the special interrogatories to determine whether Plaintiff could possibly state an IIED claim, nothing in the interrogatory answers changes Defendants' ability to argue that Komura is a sham defendant. <underscore>See Simpson v. Union Pac. R.R. Co.</underscore>, 282 F. Supp. 2d 1151, 1154 (N.D. Cal. 2003).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>ii. Fraudulent Joinder</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">Notwithstanding Defendants' untimely removal, Defendants fail to meet their burden of proving that there is no possibility for Plaintiff to state an IIED claim. <underscore>See Morris</underscore>, 236 F.3d at 1068. Defendants fail to establish that, under California law, Plaintiff has either not stated an IIED claim or would not be given leave to amend the complaint to adequately state an IIED claim. <underscore>See, e.g., Burris</underscore>, 2006 WL 2038040 at *2.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Defendants cite to several California decisions involving IIED claims in the insurance context. While these cases may establish that Plaintiff has not adequately alleged an IIED claim in her complaint, the cases suggest that a California court would allow Plaintiff to amend her complaint. For example, in <underscore>Ricard</underscore>, the trial court dismissed plaintiff's second amended complaint. <underscore>See Ricard</underscore>, 132 Cal. App. 3d at 895. In <underscore>Schlauch</underscore>, the Court of Appeal explained what the plaintiff would need to state in an amended complaint to adequately state a claim for IIED. <underscore>See Schlauch</underscore>, 146 Cal. App. 3d at 936. Moreover, federal district courts addressing remand motions involving California IIED claims also appear to allow amendment of the complaint. <underscore>See, e.g., Barsell</underscore>, 2009 WL 1916495 at *6-*9; <underscore>Burris</underscore>, 2006 WL 2038049 at *2.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">While there may be deficiencies with Plaintiff's IIED claim, Plaintiff has made at least a &#x201C;colorable&#x201D; claim against defendant Komura. <underscore>See Charlin</underscore>, 19 F. Supp. 2d at 1140. In both the complaint and her interrogatory answers, Plaintiff discusses Komura's knowledge of her physical injuries and mental distress, which can be a basis of demonstrating &#x201C;outrageous&#x201D; conduct. (<underscore>See</underscore> Complaint &#182; 40; Zhordania Decl., Ex. 1 at 2-3); <underscore>Hailey</underscore>, 158 Cal. App. 4th at 474. Defendants have also failed to demonstrate that Plaintiff's interrogatory answers preclude her from adequately stating an IIED claim.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">Accordingly, the Court GRANTS Plaintiff's motion to remand on the basis that Defendants' removal was untimely. Furthermore, even considering Defendants' argument on the merits, Defendants fail to demonstrate that Komura is a sham defendant.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED.</bold></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>