<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
<venue.name>SOUTHERN DIVISION</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>ALL CITIES REALTY, INC., Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>HOLLYMAX REALTY, INC., et al., Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>SA CV 08-195 AHS (MLGx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>SA CV 08-195 AHS (MLGx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">8:08-cv-00195-AHS-MLG</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 10/20/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">ORDER GRANTING DEFENDANTS' MOTIONS TO DISMISS (DKT NOS. 59 &#38; 60) WITH LEAVE TO AMEND</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">LAICEMARIE H. STOTLER U.S. DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. <underscore>PROCEDURAL BACKGROUND</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">On February 21, 2008, plaintiff All Cities Realty, Inc. (&#x201C;plaintiff&#x201D;) filed a complaint for trademark infringement and unfair competition against Hollymax Realty, Inc. (&#x201C;Hollymax&#x201D;), Commbroker, Inc. (&#x201C;Commbroker&#x201D;) (collectively, &#x201C;Corporate Defendants&#x201D;), Byron Rife, Jr. (&#x201C;Rife&#x201D;), Dale A. Eleniak (&#x201C;Eleniak&#x201D;), and numerous agents. The individual agents named as defendants are: Kenneth G. Davis, Farzad Andy Dorrani, Allen Jackson, Arianne Kays, Jeanette Gurza-Junco, Jiao Hong Kuleck, Rob O'Sullivan, Shannan O'Sullivan, Colette Stevens, Susan Williams, Omid Benjamin Arasteh, Glen Beer, Maurice Benitah, Nina Dhillon, Matthew Freedman, Jack Khalili, Jihan Kim, Robert Melamed, Gina Saeidian, and Simon Shaheri (referred to as &#x201C;Hollymax Individual Defendants&#x201D; and &#x201C;Commbroker Individual Defendants&#x201D; in the Complaint and First Amended Complaint, referred to herein as &#x201C;Agent Defendants&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On December 11, 2008, the Court granted defendants' motion to dismiss with leave to file an amended complaint. Plaintiff's First Amended Complaint (&#x201C;FAC&#x201D;) alleging claims for federal and state trademark infringement, vicarious trademark infringement, and unfair competition, both common law and statutory, was filed on December 23, 2008, adding Kelli Todd-Amundson, aka Kelli Todd (&#x201C;Todd&#x201D;), as an additional defendant.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">On January 9, 2009, Eleniak filed a motion to dismiss the FAC pursuant to Rule 12(b)(6) of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure. On January 12, 2009, Hollymax, Commbroker, Todd, Rife, and the Agent Defendants (collectively, &#x201C;Hollymax Defendants&#x201D;) filed a separate Rule 12(b)(6) motion to dismiss. On January 19, 2009, plaintiff filed oppositions to both motions. On January 23, 2009, plaintiff filed a request for judicial notice in connection with its opposition to the Eleniak motion. On January 26, 2009, Eleniak and the Hollymax Defendants filed separate replies in further support of their respective motions.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">On January 27, 2009, shortly before the hearing date for the motions, Commbroker filed notice of its petition for bankruptcy on January 23, 2009. On January 28, 2009, the Court stayed the action and ordered the hearings vacated and off calendar.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">On June 3, 2009, the Court lifted the stay as to all non-debtor parties. (Commbroker remains subject to the mandatory stay and is not addressed in this Order.) On July 17, 2009, the Court took the motions to dismiss under submission. By this order, the Court grants Eleniak's and the Hollymax Defendants' motions.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. <underscore>SUMMARY OF FIRST AMENDED COMPLAINT</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">Plaintiff, a California corporation offering real estate brokerage and appraisal services, is the owner of the federal service mark, &#x201C;All Cities Realty.&#x201D; (FAC &#182;&#182; 2, 15.) Since 1997, plaintiff has marketed its business on the internet and maintains a prominent internet presence, including the domain name &#x201C;allcitiesrealty.com.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 16, 25.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">In 2002, non-party CF Real Estate Loans, Inc. (&#x201C;CFRELI&#x201D;), a competing corporate real estate broker, began using the &#x201C;All Cities Realty&#x201D; name. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 18.) Like plaintiff, CFRELI operates in California and makes significant use of internet marketing. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 19.) At the time it began using the &#x201C;All Cities Realty&#x201D; name, CFRELI purchased the domain name &#x201C;allcitiesrealty.net&#x201D; to use as its website. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 26.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">In 2003, CFRELI commenced an extensive marketing campaign in both print media and on the internet using the names &#x201C;All Cities Realty&#x201D; and &#x201C;Re/Max All Cities Realty.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 20.) As part of the campaign, CFRELI created numerous websites that displayed the &#x201C;All Cities Realty&#x201D; mark. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Hollymax, Commbroker, and the Agent Defendants participated in CFRELI's infringing activities by maintaining webpages that were integrated into the Re/Max All Cities Realty site, suggesting that defendants were conducting business under the Re/Max All Cities Realty moniker. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 20-22, 33-35.) Defendants' actions had the effect of diluting plaintiff's trade name and web presence and created actual consumer confusion and/or a likelihood of consumer confusion. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 20, 23.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Plaintiff eventually discovered defendants' infringing activities and demanded that they cease and desist using the &#x201C;All Cities Realty&#x201D; mark. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 24.) Defendants initially agreed to plaintiff's demand but ultimately failed to cease their infringing activities. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 25.) Without informing plaintiff, defendants also decided to forward all visitors from its &#x201C;allcitiesrealty.net&#x201D; website to plaintiff's &#x201C;allcitiesrealty.com&#x201D; website. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 26.) This exacerbated consumer confusion by creating a direct link between the two companies. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Although Hollymax, Commbroker, and CFRELI are technically separate corporate entities, they are owned, controlled, and managed by the same &#x201C;ownership group,&#x201D; which is &#x201C;managed, dominated, and controlled by Defendant Kelli Todd.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 3-4, 34.) CFRELI has assumed control of the agents and operations of Hollymax and Commbroker &#x201C;such that any individuality and separateness no longer exists between<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> entities.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 3.) Because there exists a unity of interest between Hollymax, Commbroker, and Todd, the Court should disregard the corporate form and treat Hollymax and Commbroker as Todd's alter egos. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 13-14.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>III. <underscore>SUMMARY OF PARTIES' CONTENTIONS</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Defendants' Motions</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>1. Todd</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Plaintiff fails to plead facts that would give rise to a claim against Todd as the alter ego of Hollymax and Commbroker. To properly plead alter ego liability, plaintiff must allege: (1) a unity of interest and ownership that destroys the separate personalities of the corporation and individual; and (2) that continuing to treat the corporation and individual separately would lead to an inequitable result. <underscore>Mieuli v. DeBartolo</underscore>, No. C-00-3225 JCS, 2001 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 22518, at *27 (N.D. Cal. Jan. 16, 2001). Conclusory alter ego allegations are insufficient to survive a motion to dismiss. <underscore>See Hockey v. Medhekar</underscore>, 30 F. Supp. 2d 1209, 1211 n.1 (N.D. Cal. 1998); <underscore>Hokama v. E.F. Hutton &#38; Co., Inc.</underscore>, 566 F. Supp. 636, 647 (C.D. Cal. 1983).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Plaintiff fails to allege that Todd is the owner of Hollymax or Commbroker. Instead, plaintiff alleges that Hollymax and Commbroker are owned and controlled by the same &#x201C;ownership group&#x201D; as non-party CFRELI. Moreover, plaintiff's remaining alter ego allegations are either conclusory or irrelevant. Absent any specific factual allegations relevant to alter ego liability, <underscore>see Wady v. Provident Life &#38; Accident Ins. Co. of Am.</underscore>, 216 F. Supp. 2d 1060, 1067 (C.D. Cal. 2002), plaintiff fails to state a claim against Todd as the alter ego of Hollymax and Commbroker. Plaintiff's claims against Todd should be dismissed without leave to amend.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>2. Rife</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">The Court should also dismiss plaintiff's claims against Rife, who, at various times, served as Hollymax's and Commbroker's broker of record. Under California law, the designated real estate broker of a real estate corporation is personally responsible for ensuring corporate compliance with real estate law. <underscore>See</underscore> Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167; 10159.2(a); <underscore>Holley v. Crank</underscore>, 400 F.3d 667, 671-72 (9th Cir. 2004). The broker's specific obligations are set forth in Title 10, &#167; 2725 of the California Code of Regulations. Section 2725 does not require the broker to ensure compliance with federal and state trademark law. Even if &#167; 2725 could be construed to impose such a requirement, the broker of record is not personally liable to third parties for failure to adequately supervise corporate employees absent some personal misconduct. <underscore>See Walters v. Marler</underscore>, 83 Cal. App. 3d 1, 25, 147 Cal. Rptr. 655 (1978), <underscore>overruled on other grounds, Gray v. Don Miller &#38; Assocs., Inc.</underscore>, 35 Cal. 3d 498, 198 Cal. Rptr. 551 (1984).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Plaintiff also lacks standing to bring suit against Rife because plaintiff is not among the class of consumers meant to be protected by California's real estate laws. <underscore>See Coldwell Banker Residential Brokerage Co., Inc. v. Superior Court</underscore>, 117 Cal. App. 4th 158, 164, 11 Cal. Rptr. 3d 564 (2004). Thus, plaintiff fails to state claims against Rife for trademark infringement and unfair competition.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>3. Eleniak</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">The Court should dismiss plaintiff's claims against Eleniak, who preceded Rife as broker of record. As with Rife, plaintiff attempts to hold Eleniak secondarily liable for trademark infringement. But secondary liability for trademark infringement attaches only where the defendant is a joint tortfeasor, and there is no such allegation in the FAC. <underscore>See Hard Rock Licensing Corp. v. Concession Servs., Inc.</underscore>, 955 F.2d 1143, 1150 (7th Cir. 1992). Furthermore, as the designated broker, Eleniak's actions are imputed to the corporation. Thus, plaintiff's claims, if any, are against the Corporate Defendants, not against Eleniak personally. <underscore>See Walters</underscore>, 83 Cal. App. 3d at 34-35.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>4. Agent Defendants</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Plaintiff fails to state a claim against the Agent Defendants. To state a claim for trademark infringement under 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1114, plaintiff must allege that the Agent Defendants' use of the mark or a similar mark would create a likelihood of consumer confusion. <underscore>Murray v. Cable Nat'l Broad. Co.</underscore>, 86 F.3d 858, 860 (9th Cir. 1996). Plaintiff's allegations are too vague and conclusory to establish that the Agent Defendants used the &#x201C;All Cities Realty&#x201D; mark.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>5. Corporate Defendants</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Finally, plaintiff fails to state a claim against Hollymax and Commbroker because the FAC contains no allegation that Hollymax or Commbroker made actual use of the All Cities Realty mark.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Plaintiff's Oppositions</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">Defendants' arguments were previously raised and implicitly rejected when the Court granted defendants' first motion to dismiss on other grounds.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>1. Rife</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Rife, as the broker of record for Hollymax and Commbroker, is personally responsible for the companies' business activities. <underscore>See Holley v. Crank</underscore>, 386 F.3d 1248, 1254 (9th Cir. 2004), <underscore>amended and superseded by</underscore> 400 F.3d 667 (9th Cir. 2004). Under California Business and Professions Code &#167; 10159.2(a), the broker of record must supervise and familiarize salespersons with the requirements of state and federal law. <underscore>Id.</underscore> The broker's obligations are not limited to laws and activities related to real estate sales and, as relevant here, include overseeing compliance with federal and state trademark laws. <underscore>See Valdez v. Downey Sav. &#38; Loan Ass'n</underscore>, No. C 06-2541-JF (HRL), 2007 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 31290, at *26 (N.D. Cal. Apr. 17, 2007).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">Even if the broker's responsibilities under &#167; 10159.2 are construed narrowly, the broker is undoubtedly liable for actions related to real estate sales. In the FAC, plaintiff alleges that Hollymax and Commbroker conducted illegal real estate sales activity, including: (1) using plaintiff's mark to conduct sales and broker activity in violation of federal law; (2) using plaintiff's mark to conduct sales and broker activity in violation of state law; and (3) using the names &#x201C;All Cities Realty&#x201D; and &#x201C;Re/Max All Cities Realty&#x201D; without a proper license from the California Department of Real Estate (&#x201C;DRE&#x201D;). Defendants' reliance on <underscore>Walters</underscore> is unpersuasive because <underscore>Walters</underscore> predates the enactment of &#167; 10159.2 and has been superseded by statute and overruled by subsequent case law.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>2. Eleniak</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Like Rife, Eleniak is liable for the acts of the Corporate Defendants as their broker of record. <underscore>See Holley</underscore>, 386 F.3d at 1254; <underscore>Valdez</underscore>, 2007 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 31290, at *26. Moreover, plaintiff's allegations are sufficient to hold Eleniak secondarily liable under a contributory trademark infringement theory. Contributory infringement may occur when the defendant intentionally induces a third party to infringe plaintiff's mark or is willfully blind to the ongoing violations of a third party for which defendant bears some responsibility. <underscore>Lockheed Martin Corp. v. Network Solutions, Inc.</underscore>, 194 F.3d 980, 983 (9th Cir. 1999); <underscore>Fonovisa, Inc. v. Cherry Auction, Inc.</underscore>, 76 F.3d 259, 265 (9th Cir. 1996). Eleniak's approval was needed before CFRELI could do business as &#x201C;Re/Max All Cities Realty,&#x201D; suggesting that Eleniak either participated in the decision to use plaintiff's mark or was willfully blind to the infringement.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>3. Corporate and Agent Defendants</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">The Corporate and Agent Defendants seek dismissal because plaintiff purportedly fails to allege that they actually used plaintiff's mark in the course of their business. However, drawing all inferences in plaintiff's favor, <underscore>see Peloza v. Capistrano Unified Sch. Dist.</underscore>, 37 F.3d 517, 521 (9th Cir. 1994), the FAC adequately alleges that defendants conducted business using plaintiff's mark. Defendants also mistakenly characterize plaintiff's claims as seeking liability for vicarious trademark infringement. &#x201C;Plaintiff alleges direct infringement, not vicarious infringement.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Opp. to Hollymax Mot. at 14.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>4. Todd</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Plaintiff's allegations are sufficient to state a claim against Todd as the alter ego of Hollymax and Commbroker. Paragraphs 3, 13, and 14 of the FAC, if true, establish (1) a unity of ownership and interests and (2) &#x201C;improper corporate conduct by treating the company as the owners' personal fiefdom to the detriment of the creditors.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Opp. to Hollymax Mot. at 18.) These allegations are sufficient to create alter ego liability under California law. <underscore>See Sonora Diamond Corp. v. Superior Court</underscore>, 83 Cal. App. 4th 523, 538-39, 99 Cal. Rptr. 2d 824 (2000); <underscore>Arnold v. Browne</underscore>, 27 Cal. App. 3d 386, 394-95, 103 Cal. Rptr. 775 (1972).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Defendants' Replies</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Plaintiff fails to contest defendants' arguments with respect to Hollymax and Commbroker. Accordingly, the motion to dismiss should be granted as to the Corporate Defendants for lack of opposition. Similarly, the Court should dismiss plaintiff's claim for vicarious trademark infringement because plaintiff disclaims that cause of action in its opposition.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Plaintiff's contention that California Business and Professions Code &#167; 10159.2 and Title 10, &#167; 2725 of the California Code of Regulations encompass trademark infringement is based on an overbroad reading of the statutes. Ensuring compliance with state and federal trademark law lies outside the scope of the broker's responsibilities. Plaintiff argues, incorrectly, that <underscore>Holley</underscore> and <underscore>Valdez</underscore> expanded the broker's supervisory responsibilities to all state and federal laws. Both cases, however, dealt with the specifically-enumerated categories of activities for which the broker is liable; neither court expanded broker liability to all state and federal laws, or trademark law in particular. Moreover, plaintiff does not allege any failure to supervise, rendering &#167; 10159.2 inapplicable.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">Plaintiff's allegations are either too speculative, conclusory, or incomplete to state claims against the remaining defendants.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>IV. <underscore>LEGAL STANDARD</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">A Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6) motion tests the legal sufficiency of the claims in the complaint. <underscore>Navarro v. Block</underscore>, 250 F.3d 729, 732 (9th Cir. 2001). &#x201C;To survive a motion to dismiss, a complaint must contain sufficient factual matter, accepted as true, to&#x201D; state a facially plausible claim for relief. <underscore>Ashcroft v. Iqbal</underscore>, --- U.S. ---, 129 S. Ct. 1937, 1949, --- L. Ed. 2d --- (2009). &#x201C;A claim has facial plausibility when the plaintiff pleads factual content that allows the court to draw the reasonable inference that the defendant is liable for the misconduct alleged.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> Mere &#x201C;labels and conclusions&#x201D; or &#x201C;a formulaic recitation of the elements of a cause of action will not do.&#x201D; <underscore>Bell Atl. Corp. v. Twombly</underscore>, 550 U.S. 544, 555, 127 S. Ct. 1955, 167 L. Ed. 2d 929 (2007).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">In deciding the motion, &#x201C;[a]llegations of fact are taken as true and construed in the light most favorable to the plaintiff.&#x201D; <underscore>Nat'l Wildlife Fed'n v. Espy</underscore>, 45 F.3d 1337, 1340 (9th Cir. 1995). However, the court need not accept &#x201C;[t]hreadbare recitals of the elements of a cause of action, supported by mere conclusory statements.&#x201D; <underscore>Iqbal</underscore>, 129 S. Ct. at 1949.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>V. <underscore>DISCUSSION</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Hollymax</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Defendants seek dismissal of Hollymax because plaintiff purportedly fails to allege that Hollymax actually used the mark at issue.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Under the Trademark Act of 1946 (&#x201C;Lanham Act&#x201D;), &#x201C;[t]he holder of a registered mark<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> has a civil action against anyone employing an imitation of it in commerce when &#x2018;such use is likely to cause confusion, or to cause mistake, or to deceive.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>KP Permanent Make-Up, Inc. v. Lasting Impression I, Inc.</underscore>, 543 U.S. 111, 117, 125 S. Ct. 542, 160 L. Ed. 2d 440 (2004) (quoting 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1114(1)(a)); <underscore>see also</underscore> 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1125(a). Infringement claims under the Lanham Act &#x201C;are subject to a commercial use requirement,&#x201D; as defined in 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1127. <underscore>Bosley Med. Inst., Inc. v. Kremer</underscore>, 403 F.3d 672, 676 (9th Cir. 2005); <underscore>Karl Storz Endoscopy-Am., Inc. v. Surgical Techs., Inc.</underscore>, 285 F.3d 848, 853, 855 (9th Cir. 2002). That is, to state a claim for trademark infringement, plaintiff must allege, <ital>inter alia</ital>, that defendant &#x201C;is using a mark confusingly similar [to] its own,&#x201D; <underscore>GoTo.Com, Inc. v. Walt Disney Co.</underscore>, 202 F.3d 1199, 1205 (9th Cir. 2000), &#x201C;in connection with the sale, offering for sale, distribution, or advertising of any goods or services,&#x201D; 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1114(1)(a).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p30">&#8195;In their reply, the Hollymax Defendants also argue that dismissal is warranted because &#x201C;[n]owhere in its opposition brief does Plaintiff oppose Hollymax and Commbroker's motion.&#x201D; (Hollymax Defs.' Reply at 3.) Plaintiff mentions the Corporate Defendants only briefly, but it is enough to preclude granting defendants' motion for lack of opposition. (<underscore>See</underscore> Pl.'s Opp. to Hollymax Mot. at 13.)</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">As defendants observe, many of plaintiff's allegations are devoted to the actions of non-party CFRELI, (<underscore>see</underscore> Hollymax Defs.' Mot. at 16), which, according to the FAC, impermissibly adopted plaintiff's mark, initiated the marketing campaign using the mark, and created and owned the infringing websites through which many of the violations are alleged to have occurred, (FAC &#182;&#182; 18, 20, 25-26, 36-37). Hollymax's role in the alleged infringement is unclear. Plaintiff asserts, without elaboration, that Hollymax &#x201C;knowingly participated&#x201D; in the CFRELI marketing campaign, marketed itself using plaintiff's mark, and used plaintiff's mark in the &#x201C;actual conduct of real estate business.&#x201D; (FAC &#182;&#182; 20, 37, 40.) These allegations are &#x201C;devoid of further factual enhancement&#x201D; and, consequently, are not entitled to a presumption of truth. <underscore>Iqbal</underscore>, 129 S. Ct. at 1949, 1951 (internal quotation marks and citation omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">The remainder of plaintiff's allegations concerns the allegedly infringing websites, on which Hollymax appeared as an office or component of CFRELI. (<underscore>See</underscore> FAC &#182;&#182; 20, 22, 33, 36.) Plaintiff does not allege, however, that Hollymax is responsible for creating, maintaining, or operating the websites. Nor does plaintiff allege that Hollymax took part in creating its own &#x201C;integral page[] [on] the Re/Max All Cities Realty website.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 22.) Because plaintiff writes many of its allegations without identifying a responsible actor,<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> it is virtually impossible to assign responsibility for the alleged acts of infringement to any particular defendant. As the Court remarked previously, &#x201C;[a]side from conclusory allegations of lawbreaking, [plaintiff] does not allege that Defendants <ital>did</ital> anything at all.&#x201D; (Dec. 11, 2008 Ord. at 4 (emphasis in original).)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p33">&#8195;See, for example, paragraph 20 (&#x201C;Defendants Hollymax, Commbroker and all agents<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> were prominently featured as part of the Re/Max All Cities Realty websites.&#x201D;); paragraph 22 (&#x201C;The Defendant corporations<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> each had their own page on the Re/Max All Cities Realty website<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;); paragraph 33 (&#x201C;<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> Hollymax<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> appeared as [an] &#x2018;office[]&#x2019; of Re/Max All Cities Realty on the Re/Max All Cities Realty website<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;); paragraph 36 (&#x201C;At all times relevant to this action, the CFRELI Loans website using the domain name www.realestatelosangeles.com, advertised itself as &#x2018;Re/Max All Cities Realty&#x2019; under which Hollymax and Commbroker and all Defendant agents knowingly were integrated<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;); and paragraph 37 (&#x201C;Hollymax is being marketed under the All Cities Realty&#174; name<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Because plaintiff fails to adequately allege &#x201C;use&#x201D; within the meaning of the Lanham Act, the Court dismisses plaintiff's first claim for federal trademark infringement against Hollymax. Plaintiff's second claim for infringement under California law, third claim for California common law unfair competition, and fifth claim for unfair competition under California Business and Professions Code &#167;&#167; 17200, <ital>et seq.</ital>, are &#x201C;substantially congruent&#x201D; and are, therefore, ordered dismissed as to Hollymax on the same grounds.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> <underscore>Playboy Enters., Inc. v. Netscape Commc'ns Corp.</underscore>, 354 F.3d 1020, 1024 n.10 (9th Cir. 2004) (quoting <underscore>Denbicare U.S.A. Inc. v. Toys &#x201C;R&#x201D; Us, Inc.</underscore>, 84 F.3d 1143, 1152 (9th Cir. 1996)).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p35">&#8195;Plaintiff asserts a fourth claim against all defendants, including Hollymax, for vicarious trademark infringement, but appears to abandon this claim in its opposition. (<underscore>See</underscore> Pl.'s Opp. at 14 (&#x201C;Defendants<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> attempt to characterize the claims made by Plaintiff as &#x2018;vicarious trademark&#x2019; infringements. Nowhere in the complaint does Plaintiff use that term or even imply it. It is a fiction invented by Defendants for their convenience. As pointed out above, Plaintiff alleges direct infringement, not vicarious infringement.&#x201D;).)</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Todd</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Plaintiff claims that Todd is liable for the alleged acts of infringement as the alter ego of Hollymax and Commbroker. (FAC &#182;&#182; 13-14.) &#x201C;A claim against a defendant, based on the alter ego theory&#x201D; is not substantive in nature. <underscore>Hennessey's Tavern, Inc. v. Am. Air Filter Co.</underscore>, 204 Cal. App. 3d 1351, 1359, 251 Cal. Rptr. 859 (1988). Alter ego liability is &#x201C;derivative of the substantive cause of action against the corporate defendant.&#x201D; <underscore>Smith v. Simmons</underscore>, --- F. Supp. 2d ---, No. 1:05-CV-01187-OWW, 2009 WL 1883672, at *9 n.14 (E.D. Cal. June 23, 2009). Because plaintiff lacks a cognizable substantive claim against the Corporate Defendants, the derivative claims against Todd fail in the first instance.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p37">&#8195;The Court does not reach the sufficiency of plaintiff's alter ego allegations, but Hollymax Defendants' contentions on this issue deserve due consideration. <underscore>See Neilson v. Union Bank of Cal., N.A.</underscore>, 290 F. Supp. 2d 1101, 1116 (C.D. Cal. 2003) (&#x201C;Conclusory allegations of &#x2018;alter ego&#x2019; status are insufficient to state a claim. Rather, a plaintiff must allege specifically both of the elements of alter ego liability, as well as facts supporting each.&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="0">//</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="0">//</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="0">//</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Rife and Eleniak</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that Rife and Eleniak are &#x201C;vicariously responsible for the wrongs committed against Plaintiff&#x201D; by virtue of their status as the Corporate Defendants' brokers of record. (FAC &#182; 8.) To state a claim for vicarious trademark infringement, plaintiff must allege that defendant and the direct infringer have an actual or apparent partnership, possess &#x201C;the authority to bind one another in transactions with third parties, or exercise joint ownership or control over the infringing product&#x201D; or service. <underscore>Perfect 10, Inc. v. Visa Int'l Serv., Ass'n</underscore>, 494 F.3d 788, 807 (9th Cir. 2007) (citation and internal quotation marks omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">Plaintiff does not adequately allege the above requirements as to Rife and Eleniak. At paragraph 61, plaintiff alleges that:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p43" first-line="1" turnover="1">The individually named defendants herein exercised control over Plaintiff's service mark because, on information and belief, the individually named defendants in fact used Plaintiff's service mark in the conduct of their real estate business activities under the &#x2018;authority&#x2019; of Hollymax and Commbroker without Plaintiff's prior knowledge, permission or control.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p44" contd-flag="y">(FAC &#182; 61.) The Court assumes that Rife and Eleniak are included among the &#x201C;individually named defendants.&#x201D; Even so, this allegation, if true, establishes only that the &#x201C;individually named defendants&#x201D; used plaintiff's mark under the authority of the Corporate Defendants; it does not establish that Rife or Eleniak &#x201C;exercise[d] joint ownership or control&#x201D; over the mark with Hollymax or Commbroker. The allegation that defendant &#x201C;in fact used&#x201D; the mark at issue sounds in direct, not vicarious, infringement. Equating &#x201C;use&#x201D; with &#x201C;joint ownership or control&#x201D; conflates two distinct causes of action.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">Relying on California Business and Professions Code &#167; 10159.2 and a corresponding provision of the California Code of Regulations, plaintiff argues that Rife and, by extension, Eleniak, are &#x201C;personally responsible&#x201D; for the actions of the Corporate Defendants separate and apart from the federal requirements for vicarious trademark infringement. (Pl.'s Opp. to Hollymax Mot. at 10.) Plaintiff's argument is unpersuasive.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">California law prohibits any person from &#x201C;advertis[ing] or assum[ing] to act as a real estate broker<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> without first obtaining a real estate license from the [DRE].&#x201D; Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167; 10130. Corporate brokers must operate through a designated individual broker who is licensed by the DRE. <underscore>Holley</underscore>, 400 F.3d at 671. The designated broker, in turn, is</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p47" first-line="1" turnover="1">responsible for the supervision and control of the activities conducted on behalf of the corporation by its officers and employees as necessary to secure full compliance with the provisions of this division, including the supervision of salespersons licensed to the corporation in the performance of acts for which a real estate license is required.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p48" contd-flag="y">Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167; 10159.2(a). Section 10159.2 provides a basis for disciplinary sanctions against the individual broker, but &#x201C;[n]othing in the statutory scheme of the Real Estate Act, or the plain language of &#167; 10159.2, suggests that it creates a private right of action<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; <underscore>In re Grabau</underscore>, 151 B.R. 227, 232 (N.D. Cal. 1993). Although &#167; 10159.2 does not, by itself, create vicarious liability, <underscore>In re Grabau</underscore>, 151 B.R. at 232, a plaintiff may use &#167; 10159.2 in conjunction with agency principles to impose vicarious liability for certain acts, <underscore>see, e.g., Holley</underscore>, 400 F.3d at 673-74. Here, plaintiff's reliance on Rife's and Eleniak's designated broker status, without more, is insufficient to create vicarious liability.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">Moreover, plaintiff fails to allege any connection between the other defendants' alleged acts of infringement and the supervisory obligations of Rife and Eleniak under &#167; 10159.2. Contrary to plaintiff's contention, (<underscore>see</underscore> Pl.'s Opp. to Hollymax Mot. at 9), there is no indication that the scope of &#167; 10159.2 is unlimited. Designated brokers are responsible for ensuring &#x201C;full compliance&#x201D; with California real estate law, including reasonable supervision over the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p50" first-line="1" turnover="1">(a) Transactions requiring a real estate license.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p51" first-line="1" turnover="1">(b) Documents which may have a material effect upon the rights or obligations of a party to the transaction.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p52" first-line="1" turnover="1">(c) Filing, storage and maintenance of such documents.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p53" first-line="1" turnover="1">(d) The handling of trust funds.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p54" first-line="1" turnover="1">(e) Advertising of any service for which a license is required.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p55" first-line="1" turnover="1">(f) Familiarizing salespersons with the requirements of federal and state laws relating to the prohibition of discrimination.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p56" first-line="1" turnover="1">(g) Regular and consistent reports of licensed activities of salespersons.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p57" contd-flag="y">Cal. Code Regs. tit. 10, &#167; 2725. Plainly, compliance with state and federal trademark law is not listed among a broker's obligations. To the extent plaintiff argues that Rife and Eleniak are liable for activities in categories (a) and (e), the allegations of the FAC are too vague to determine whether defendants needed a license to advertise, market, and conduct unspecified &#x201C;real estate business.&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> FAC &#182;&#182; 36-41.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p58" level="1">Plaintiff's newly-minted claim for contributory trademark infringement and its factual basis<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> appear nowhere in the FAC and will not be considered here. <underscore>See Schneider v. Cal. Dep't of Corrections</underscore>, 151 F.3d 1194, 1197 (9th Cir. 1998).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p59">&#8195;Plaintiff alleges for the first time in its opposition that Eleniak was the designated broker for CFRELI and &#x201C;had final and sole discretion to either adopt the [trade] name, or prevent its use; the power of final approval was ultimately his personal decision and no one else.&#x201D; (Pl.'s Opp. to Eleniak Mot. at 2, 4 (citing FAC &#182; 18).) Plaintiff also seems to suggest that Eleniak must have participated in the alleged infringement because, under California law, Eleniak was required to approve any application to use &#x201C;Re/Max All Cities Realty&#x201D; as the fictitious business name listed on a real estate license. The FAC, however, states that the Corporate Defendants &#x201C;never obtained or [were] granted a real estate license under the &#x2018;Re/Max All Cities Realty&#x2019; or &#x2018;All Cities Realty&#x2019; names.&#x201D; (FAC &#182;&#182; 31-32.) Plaintiff's request for judicial notice in connection with this contention is denied.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p60" level="1">Accordingly, the Court dismisses all claims against Rife and Eleniak.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>D. Agent Defendants</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p61" level="1">Plaintiff's allegations of infringement against the Agent Defendants are substantially similar to the allegations against Hollymax. (<underscore>See, e.g.</underscore>, FAC &#182;&#182; 20-22.) As with Hollymax, the allegations are insufficient to show that the Agent Defendants used the mark at issue. Accordingly, the Court dismisses plaintiff's federal and &#x201C;substantially congruent&#x201D; state claims with respect to the Agent Defendants. <underscore>See Playboy</underscore>, 354 F.3d at 1024 n.10.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>E. Leave to Amend</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p62" level="1">Rule 15(a) of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure provides that &#x201C;leave [to amend pleadings] shall be freely given when justice so requires.&#x201D; The Court considers five factors in determining whether leave to amend is warranted: &#x201C;(1) bad faith, (2) undue delay, (3) prejudice to the opposing party, (4) futility of amendment; and (5) whether plaintiff has previously amended his complaint.&#x201D; <underscore>Allen v. City of Beverly Hills</underscore>, 911 F.2d 367, 373 (9th Cir. 1990). However, prejudice to the nonmovant is the &#x201C;touchstone of the inquiry.&#x201D; <underscore>Eminence Capital, LLC v. Aspeon, Inc.</underscore>, 316 F.3d 1048, 1052 (9th Cir. 2003) (quoting <underscore>Lone Star Ladies Inv. Club v. Schlotzsky's Inc.</underscore>, 238 F.3d 363, 368 (5th Cir. 2001)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p63" level="1">Because the foregoing factors weigh in favor of amendment, the Court grants plaintiff leave to file a second amended complaint. Defendants do not provide persuasive grounds for denying leave to amend and, more importantly, do not identify any prejudice they would suffer from the amendment.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>VI. <underscore>CONCLUSION</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p64" level="1">For the reasons stated above, the Court grants defendants' motion to dismiss the FAC. Plaintiff may file a Second Amended Complaint no later than November 3, 2009. Failure to do so will result in dismissal of the action.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p65" level="1">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p66" level="1">IT IS FURTHER ORDERED that the Clerk shall serve a copy of this Order on counsel for all parties in this action.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p67" level="1">DATED: October 20, 2009.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>