<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>FOR THE CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>DOREEN PARKER, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>IT'S A LAUGH PRODUCTIONS ET AL, Defendant.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line><bold>Case No. CV 09-02442 GAF (JCx)</bold></docket.line>
<docket.number><bold>CV 09-02442 GAF (JCx)</bold></docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-02442-GAF-JC</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 05/28/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">MEMORANDUM &#38; ORDER REGARDING PLAINTIFF'S MOTION TO REMAND</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">Judge Gary Allen Feess United States District Court</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. INTRODUCTION &#38; BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><underscore>A. <csc>Statement of Facts</csc></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Doreen Parker was a set painter on the Disney Channel hit show &#x201C;Jonas Brothers.&#x201D; (Compl. &#182; 13.) She was also a member of the Motion Picture Set Painters and Sign Writers Union, Local No. 729 (hereinafter referred to as &#x201C;Union&#x201D;).<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) According to Parker, after working for the Disney Channel for about a month-and-a-half, Parker's direct boss, Ken Lavelle, stopped her as she was returning from her lunch break and asked her to step outside with him. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 16.) Parker alleges that once outside, Lavelle advised Parker he was terminating her for using cocaine in the bathroom; he instructed her to vacate the premises immediately. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) &#x201C;Parker demanded to see an agent of Defendant It's A Laugh Productions as they were the set managers for the show and made the final decisions as to firing employees.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 17.) Parker was taken to see Pat Mahoney, who was the vice president of production at Hollywood Center Studios and oversaw the day-to-day operations of the lot. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 18; Motion at 5.) Mahoney, in the presence of Parker's co-workers, &#x201C;blatantly disclosed, once again, that Parker was being terminated because somebody had reported seeing [her] snorting cocaine in the bathroom.&#x201D; (Compl. &#182; 18.) Parker claims she was never asked to take a drug test, and no investigation of any sort was conducted into the false allegations of her drug use. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 20.) Parker herself immediately went to a local medical clinic to receive a full screening drug test, which came back negative for cocaine and all other drugs. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 22-23.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p2">&#8195;The Union is a branch of the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Technicians, Artists and Allied Crafts of the United States and is a &#x201C;labor organization&#x201D; as defined by the Labor Management Relations Act.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">In the aftermath of the events of her termination, Parker alleges she &#x201C;knew that the news of her termination had spread quickly because as she was walking back to the stage to get her belongings, less than an hour after being terminated, a number of people carne up to her to tell her that it was completely unfair how the Defendants had handled the situation.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 21.) Parker alleges she &#x201C;was completely humiliated and broken, and was suffering from severe anxiety over the fact that she no longer had a job, that all of her co-workers and friends thought she was a drug addict, and from wondering whether the defendants could possibly attempt to file drug charges against her.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 24.) Parker alleges her main medical provider prescribed her anxiety medication and advised her to go on disability. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) According to the complaint, &#x201C;[a]s a result of [her] termination, [Parker] has been unable to secure steady employment as her chosen profession of a set designer, has lost numerous union benefits and retirement compensation, has had her reputation blackened among her friends and co-workers, and has suffered severe emotional distress over the matter.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 26.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><underscore><csc><bold>B. Procedural History</bold></csc></underscore></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><ital><bold>1. The Complaint</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">In response to being labeled a drug-user and losing her job, Parker filed a lawsuit against: her former employers It's A Laugh Productions and Disney-ABC Television Group; Hollywood Center Studios, the venue at which she worked; Pat Mahoney, an employee of Hollywood Center Studios; and Does 1 through 50. The suit was filed on February 19, 2009 in Los Angeles County Superior Court and alleged the following state law claims against all defendants: (1) defamation/slander; (2) negligent infliction of emotional distress; (3) intentional infliction of emotional distress; (4) false light invasion of privacy; and (5) wrongful termination. Parker alleges Defendants are liable for defamation and slander because each of them &#x201C;orally published false and unprivileged statements concerning Parker&#x201D; when they publicly announced she was being terminated for using cocaine in the lot bathroom. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 28&#8211;29.) She claims negligent infliction of emotional distress based on the Defendants' breach of their duty &#x201C;[a]s Parker's employer,<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> not to wrongfully harm her reputation or abuse the employer-employee relationship.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182;&#182; 40&#8211;41.) She alleges Defendants intentionally inflicted her emotional distress by extreme and outrageous conduct &#x201C;not within the normal part of the employment relationship.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 49.) Parker complains, &#x201C;Defendants have invaded Parker's privacy and placed her in a false light by publishing statements<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> in front of Parker's co-workers and friends that she was using cocaine in the bathroom.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 54.) Finally, Parker brings suit for wrongful termination in violation of public policy, including allegations that &#x201C;Parker was placed in a hostile work environment where she was falsely accused of drug use thereby violating her constitutional rights.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 66.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><ital><bold>2. The Removal</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Defendants removed the case to federal court on the basis that the Labor Management Relations Act (&#x201C;LMRA&#x201D;), 29 U.S.C. &#167; 141 <underscore>et seq.</underscore>, wholly preempts all purported state law causes of action by an employee concerning a dispute over the terms and conditions of her employment if that employment is governed by a collective bargaining agreement (&#x201C;CBA&#x201D;). <underscore>See Firestone v. S. Cal. Gas Co.</underscore>, 281 F.3d 801, 802 (9th Cir. 2002). Pursuant to the &#x201C;artful pleading&#x201D; doctrine, a claim arises under and is governed by Section 301(a) of the LMRA if the nature of the claim depends upon or requires interpretation of a CBA, even if the plaintiff omits reference to the CBA in her complaint or purports to base her claims on state law. <underscore>See Lingle v. Norge Div. of Magic Chef, Inc.</underscore>, 486 U.S. 399, 405-06 (1988). However, &#x201C;[a] claim that requires only reference to the collective bargaining agreement, but no interpretation, is not preempted.&#x201D; <underscore>Firestone</underscore>, 281 F.3d at 802.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><underscore><csc><bold>C. Parker's Motion to Remand</bold></csc></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">Parker does not dispute that her employment with It's A Laugh Productions, Inc. was governed by the terms and conditions of the CBA, a/k/a the Basic Agreement (Not. of Removal, Ex. F), between It's A Laugh Productions, Inc. and the Union as well as a Local Agreement (<underscore>id.</underscore>, Ex. E). Instead, Parker bases her pending motion to remand on her contention that none of her state law tort claims require the interpretation of the CBA. Nonetheless, the CBA is extensive and covers drug and alcohol abuse as well as dispute resolution procedures. For example, Article XXXIII at page 90 of the CBA concerns an Employee Assistance Program for Drug and Alcohol Abuse. The provision states:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p7" first-line="1" turnover="1">An employee who has an alcohol or drug abuse problem which interferes with job performance or attendance will be disciplined in accordance with normal disciplinary procedures. In such cases, <ital><bold>before an employee is discharged</bold></ital> or disciplinary action is taken, the Producer will give advance notice to the applicable Local Union and will meet or confer with such Local Union representative. As a part of those procedures or as an alternative thereto, such an employee may be referred to counselling [sic] through a qualified employee assistance program.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p8" contd-flag="y">(<underscore>See</underscore> Not. of Removal, Ex. F [Basic Agreement] (emphasis added).) Article 7 of the Local Agreement governs grievance and arbitration procedure, and provides:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p9" first-line="1" turnover="1">In the event of any dispute between the Local Union or any of the persons subject to this Agreement and the Producer with regard to wage scales, hours of employment, or working conditions or with regard to the interpretation of this Agreement concerning such provisions, the procedure, unless otherwise specifically provided herein, shall be as follows<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill></paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p10" contd-flag="y">(<underscore>See</underscore> Not. of Removal, Ex. E [Local Agreement] at 4.) Parker made no mention of the CBA or the Local Agreement in her complaint.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Parker's motion to remand retreats from the broader allegations in her complaint and characterizes her claims as limited to the allegedly false accusations made by Mahoney after Parker claims she had already been terminated by Lavelle. (Mot. at 10.) But Defendants point out that if Parker's claims are in fact limited to the post-termination conduct of Mahoney, an employee of Hollywood Center Studios, Parker has no basis to pursue any claim against It's A Laugh Productions or Disney-ABC. (Opp. at 1-2.) Indeed, after receiving Parker's motion to remand, counsel for It's A Laugh Productions and Disney-ABC contends she contacted Parker's counsel to determine whether Parker would dismiss the two parties in light of her new representations. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) According to defense counsel, Parker's counsel never responded to her suggestion of dismissal. (Opp. at 2.) Parker's counsel has not filed a reply brief in this matter, and thus, again fails to respond to defense counsel's suggestion.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Whatever resolution the parties may reach on the subject, it has no impact on the Court's consideration of the pending motion. Parker cannot alter the allegations in her complaint to eliminate federal question jurisdiction. <underscore>Sparta Surgical Corp. v. National Assoc. of Secs. Dealers, Inc.</underscore>, 159 F.3d 1209, 1213 (9th Cir. 1998). Removal jurisdiction is determined by the complaint at the time of removal, without reference to subsequent amendments. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Accordingly, in the present context, the Court must examine the allegations in Parker's complaint and determine whether the LMRA preempts her state law claims.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><underscore><csc><bold>A. Removal Jurisdiction &#8211; The Well Pleaded Complaint Rule</bold></csc></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Like any other party asserting federal subject matter jurisdiction, Defendants who remove a suit to federal court have the burden of establishing that removal was proper. <underscore>Harris v. Provident Life and Accident Ins. Co.</underscore>, 26 F.3d 930, 932 (9th Cir. 1994). A suit may be removed to federal district court only if it could have been brought here originally. 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1441(a); <underscore>Caterpillar, Inc. v. Williams</underscore>, 482 U.S. 386, 392 (1987). Where a defendant removes on the basis of federal question jurisdiction, the Court analyzes the complaint under the &#x201C;well-pleaded complaint&#x201D; rule, which provides that federal jurisdiction ordinarily exists only when a federal question is presented on the face of the plaintiff's properly pleaded complaint. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><underscore><csc><bold>B. The Complete Preemption Doctrine</bold></csc></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">An exception to the literal application of this rule applies in cases where the subject matter of the complaint falls within an area where federal law occupies the entire field which gives rise to the complete preemption doctrine. Under the complete preemption doctrine, the preemptive force of a federal statute converts an ordinary state common-law complaint into one stating a federal claim for purposes of the well-pleaded complaint. <underscore>Caterpillar</underscore>, 482 U.S. at 393; <underscore>Jackson v. S. Cal. Gas Co.</underscore>, 881 F.2d 638, 641 (9th Cir. 1989). Section 301(a) of the LMRA, which establishes federal jurisdiction over &#x201C;suits for violation of contracts between an employer and a labor organization,&#x201D; 29 U.S.C. &#167; 185(a), gives rise to the complete preemption doctrine where a state claim requires interpretation or application of the terms of a collective bargaining agreement. <underscore>See Allis-Chalmers Corp. v. Lueck</underscore>, 471 U.S. 202, 209-10 (1985); <underscore>Burnside v. Kiewit Pacific Corp.</underscore>, 491 F.3d 1053, 1059-60 (9th Cir. 2007); see also <underscore>Franchise Tax Bd. v. Constr. Laborers Vacation Trust</underscore>, 463 U.S. 1, 23 (1983).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1"><underscore>Allis-Chalmers</underscore>, the leading case interpreting Section 301, held that a plaintiff could not escape the preemptive effect of Section 301 by casting his or her claim as a state tort cause of action instead of a breach of contract claim. 471 U.S. 202, 210. The Court further held that the key to determining the scope of preemption is not how the complaint is cast, but whether the claims can be resolved without referring to the terms of the CBA. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 213. &#x201C;Any other result would elevate form over substance and allow parties to evade the requirements of &#167; 301 by relabeling their contract claims as claims for tortious breach of contract.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 211. Thus, to determine whether this case is preempted under Section 301, the Court must first conduct</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="1" turnover="1">an inquiry into whether the asserted cause of action involves a right conferred upon an employee by virtue of state law, not by a CBA. If the right exists solely as a result of the CBA, then the claim is preempted, and [the Court's] analysis ends there. If, however, the right exists independently of the CBA, [the Court] must still consider whether it is nevertheless &#x2018;substantially dependent on analysis of a collective-bargaining agreement.&#x2019; If such dependence exists, then the claim is preempted by section 301; if not, then the claim can proceed under state law.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p17" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Burnside</underscore>, 491 F.3d at 1059-60 (citations omitted). To determine whether a right inheres in state law or is grounded in the CBA, the Court must consider the legal character of a claim, and not merely whether a grievance could be pursued under the CBA. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1060. To determine whether a state law right is &#x201C;substantially dependent&#x201D; on the terms of a CBA, the Court must decide whether the claim can be resolved by &#x201C;looking to&#x201D; the CBA rather than &#x201C;interpreting&#x201D; the CBA. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">Thus, with respect to this case, the removal is proper if, at the time the case was removed, Parker's complaint contained allegations which required the interpretation of, or depended upon the terms, of the CBA.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><underscore><csc><bold>C. Analysis of Parker's Claims</bold></csc></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Parker's claims are based on two separate allegations of wrongful conduct: termination and public accusations of drug use. The question of whether Parker's termination was wrongful is one that requires the examination and interpretation of the CBA. The question of whether Defendants violated state law by publicly accusing Parker of using drugs does not. Thus, under the above legal standards, Defendants' removal of this action was appropriate because Parker's wrongful termination claim &#8211; and the two emotional distress claims, to the extent they are premised upon it &#8211; are preempted by Section 301. However, Parker's defamation and invasion of privacy claims, which arise from the public accusations of drug use, and the two emotional distress claims &#8211; to the extent they are premised upon the accusations &#8211; are not preempted. The Court explains its reasoning below.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>1. <csc>Defamation</csc></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">The Court finds that Parker's defamation claim does not assert any rights which derive from the CBA or require interpretation of its terms. Defendants argue all of Parker's claims, including the defamation claim, arise from statements made during the course of her discharge and are thus preempted. The Court does not agree. Even if Lavelle's and Mahoney's accusations of drug use were made during the course of Parker's termination,<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> Mahoney's allegedly defamatory statements were not made to necessary parties and are not &#x201C;inextricably intertwined&#x201D; with termination procedures provided in the CBA. <underscore>See Busey v. P.W. Supermarkets, Inc.</underscore>, 368 F. Supp. 2d 1045, 1050-51 (N.D. Cal. 2005) (employee's state law claims against employer for defamation were not preempted by the LMRA because the allegedly false statements were not made in the course of a grievance proceeding specifically outlined by the CBA and did not require an interpretation of the CBA).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p21">&#8195;The parties disagree about whether Mahoney's statements were made during the course of Parker's termination or after Lavelle had finished her termination.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Only Lavelle's statement was made as a necessary part of Parker's termination, but his statement cannot be defamatory because it was not made in the presence of others. <underscore>See Ringler Assocs. Inc. v. Maryland Cas. Co.</underscore>, 80 Cal. App. 4th 1165, 1179 (2000) (explaining that defamation requires publication, which &#x201C;is defined as a communication to some third person who understands both the defamatory meaning of the statement and its application to the person to whom reference is made&#x201D;) A defamation action premised on Mahoney's statement, if it implicates Parker's discharge at all, implicates only the <ital><bold>manner</bold></ital> of the discharge, which is not covered by the CBA. <underscore>Farmer v. United Brotherhood</underscore>, 430 U.S. 290, 305 (1977); <underscore>Busey</underscore>, 368 F. Supp. 2d at 1052 (after reviewing the CBA, determining that &#x201C;interpretation of the CBA is required when an employee wishes to challenge the fact that he was discharged, rather than the manner in which he was discharged&#x201D;). Defendants have pointed the Court to no provision in the CBA or the Local Agreement that governs the manner in which employees are to be discharged. Parker's defamation claim is therefore not preempted because it does not depend on an interpretation of the CBA.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">The Ninth Circuit's opinion in <underscore>Tellez v. Pac. Gas and Elec. Co.</underscore>, 817 F.2d 536 (9th Cir. 1987), is instructive. In <underscore>Tellez</underscore>, an employer was alleged to have injured an employee by distributing a letter to eleven managers falsely accusing the employee of buying cocaine on the job and suspending the employee without pay for ten days. After the employer removed the case, the employee moved to remand, and the district court held the claims for defamation and negligent and intentional infliction of emotional distress were preempted by the LMRA. On appeal, the Ninth Circuit held the claims were not preempted because the employee's rights did not derive from the CBA and did not require interpretation of the CBA's terms. &#x201C;One can sue for defamation regardless of employment status or union membership.&#x201D; <underscore>Tellez</underscore>, 817 F.2d at 538. The court distinguished <underscore>Green v. Hughes Aircraft Co.</underscore>, 630 F. Supp. 423 (S.D. Cal. 1985), which held statements made in the context of disciplinary investigations are automatically preempted by Section 301, because in <underscore>Tellez</underscore>, like here, the defamatory statements were published &#x201C;beyond those who had a legitimate employment interest in them.&#x201D; <underscore>Tellez</underscore>, 817 F.2d at 538 n.3. Where the allegedly defamatory statement is not within a category of communications required by the CBA and is not made as a part of the grievance process, Section 301 does not preempt a defamation claim. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 538-39. With respect to the emotional distress claims, the Ninth Circuit held &#x201C;[t]he collective bargaining agreement does not envision such behavior, and its grievance mechanism is not equipped to redress it.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 539; <underscore>see Jackson</underscore>, 881 F.2d at 645-46 (the accusations were not made pursuant to any requirements of the disciplinary procedures and therefore the defamation claims did not implicate the CBA).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Similarly, Parker's defamation claims are not preempted because the allegedly defamatory statements were not made in the context of a disciplinary investigation or the grievance process, such as might require interpretation of the CBA. Here, Mahoney's statements were related to Parker's termination; however, they were not made as a formal part of the termination process and were published &#x201C;beyond those who had a legitimate employment interest in them.&#x201D; <underscore>See Tellez</underscore>, 817 F.2d at 538 n.3.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>2. <csc>False Light Invasion of Privacy</csc></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">The Court finds the invasion of privacy claim is premised on Defendants' accusations of drug use rather than on Parker's termination. Parker alleges &#x201C;Defendants have invaded her privacy and placed her in a false light by publishing statements<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> in front of Parker's co-workers and friends that she was using cocaine in the bathroom.&#x201D; (Compl. &#182;&#182; 28&#8211;29.) Defendants contend, as they do with respect to all of Parker's claims, that the statements at issue were made during the course of her discharge and propriety determinations are thus preempted by Section 301. For the same reasons that Parker's closely-related defamation claim is not preempted, namely, because it is unrelated to and does not require interpretation of the CBA, the Court finds Parker's invasion of privacy claim is an independent state claim not preempted by Section 301. <underscore>See Cortes v. Am. Stores Co.</underscore>, No. C97-4171 FMS, 1998 WL 61323, *6 (N.D. Cal. Feb. 4, 1998) (holding false light invasion of privacy claim was not preempted by the LMRA, where the plaintiff alleged management made false statements to unprivileged third parties that she was taking drugs, because no provisions of the CBA addressed such conduct); <underscore>Lawton v. United Parcel Serv., Inc.</underscore>, 338 F. Supp. 2d 347, 349 (D. Conn. 2004) (state law defamation and false light invasion of privacy claims not preempted by Section 301 of the LMRA because they did not require interpretation of a CBA).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>3. <csc>Wrongful Termination</csc></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">A wrongful termination claim is not preempted if it poses no significant threat to the collective bargaining process and furthers a state interest in protecting the public that transcends the employment relationship. <underscore>Young v. Anthony's Fish Grottos, Inc.</underscore>, 830 F.2d 993, 1001 (9th Cir. 1987). &#x201C;A claim is preempted, however, if it is not based on any genuine state public policy, or if it is bound up with interpretation of the collective bargaining agreement and furthers no state policy independent of the employment relationship.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> (citations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Parker argues her claim for wrongful termination in violation of public policy is based on her fundamental right to privacy under the California Constitution, which she contends includes being free from accusations of criminal conduct in the workplace. Parker, however, has failed to explain how her allegedly wrongful termination violated her privacy rights. Instead, as noted above, Defendant unambiguously contends that the allegedly defamatory statements &#8211; not her termination &#8211; violated her privacy. Thus, the Court finds Parker has failed to identify a relevant public policy of California that transcends her employment relationship.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">In these circumstances, Parker's employment relationship is governed by a CBA, which provides for mandatory grievance arbitration. (Not. of Removal, Ex. F at 279&#8211;86.) Therefore, Parker's state law theory of wrongful termination is preempted and is subject to re-characterization as a Section 301 claim for breach of the CBA. <underscore>Buscemi v. McDonnell Douglas Corp.</underscore>, 736 F.2d 1348, 1351 (9th Cir. 1984); <underscore>Fristoe v. Reynolds Metals Co.</underscore>, 615 F.2d 1209, 1212 (9th Cir. 1980). Because she is covered by a CBA, which requires mandatory arbitration of grievances, she may bring an action against her employers only if she shows she attempted to exhaust her arbitration remedies <ital><bold>and</bold></ital> shows that her union violated its fair representation duty in processing her grievance. <underscore>Vaca v. Sipes</underscore>, 386 U.S. 171, 184-86 (1967). Where the union meets its obligation of fair representation to an employee covered by a CBA, the employee's exclusive remedy for breach of that agreement is arbitration which is binding and final. <underscore>Id</underscore>. Because Parker's complaint fails to allege that the union breached its duty of fair representation,<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> the Court <bold>DISMISSES</bold> Parker's wrongful termination claim.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p29">&#8195;Parker's motion to remand argues that she did file a grievance with the Union; however, &#x201C;the retribution sought in that matter was not for the slanderous remarks but for the reason that the Defendants immediately brought in a replacement set designer without waiting one (1) day as is required by the CBA.&#x201D; (Mot. at 11.) Parker's complaint does not include allegations that she brought a grievance for wrongful termination, although the grievance letter she attaches to her motion states as much. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>, Ex. 3; Not. of Remov., Ex. G.) According to the grievance letters included with the notice of removal, the Union has already been involved in Parker's attempted resolution of her claims. On September 30, 2008, the Union demanded a grievance meeting with the executive producer of the &#x201C;Jonas Brothers&#x201D; television program to address what the Union characterized as wrongful termination, slander and harassment, and discrimination against Parker. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) On December 3, 2008, the Union reached an agreement with the television show and received a settlement check, which closed the grievance. (Notice of Removal, Ex. H.)</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>4. <csc>Emotional Distress</csc></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">In the context of claims for negligent and intentional infliction of emotional distress, courts have generally found that analysis of the CBA is necessary to resolve such a claim if the conduct which allegedly gave rise to the emotional distress is addressed by the CBA. <underscore>See Jackson</underscore>, 881 F.2d at 645-46 (finding emotional distress claims preempted because they were based on matters of discipline governed by the CBA). Thus, while emotional distress claims are often found to be preempted for this reason, the Ninth Circuit has clearly &#x201C;recognized that if a claim for intentional infliction of emotional distress arises from conduct not addressed by a [CBA], such a claim may not necessarily be preempted.&#x201D; <underscore>Milne Employees Assoc. v. Sun Carriers</underscore>, 960 F.2d 1401, 1412 (9th Cir.1991); <underscore>see Tellez</underscore>, 817 F.2d at 539; <underscore>Perugini v. Safeway</underscore>, 935 F.2d 1083, 1088-89 (9th Cir. 1991). Here, Parker's allegations of emotional distress arise from her wrongful termination claim <ital><bold>and</bold></ital> her defamation and invasion of privacy claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">To the extent Parker's claims of negligent and intentional infliction of emotional distress are based on wrongful termination, they are preempted. <underscore>Cook v. Lindsay Olive Growers</underscore>, 911 F.2d 233, 239-40 (9th Cir. 1990) (holding that employee's wrongful termination-based emotional distress claim was preempted because whether the employer's actions were outrageous for purposes of this claim depended on the interpretation of the CBA's provision for &#x201C;just cause&#x201D; discharge); <underscore>Chmiel v. Beverly Wilshire Hotel Co.</underscore>, 873 F.2d 1283, 1286 (9th Cir. 1989) (claim of intentional infliction of emotional distress resulting from the termination of employment cannot be decided without interpreting the terms of the CBA); <underscore>Young</underscore>, 830 F.2d at 1002; <underscore>Scott v. Machinists Auto. Trades</underscore>, 827 F.2d 589, 594 (9th Cir. 1987) (&#x201C;[S]tate tort claims for intentional infliction of emotional distress are preempted when they arise out of the employee's discharge or the conduct of the defendants in the investigatory proceedings leading up to the discharge.&#x201D;); <underscore>Buscemi</underscore>, 736 F.2d at 1352.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">However, to the extent Parker's emotional distress claims are premised on the accusations of drug use, they are not preempted. Since the Court has held that Parker's defamation and invasion of privacy claims, which are the underlying claims, are not preempted, neither are Parker's third and fourth claims for negligent and intentional infliction of emotional distress. <underscore>See Tellez</underscore>, 817 F.2d at 538-39 (holding Section 301 did not preempt an employee's claims for intentional infliction of emotional distress where the underlying claim for defamation was not preempted by Section 301).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><underscore><csc><bold>B. Failure to Conduct Conference of Counsel</bold></csc></underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">Parker failed to contact opposing counsel to discuss the substance of her motion to remand before filing it with the Court. <underscore>See</underscore> C.D. Cal. R. 7-3. The Court's local rules require that &#x201C;counsel contemplating the filing of any motion shall first contact opposing counsel to discuss thoroughly, preferably in person, the substance of the contemplated motion and any potential resolution.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> The purpose of the meet and confer requirement imposed by Local Rule 7-3 is to allow the parties to reach a more refined understanding of the issues before concluding a dispute cannot be resolved without the Court's intervention. The meet and confer requirement is intended to conserve judicial resources, as well as the parties' resources.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">For a &#x201C;meet and confer&#x201D; to be conducted in earnest, &#x201C;a live exchange of ideas and opinions is required.&#x201D; <underscore>Soto v. City of Concord</underscore>, 162 F.R.D. 603, 623 (N.D. Cal. 1995). Parker did not meet and confer regarding her motion to remand. Moreover, she did not file a reply brief. Thus, Parker has not responded in any way to It's A Laugh Productions' and Disney-ABC's suggestion that Parker's defamation, invasion of privacy, and emotional distress claims against the two employers are improper in the event that Parker intends to limit her claims to Mahoney's statements.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">Although the Court disposes of this case today by dismissing the wrongful termination claim and remanding the remaining claims, it advises the parties that a frank discussion may still save resources in this case.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">The Court finds Parker's wrongful termination claim is preempted by the LMRA and is <bold>DISMISSED WITHOUT PREJUDICE.</bold> Plaintiff has until June 25, 2009, to amend to attempt to state a claim under Section 301 of the LMRA. The remaining claims are independent state law causes of action, over which the Court has no independent jurisdiction. If Plaintiff files no amended complaint, the Court will dismiss the remaining claims without prejudice pursuant to 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1367(c). The hearing scheduled for Monday, June 1, 2009 is hereby <bold>VACATED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="0">DATED: May 28, 2009</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>