<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>HERMAN CLAVON, III, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>JAY PATEL, an individual dba AMERICAS BEST VALUE INNOXNARD/ PORT HUENEME, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 09-04947 DDP (CWx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-04947 DDP (CWx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-04947-DDP-CW</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 09/22/2010</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">ORDER DENYING DEFENDANTS' MOTION FOR SUMMARY JUDGMENT</headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center">[Motion filed on 8/4/2010]</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">DEAN D. PREGERSON United States District Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Presently before the court is Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment. After reviewing the parties' moving papers and hearing oral argument, the court denies the motion and adopts the following order.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">Plaintiff Herman Clavon III (&#x201C;Clavon&#x201D;) is an African-American male. (First Amended Complaint (&#x201C;FAC&#x201D;) &#182; 13.) He is disabled and requires the assistance of a service animal. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) The FAC states that Plaintiff &#x201C;is disabled within the meaning of and definition set forth in the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, 42 U.S.C. &#167; 1201, <ital>et seq.</ital>,&#x201D;. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) Clavon has no use of his right leg, suffers from shoulder injuries, and relies upon crutches or a wheelchair for mobility. (Declaration of Herman Clavon III In Support of Plaintiff's Opposition to Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment (&#x201C;Clavon Dec.&#x201D;) &#182; 1.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Clavon claims that he and his wife have &#x201C;often&#x201D; visited Ventura County and the central coast of California for the past thirty years. (Clavon Dec. &#182; 6.) Clavon knows many people in Los Angeles and Ventura counties. <underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 8. Because of his disability, Clavon is unable to walk on sandy beaches, but enjoys being near the beach. <underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 10.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that in November 2007 and on December 4, 2008, he was denied public accommodation at Defendants' hotel &#8211; the America's Best Value Inn Oxnard/Port Hueneme &#8211; &#x201C;because he is a minority and was then accompanied by a service animal.&#x201D; (FAC &#182; 15.) Clavon claims he was denied a room on six separate occasions. (Clavon Dec. &#182; 15.) The FAC also states that Defendants' hotel has &#x201C;refused and continue[s] to refuse to make reasonable modifications to their policies, practices and procedures in order to allow persons such as Plaintiff who are of African-American descent and are disabled to enter&#x201D; the establishment. (FAC &#182; 16.) Clavon claims that he has seen a white man with a dog at the hotel, and that the hotel has discriminated against Clavon because he is disabled and is African American. (Clavon Dec. &#182;&#182; 32, 43-44.) Clavon also claims to suffer from memory loss attributable to pain and inflammation medications. <underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 39.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Plaintiff filed the present action seeking damages, an injunction, and declaratory relief on July 10, 2009, and filed the FAC on September 30, 2009. The FAC alleges violations of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, 42 U.S.C. &#167; 2000, <ital>et seq.</ital>, the Americans with Disabilities Act, 42 U.S.C. &#167; 12101, <ital>et seq.</ital>, and California Civil Code &#167;&#167; 51, <ital>et seq.</ital>, 52, <ital>et seq.</ital>, and 54, <ital>et seq.</ital> Defendants now seek summary judgment or dismissing Clavon's complaint or, in the alternative, partial summary judgment on each of Clavon's claims.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. Legal Standard</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">A motion for summary judgment must be granted when &#x201C;the pleadings, depositions, answers to interrogatories, and admissions on file, together with the affidavits, if any, show that there is no genuine issue as to any material fact and that the moving party is entitled to a judgment as a matter of law.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c). A party seeking summary judgment bears the initial burden of informing the court of the basis for its motion and of identifying those portions of the pleadings and discovery responses that demonstrate the absence of a genuine issue of material fact. <underscore>See Celotex Corp. v. Catrett</underscore>, 477 U.S. 317, 323 (1986).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">Where the moving party will have the burden of proof on an issue at trial, the movant must affirmatively demonstrate that no reasonable trier of fact could find other than for the moving party. On an issue as to which the nonmoving party will have the burden of proof, however, the movant can prevail merely by pointing out that there is an absence of evidence to support the nonmoving party's case. <underscore>See id.</underscore> If the moving party meets its initial burden, the non-moving party must set forth, by affidavit or as otherwise provided in Rule 56, &#x201C;specific facts showing that there is a genuine issue for trial.&#x201D; <underscore>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc.</underscore>, 477 U.S. 242, 250 (1986).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">It is not the court's task &#x201C;to scour the record in search of a genuine issue of triable fact.&#x201D; <underscore>Keenan v. Allan</underscore>, 91 F.3d 1275, 1278 (9th Cir. 1996). Counsel have an obligation to lay out their support clearly. <underscore>Carmen v. San Francisco Sch. Dist.</underscore>, 237 F.3d 1026, 1031 (9th Cir. 2001). The court &#x201C;need not examine the entire file for evidence establishing a genuine issue of fact, where the evidence is not set forth in the opposition papers with adequate references so that it could conveniently be found.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. Discussion</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><underscore>A. Standing</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Defendants first assert that Clavon lacks standing to sue. (Motion for Summary Judgment (&#x201C;MSJ&#x201D;), Dkt. No. 34, at 7.) Specifically, Defendants argue that Clavon has not met his burden to demonstrate that he has suffered an actual or imminent injury. <underscore>See Lujan v. Defenders of Wildlife</underscore>, 504 U.S. 555, 560 (1992). &#x201C;In the context of a suit for injunctive relief, this requirement may only be satisfied where a plaintiff demonstrates a sufficient likelihood that he will again be wronged in a similar way.&#x201D; <underscore>D'Lil v. Best Western Encina Lodge &#38; Suites</underscore>, 538 F.3d 1031, 1036 (9th Cir. 2008). In an ADA case such as this one, a disabled person &#x201C;who is currently deterred from patronizing a public accommodation due to a defendant's failure to comply with the ADA has suffered &#x2018;actual injury.&#x2019; Similarly, a plaintiff who is threatened with harm in the future because of existing or imminently threatened non-compliance with the ADA suffers &#x2018;imminent injury.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore>, citing <underscore>Pickern v. Holiday Quality Foods, Inc.</underscore>, 293 F.3d 1133, 1138 (9th Cir. 2002).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Defendants argue that Clavon has not established a threat of immediate injury because he has no concrete plans to return to the hotel. Contrary to Defendants' argument, however, this case is not like <underscore>Molski v. Kahn Winery</underscore>, 405 F.Supp.2d 1160, 1164 (C.D. Cal. 2005), in which the court found that the plaintiff did not have a sincere, credible intent to return to the place of public accommodation. Clavon's case is more like <underscore>D'Lil</underscore>, where the Ninth Circuit held that an ADA plaintiff adequately established her intent to return to a hotel because the plaintiff had repeatedly visited the area, declared a fondness for the region, and expressed a desire to return to the hotel, but was prevented from doing so due to the defendants' conduct. <underscore>D'Lil</underscore>, 538 F.3d at 1038-39.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Here, Clavon declared that he had visited Ventura county for thirty years, that he had attempted to stay at Defendants' hotel six times, that he enjoys the Oxnard/Port Hueneme area, and that he &#x201C;want[s] to stay at defendants' Americas Best Value and [he] will when this Court orders that [he] will not be turned away.&#x201D; (Clavon Dec. &#182; 41.) As in <underscore>D'Lil</underscore>, the obvious and most reasonable inference to be drawn from Clavon's testimony is that he intends to return to the hotel. <underscore>See D'Lil</underscore>, 538 F.3d at 1038. Under such circumstances, ADA plaintiffs need not engage in the &#x201C;futile gesture&#x201D; of returning to an inaccessible location in order to establish standing. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1037.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Defandants seek to minimize Clavon's declaration by pointing to supposed contradictions between the declaration and Clavon's prior deposition testimony. <underscore>See</underscore> Defendants' Reply at 2. At his deposition, Clavon was unable to recall several details related to his claim. For example, Clavon stated that he did not know whether he had friends in Ventura County, and that it was possible that he had friends in Los Angeles County. (Declaration of Bret G. Anderson in Support of Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment, Exhibit T (&#x201C;Anderson Dec.&#x201D;) at 14-15. Clavon also stated that he had never been to the beach in Oxnard or Port Hueneme. (Supplemental Declaration of Bret G. Anderson, Exhibit A at 13).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">&#x201C;A party cannot create an issue of fact by an affidavit contradicting his prior deposition testimony.&#x201D; <underscore>Kennedy v. Allied Mut. Ins. Co.</underscore>, 952 F.2d 262, 266 (9th Cir. 1991). Before rejecting an affidavit that is at odds with earlier testimony, however, this court must find that a contradictory testimony is a sham, intended to create an issue of fact and avoid summary judgment. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 267. Here, the court is not convinced that Clavon's deposition testimony is a sham.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Though Clavon appears to have suffered from memory failures at his deposition, his later declaration does not directly conflict with his prior deposition testimony. For example, Clavon's assertion that he knows many people in Los Angeles and Ventura counties does not flatly contradict earlier statements, in which, in response to a question about his contacts in Oxnard or elsewhere in Ventura County, Clavon stated &#x201C;I don't know,&#x201D; and that Ventura County is a &#x201C;big county.&#x201D; (Anderson Dec. at 12.) Clavon's earlier testimony suggests a lack of knowledge of county and city boundaries, but does not necessarily evince an intent to dissemble or deceive. Though Clavon did testify that he did not visit the beach in Oxnard or Port Hueneme, his declaration explains that he is unable to walk on sand, and therefore tries to get as close to the beach as possible without visiting the beach itself. (Clavon Dec. &#182; 10.) Nor is Clavon's declaration of a desire and intent to stay at the hotel inconsistent with his prior testimony, in which Clavon stated that through this action, &#x201C;I hope that I will be able to be in [Defendants'] hotel without a problem&#x201D; as soon as these proceedings conclude. (Anderson Dec. at 168.) Because Clavon's declaration does not directly contradict, but rather helps explain, his earlier deposition testimony, the court is not persuaded that Clavon has provided sham testimony intended solely to defeat summary judgment.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p15">&#8195;Defendants also suggest that Clavon's prior litigation history casts doubt upon his sincerity and credibility, and ask this court to take judicial notice of several other ADA cases in which Clavon and/or counsel are involved. (MSJ at 6.) The Ninth Circuit has recognized, however, that &#x201C;[f]or the ADA to yield its promise of equal access for the disabled, it may indeed be necessary and desirable for committed individuals to bring serial litigation advancing the time when public accommodations will be compliant with the ADA.&#x201D; <underscore>Molski v. Evergreen Dynasty Corp.</underscore>, 500 F.3d 1047, 1062 (9th Cir. 2007). The Ninth Circuit has also cautioned that courts must be extremely careful in using past litigation history as the basis for an adverse credibility determination that would prevent a litigant from pursuing a valid claim. <underscore>D'Lil</underscore>, 538 F.3d at 1040. This court therefore does not find Clavon incredible or insincere.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><underscore>B. Discrimination claims</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Defendants alternatively move for partial summary judgment on each of Clavon's discrimination claims.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> Defendants contend that Clavon has not presented sufficient evidence that he was discriminated against on the basis of race or disability. MSJ at 12, 14.) Defendants' reply in support of their motion, however, focuses largely on the standing issue, devotes only one paragraph to arguing that Clavon has failed to make a prima facie case of racial discrimination, and makes no mention at all of Clavon's disability discrimination claim. (Reply at 9.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p17">&#8195;As discussed above, the FAC alleges violations of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, 42 U.S.C. &#167; 2000, <ital>et seq.</ital>, the Americans with Disabilities Act, 42 U.S.C. &#167; 12101, <ital>et seq.</ital>, and California Civil Code &#167;&#167; 51, <ital>et seq.</ital>, 52, <ital>et seq.</ital>, and 54, <ital>et seq.</ital></paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">To defeat a motion for summary judgment, a plaintiff alleging discrimination bears the burden to establish a prima facie case. That is, he &#x201C;must offer evidence that gives rise to an inference of unlawful discrimination.&#x201D; <underscore>Godwin v. Hunt Wesson, Inc.</underscore>, 150 F.3d 1217, 1220 (9th Cir. 1998) (internal quotation omitted). A prima facie case may be based on direct evidence of discriminatory intent or on a presumption based on factors the Supreme Court set out in <underscore>McDonnell Douglas Corp. v. Green</underscore>, 411 U.S. 792 (1973). Those factors, in the employment context, include whether the plaintiff is a minority, whether he applied for a job, and whether he was rejected for a position that remained open. <underscore>McDonnell Douglas</underscore>, 411 U.S. at 802. Courts have recognized that the <underscore>McDonnell Douglas</underscore> factors also apply in other discrimination cases. <underscore>See, e.g., Lindsey v. SLT Los Angeles, Inc.</underscore>, 447 F.3d 1138, 1144-45 (9th Cir. 2006) (applying <underscore>McDonnell Douglas</underscore> factors to 42 U.S.C. &#167; 1981 claim). The degree of proof required to make a prima facie case is &#x201C;minimal.&#x201D; <underscore>Godwin</underscore>, 150 F.3d at 1220.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Defendants argue that Clavon has not alleged facts sufficient to establish that he was denied access to the hotel on the basis of race, but do not dispute that Clavon has satisfied the <underscore>McDonnell Douglas</underscore> factors. Furthermore, Clavon has presented direct evidence of discriminatory intent. He was repeatedly denied a room because of his service dog. (Clavon Dec. &#167;&#167; 19, 20.) At other times, however, hotel staff told Clavon that dogs were allowed, and Clavon personally observed a white man with a dog inside the hotel. (Id. &#167; 33.) Clavon's evidence is sufficient to give rise to an inference of unlawful discrimination on the basis of race, disability, or both.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. Conclusion</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">For the reasons set forth above, Defendants' motion for summary judgment is DENIED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="0">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="0">Dated: September 22, 2010</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>