<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
<venue.name>WESTERN DIVISION</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>L.A. PRINTEX INDUSTRIES, INC. Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>G&#38;G MULTITEX, INC., et al., Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>CASE NO. CV 09-3812 ODW (RZx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-3812 ODW (RZx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-03812-ODW-RZ</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 09/13/2010</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">ORDER GRANTING PLAINTIFF'S MOTION FOR SUMMARY ADJUDICATION [39]</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">OTIS D. WRIGHT II UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. INTRODUCTORY BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Plaintiff L.A. Printex, Inc. (&#x201C;Plaintiff&#x201D; or &#x201C;L.A. Printex&#x201D;) brings this action for copyright infringement against G&#38;G Multitex, Inc. (&#x201C;Defendant&#x201D; or &#x201C;Multitex&#x201D;) (Mot. at 7.) Plaintiff alleges Defendant infringed a certain copyrighted design (&#x201C;Design&#x201D;) &#x201C;by sub-licensing it to a third party to create derivat[ive] works in the form of garments.&#x201D; (Id. at 10.) Plaintiff now moves for summary adjudication, essentially arguing that no genuine issue of material fact &#x201C;exists as to Plaintiff's ownership of the [ ] Design, or Defendant's infringement of the [ ] Design by sub-licensing it to a third party<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; (Id.) As Defendant does not contest L.A. Printex's ownership claim (<ital>see</ital> UF 16), the issue of ownership is deemed undisputed for purposes of this motion. The Court therefore turns to L.A. Printex's argument that Multitex infringed its Design.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">The following facts are largely undisputed, though the parties disagree on their legal significance. On September 12, 2006, Plaintiff purchased the rights to an original work of art titled &#x201C;MAE0600324&#x201D; from Blue Studio, a non-party European art studio. (UF 2.) &#x201C;A member of Plaintiff's design team, Jennifer Kwon, in the course and scope of her employment with Plaintiff, formatted and modified this artwork to create a design designated D40403 by Plaintiff [, which is the subject Design in this action.]&#x201D; (UF 4.) The Design was duly registered with the Copyright Office in late 2006. (UF 6.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Starting in January 2007, Plaintiff sold thousands of yards of fabric bearing the Design to customers. (UF 7.) Plaintiff subsequently discovered that garments with a fabric design identical or substantially similar to the Design were being sold by others. (UF 9.) The allegedly infringing garments had been manufactured by defendant &#x201C;Unger [Fabrik, LLC (&#x201C;Unger&#x201D;)] pursuant to an alleged sub-license from Multitex which purportedly allowed use of the Design.&#x201D; (UF 10.)<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p4">&#8195;Unger has been dismissed as a defendant from this action.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Multitex was one of L.A. Printex's customers. (UF 11.) In or about February 2007, L.A. Printex sold some sample fabrics to Multitex bearing the Design, which Multitex distributed to its customers to find out if they might be interested in purchasing the fabric. (Opp'n at 2) (citations omitted). In September 2007, Unger informed Multitex that it &#x201C;might need approximately 15,000 yards of fabric to be printed with the Design through a wet print process.&#x201D; (Id.) &#x201C;Because Multitex cannot perform a wet print process, and in order to reduce costs, Multitex and Unger discussed having the printing performed by another company overseas.&#x201D; (Id.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">Multitex's Vice President, Robert Ghodooshim, then contacted Daniel Jung at L.A. Printex and informed him that a Multitex customer was interested in having the Design printed overseas. (Opp'n at 2.) &#x201C;They [ ] negotiated the terms of the license, and the royalty rate was reduced to 10 cents a yard, as stated in an e-mail that Mr. Jung sent to Mr. Ghodooshim on or about September 21, 2007.&#x201D; (Id.) (citations omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">The e-mail Jung sent Ghodooshim states:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p8" first-line="1" turnover="1">Regarding the pattern you want to use [ ] in the other place for 15,000yds of rayon wet paint, we LA Printex allow it under royalty 10 cent per yard as request. [sic] This is limited quantity only, and both parties [have] to make contract for this. After you and LAP sign[] this contract, LAP will give you full repeat file on CD. I want your business getting bigger. [sic]</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p9" contd-flag="y">(Reply at 3 n.1.) A copy of the e-mail was sent to L.A. Printex employee, Joanne.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">A few days after the e-mail communication, Unger informed Multitex that its original estimate of 15,000 yards had now increased to 19,200 yards. (Ghodooshim Decl. &#182; 11.) Multitex revised the quantity from 15,000 to 19,200 yards and sent a purchase order to L.A. Printex stating the revised quantity and the royalty amount of 10 cents per yard. (Ghodooshim Decl., Exh. 2) (&#x201C;This is a royalty charge for pattern # 40403.&#x201D;) Defendant argues in its Opposition that &#x201C;[s]uch purchase orders are often referred to as &#x2018;contracts&#x2019; and it is common practice for payments to be made after an invoice is received, in order to identify the payment with an invoice number.&#x201D; (Opp'n at 3) (citation omitted). L.A. Printex is silent on the issue in its Reply.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">After receiving the purchase order from Multitex, an L.A. Printex employee (Joanne, as Multitex alleges) delivered to Multitex a CD containing a full repeat file of the Design, as proposed in the e-mail described above. (Opp'n at 3.) Multitex itself has not printed or otherwise produced any fabric or goods bearing the Design. Nor has Multitex authorized any person or entity, other than Unger, to use the Design. (Id. at 4.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">L.A. Printex contends &#x201C;Defendant concedes two very important facts in its opposition that prove as a matter of law that no license was ever effectuated. Without a license, any use of the [D]esign [ ] constituted infringement.&#x201D; (Reply at 2.) The two salient facts are: &#x201C;1. No signed contract exists confirming the license agreement, though such a contract was expressly required before a license could come into being. 2. Multitex never paid to Plaintiff any license fees; such as, even if a license had been granted, it would fail because no consideration was ever provided by Multitex.&#x201D; (Id.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><ital>1. Legal Standard</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Rule 56(c) requires summary judgment for the moving party when the evidence, viewed in the light most favorable to the nonmoving party, shows that there is no genuine issue as to any material fact, and that the moving party is entitled to judgment as a matter of law. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">The moving party bears the initial burden of establishing the absence of a genuine issue of material fact. <ital>Celotex Corp. v. Catrett</ital>, 477 U.S. 317, 323-24 (1986). That burden may be met by &#x201C;showing&#8211;that is, pointing out to the district court&#8211;that there is an absence of evidence to support the nonmoving party's case.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 325. Once the moving party has met its initial burden, Rule 56(e) requires the nonmoving party to go beyond the pleadings and identify specific facts that show a genuine issue for trial. <ital>Id.</ital> at 323-34; <ital>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc.</ital>, 477 U.S. 242, 248 (1968). &#x201C;[A] scintilla of evidence or evidence that is merely colorable or not significantly probative [] [does] not present a genuine issue of material fact.&#x201D; <ital>Addisu v. Fred Meyer</ital>, 198 F.3d 1130, 1134 (9th Cir. 2000). Only genuine disputes&#8211;where the evidence is such that a reasonable jury could return a verdict for the nonmoving party&#8211;over facts that might affect the outcome of the suit under the governing law will properly preclude the entry of summary judgment. <ital>Anderson</ital>, 477 U.S. at 248.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">It is not the task of the district court &#x201C;to scour the record in search of a genuine issue of triable fact. [Courts] rely on the nonmoving party to identify with reasonable particularity the evidence that precludes summary judgment.&#x201D; <ital>Keenan v. Allan</ital>, 91 F.3d 1275, 1279 (9th Cir. 1996). <ital>See also Carmen v. San Francisco Unified Sch. Dist.</ital>, 237 F.3d 1026, 1031 (9th Cir. 2001) (&#x201C;The district court need not examine the entire file for evidence establishing a genuine issue of fact, where the evidence is not set forth in the opposing papers with adequate references so that it could conveniently be found.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><ital>2. Plaintiff's Motion</ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">As L.A. Printex argues, Multitex must not only establish it had a license to use the Design from L.A. Printex, but also that it received express permission from L.A. Printex to sub-license the artwork to Unger. (Mot. at 12-13, 15.)</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><ital><bold>The License</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">&#x201C;The Copyright Act permits copyright holders to grant nonexclusive copyright licenses by implication.&#x201D; <ital>Foad Consulting Group, Inc. v. Azzalino</ital>, 270 F.3d 821, 831 (9th Cir. 2001). But whether a copyright holder has properly granted another a nonexclusive license by implication is a matter of state contract law, provided that the state law does not conflict with the Copyright Act or its underlying policies. <ital>Id.</ital> at 832.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">Plaintiff acknowledges &#x201C;the best [ ] Multitex can assert is that they hold a non-exclusive license, which does not need to be granted in writing and may be oral or implied from conduct.&#x201D; (Mot. at 13) (citing 3-10 Nimmer on Copyrights &#167; 10.03(7) (LexisNexis 2010)). Yet Plaintiff argues Defendant cannot establish such a license.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Plaintiff first contends the e-mail discussed above &#x201C;reflects a clear agreement that the license would only come into effect when a contract was signed by both parties.&#x201D; (Id. at 15) (citations omitted). Plaintiff adds that because no contract was signed by the parties, no license could be found. This argument fails for several reasons. Chiefly, as Plaintiff itself notes, &#x201C;it is a cornerstone of contract law that preliminary discussions regarding the terms of a contract do not create a contract.&#x201D; (Id. at 14.) In the context of this case, the email was not an agreement between the parties, as L.A. Printex would have it, but merely a physical confirmation of preliminary discussions. And, just as the quantity was modified from the 15,000 yards stated in the e-mail to the 19,200 stated in the purchase order, it is entirely possible that other provisions in the e-mail (like the writing requirement) were similarly modified before reaching final agreement. In any event, the purchase order satisfies the <ital>alleged</ital> writing requirement and, coupled with the parties' interactions, the Court finds that a license was created by the parties' course of conduct.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">After inquiring by telephone about obtaining a license, Multitex received an e-mail from L.A. Printex confirming the discussion. Multitex then sent L.A. Printex a purchase order stating the revised quantity (19,200 yards) and the royalty amount contemplated by the parties, as noted in the e-mail. Multitex contends, and L.A. Printex does not dispute that &#x201C;[s]uch purchase orders are often referred to as &#x2018;contracts&#x2019;<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; (Opp'n at 3) (citation omitted). While L.A. Printex remained silent on that issue, however, it spoke rather loudly when it delivered to Multitex the full repeat file after receiving Multitex's purchase order. This strongly suggests L.A. Printex agreed to the terms of the purchase order sent by Multitex. The Court therefore finds, from the totality of the circumstances, that L.A. Printex licensed Defendant's use of the 19,200 yards of fabric stated in the purchase order.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">L.A. Printex argues no license can arise from the parties' course of conduct because &#x201C;Multitex conceded that this was virtually the only time it could recall &#x2018;licensing&#x2019; a design from L.A. Printex. (Reply at 4.) L.A. Printex mistakes &#x201C;course of performance&#x201D; for &#x201C;course of dealing.&#x201D; The relevant inquiry here is not how the parties conducted themselves in prior business dealings, but how this particular transaction was handled. Thus, it is of no moment that this transaction was the parties' first. As relevant here, the circumstances surrounding the parties' first transaction reveal their operative agreement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Similarly faulty is Plaintiff's argument that the license fails for lack of consideration. While it is true Plaintiff has not received payment for licensing the Design, Multitex argues (without opposition) that &#x201C;it is common practice for payments to be made after an invoice is received&#x201D; (Opp'n at 3), and that L.A. Printex has yet to send Multitex an invoice. (Id. at 5.) In any event, the consideration that Multitex offered was its <ital>promise</ital> to pay royalty on the design, as provided in the purchase order. The fact that Multitex has yet to actually tender payment does not mean consideration was lacking in the first instance; it merely gives L.A. Printex a meritorious claim for breach of contract. In sum, the Court finds the parties reached agreement by way of the purchase order, which reflects some, but not all of the parties' prior discussions. The agreement was a license to use 19,200 yards of the Design.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><ital><bold>The Sub-license</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">As L.A. Printex argues, Multitex must next &#x201C;prove that it received express permission from L.A. Printex to sub-license the artwork to Unger.&#x201D; (Mot at 15.) The burden is on Multitex to secure L.A. Printex's express consent to the sub-license either during or after contract negotiations. <ital>Gardner v. Nike, Inc.</ital>, 279 F.3d 774, 781 (9th Cir. 2002) (&#x201C;[L]icensee has the burden of obtaining the licensor's consent before it may assign its rights, absent explicit contractual language to the contrary.&#x201D;). &#x201C;Placing the burden on the licensee assures that the licensor will be able to monitor the use of the copyright.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Here, Multitex offers no evidence whatsoever it was granted specific permission to sublicense the Design to Unger. Multitex's sole argument is that, because L.A. Printex knew Multitex could only engage in one kind of printing (not the wet printing associated with the Design), &#x201C;it had to know that Multitex would be sub-licensing the [D]esign to a third party, and thus implicitly authorized this sub-licensing.&#x201D; (Reply at 4.) The consent necessary to properly effectuate a sub-license must be express or explicit, however, not loosely implied from the circumstances. <ital>See, e.g., Miller v. Glenn Miller Productions, Inc.</ital>, 454 F.3d 975, 988 (9th Cir. 2006) (&#x201C;It is well established in patent and copyright law that a patent or copyright licensee may not sub-license his licensed intellectual property rights without express permission from the licensor.&#x201D;) (citations omitted). Although the purchase order list Target as the &#x201C;end user,&#x201D; moreover, it nowhere identifies Unger as a sub-licensee.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Indeed, since Multitex never even revealed Unger's identity to L.A. Printex (Reply Exh. 11, Ghodooshim Decl. at 34), it cannot be said that L.A. Printex could have consented to Multitex sub-licensing the Design to Unger. Without knowing the identity of the sublicensee, after all, it is hard to imagine how Plaintiff could effectively monitor the use of its copyright. It is, however, &#x201C;easy to imagine the troublesome and potentially litigious situations that could arise from allowing the original licensor to be excluded from the negotiations with a sublicensee.&#x201D; <ital>Gardner</ital>, 279 F.3d at 781. This matter of course represents one such example of those problems that could arise when the licensor is excluded from negotiations concerning a sub-license.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">L.A. Printex licensed Multitex's use of 19,200 yards of fabric bearing the Design, but Multitex fails to raise a genuine issue that it had express consent from L.A. Printex authorizing the sub-license to Unger. Accordingly, Plaintiff's motion for summary adjudication is GRANTED as stated herein.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1"><bold>SO ORDERED</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">September 13, 2010</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>