<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><bold>CIVIL MINUTES &#8212; GENERAL</bold></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>Mellissa Withers, et al.</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>eHarmony, Inc.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 09-2266-GHK(RCx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-2266-GHK(RCx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-02266-GHK-RC</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 04/01/2010</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Jake Yerke, Deputy Clerk, ATTORNEYS PRESENT FOR PLAINTIFFS: None Present</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">None, Court Reporter, ATTORNEYS PRESENT FOR DEFENDANTS: None Present</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1"><bold>DOCKET ENTRY</bold></attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>PROCEEDINGS: (IN CHAMBERS) ORDER GRANTING, IN PART, AND DENYING, IN PART, PLAINTIFFS' MOTION TO COMPEL AMENDED RULE 26 DISCLOSURES AND FURTHER RESPONSE TO INTERROGATORY NO. 13</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1"><bold>HON. ROSALYN M. CHAPMAN, UNITED STATES MAGISTRATE JUDGE</bold></judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">On March 17, 2010, plaintiffs filed a notice of motion to compel amended Rule 26 disclosures and further response to Interrogatory no. 13, a joint stipulation and the supporting declarations of Michael D. McLachlan with exhibits and Kiley L. Grombacher with exhibit, and defendant filed the opposing declaration of James P. Fogelman with exhibit. On March 24, 2010, plaintiffs filed their supplemental memorandum. This matter is decided in Chambers without oral argument, pursuant to Local Rule 7-15.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>DISCUSSION I</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">The defendant initially served plaintiffs with its Rule 26(a) disclosures on June 16, 2009, and those disclosures identified only two witnesses: plaintiff Mellissa Withers and Patrick Giordani, Director of Matching. Declaration of Michael D. McLachlan (&#x201C;McLachlan Decl.&#x201D;) &#182; 2, Exh. B; Declaration of James P. Fogelman (&#x201C;Fogelman Decl.&#x201D;) &#182; 2. On July 1, 2009, defendant served plaintiffs with its first amended Rule 26(a) disclosures, adding two additional witnesses, both of whom are defendant's employees: Suzanne Nagel, Senior Director of Marketing, and Ella Grutman, Director, Risk Management and Office of the President. McLachlan Decl. &#182; 4, Exh. D; Fogelman Decl. &#182; 2. On January 29, 2010, defendant served plaintiffs with its second amended Rule 26(a) disclosures, which identified 31 new witnesses, including 26 individuals who are or were employed by defendant, intervenor plaintiff Peter Schmidt, and plaintiff Mellissa Withers's boyfriend, mother, sister and neighbor. McLachlan Decl. &#182; 5, Exh. E; Fogelman Decl. &#182; 2. Finally, on March 15, 2010, defendant served plaintiffs with its third amended Rule 26(a) disclosures, which added defendant's employee Chak Din, Senior Data Analyst in the Business Analytics Department, to the list of witnesses. Fogelman Decl. &#182; 2, Exh. A.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(a) requires that, within 14 days after the Rule 26(f) conference, &#x201C;a party must, without awaiting a discovery request, provide to the other parties: [&#182;] (i) the name and, if known, the address and telephone number of each individual likely to have discoverable information &#8212; along with <bold>the subjects of that information</bold> &#8212; that the disclosing party may use to support its claims or defenses, unless the use would be solely for impeachment<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 26(a)(1) (emphasis added). These initial disclosures must be based on the information &#x201C;reasonably available&#x201D; to the party at the time of the Rule 26(f) conference. Thereafter, Rule 26(e) imposes a continuing duty to &#x201C;supplement or correct&#x201D; the Rule 26(a) disclosures:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p4" first-line="1" turnover="1">in a timely manner if the party learns that in some material respect the disclosure<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> is incomplete or incorrect, and if the additional or corrective information has not otherwise been made known to the other parties during the discovery process<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill></paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p5" contd-flag="y">Rule 26(e)(1)(A).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">Several courts have noted that &#x201C;guidance as to the adequacy of the disclosures must be gleaned from Rule 26(a)'s purpose: to &#x2018;accelerate the exchange of basic information&#x2019; that is &#x2018;needed in most cases to prepare for trial or make an informed decision about settlement.&#x2019; Moreover, early disclosure also functions to assist the parties in focusing and prioritizing their organization of discovery.&#x201D; <underscore>City and County of San Francisco v. Tutor-Saliba Corp.</underscore>, 218 F.R.D. 219, 221 (N.D. Cal. 2003); <underscore>Sender v. Mann</underscore>, 225 F.R.D. 645, 650 (D. Colo. 2004); <underscore>see also Kullman v. New York</underscore>, 2009 WL 1562840, *5 (N.D. N.Y. 2009) (&#x201C;A primary purpose of the requirements for initial disclosure of witnesses and supplementation is to afford notice to opposing parties at the earliest possible time so that opposing parties may prepare to defend against such testimony by, for example, taking the depositions of such witnesses.&#x201D;) (citation omitted)). &#x201C;Initial disclosures should provide the parties &#x2018;with information essential to the proper litigation of all relevant facts, to eliminat[e] surprise, and to promot[e] settlement.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Sender</underscore>, 225 F.R.D. at 650.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">&#x201C;[T]he Rule 26(a)(1) disclosure requirements should &#x2018;be applied with common sense in light of the principles of Rule 1, keeping in mind the salutary purposes that the rule is intended to accomplish. The litigants should not indulge in gamesmanship with respect to the disclosure obligations.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Sender</underscore>, 225 F.R.D. at 650. &#x201C;To that end, initial disclosures should be &#x2018;complete and detailed,&#x2019; and should &#x2018;give the opposing party information as to the identification and location of persons with knowledge so that they can be contacted in connection with the litigation.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> (citations omitted). &#x201C;&#x2018;Indicating briefly the general topics on which such persons have information should not be burdensome, and will assist other parties in deciding which depositions will actually be needed.&#x2019; <underscore>See</underscore> Advisory Committee Notes on the 1993 Amendments to Fed. R. Civ. P. 26(a).&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">The plaintiffs complain about defendant's disclosures of 19 witnesses listed in its second amended Rule 26(a) disclosures, stating:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p9" first-line="1" turnover="1">Nine of these witnesses share the identical designation: &#x201C;Matters pertaining to eHarmony's [Singles Service].&#x201D; Seven others are all listed as having knowledge of &#x201C;Matters pertaining to eHarmony's website eHamony.com [sic].&#x201D; Three of these witnesses are each identified with: &#x201C;Matters pertaining to eHarmony's marketing and advertising of its Singles Service.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p10" contd-flag="y">Jt. Stip. at 11:1-5.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> In response, defendant argues, first, that under Rule 26(e)(1)(A), it has no obligation to supplement its initial disclosures because &#x201C;plaintiffs are fully aware of the information they claim is lacking in [defendant's] [Rule] 26(a) disclosures.&#x201D; Jt. Stip. at 17:28-18:14, 20:25-21:19. Second, defendant asserts that its disclosures are more than adequate since they state the &#x201C;general topics&#x201D; on which each witness has information. Jt. Stip. at 21:21-22:12; <underscore>see also</underscore> Jt. Stip. at 22:16-17 (&#x201C;The descriptions as stated give the Plaintiffs clear insight as to the general content of the discoverable information.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p11">&#8195;The Court infers plaintiffs' complaint does not include the other seven witnesses employed by defendant who are listed in the second amended disclosures.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Here, defendant's disclosures range from a broad or general description of the &#x201C;subjects of th[e] information&#x201D; some witnesses have, <underscore>see</underscore>, e.g., Bob Holden, Vice President in the Singles Product Department (information about &#x201C;[m]atters pertaining to eHarmony's website eHarmony.com&#x201D;), to a more narrow or detailed description of the &#x201C;subjects of th[e] information&#x201D; other witnesses have. <underscore>See</underscore>, e.g., Patricia Wood, Director of Quality Assurance and Consistency in the Consumer Care Department (information about &#x201C;[m]atters pertaining to eHarmony's customer relations, including its communications with customers, and the Frequently Asked Questions posted on the website eHarmony.com&#x201D;). McLachlan Decl. &#182; 5, Exh. A at 18. Yet, Rule 26(a)(1) initial disclosures are to give notice to the other party of witnesses whom the disclosing party &#x201C;may use to support its claims or defenses<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 26(a)(1); <underscore>see also</underscore> Advisory Committee Notes to 2000 Amendment to Rule 26(a)(1) (&#x201C;A party is no longer obligated to disclose witnesses<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> whether favorable or unfavorable, that it does not intend to use.&#x201D;). Although defendant's description of the informational &#x201C;subjects&#x201D; of Patricia Wood's knowledge clearly advises plaintiffs of the possible topics of any testimony by Ms. Woods, the same cannot be said of defendant's description of Bob Holden's informational &#x201C;subjects.&#x201D; In short, defendant has not provided plaintiffs with enough details for them to determine whether to depose Mr. Holden about his knowledge or information. Thus, the Court finds defendant has not met the requirements of Rule 26(a)(1) regarding Mr. Holden and all other witnesses whose informational &#x201C;subjects&#x201D; are broadly described as either &#x201C;[m]atters pertaining to eHarmony's website eHarmony.com&#x201D; or &#x201C;[m]atters pertaining to eHarmony's [Singles Service].&#x201D; On the other hand, the Court finds defendant's description of some witnesses' &#x201C;subjects&#x201D; as &#x201C;[m]atters pertaining to eHarmony's marketing and advertising of its Singles Service&#x201D; is specific enough to comply with Rule 26(a)(1). Since defendant has now had sufficient time to conduct a reasonable inquiry into the informational &#x201C;subjects&#x201D; of the witnesses identified in the second amended Rule 26(a) disclosures, it should not burden defendant to supplement those disclosures to provide more detail about the informational &#x201C;subjects&#x201D; for the witness described above. Thus, plaintiffs' motion to compel defendant's further amendment of the Rule 26(a)(1) disclosures <bold>is granted</bold>, in part.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">On October 26, 2009, defendant served its initial responses to plaintiffs' first set of request for production of documents, and based on defendant's responses, plaintiffs propounded Interrogatory no. 13 to defendant. McLachlan Decl. &#182;&#182; 8-9, Exhs. G-H. Interrogatory nos. 13 asks the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p14" first-line="1" turnover="1">For each [of the 25] person[s] identified in YOUR responses to Plaintiff's request for Production of Documents, Set 1, including without limitation page 4, lines 21 through 28, please:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" first-line="2" turnover="hanging">(a) State the group or department that person currently works in, or most recently worked in if he or she is no longer employed by YOU;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="2" turnover="hanging">(b) State the person's current job title, or the job title he or she had when last employed by YOU;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" first-line="2" turnover="hanging">(c) Summarize that person's current job duties or his or her job duties when last employed by YOU;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" first-line="2" turnover="hanging">(d) IDENTIFY that person's immediate supervisor at present, or if such person is no longer employed by YOU, the immediate supervisor on the date that person was last employed by YOU;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" first-line="2" turnover="hanging">(e) IDENTIFY that person's predecessor in the job title or position identified in 1(b) above;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" first-line="2" turnover="hanging">(f) State the length of time that person has held his or her current job title, or if no longer employed by YOU, the length of time he or she held the last job title;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" first-line="2" turnover="hanging">(g) State whether that person has signed a confidentiality agreement in conjunction with his or her employment by YOU; [and]</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" first-line="2" turnover="hanging">(h) Describe the work that person performed, if any, in responding to Plaintiff's document requests in this lawsuit (Sets 1 through 4), including without limitation IDENTIFYING the DOCUMENTS YOU produced that he or she helped prepare.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p23" contd-flag="y">McLachlan Decl. &#182; 9, Exh. H at 12. In response to Interrogatory no. 13, defendant set forth 13 General Objections, including General Objection no. 1, which objected to the interrogatories &#x201C;on the ground that they are compound and exceed the number of interrogatories permitted under the Rules of Civil Procedure.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 2. Additionally, defendant specifically objected to Interrogatory no. 13 on the grounds it &#x201C;is compound, vague and ambiguous, overbroad, and calls for information that is not relevant nor likely to lead to the discovery of admissible information.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 13. Despite these objections, defendant provided the name of the group or department in which each of the 25 individuals works (subquestion (a)), the job title for some of the individuals (subquestion (b)), and noted one person was &#x201C;no longer with the company.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 13-14.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Clearly, Interrogatory no. 13 is a compound interrogatory<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> &#8212; and even plaintiffs do not dispute that. First, Interrogatory no. 13 seeks information about <bold>25</bold> named individuals! <underscore>Trevino</underscore>, 232 F.R.D. at 614. Second, as to each of the 25 named individuals, Interrogatory no. 13 has at least seven &#x201C;discrete subparts&#x201D; asking for information regarding: job title/department; duties; immediate supervisor; predecessor; length of employment; existence of confidentiality agreement; and description of work and identifying documents each named individual prepared. <underscore>Id.</underscore>; <underscore>Safeco of Am.</underscore>, 181 F.R.D. at 445-48; <underscore>cf. Banks v. Office of the Senate Sergeant-At-Arms</underscore>, 222 F.R.D. 7, 10 (D. D.C. 2004) (An &#x201C;obvious example&#x201D; of a discrete subpart &#x201C;is the combining in a single interrogatory of a demand for information and a demand for the documents that pertain to that event. Clearly, these are two distinct demands because knowing that an event occurred is entirely different from learning about the documents that evidence it occurred. Thus, a demand for information about a certain event and for the documents about it should be counted as two separate interrogatories.&#x201D;). Thus, the Court sustains defendant's &#x201C;compound&#x201D; objection to Interrogatory no. 13, and <bold>denies</bold> plaintiffs' motion to compel further response to it.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p25">&#8195;Since defendant made the &#x201C;compound&#x201D; objection in response to Interrogatory no. 13, as well as in its General Objections, the Court need not address plaintiffs' argument that the Court should not consider defendant's improper General Objections. Moreover, as a compound interrogatory, Interrogatory no. 13 also violates Rule 33(a), which prohibits a party from serving &#x201C;more than 25 written interrogatories, including all discrete subparts.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 33(a). &#x201C;Although the term &#x2018;discrete subparts&#x2019; does not have a precise meaning, courts generally agree that &#x2018;interrogatory subparts are to be counted as one interrogatory<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> if they are logically or factually subsumed within and necessarily related to the primary question.&#x2019;&#x201D; <underscore>Trevino v. ACB Am., Inc.</underscore>, 232 F.R.D. 612, 614 (N.D. Cal. 2006) (citations omitted); <underscore>Safeco of Am. v. Rawstron</underscore>, 181 F.R.D. 441, 445 (C.D. Cal. 1998).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">1. Plaintiffs' motion to compel amended Rule 26(a) disclosures <bold>IS GRANTED</bold>, in part, and defendant shall, within 14 days of the date of this Order, supplement its second amended disclosures to restate the &#x201C;subjects of th[e] information&#x201D; for those individuals whom defendant currently states have information regarding: &#x201C;Matters pertaining to eHarmony's website eHarmony.com&#x201D; and &#x201C;[m]atters pertaining to eHarmony's [Singles Service].&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">2. Plaintiffs' motion to compel further response to Interrogatory no. 13 <bold>IS DENIED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Initials of Deputy Clerk_JY_</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>