<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><bold>CIVIL MINUTES &#8212; GENERAL</bold></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>ANGELA C. ANDRADE</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>US BANK NATIONAL ASSOCIATION</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 09-2706 CAS (JCx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-2706 CAS (JCx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-02706-CAS-JC</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 06/15/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">CATHERINE JEANG, Deputy Clerk, Attorneys Present For Plaintiffs: Gary Starre</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">LAURA ELIAS, Court Reporter / Recorder, Attorneys Present For Defendants: Valerie Brennan</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">N/A, Tape No.</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Proceedings: DEFENDANT'S MOTION TO DISMISS</bold> (filed 04/24/09)</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">The Honorable CHRISTINA A. SNYDER</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. INTRODUCTION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">On March 18, 2009, plaintiff Angela C. Andrade filed a first amended complaint against defendants US Bank National Association (&#x201C;US Bank&#x201D;) and Does 1 to 100 in Los Angeles County Superior Court alleging claims for (1) breach of contract; (2) promissory estoppel; (3) violations of the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (&#x201C;RESPA&#x201D;); (4) violations of the Federal Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (&#x201C;FDCPA&#x201D;); (5) violations of the California Robbins-Rosenthal Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (&#x201C;RFDCPA&#x201D;); (6) to set aside a trustee's sale based on defective notice; (7) to set aside a trustee's sale based on lack of authority to enforce the security instrument; (8) cancellation of trustee's deed; (9) cancellation of deed of trust; and (10) injunctive relief. On April 20, 2009, defendant US Bank removed this action to this Court on the basis of federal question jurisdiction.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On April 24, 2009, defendant US Bank filed the instant motion to dismiss plaintiff's claims. On May 29, 2009, plaintiff filed her opposition. On June 8, 2009, defendant filed its reply. A hearing was held on June 15, 2009. After carefully considering the parties' arguments, the Court finds and concludes and follows.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">This case arises out of the foreclosure of plaintiff's property located at 6943 Whitaker Avenue, Van Nuys, California. Plaintiff obtained a mortgage loan from Fremont Investment &#38; Loan in the amount of $750,000, which was secured by a deed of trust encumbering the subject property. The deed of trust, recorded on October 11, 2005, identifies Fremont Investment &#38; Loan as the lender, Mortgage Electronic Registration Systems, Inc. as the beneficiary, and Fremont General Credit Corporation as the trustee. Plaintiff failed to make all of the payments on her loan and on or about May 8, 2007, a notice of default was recorded. The notice of default indicated that as of May 7, 2007, plaintiff was $49,489.99 in arrears on her loan.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">On or about June 15, 2007, an assignment of deed of trust was recorded with the Los Angeles County Recorder's Office and all beneficial interest was transferred to US Bank. On or about June 25, 2007, a substitution of trustee was recorded with the Los Angeles County Recorder's Office substituting NDEx West, LLC as trustee. A notice of trustee's sale was recorded with the Los Angeles County Recorder's Office on August 24, 2007, and February 8, 2008. Plaintiff failed to reinstate the loan and the property was sold at a trustee's sale. A trustee's deed upon sale was recorded on or about October 16, 2008.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. LEGAL STANDARD</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">A Rule 12(b)(6) motion tests the legal sufficiency of the claims asserted in a complaint. &#x201C;While a complaint attacked by a Rule 12(b)(6) motion to dismiss does not need detailed factual allegations, a plaintiff's obligation to provide the &#x2018;grounds&#x2019; of his &#x2018;entitlement to relief&#x2019; requires more than labels and conclusions, and a formulaic recitation of the elements of a cause of action will not do.&#x201D; <underscore>Bell Atlantic Corp. v. Twombly</underscore>, 127 S. Ct. 1955, 1964-65 (2007). &#x201C;[F]actual allegations must be enough to raise a right to relief above the speculative level.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1965.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">In considering a motion pursuant to Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(b)(6), a court must accept as true all material allegations in the complaint, as well as all reasonable inferences to be drawn from them. <underscore>Pareto v. F.D.I.C.</underscore>, 139 F.3d 696, 699 (9th Cir. 1998). The complaint must be read in the light most favorable to the nonmoving party. <underscore>Sprewell v. Golden State Warriors</underscore>, 266 F.3d 979, 988 (9th Cir. 2001); <underscore>Parks Sch. of Bus., Inc. v. Symington</underscore>, 51 F.3d 1480, 1484 (9th Cir. 1995). However, a court need not accept as true unreasonable inferences or conclusory legal allegations cast in the form of factual allegations. <underscore>Sprewell</underscore>, 266 F.3d at 988; <underscore>W. Mining Council v. Watt</underscore>, 643 F.2d 618, 624 (9th Cir. 1981).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">Dismissal pursuant to Rule 12(b)(6) is proper only where there is either a &#x201C;lack of a cognizable legal theory or the absence of sufficient facts alleged under a cognizable legal theory.&#x201D; <underscore>Balistreri v. Pacifica Police Dept.</underscore>, 901 F.2d 696, 699 (9th Cir. 1990).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Furthermore, unless a court converts a Rule 12(b)(6) motion into a motion for summary judgment, a court cannot consider material outside of the complaint (<underscore>e.g.</underscore>, facts presented in briefs, affidavits, or discovery materials). <underscore>In re American Cont'l Corp./Lincoln Sav. &#38; Loan Sec. Litig.</underscore>, 102 F.3d 1524, 1537 (9th Cir. 1996), <underscore>rev'd on other grounds sub nom Lexecon, Inc. v. Milberg Weiss Bershad Hynes &#38; Lerach</underscore>, 523 U.S. 26 (1998). A court may, however, consider exhibits submitted with or alleged in the complaint and matters that may be judicially noticed pursuant to Federal Rule of Evidence 201. <underscore>In re Silicon Graphics Inc. Sec. Litig.</underscore>, 183 F.3d 970, 986 (9th Cir. 1999); <underscore>Lee v. City of Los Angeles</underscore>, 250 F.3d 668, 689 (9th Cir. 2001).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">For all of these reasons, it is only under extraordinary circumstances that dismissal is proper under Rule 12(b)(6). <underscore>United States v. City of Redwood City</underscore>, 640 F.2d 963, 966 (9th Cir. 1981).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">As a general rule, leave to amend a complaint which has been dismissed should be freely granted. Fed. R. Civ. P. 15(a). However, leave to amend may be denied when &#x201C;the court determines that the allegation of other facts consistent with the challenged pleading could not possibly cure the deficiency.&#x201D; <underscore>Schreiber Distrib. Co. v. Serv-Well Furniture Co.</underscore>, 806 F.2d 1393, 1401 (9th Cir. 1986); <underscore>see Lopez v. Smith</underscore>, 203 F.3d 1122, 1127 (9th Cir. 2000).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Plaintiff's First Claim for Breach of Contract</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that Chase Bank &#x201C;was the loan agent for FREMONT, and Defendants Does 11 through 20, and/or US Bank.&#x201D; Plaintiff further alleges that &#x201C;[b]y agreeing to negotiate a loan modification with Plaintiff in exchange for her dismissal of her bankruptcy petition, Plaintiff and CHASE entered into a valid contract supported by consideration. Additionally, by dismissing her bankruptcy petition, Plaintiff fully performed under the contract and provided CHASE with valuable consideration. Further, by failing to negotiate a loan modification with Plaintiff, CHASE breached that contract.&#x201D; FAC &#182; 23. Plaintiff merely alleges an agreement to negotiate; plaintiff does not allege an agreement to modify the loan.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Defendant argues that plaintiff fails to allege the existence of any contract between the parties or any breach by defendant. Mot. at 3. Defendant argues that it is not a party to the alleged contract between plaintiff and Chase. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Defendant further argues that plaintiff has not &#x201C;set forth the material, specific facts constituting the defendant's breach stated in the words of the alleged contract.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 4. Moreover, defendant argues that plaintiff fails to allege that any agreement to modify plaintiff's loan was reached. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Defendant contends that even if plaintiff properly alleged the existence of an oral agreement, an oral agreement to modify the terms of the deed of trust is not binding by reason of the statute of frauds. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Defendant further contends that &#x201C;an agreement by which a lender agrees to forbear from exercising the right to foreclosure upon a deed of trust securing an interest in real property comes within the statute of frauds and therefore must be in writing.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> (citing <underscore>Secrest v. Security National Mortgage Loan Trust 2002-2</underscore>, 167 Cal. App. 4th 544, 547 (2008)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Plaintiff responds that statute of frauds does not pose a bar to enforcement because plaintiff fully performed her obligations under the agreement and she will suffer extreme loss if the agreement is not enforced. Opp'n at 10 (citing <underscore>Secrest v. Security Nat'l Mortg. Loan Trust</underscore>, 167 Cal. App. 4th 544, 556 (2007)). Plaintiff further argues that &#x201C;[i]n the financial world, one does not &#x2018;negotiate a loan&#x2019; in the absence of entering into the same.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 11.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">The Court concludes that plaintiff's claim for breach of contract should be dismissed. &#x201C;An agreement by which a lender agreed to forbear from exercising the right of foreclosure under a deed of trust securing an interest in real property comes within the statute of frauds&#x201D; and must be in writing. <underscore>Secrest v. Security Nat. Mortg. Loan Trust 2002-2</underscore>, 167 Cal. App. 4th 544, 547 (2008). Plaintiff cannot avoid the writing requirement on the basis of full performance because she has not demonstrated that she provided any consideration; plaintiff's Chapter 13 bankruptcy petition was dismissed due to failure to meet the requirements of 11 U.S.C. &#167; 1325. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 6 (citing Def's RJN, Ex. 8). Lastly, plaintiff has not adequately pled a breach of an agreement to negotiate a loan modification because &#x201C;[f]ailure to agree is not, itself, a breach of [a] contract to negotiate.&#x201D; <underscore>Copeland v. Baskin Robbins U.S.A.</underscore>, 96 Cal. App. 4th 1251, 1257 (2002)).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Plaintiff's Second Claim for Promissory Estoppel</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that &#x201C;CHASE promised Plaintiff that it would negotiate a loan modification with her in exchange for her dismissal of her bankruptcy petition.&#x201D; FAC &#182; 26.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Defendant argues that plaintiff fails to allege that defendant made a promise. Mot. at 5. Defendant contends that plaintiff only alleges that &#x201C;Chase&#x201D; promised to enter into a loan modification with her. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Defendant further contends that plaintiff fails to adequately plead reliance. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Defendant argues that it is &#x201C;inconceivable&#x201D; that plaintiff took any steps to dismiss her bankruptcy petition in reliance upon any purported &#x2018;promise&#x2019; made by US Bank because plaintiff's Chapter 13 bankruptcy petition was dismissed because plaintiff &#x201C;failed to meet the requirements of 11 U.S.C. &#167; 1325.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 6 (citing Def's RJN, Ex. 8).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Plaintiff responds that defendant made a clear and unambiguous promise that it would negotiate a loan modification with plaintiff in exchange for dismissal of her bankruptcy petition. Opp'n at 11-12. Plaintiff argues that she reasonably and foreseeably relied on defendant's promise by taking actions that resulted in the dismissal of her bankruptcy petition. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 12.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The elements of a promissory estoppel claim are: &#x201C;(1) a promise clear and unambiguous in its terms; (2) reliance by the party to whom the promise is made; (3) [the party's] reliance must be both reasonable and foreseeable; and (4) the party asserting the estoppel must be injured by his reliance.&#x201D; <underscore>Laks v. Coast Fed. Sav. &#38; Loan Assn.</underscore>, 60 Cal. App. 3d 885, 890 (1976).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">The Court concludes that plaintiff's claim for promissory estoppel should be dismissed. Plaintiff has not alleged that defendant made a clear and unambiguous promise. Furthermore, plaintiff cannot establish reliance because her bankruptcy petition was not voluntarily dismissed, but was dismissed because plaintiff &#x201C;failed to meet the requirements of 11 U.S.C. &#167; 1325.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Def's RJN, Ex. 8.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p20">&#8195;At oral argument plaintiff's counsel argued that plaintiff's promissory estoppel claim should not be dismissed because plaintiff has established reliance. However, the record demonstrates that plaintiff did not voluntarily dismiss her bankruptcy petition and she therefore did not take any action in reliance on plaintiff's alleged promise.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p21">&#8195;Under Fed. R. Evid. 201, a court may take judicial notice of &#x201C;matters of public record.&#x201D; <underscore>Mack v. South Bay Beer Distrib.</underscore>, 798 F.2d 1279, 1282 (9th Cir.1986). Accordingly, the Court takes judicial notice of <underscore>In re Angela Consuelo Andrade</underscore>, Case No. SV 07-13330-GM (Bankr. C.D. Cal. Jan. 18, 2008), attached as Exhibit 8 to defendant's request for judicial notice, for purposes of defendants' Fed. R. Civ. P. 12(b)(1) motion only.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Plaintiff's Third Claim for Violation of RESPA</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that Chase violated RESPA, 12 U.S.C. &#167; 2605(e), by failing to respond to plaintiff's qualified written request on July 22, 2008. FAC &#182; 30.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Defendant argues that plaintiff's RESPA claims pursuant to 12 U.S.C. &#167; 2605(e) should be dismissed because that section of RESPA addresses the duties of loan servicers. Mot. at 6. Defendant contends that plaintiff does not, and cannot, allege that defendant is the servicer of her loan. Defendant further contends that plaintiff has failed to allege proximate causation because there is no nexus between defendant's alleged failure to respond to a qualified written request for information and the foreclosure. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 7.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Plaintiff responds that if defendant's agent had responded to plaintiff's &#x201C;qualified written request,&#x201D; she &#x201C;most likely&#x201D; would have had the opportunity to modify her course of conduct and mitigate her liability on the underlying debt. Opp'n at 14. Plaintiff further argues that her FAC alleges that she suffered damages from defendant's failure to respond, including a diminution in property value and loss of rents. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 15.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Under RESPA, the servicer of a &#x201C;federally related mortgage loan,&#x201D; is required to provide a written response within twenty days of receiving a &#x201C;qualified written request&#x201D; for information about the servicing of such a loan, unless the action requested is taken within that period. 12 U.S.C. &#167; 2605(e)(1); <underscore>Cortez v. Keystone Bank, Inc.</underscore>, 2000 WL 536666 at *10 (E.D. Pa. May 2, 2000). RESPA explicitly provides for individual causes of action and allows for actual damages, as well as statutory damages, upon a showing of a pattern or practice of noncompliance with the duty to respond to borrower inquiries. 12 U.S.C. &#167; 2605(f).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">The Court concludes that plaintiff's RESPA claim should be dismissed. Although plaintiff alleges that Chase was an agent of defendant and serviced her loan, plaintiff fails to allege that defendant's failure to respond caused her any damage.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> Plaintiff does not allege the content of the written request or that a response would have somehow avoided foreclosure. 12 U.S.C. &#167; 2605(f)(1)(A) (&#x201C;Whoever fails to comply with any provision of this section shall be liable to the borrower for each such failure in the following amounts:<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> (A) any actual damages to the borrower as a result of the failure.&#x201D;); <underscore>Katz v. Dime Sav. Bank, FSB</underscore>, 992 F. Supp. 250, 255 (W.D.N.Y. 1997).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p27">&#8195;At oral argument plaintiff's counsel argued that plaintiff has adequately shown damage. However, plaintiff has failed to demonstrate that her damages flow from defendant's alleged violation of RESPA.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>D. Plaintiff's Fourth Claim for Violation of FDCPA</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that Chase, as a loan servicer for US Bank, is a debt collector under the FDCPA. FAC &#182; 33. Plaintiff further alleges that &#x201C;[b]y making false, misleading and deceptive representations to Plaintiff about pursuing loan modification in exchange for dismissing her bankruptcy petition so that it could reinitiate foreclosure proceedings, CHASE's conduct constitutes an unfair debt collection practice in violation of this statute.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Defendant argues that plaintiff's FDCPA claim should be dismissed because plaintiff fails to allege that defendant is a &#x201C;debt collector&#x201D; as defined by the FDCPA and fails to identify the provisions of the FDCPA that defendant allegedly violated. Mot. at 8. Defendant further argues that foreclosing upon a property cannot be the basis of an FDCPA claim. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 9.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">Plaintiff responds that defendant is vicariously liable for violations of the FDCPA by virtue of Chase's debt collection actions. Opp'n at 15. Plaintiff argues that Chase qualifies as a debt collector because it regularly engages in the business of collecting moneys owed on home loans and other consumer credit products. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 16.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">The FDCPA was enacted &#x201C;to eliminate abusive debt collection practices by debt collectors, to insure that those debt collectors who refrain from using abusive debt collection practices are not competitively disadvantaged, and to promote consistent State action to protect consumers against debt collection abuses.&#x201D; 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1692(e). To effectuate this purpose, the FDCPA prohibits a &#x201C;debt collector&#x201D; from making false or misleading representations and from engaging in various abusive and unfair practices. To be held liable for violation of the FDCPA, a defendant must &#8211; as a threshold requirement &#8211; fall within the FDCPA's definition of &#x201C;debt collector.&#x201D; <underscore>See Heintz v. Jenkins</underscore>, 514 U.S. 291, 294 (1995); <underscore>see also, e.g., Romine v. Diversified Collection Servs.</underscore>, 155 F.3d 1142, 1146 (9th Cir. 1998).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">The Court concludes that plaintiff's claim for violation of the FDCPA should be dismissed because &#x201C;the law is well-settled<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> that creditors, <ital>mortgagors</ital>, and <ital>mortgage servicing companies</ital> are not debt collectors and are statutorily exempt from liability under the FDCPA.&#x201D; <underscore>Scott v. Wells Fargo Home Mortg.</underscore>, 326 F. Supp. 2d 709, 718 (E.D. Va. 2003) (emphasis in original). Defendant and Chase are not debt collectors as defined by the FDCPA and plaintiff's claim should therefore be dismissed.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> <underscore>Id.</underscore>; 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1692a(6).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p33">&#8195;At oral argument plaintiff's counsel argued that the Fourth Circuit has held that foreclosure constitutes debt collection. However, the case cited by plaintiff, <underscore>Wilson v. Draper &#38; Goldberg, PLLC</underscore>, 443 F.3d 373 (4th Cir. 2006), is inapplicable to this case because plaintiff does not allege that defendant regularly engages in consumer debt collection activity. <underscore>Wilson</underscore>, 443 F.3d at 379 (&#x201C;lawyers who regularly engage in consumer-debt-collection activity should not be allowed to thwart [the purpose of the FDCPA] merely because they proceed in the context of a foreclosure.&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>E. Plaintiff's Fifth Claim for Violation of the RFDCPA</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Plaintiff alleges that defendant, through Chase, violated the RFDCPA by &#x201C;falsely representing to Plaintiff that it would negotiate a loan modification with her and by reinstating non-judicial foreclosure proceedings instead after she agreed to dismiss her bankruptcy petition.&#x201D; FAC &#182; 37.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">Defendant argues that plaintiff's RFDCPA claim should be dismissed because plaintiff does not allege that defendant is a debt collector or that it was attempting to collect a debt. Mot. at 10. Defendant further argues that foreclosure does not constitute debt collection under the RFDCPA. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Like the FDCPA, the RFDCPA applies only to debt collectors. <underscore>Izenberg v. ETS Services, LLC</underscore> 589 F. Supp. 2d 1193, 1199 (C.D. Cal. 2008). The definition of &#x201C;debt collector&#x201D; found in the state statute is broader than that contained in the FDCPA. <underscore>Id.</underscore> However, &#x201C;foreclosure does not constitute debt collection under the RFDCPA.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">The Court concludes that plaintiff's RFDCPA claim should be dismissed because neither defendant nor Chase is a &#x201C;debt collector&#x201D; as defined in the RFDCPA. Plaintiff does not allege that defendant regularly collects debts and &#x201C;foreclosure does not constitute debt collection under the RFDCPA.&#x201D; <underscore>Izenberg</underscore>, 589 F. Supp. 2d at 1199.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>F. Plaintiff's Sixth, Seventh, Eighth and Ninth Claims to Set Aside the Trustee's Sale or Cancel the Deed of Trust</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">Plaintiff's sixth, seventh, eighth, and ninth claims all seek to set aside the foreclosure sale. Plaintiff's sixth claim alleges that defendant mailed, but did not post, notice of the postponement of the foreclosure sale from February 26, 2008, to July 22, 2008, in violation of Cal. Civ. Code &#167; 2924g(d). FAC &#182; 40. Plaintiff's seventh claim alleges that defendant did not have authority to conduct the foreclosure because it was not the holder of the note. FAC &#182; 42. Plaintiff's eighth claim alleges that defendant &#x201C;had no right to enforce the deed of trust<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> because of defective notice procedures and failure to possess the original properly endorsed promissory note.&#x201D; FAC &#182; 47. Plaintiff's ninth claim alleges that &#x201C;[b]ecause Defendant did not possess a promissory note properly endorsed, the Deed of Trust<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> was an unenforceable nullity.&#x201D; FAC &#182; 50.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">Defendant argues that a condition precedent to any cause of action arising from an alleged improper foreclosure is the borrower's tender or offer to tender a sum sufficient to cure the default. Mot. at 10-11 (citing <underscore>Abdallah v. United Sav. Bank</underscore>, 43 Cal. App. 4th 1101, 1109 (1996); <underscore>United States Cold Storage v. Great Western Savings &#38; Loan Ass'n</underscore>, 165 Cal. App. 3d 1214, 1225 (1985)). Defendant contends that plaintiff has failed to allege that she made a valid and viable tender of payment of the indebtedness owing under the deed of trust.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">Defendant further argues that plaintiff fails to allege any procedural irregularity in the trustee's sale. Mot. at 12. Defendant contends that the only basis for plaintiff's claims of irregularity are (1) that defendant was not the holder of the note and (2) that defendant allegedly did not physically post the reason for the postponement of the originally scheduled trustee's sale of February 28, 2008. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Defendant argues that to set aside a presumptively valid foreclosure sale, the claimed irregularity must arise from the foreclosure proceeding itself. <underscore>Id.</underscore> (citing <underscore>Nguyen v. Calhoun</underscore>, 105 Cal. App. 4th 428, 445 (2003)). Defendant contends that plaintiff fails to allege any procedural defect associated with the foreclosure proceedings. Defendant argues that pursuant to Cal. Civ. Code &#167; 2924g(c)(1), a foreclosure trustee may orally postpone a foreclosure sale for a period up to 365 days from the date set forth in the notice of sale. Defendant further argues that Cal. Comm. Code &#167; 3301 permits a non-holder of a note to enforce the provision in a deed of trust securing the obligation. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 13. Defendant contends that California law provides that the foreclosure process may be conducted by the &#x201C;trustee, mortgagee or beneficiary or any of their authorized agents.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 14 (citing Cal. Civ. Code &#167; 2924a(1); <underscore>Moeller v. Lien</underscore>, 25 Cal. App. 4th 822, 834 (1994)). Therefore, defendant argues that it was entitled, as assignee of the beneficial interest under the deed of trust, to commence foreclosure proceedings on the subject property. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">&#x201C;It is settled that an action to set aside a trustee's sale for irregularities in sale notice or procedure should be accompanied by an offer to pay the full amount of the debt for which the property was security.&#x201D; <underscore>Arnolds Management Corp. v. Eischen</underscore>, 158 Cal. App. 3d 575, 578 (1984). To justify setting aside a presumptively valid foreclosure sale, the claimed irregularity must arise from the foreclosure proceeding itself. <underscore>Nguyen v. Calhoun</underscore>, 105 Cal. App. 4th 428, 445 (2003).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">The Court concludes that plaintiff's sixth, seventh, eighth, and ninth claims should be dismissed. Plaintiff is not required to physically post a notice of postponement and plaintiff acknowledges that she received actual notice of the postponement. Cal. Civ. Code &#167; 2924g(c). Furthermore defendant was entitled, as assignee of the beneficial interest under the deed of trust, to conduct the non-judicial foreclosure proceedings. <underscore>Neal v. Juarez</underscore>, 2007 WL 2140640, *8 (S.D. Cal. 2007) (&#x201C;allegation that the trustee did not have the original note or had not received it is insufficient to render the foreclosure proceeding invalid.&#x201D;) Lastly, plaintiff cannot challenge the foreclosure sale because she does not allege that she tendered payment of the indebtedness owing under the deed of trust.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>G. Plaintiff's Tenth Claim for Injunctive Relief</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">Plaintiff seeks a temporary restraining order, preliminary injunction, and permanent injunction. FAC &#182; 52. Defendant argues that plaintiff's claim for injunctive relief should be dismissed because plaintiff has failed to establish a likelihood of success on the merits. Mot. at 14-15.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">The Court concludes that plaintiffs' claim for injunctive relief should be dismissed as moot because the foreclosure sale has already taken place.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>V. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">In accordance with the foregoing, the Court hereby GRANTS defendant's motion to dismiss without prejudice. Plaintiff shall have 45 days from the entry of this order to file an amended complaint. In the event that plaintiff does not amend her complaint within 45 days, this order will operate as a dismissal with prejudice.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p47" level="1"><underscore>00 : 00</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p48" level="1">Initials of Preparer <underscore>CMJ</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>