<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><bold>CIVIL MINUTES &#8212; GENERAL</bold></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment><ital>Mellissa Withers</ital></title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment><ital>eHarmony, Inc.</ital></title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 09-2266-GHK(RCx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-2266-GHK(RCx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-02266-GHK-RC</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 06/02/2010</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Beatrice Herrera, Deputy Clerk, Attorneys Present For Plaintiffs: None</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">N/A, Court Reporter / Recorder, Attorneys Present For Defendants: None</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">N/A, Tape No.</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Proceedings: (In Chambers)</bold> Order re: Plaintiff-in-Intervention's Motion for Class Certification [122]</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1"><bold>The Honorable GEORGE H. KING, U.S. DISTRICT JUDGE</bold></judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Plaintiff-in-Intervention Peter Schmidt (&#x201C;Schmidt&#x201D;), the putative class representative in this action against Defendant eHaromony, Inc. (&#x201C;eHarmony&#x201D;), moves to certify a class of subscribers to eHarmony's online dating service in connection with eHarmony's alleged violations of California statutory and common law. We have considered the papers filed in support of and opposition to Schmidt's Motion for Class Certification, and deem this matter appropriate for resolution without oral argument. L.R. 7-15. As the Parties are familiar with the facts, we will repeat them only as necessary. Accordingly, we rule as follows.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. Introduction and Factual Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">eHarmony distinguishes its &#x201C;Singles Service&#x201D; from other online dating services by its &#x201C;unique and patented matching process&#x201D; which pairs individuals based on criteria that emphasizes long-term compatibility. (Complaint-in-Intervention &#182; 6). Members complete a detailed personality questionnaire that provides the basis for eHarmony to select potentially compatible matches from among its other members. According to the Complaint-in-Intervention, &#x201C;people who choose eHarmony instead of its competitors are told that they are trading the ability to access a large number[ ] of members&#8212;in some cases thousands or tens of thousands&#8212;for a fewer number of select and high-quality matches generated by eHarmony's patented matching system that will allegedly greatly increase one's chance of meeting a long-term partner.&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital> &#182; 11). The mere creation of an eHarmony profile is free, as is the opportunity to view the profiles of those members that eHarmony identifies as a match. However, if a member wishes to communicate with a match whose profile piques his interest, he must first become a paying subscriber. (<ital>Id.</ital> &#182; 14).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">The claims in this putative class action arise from eHarmony's practice of matching paying Singles Service subscribers with non-subscribers who have created free profiles or former subscribers whose profiles are maintained in eHarmony's database after their paid term of subscription has expired. Member profiles do not indicate whether an individual selected as a match is a non-subscriber without the present ability to communicate, and Schmidt alleges that eHarmony fails to otherwise adequately disclose its practice of matching subscribers with non-subscribers. (<ital>Id.</ital> &#182;&#182; 14-15). As a result, a subscriber may erroneously assume that a match provided by eHarmony is likewise an active subscriber with the present ability to respond to a communication request. (<ital>Id.</ital>). The Complaint-in-Intervention alleges claims for unlawful, unfair, and fraudulent business practices in violation of California's Unfair Competition Law (&#x201C;UCL&#x201D;), California Business and Professions Code &#167; 17200 <ital>et seq.</ital>, unfair or deceptive practices under California's Consumer Legal Remedies Act (&#x201C;CLRA&#x201D;), California Civil Code &#167; 1750 <ital>et seq.</ital>, and breach of contract. Schmidt now seeks to certify the following nationwide class pursuant to Federal Rules of Civil Procedure 23(a) and 23(b)(3): &#x201C;All residents of the United States of America who, at any time during the period of January 30, 2005 through [the date of certification], were paid subscribers of the eHarmony Singles Service.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p4">&#8195;Alternatively, Schmidt requests certification of a state-wide class, defined as &#x201C;Plaintiff Peter Schmidt and all residents of the State of California who, at any time during the period of January 30, 2005 through [the date of class certification], were paid subscribers of the eHarmony Singles Service.&#x201D; Without addressing the propriety of Schmidt, a Wisconsin resident, representing a sub-class consisting solely of California residents, we note that the reasoning contained in this Order applies with equal force to either of the proposed definitions.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. Motion for Class Certification</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 23 &#x201C;provides district courts with broad discretion to determine whether a class should be certified, and to revisit that certification throughout the legal proceedings before the court.&#x201D; <ital>Dukes v. Wal-Mart Stores, Inc.</ital>, 603 F.3d 571, 579 (9th Cir. 2010) (<ital>en banc</ital>) (citation omitted). &#x201C;The party seeking certification bears the burden of showing that each of the four requirements of Rule 23(a) and at least one requirement of Rule 23(b) have been met.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 580. Whether the individual requirements for class certification are met are questions of law, and we &#x201C;must conduct a &#x2018;rigorous analysis&#x2019; into whether the prerequisites of Rule 23 are met.&#x201D; <ital>Valentino v. Carter-Wallace, Inc.</ital>, 97 F.3d 1227, 1233 (9th Cir. 1996). In doing so, we are generally bound to take the substantive allegations of the complaint as true, but may consider matters beyond the pleadings in order to ascertain whether the asserted claims or defenses are susceptible of resolution on a class-wide basis. <ital>See Hanon v. Dataproducts Corp.</ital>, 976 F.2d 497, 509 (9th Cir. 1992); <ital>Dukes</ital>, 603 F.3d at 590 (&#x201C;While plaintiffs need not make more than allegations as to their substantive claims, whether the suit is appropriate for class resolution must be actually demonstrated, not just alleged, to the district court's satisfaction.&#x201D;). Indeed, determining whether the requirements of Rule 23 have been met will often &#x201C;require looking behind the pleadings, even to issues overlapping with the merits of the underlying claims.&#x201D; <ital>Dukes</ital>, 603 F.3d at 581.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><ital><bold>A. Rule 23(a)</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">A class representative must &#x201C;possess the same interest and suffer the same injury&#x201D; as the class members. <ital>Gen. Tel. Co. of the Sw. v. Falcon</ital>, 457 U.S. 147, 156 (1982) (internal quotation marks omitted). Accordingly, the typicality requirement under Rule 23(a)(3) requires that &#x201C;the claims and defenses of representative parties are typical of the claims or defenses of the class.&#x201D; The purpose of the requirement is &#x201C;to assure that the interest of the named representative aligns with the interests of the class.&#x201D; <ital>Hanon</ital>, 976 F.2d at 508. Class certification is inappropriate &#x201C;where a putative class representative is subject to unique defenses which threaten to become the focus of the litigation.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> (citation omitted). For instance, &#x201C;a named plaintiff's motion for class certification should not be granted&#x201D; where the plaintiff's &#x201C;unique background and factual situation require him to prepare to meet defenses that are not typical of the defenses which may be raised against other members of the proposed class.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>1. UCL and CLRA Claims</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">The UCL prohibits any &#x201C;unlawful, unfair or fraudulent business act or practice.&#x201D; <csc>Cal. Bus</csc>. &#38; <csc>Prof. Code</csc> &#167; 17200. Although Schmidt is correct in asserting that individualized proof of causation and injury is not required for absent class members under the UCL, the named plaintiff must demonstrate the requisite elements of standing to bring a representative suit. <ital>In re Tobacco II Cases</ital>, 46 Cal. 4th 298, 320-21 (2009). Thus, where a &#x201C;UCL action is based on a fraud theory involving false advertising and misrepresentations to consumers,&#x201D; the class representative must demonstrate &#x201C;actual reliance.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 325 n.17, 326. This reasoning &#x201C;applies equally to the &#x2018;unlawful&#x2019; prong of the UCL, when, as here, the predicate unlawful conduct is misrepresentation.&#x201D; <ital>Hale v. Sharp Healthcare</ital>, 183 Cal. App. 4th 1373, No. D054637, 2010 WL 1529329, at *6 (Cal. Ct. App. Apr. 19, 2010). Thus, whether a defendant's deceptive conduct is labeled as unlawful, unfair, or fraudulent, a &#x201C;consumer's burden of pleading causation in a UCL action should hinge on the nature of the alleged wrongdoing rather than the specific prong of the UCL the consumer invokes.&#x201D; <ital>Durell v. Sharp Healthcare</ital>, 183 Cal. App. 4th 1350, No. D054261, 2010 WL 1529322, at *6 (Cal. Ct. App. Apr. 19, 2010). &#x201C;While only the named plaintiff in a UCL class action based on fraudulent conduct must demonstrate reliance and causation, [a] plaintiff's unique susceptibility to a challenge based on her standing to pursue a UCL claim is fatal&#x201D; to establishing typicality. <ital>Quezada v. Loan Ctr. of Calif., Inc.</ital>, No. 08-cv-00177-WBS, 2009 WL 5113506, at *7 (E.D. Cal. Dec. 18, 2009) (citing <ital>In re Tobacco II Cases</ital>, 46 Cal. 4th at 321).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Similarly, the CLRA makes it unlawful to use &#x201C;unfair methods of competition and unfair or deceptive acts or practices&#x201D; in the sale of goods or services to a consumer. <csc>Cal. Civ. Code</csc> &#167; 1770(a). &#x201C;Relief under the CLRA is specifically limited to those who suffer damage, making causation a necessary element of proof.&#x201D; <ital>Wilens v. TD Waterhouse Group, Inc.</ital>, 120 Cal. App. 4th 746, 754 (2003). Accordingly, &#x201C;plaintiffs in a CLRA action [must] show not only that a defendant's conduct was deceptive but that the deception caused them harm,&#x201D; although materially deficient representations are &#x201C;sufficient to give rise to the inference of common reliance&#x201D; as to absent class members. <ital>Mass. Mut. Life Ins. Co. v. Superior Court</ital>, 97 Cal. App. 4th 1282, 1292-93 (2002); <ital>see also Anunziato v. eMachines, Inc.</ital>, 402 F. Supp. 2d 1133, 1136 (C.D. Cal. 2005) (recognizing the CLRA imposes a reliance requirement).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">eHarmony has marshalled evidence to support its assertion that, notwithstanding the alleged inadequacy of eHarmony's disclosures, Schmidt's familiarity with eHarmony's service as a non-subscriber placed him on inquiry notice of the challenged practice. For instance, Schmidt used eHarmony's free matching service, and received communication requests, before becoming a paying subscriber for the first time and during subsequent periods when his subscription lapsed. (Din Decl. &#182;&#182; 33-38; Ex. P). Indeed, Schmidt contacted eHarmony's customer service in January 2008 to complain of matches with non-subscribers. (Wood Decl. &#182; 11; Ex. G at eH078541). Schmidt's deposition testimony would appear to affirm that he was aware of the practice at some point before re-subscribing. (Orren Decl., Ex. C [Schmidt Tr. 172:21-173:1]).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">In his Reply, Schmidt acknowledges that &#x201C;at certain points during the deposition [cited by eHarmony], Defendant obtained testimony from Mr. Schmidt that, on its face, appears to be inconsistent on the issue of when he first &#x2018;knew&#x2019; (as opposed to suspected) that he was being matched with non-subscribers.&#x201D; (Reply 11). Schmidt explains that &#x201C;the first time that he <ital>actually knew</ital> that he was being matched with non-subscribers&#x201D; was not until October 2009, during his most recent subscription period, when he was matched with a woman named Christine, whom he had previously dated and knew to no longer be an active subscriber. (<ital>Id.</ital> at 10-11 (emphasis in original)). He further argues that &#x201C;there is no way that he could have known (as opposed to suspected) until he was matched with someone like Christine.&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital> at 11). Irrespective of when Schmidt claims to have confirmed his suspicion that he was being matched with non-subscribers during his paid subscription periods, his suspicion of the allegedly deceitful practice may be sufficient to preclude him from reasonably relying on eHarmony's representations. &#x201C;In determining whether one can reasonably or justifiably rely on an alleged misrepresentation, the knowledge, education and experience of the person claiming reliance must be considered.&#x201D; <ital>Guido v. Koopman</ital>, 1 Cal. App. 4th 837, 843 (1991). Schmidt's prior experience with eHarmony's matching practices as a non-subscriber may negate the element of reliance necessary for Schmidt to establish standing to bring these claims individually, and to entitle him to an inference of class-wide reliance. Simply put, it affords eHarmony a full defense to Schmidt's UCL and CLRA claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Schmidt has also testified that he did not review eHarmony's website or its Terms of Service before subscribing. (Orren Decl., Ex. C [Schmidt Tr. 28:4-7, 31:1-7]). Citing this admission, eHarmony argues that Schmidt lacks typicality as he cannot establish reliance on the allegedly deficient disclosures underlying his claims. (<ital>See</ital> Opp'n 16). In response, Schmidt asserts that &#x201C;the eHarmony Terms of Service do not incorporate the website&#x201D; and that &#x201C;the Terms of Service say nothing about subscribers being matched with non-subscribers.&#x201D; (Reply 3, 9). As stated in the Reply, &#x201C;<ital>none</ital> of [Schmidt's] claims is premised on or require[s] a showing of reliance on false representations,&#x201D; seemingly implying that the materiality of an omission exists independent of a consumer's awareness of the allegedly deceptive disclosure. (<ital>Id.</ital> at 3 (emphasis in original); <ital>id.</ital> at 2 (&#x201C;Defendant misunderstands the theory of Plaintiffs' case. Plaintiffs are not claiming that they relied upon advertisements and website statements as the basis for their purchasing decision.&#x201D;)). Contrary to Schmidt's apparent understanding, when a claim is based on fraudulent omissions, as opposed to affirmative misrepresentations, a plaintiff must prove reliance by showing that, &#x201C;had the omitted information been disclosed, [he] would have been aware of it and behaved differently.&#x201D; <ital>Mirkin v. Wasserman</ital>, 5 Cal. 4th 1082, 1093 (1993). eHarmony may thus argue that Schmidt would not have behaved any differently since he never read the Terms of Service or relied on its provisions when first deciding to become a subscriber. <ital>See Gawara v. U.S. Brass Corp.</ital>, 63 Cal. App. 4th 1341, 1349-50 (1998) (&#x201C;Since [plaintiffs] would not have been aware of the omitted information because they had not read the prospectuses or heard the public communications, they had failed to plead the necessary reliance.&#x201D;). In sum, whether Schmidt detrimentally relied on eHarmony's allegedly deficient representations will likely become a focus of the litigation, and precludes him from demonstrating the requisite typicality as a representative with respect to his UCL and CLRA claims.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>2. Breach of Contract Claim</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Schmidt also alleges that eHarmony's practice of matching subscribers with non-subscribers constitutes a breach of eHarmony's contractual obligations under its Terms of Service. Yet, Schmidt does not contend that any of the permutations of eHarmony's Terms of Service expressly stated that subscribers would only be matched with other subscribers. He asserts, rather, that &#x201C;uniformly, the Terms of Service <ital>do not</ital> disclose that subscribers will be matched with non-subscribers&#x201D; and that &#x201C;the reasonable expectation of a prospective subscriber&#x201D; is that &#x201C;she will be matched with other paying subscribers.&#x201D; (Reply 17 (emphasis in original)). According to Schmidt, &#x201C;[g]iven the reasonable expectation of subscribers that they <ital>will not</ital> be matched with non-subscribers and the omission of any statement in the Terms of Service that subscribers <ital>will be</ital> matched with non-subscribers<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> it is a breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing implied by law in the Terms of Service for eHarmony to match subscribers with non-subscribers.&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital> at 18 (emphasis in original)). Schmidt asserts that his own &#x201C;failure to read the Terms of Service has absolutely no bearing on his claim for breach of contract&#x201D; given that the contract is binding irrespective of whether he read it before agreeing to its terms. (<ital>Id.</ital> at 8-9).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">The covenant of good faith and fair dealing is implied by law in every contract, but it &#x201C;exists merely to prevent one contracting party from unfairly frustrating the other party's right to receive the <ital>benefits of the agreement actually made</ital>.&#x201D; <ital>Guz v. Bechtel Nat'l Inc.</ital>, 24 Cal. 4th 317, 349 (2000) (emphasis in original). The covenant, therefore, &#x201C;cannot be endowed with an existence independent of its contractual underpinnings&#x201D; and &#x201C;cannot impose substantive duties or limits on the contracting parties beyond those incorporated in the specific terms of their agreement.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 349-50 (internal quotation marks and citations omitted). In the absence of any express language giving rise to an implied agreement by eHarmony to only match subscribers with other subscribers, &#x201C;the question at hand is whether such a term may be implied without altering or varying the terms of the agreement and whether the circumstances give rise to other conditions permitting a court to imply such terms,&#x201D; including whether the omitted provision is &#x201C;indispensable to effectuating the parties' intentions.&#x201D; <ital>In re Marriage of Corona</ital>, 172 Cal. App. 4th 1205, 1222 (2009).<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> To ascertain the mutual intention of the parties, a court may consider the &#x201C;circumstances surrounding and leading to the execution of a contract&#x201D; and other objective manifestations of the parties' intent. <ital>Kashmiri v. Regents of the Univ. of Cal.</ital>, 156 Cal. App. 4th 809, 838 (2007).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p14">&#8195;Under California law, a court may find that a contract includes an implied term only if: &#x201C;(1) the implication either arises from the contract's express language or is indispensable to effectuating the parties' intentions; (2) it appears that the implied term was so clearly within the parties' contemplation when they drafted the contract that they did not feel the need to express it; (3) legal necessity justifies the implication; (4) the implication would have been expressed if the need to do so had been called to the parties' attention; and (5) the contract does not already address completely the subject of the implication.&#x201D; <ital>In re Marriage of Corona</ital>, 172 Cal. App. 4th at 1222.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Schmidt readily concedes that the Terms of Service are silent on the issue of eHarmony's matching practices, but simultaneously contends that &#x201C;[t]he question of whether [eHarmony] breached its contracts necessitates no inquiry into what class members saw, heard or understood.&#x201D; (Reply 2). Schmidt's argument fails to appreciate that his theory of liability is contractually based, and &#x201C;[t]he implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing does <ital>not</ital> extend beyond the terms of the contract at issue.&#x201D; <ital>Poway Royal Mobilehome Owners Ass'n v. City of Poway</ital>, 149 Cal. App. 4th 1460, 1477 (2007) (emphasis in original). The parameters of any implied terms on which Schmidt relies will turn on the mutual intention of the parties; the extent of Schmidt's familiarity with eHarmony's practice of matching subscribers with non-subscribers will be both a relevant and necessary inquiry of contract interpretation. Schmidt's preoccupation with resolving this fact-intensive issue will detract from his ability to protect the interests of the class. Moreover, Schmidt's personal experience with eHarmony's Singles Service as a non-subscriber before agreeing to its Terms of Service as a subscriber precludes him from showing the requisite typicality to serve as class representative.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><ital><bold>B. Rule 23(b)(3)</bold></ital></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">In addition to meeting the requirements under Rule 23(a), Schmidt must establish that one or more of the grounds for maintaining the suit as a class action are met under Rule 23(b). Pursuant to Rule 23(b)(3), we may certify a class only if we first determine that &#x201C;the questions of law or fact common to class members predominate over any questions affecting only individual members, and that a class action is superior to other available methods for fairly and efficiently adjudicating the controversy.&#x201D; <csc>Fed</csc>. R. <csc>Civ</csc>. P. 23(b)(3).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">&#x201C;The Rule 23(b)(3) predominance inquiry tests whether proposed classes are sufficiently cohesive to warrant adjudication by representation.&#x201D; <ital>Amchem Prods., Inc. v. Windsor</ital>, 521 U.S. 591, 623 (1997). Schmidt contends that the predominance requirement is met here given the common factual and legal underpinnings of his claims shared by class members. The question of predominance presumes the existence of common issues; thus, a mere showing of commonality is not enough. <ital>Hanlon v. Chrysler Corp.</ital>, 150 F.3d 1011, 1022 (1998); <ital>see also Amchem</ital>, 521 U.S. at 623-24 (predominance criterion is &#x201C;far more demanding&#x201D; than Rule 23(a)'s commonality requirement). Predominance focuses on the relationship between the common and individual issues, requiring that the common issues be qualitatively substantial in relation to the issues peculiar to individual class members. <ital>See Hanlon</ital>, 150 F.3d at 1022; <ital>Edwards v. The First Am. Corp.</ital>, 251 F.R.D. 454, 458 (C.D. Cal. 2008) (&#x201C;Predominance is determined not by counting the number of common issues, but by weighing their significance.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">&#x201C;There is no definitive test for determining whether common issues predominate, however, in general, predominance is met when there exists generalized evidence which proves or disproves an [issue or] element on a simultaneous, class-wide basis, since such proof obviates the need to examine each class members' individual position.&#x201D; <ital>In re Vitamins Antitrust Litig.</ital>, 209 F.R.D. 251, 262 (D.D.C. 2002) (internal quotation marks omitted). Schmidt argues that the breach of contract, UCL, and CLRA claims are each susceptible to common proof because, notwithstanding any disclosures made by eHarmony in its advertisements and elsewhere on its website, every permutation of eHarmony's Terms of Service is silent on the practice of matching non-subscribers and that this constitutes a material omission. Schmidt thus argues that &#x201C;the trier of fact will have to consider facts that are common to all class members&#8212;namely, the utility of the so-called &#x2018;disclosures&#x2019; to which [eHarmony] points as proof that it adequately disclosed its practice of matching subscribers with non-subscribers.&#x201D; (Reply 22; <ital>see also id.</ital> at 8 (arguing that &#x201C;because the Terms of Service are uniform in their material terms as to the issue of matching subscribers with non-subscribers, this breach of contract claim is subject to common proof&#x201D;)). However, as discussed above, absent class members are not entitled to an inference of class-wide reliance on a material omission under the UCL or CLRA claims without actual reliance having been established by the class representative. Moreover, whether an individual member understood that eHarmony matched subscribers with non-subscribers before agreeing to its Terms of Service for a paid subscription may depend on whether she had previously been provided matches as a non-subscriber, received a communication request from a subscriber, and found that subscription was required in order to reciprocate. An individual's familiarity with eHarmony's service is also integral to an evaluation of any implied terms purported to arise from eHarmony's Terms of Service. Engaging in this individualized inquiry for all putative class members within the proposed definition would overwhelm the progress of litigation.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. Conclusion</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">In light of the foregoing discussion, Schmidt's Motion for Class Certification is <bold>DENIED</bold>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1"><underscore>-- : --</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Initials of Deputy Clerk <underscore>Bea</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>