<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>FOR THE CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment><bold>VETRA PERRY-ROMAN, Plaintiff(s)</bold>,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment><bold>AIG RETIREMENT ADVISORS, INC., Defendant(s).</bold></title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line><bold>CASE NO. CV 09-2287 DOC (RNBx)</bold></docket.line>
<docket.number><bold>CV 09-2287 DOC (RNBx)</bold></docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-02287-DOC-RNB</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 04/26/2010</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER DENYING MOTION FOR SUMMARY JUDGMENT</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">DAVID O. CARTER United States District Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Before the Court is Defendants AIG Retirement Advisors, Inc. (&#x201C;AIG&#x201D;) and the Variable Annuity Life Insurance Company (&#x201C;VALIC&#x201D;) (collectively &#x201C;Defendants&#x201D;)' Motion for Summary Judgment (the &#x201C;Motion&#x201D;). After considering the moving, opposing, and replying papers, as well as the parties' oral argument, the Court DENIES the Motion.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">This lawsuit concerns the non-payment of overtime compensation to Plaintiff Vetra Perry-Roman (&#x201C;Perry&#x201D; or &#x201C;Plaintiff&#x201D;) by VALIC. VALIC retained Perry as one of approximately 200 Financial Advisors (&#x201C;FAs&#x201D;) in California, by an employment offer letter from AIG dated May 30, 2008. <ital>See</ital> Ex. A to Giovanne Decl. (Perry Depo Tr.) at 10; Docket 182-13 (UF) at 2. The offer letter stated that: (1) Plaintiff would receive a training allowance over a 48-week period; and (2) Plaintiff would receive &#x201C;commissions pursuant to [her] Registered Representative Agreement.&#x201D; UF 16. During her deposition, Plaintiff testified, over her counsel's objection, that she believed the &#x201C;training allowance&#x201D; existed to provide her with a &#x201C;living wage cushion until such time that I was able to earn an adequate living.&#x201D; VALIC's formal commission structure provides that commissions will issue both from &#x201C;sales&#x201D; and from the time spent advising and servicing potential and existing clients. <ital>See</ital> Opp. To UF at 6.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Plaintiff thereafter accepted VALIC's employment offer and signed a registered representative agreement with VALIC on June 9, 2008. Ex. 1 to Perry Depo. Tr. at 10; UF 15. The Registered Representative Agreement used by VALIC notes that an FA is <ital><bold>not</bold></ital> an employee of VALIC's and works on an at-will basis. <ital>See</ital> Ex. B to Bainert Decl. VALIC FAs do not receive overtime compensation. <ital>See</ital> Ex. D to Bainert Decl. at 97.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">VALIC is engaged in the provision of financial products and services to the employees of nonprofit entities. <ital>See</ital> Poch Decl. &#182; 4. Such products and services include but are not limited to fixed variable annuities, mutual funds, multiple 401(k) and 403(b) products, 529 plans, brokerage accounts, traditional and Roth IRAs, and multiple forms of life and care insurance. <ital>Id.</ital> &#182; 5. VALIC assigns each FA a &#x201C;territory&#x201D; within which the FA must solicit and service customers. <ital>Id.</ital> Each FA must obtain one or more licenses that are legal prerequisites to the sale of registered financial products. <ital>Id.</ital> &#182; 6. VALIC reimburses the costs of its FAs' licenses. <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Perry interviewed in person with a VALIC District Manager and a Human Resources Manager and by telephone with a Regional Vice President prior to being hired. <ital>See</ital> UF 9. In addition, Perry participated on a full day ride along with a FA. <ital>Id.</ital> Perry had experience selling and servicing financial products prior to her employment with VALIC and, as a result, already had her Series 7, 9, 10, and 66 licenses. <ital>Id.</ital> She acquired her California insurance license after starting work at VALIC and VALIC reimbursed the costs of the insurance license. <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">Perry was assigned to service 11 school groups (and one hospital that was later added) within the Los Angeles County area by either engaging those groups with VALIC's products and services or servicing VALIC's existing contracts with those groups. <ital>See id.</ital> VALIC assigned Perry a laptop, printer, and blackberry, which she used to establish a &#x201C;home office&#x201D; in her dining room. <ital>See</ital> Perry Depo. Tr. at 21; UF 26.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Plaintiff was assigned for administrative purposes to VALIC's Glendale office, and testified at deposition that she worked exclusively from her home office and only used the Glendale office for administrative purposes. <ital>See</ital> UF 19; UF 25.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p7">&#8195;Plaintiff engages in pettifoggery by challenging Defendants' use of the word &#x201C;tools&#x201D; to refer to such devices. <ital>See</ital> Opp. to UF at 8.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">There are two job descriptions of the VALIC FA position in the record: (1) an online representation that &#x201C;As a [FA] a majority of your time is spent in the field engaging in activities intended to result in the sales of VALIC and non-VALIC products and services to prospective and present VALIC customers,&#x201D; <ital>see</ital> Ex. 9 to Poch Depo. Tr.; and (2) an online statement that describes the job as &#x201C;sales and service of retirement and other financial products to employees of client groups,&#x201D; <ital>see</ital> Ex. J to Bainer Decl.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">In July 2008, Perry underwent a mandatory week-long VALIC Basic Sales Training (&#x201C;BST&#x201D;) in Houston Texas. <ital>See</ital> Poch Depo. Tr. 113:10-19. The Houston training included a powerpoint presentation entitled &#x201C;The trusted AIG VALIC financial advisor,&#x201D; which introduced the new VALIC FAs to the requirements of their position. The presentation encouraged the new FAs to abstain from acting as a &#x201C;salesperson&#x201D; and instead serve as a &#x201C;trusted advisor&#x201D; to VALIC's present and prospective clients. <ital>See</ital> Ex. E to Bainert Decl. at 2418. According to the presentation, an FA's client interactions proceed in three steps (a business relationship model): (1) a client &#x201C;snapshot&#x201D; 1st sale at the first appointment; (2) a &#x201C;2nd sale&#x201D; at the second appointment; and (3) a &#x201C;3rd sale&#x201D; at the third appointment.&#x201D; <ital>See id.</ital> at 2417. FAs were directed to abandon traditional sales techniques and develop a relationship of trust with VALIC's clients. <ital>See id.</ital> at 2422.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">Plaintiff attended two additional VALIC training seminars. First, on August 1, 2008, Plaintiff attended a &#x201C;Sales Training.&#x201D; <ital>See</ital> Ex. A to Giovanni Decl. at 114. Second, on September 19, 2008, October 3, 2008 and October 17, 2008, Plaintiff attended a &#x201C;L.A. District Sales Training.' <ital>See id.</ital> at 116.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">After her interviews and training, Plaintiff understood that &#x201C;sales&#x201D; was a component of the work she would perform for VALIC, but that the position would also require other tasks. UF 13. The parties dispute whether those &#x201C;other tasks&#x201D; are incidental to the sale of VALIC's products and services &#8211; while VALIC argues that the other tasks would &#x201C;ultimately end in a sale of some sort,&#x201D; <ital>see</ital> UF 13, Plaintiff argues that she believed that only the sales related tasks would &#x201C;ultimately end in a sale of some sort.&#x201D; <ital>See</ital> Pl.'s Opp. to UF at 4.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Perry developed an annual business plan, which established the commission level she hoped to achieve. UF 8. Plaintiff had already been informed that the &#x201C;minimum expected performance&#x201D; during the first year of a VALIC FA's service &#x201C;would be somewhere around $35,000 in commissions.&#x201D; UF 14.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Plaintiff estimates that she spent approximately 25 percent of her working hours in her home office. <ital>See</ital> UF 27. The remainder of Plaintiff's time was spent attending trainings, attending to administrative tasks at the Glendale office, or meeting with customers at their worksites, homes, and at coffee shops. <ital>See</ital> UF 28. Though Plaintiff was bound by client demands, as well as her travel commitments, her schedule was not set by a central authority at VALIC. <ital>See</ital> Perry Depo. Tr. at 237:18-238:13. Rather, Plaintiff retained autonomy to set her own schedule and arrange to meet with her clients at times generally convenient for her. <ital>See id.</ital> Plaintiff testified that she estimated she spent approximately 60 to 70 percent of her time engaged with clients outside the office. <ital>See</ital> UF 30. It is hotly contested between the parties whether this time outside the office spent with clients was time spent: (a) engaged in activities intended to result in the sale of VALIC or non-VALIC financial products or services; or (b) engaged in some activities intended to result in the sale of VALIC or non-VALIC products or services and other activities intended to provide other non-sale related services to clients or prospective clients. <ital>See</ital> Perry Depo. Tr. at 241-43.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">Plaintiff met with customers in part to sell VALIC or non-VALIC financial products and services. The parties dispute the manner of Plaintiff's interactions with customers. Plaintiff argues that her interactions followed a relatively well-defined template, while Defendants argue that Plaintiff was not bound by a script (no script was attached to the parties' briefing). <ital>See</ital> Opp. to UF at 9. Plaintiff asserts that she engaged in (unnamed) activities uniquely designed to service or advise existing clients, while Defendants argue that almost all of Plaintiff's activities were directed towards making the sale. <ital>See id.</ital> at 9-10. The parties also agree as to one of Plaintiff's transactions &#8211; involving Guided Portfolio products and services suite and the RSVP Mutual Fund. Defendants suggest that Plaintiff &#x201C;sold&#x201D; both items to her customers, but Plaintiff responds that she merely helped her client &#8211; Pacific Hospital Group &#8211; &#x201C;transition[]&#x201D; to the RSVP fund from an existing product. <ital>See id.</ital> at 10.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">The parties nonetheless agree that if Plaintiff sold a VALIC or non-VALIC financial product or service to a customer, she would &#x201C;assist the customer to complete and submit the necessary paperwork and to consummate the transaction.&#x201D; UF 34. Next, VALIC would review, for compliance and regulatory reasons, the contracts and sales paperwork submitted by Plaintiff in connection with the sale. UF 35. After VALIC verified the forms, the financial product or service sold by Plaintiff was provided to the customer. UF 36. Plaintiff received some commissions for sales of certain VALIC or non-VALIC products or services. <ital>See</ital> UF 40.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Plaintiff's position required that she travel extensively to customers' workplaces, homes, and other mutually convenient sites. As a result, Plaintiff spent a considerable amount of time on the road. Plaintiff alleges that as a result of the time expended driving and visiting with customers and potential customers at remote locations, she was unable to take certain meal and rest breaks required under California law. Plaintiff nonetheless testified that during her &#x201C;ride-along&#x201D; training, she and the more experienced FA took a 30-40 minute meal break and, in addition, when Plaintiff inquired of her supervisors whether she was able to take a meal break, she was not informed that she was unable to do so.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Plaintiff's wage statements classified her as an exempt employee and, in part, failed to list her hours worked and hourly rate. <ital>See</ital> UF 50. Plaintiff voluntarily resigned before VALIC terminated her for lack of performance in or about November 2008. She filed the instant class action lawsuit on November 24, 2008 and thereafter filed her First Amended Complaint (FAC) bringing causes of action for (1) unlawful failure to pay all wages due (including overtime); (2) failure to provide meal and rest periods; (3) failure to provide accurate itemized wage statements; and (4) unfair business practices under California Business &#38; Professions Code &#167; 17200, <ital>et seq.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The Court granted Defendants' Motion to Deny Class Certification on February 24, 2010. Defendants now move for summary judgment as to all of Plaintiff's claims.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. Legal Standard</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Summary judgment is proper if &#x201C;the pleadings, the discovery and disclosure materials on file, and any affidavits show that there is no genuine issue as to any material fact and that the movant is entitled to judgment as a matter of law.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">The Court must view the facts and draw inferences in the manner most favorable to the non-moving party. <ital>United States v. Diebold, Inc.</ital>, 369 U.S. 654, 655, 82 S. Ct. 993 (1962); <ital>Chevron Corp. v. Pennzoil Co.</ital>, 974 F.2d 1156, 1161 (9th Cir. 1992). The moving party bears the initial burden of demonstrating the absence of a genuine issue of material fact for trial, but it need not disprove the other party's case. <ital>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc.</ital>, 477 U.S. 242, 256, 106 S. Ct. 2505 (1986); <ital>Celotex Corp. v. Catrett</ital>, 477 U.S. 317, 323-25, 106 S. Ct. 2548 (1986). When the non-moving party bears the burden of proving the claim or defense, the moving party can meet its burden by pointing out that the non-moving party has failed to present any genuine issue of material fact. <ital>Musick v. Burke</ital>, 913 F.2d 1390, 1394 (9th Cir. 1990).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Once the moving party meets its burden, the &#x201C;opposing party may not rely merely on allegations or denials in its own pleading; rather, its response must &#8211; by affidavits or as otherwise provided in this rule &#8211; set out specific facts showing a genuine issue for trial.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(e); <ital>see also Anderson</ital>, 477 U.S. at 248-49. Furthermore, a party cannot create a genuine issue of material fact simply by making assertions in its legal papers. There must be specific, admissible evidence identifying the basis for the dispute. <ital>S.A. Empresa de Viacao Aerea Rio Grandense v. Walter Kidde &#38; Co., Inc.</ital>, 690 F.2d 1235, 1238 (9th Cir. 1980). The Supreme Court has held that &#x201C;[t]he mere existence of a scintilla of evidence<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> will be insufficient; there must be evidence on which the jury could reasonably find for [the opposing party].&#x201D; <ital>Anderson</ital>, 477 U.S. at 252.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. Discussion</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Defendants argue that Plaintiff was exempt from overtime compensation under the California Labor Code's &#x201C;outside salesperson&#x201D; exemption, which Defendants invoked as a complete affirmative defense against Plaintiff's claims. The applicability of the outside salesperson exemption arguably causes Plaintiff's remaining causes of action &#8211; for failure to provide meal and rest breaks, failing to provide itemized wage statements, and unfair competition &#8211; to also fail as a matter of law.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Unlawful Failure to Pay All Wages Due</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">The FAC's first cause of action is predicated on separate acts, which include: (1) failure to provide overtime compensation to Plaintiff; (2) failure to provide compensation to Plaintiff for meal and rest periods; (3) failure to provide Plaintiff with certain amounts owed as commission payments; and (4) failure to provide Plaintiff with all wages due within 72 hours of termination. <ital>See</ital> FAC &#182;&#182; 33-40. Many of these claims are related and the viability of the second through fourth claims depend on the resolution of the first.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">California Labor Code &#167; 510(a) provides that work in excess of eight hours in one day and forty hours in one work week shall be compensated at certain overtime rates. Section 1171 expressly excludes from the overtime requirements &#x201C;any individual employed as an outside salesman.&#x201D; Cal. Labor Code &#167; 1171. The California Industrial Welfare Commission (IWC), the agency charged with implementing Section 1171, has defined the term &#x201C;outside salesperson&#x201D; as &#x201C;any person 18 years of age or over, who customarily and regularly works more than half the working time away from the employer's place of business selling tangible or intangible items or obtaining orders or contracts for products, services or use of facilities.&#x201D; Wage Order 4-2001(2)(J), codified at 8 Cal. Code Regs. 11070; <ital>Ramirez v. Yosemite Water Co., Inc.</ital>, 20 Cal.4th 785, 85 Cal. Rptr. 2d 844, 978 P.2d 2 (1999).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">The manner in which an employee distributed their hours during the day is a determination of fact, but the whether a particular activity or duty is &#x201C;exempt&#x201D; is a determination of law. <ital>Icicle Seafoods, Inc. v. Worthington</ital>, 475 U.S. 709, 714, 106 S.Ct. 1527 (1986). It is undisputed that Plaintiff was 18 years old and worked more than 50 percent of her time away from her workplace &#8211; her home office. <ital>See</ital> UF 10, 27, 30. The Court must therefore determine whether a genuine issue of material fact exists as to whether Plaintiff's activities and duties outside the workplace constituted the &#x201C;selling [of] tangible or intangible items or obtaining orders or contracts for products, services or use of facilities.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">Despite the dearth of cases addressing what it means to &#x201C;sell&#x201D; under Wage Order 4-2001, the California Supreme Court has provided general guidance that the court must consider the content of the employee's work and the expectations of the employer and employee. <ital>See Ramirez v. Yosemite Water Co., Inc.</ital>, 20 Cal.4th 785, 802 (1999) (stating that the &#x201C;court should consider, first and foremost, how the employee actually spends his or her time. [T]he trial court should also consider whether the employee's practice diverges from the employer's realistic expectations, whether there was any concrete expression of employer displeasure over an employee's substandard performance and whether those expressions were themselves realistic given the actual overall requirements of the job.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">In <ital>Brody v. Astra Pharms., LP</ital>, 2008 WL 6953957 (C.D. Cal. June 11, 2008), the court relied upon federal courts' application of the federal Fair Labor Standards Act (FLSA) outside salesperson exception, on the grounds that &#x201C;the California Labor Code was modeled on the [FLSA].&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at *4 (citing <ital>Monzon v. Schaefer Ambulance Serv., Inc.</ital>, 224 Cal. App. 3d 16, 31 (1990); <ital>Nordquist v. McGraw-Hill Broadcasting Co.</ital>, 32 Cal. App. 4th 555, 562 (1995); <ital>Vinole v. Countrywide Home Loans, Inc.</ital>, 246 F.R.D. 637 (S.D. Cal. 2007)). This Court agrees and adopts <ital>Brody</ital>'s approach as its own. The only distinction between the language in the FLSA and California Labor Code is that the latter identifies a percentage of time that must be spent outside the office to qualify as an outside salesperson. Since that issue is immaterial to the Court's analysis of what constitutes &#x201C;sales&#x201D; activity, the Court finds that the two statutes are sufficiently analogous that federal courts' prior consideration of this issue is instructive.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">In <ital>Nielsen v. DeVry, Inc.</ital>, 302 F. Supp. 2d 747 (W.D. Mich. 2003), the court identified a number of non-exclusive factors that may be applied when determining whether a particular activitiy constitutes &#x201C;sales activity&#x201D;: (1) &#x201C;[T]he job was advertised as a sales position and the employee was recruited based on sales experience and abilities; (2) &#x201C;Specialized sales training&#x201D;; (3) &#x201C;Compensation based wholly or in significant part on commissions&#x201D;; (4) &#x201C;Independently soliciting new business&#x201D;; and (5) &#x201C;[R]eceiving little or no direct or constant supervision in carrying out daily work tasks.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 756-58. These factors have been applied by a number of courts to determine whether an employee's activitiy fell under the outside salesperson exemption. <ital>See Barnick v. Wyeth</ital>, 522 F. Supp. 2d 1257 (C.D. Cal. 2007).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">The record demonstrates that VALIC expected that each FA would eventually make sales. For example, the mandatory training (which Plaintiff attended) directed each FA to &#x201C;use a sales process,&#x201D; &#x201C;guide a decision,&#x201D; &#x201C;build sales momentum&#x201D; and &#x201C;always focus on the sale.&#x201D; It refers to potential customers as &#x201C;prospects&#x201D; repeatedly uses the word &#x201C;close&#x201D; and giving people an &#x201C;excuse to buy&#x201D; as a basis for &#x201C;increas[ing] [ ] income.&#x201D; An entire section of the presentation is marked &#x201C;Needs-based sales process&#x201D; under which &#x201C;more sales and less prospecting&#x201D; is an identified priority. While it does confirm Plaintiff's claim &#8211; that FAs are encouraged to build relationships with customers which require servicing the customer relationship &#8211; one of the stated benefits of this policy is striking: &#x201C;Uncovering other cross-selling opportunities.&#x201D; The &#x201C;business model,&#x201D; which defines each FA's client interactions, proceeds with three &#x201C;sales&#x201D; according to a &#x201C;needs based sales process.&#x201D; The presentation reaches its conclusion with a fitting statement: &#x201C;ALWAYS ask for the sale.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">But determining the applicability of the outside salesperson exemption does not begin and end with employer expectations, a consideration the Court emphasized in denying class certification. In that Order, this Court noted the flexibility and entrepreneurial license afforded each VALIC FA. Plaintiff certainly exercised such license by, for example, engaging existing customers to shift from one line of financial services to another and providing investment advice.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Defendants proceed on the theory that all activity engaged in with a view to the sale of a product or service constitutes sales activity. There is authority for this theory. <ital>See Brody</ital>, 2008 WL 6953957, at *5 (rejecting theory that only &#x201C;consummation of sales&#x201D; can constitute sales activity); <ital>Ramirez</ital>, 20 Cal.4th at 802 (noting that activities incident to the sale of products may be classified as sales activity). But Plaintiff did more than partake in activities incident to the sale of certain products. For example, Plaintiff testified at deposition that she inherited certain accounts and held a meeting with existing VALIC customers at which she &#x201C;stress[ed] the safety of the company<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> reassur[ed] clients that their funds were safe for retirement moving forward, address[ed] questions about loss values and specific individual accounts that they had.&#x201D; <ital>See</ital> Perry Depo. Tr. at 71. Indeed, Plaintiff expressly identified one of her responsibilities as &#x201C;asset retention&#x201D; in response to a question about why her sales were not higher. <ital>See id.</ital> at 124. Moreover, Defendants' counsel spent considerable time at the deposition on Plaintiff's purported failure to service an existing client of VALIC (Pacific Hospital), which caused consternation on the part of Plaintiff's supervisors. <ital>See id.</ital> at 203-05. If anything, this claim &#8211; if true &#8211; demonstrates that Plaintiff was expected to not just sell products to new customers, but to service existing customers and provide reassurance about products already purchased by those customers.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">The examples of activities involving servicing as opposed to sales are legion. The Court nevertheless declines to enumerate each one on the basis of Plaintiff's deposition transcript and has chosen instead to highlight those examples most material to its analysis. Ultimately, Defendants' insight with respect to the motion to deny class certification provides the same basis upon which to deny summary judgment as to Plaintiff's overtime claims: it is simply insufficient to rely upon common training practices or commission structures. Once released into the field, the specific nature of the clients encountered by Plaintiff, the economic environment, and the products already in the clients' possession, required a blend of product sale and product servicing.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">Plaintiff highlights this point in her opposition to Defendants' statement of Uncontroverted Facts by noting that Plaintiff expected to also &#x201C;receive &#x2018;flow&#x2019; compensation designed to compensate [her] for time spent advising servicing [sic] potential clients.&#x201D; But Plaintiff did not receive heightened compensation for time spent after hours, even though she spent considerable amounts of time servicing existing client accounts, a fact that &#8211; if true &#8211; highlights the very purpose of the statute to ensure compensation for services rendered after the eight hour workday:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p34" first-line="1" turnover="1">[D]uring that period of time when I was employed with AIG, I was more involved with the transition from an annuity-based platform to a mutual fund platform with the Pacific Hospital group and all their subsequent satellites, and that was primarily a customer service function where I would collect documents to have them &#8211; that they had to sign to transition to the new platform or not. My purpose there was to advise and explain the transition. A great deal of time was spent on that with all my travels. And I would enroll participants.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p35" contd-flag="y"><ital>See</ital> Perry Depo. Tr. at 174-175.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Defendants' remaining arguments are unconvincing. First, in their Reply brief and at the hearing on this matter, Defendants highlighted Plaintiff's purported &#x201C;admission&#x201D; that 60-70 percent of her time was spent on sales tasks or other tasks incident to the sale of products. The relevant deposition testimony is as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p37" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">Q In terms of the total number of hours per week that you worked as a financial advisor, what percentage of the time were you working outside the office engaging in activities that were intended to result in the sale of financial products and services?</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A In terms of time spent away from home and while working, it was a combination of activities that I was involved in outside the home.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">Q Okay. But what I'm trying to figure out is what percentage of those activities outside of your home, outside of your office &#8211; what percent of the time did you spend engaged in activities that were intended to result in the sale of Valic or non-Valic financial products and services?</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A I guess I'd say &#8211; but, then again, this is just an estimate because I'm not certain in terms of quantifying it as a percentage of time &#8211; it could be between 60 to 70.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p41" contd-flag="y"><ital>See</ital> Perry Depo. Tr. at 243.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">Not only did Plaintiff express considerable confusion &#8211; both in her answer and a few minutes before, <ital>see id.</ital> at 242 &#8211; about counsel's unclear compound question, but even her answer was qualified with &#x201C;I'm not certain&#x201D; and &#x201C;could be.&#x201D; Moreover, Plaintiff's legal conclusion about the amount of time spent on sales activity contrasts the many specific examples she provided at deposition with respect to her client contact, including her servicing of existing clients, advice she rendered in encouraging clients to maintain investments with VALIC, and compensation she received for servicing client accounts.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">Second, Defendants argue that Plaintiff engages in &#x201C;semantics&#x201D; by segregating time spent &#x201C;advising&#x201D; or &#x201C;servicing&#x201D; versus &#x201C;selling,&#x201D; on the grounds that all of these activities &#x201C;had a direct relationship to an actual or attempted sale. <ital>See</ital> Reply at 2. This argument contradicts Defendants' acknowledgment, in their Supplementary Brief submitted in support of their motion to deny class certification, that at least some activities engaged in by VALIC FAs are <ital><bold>not</bold></ital> sales activities. In any event, the Court disagrees with Defendants' expansive logic: to hold that activities that merely maintain existing customer accounts are &#x201C;sales,&#x201D; because maintaining the customer relationship may result in future sales, renders the outside salesperson exception impermissibly broad. Almost any service function may benefit a customer relationship and benefit future sales. That does not mean that a serviceperson compensated on a &#x201C;flow&#x201D; commissions &#8211; which appear to resemble an hourly wage &#8211; should be categorized as a salesperson, nor have Defendants cited any authority for the proposition.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">Third, Defendants argue that &#x201C;outside salespersons must have the authority to commit a client to a binding contract, rather than merely solicit an application for sale, in order to qualify for the exemption.&#x201D; Mot. at 15 (citing <ital>Nielsen</ital>, 302 F. Supp. 2d at 754). But the ability to bind a client to sale is necessary but not sufficient to qualify as an outside salesperson. The same argument frustrates Defendants' apparent reliance on the fact that Plaintiff's clients had sufficient authority to consummate the transaction (or at least to buy). <ital>See</ital> Mot. at 16.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">Fourth, factual uncertainty exists as to whether Plaintiff was supervised. While most FAs do not receive blanket supervision, counsel for Defendants noted during Plaintiff's deposition that she received insight (and was reviewed) on the basis of her ability to interact with VALIC's existing clients.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court finds that a genuine issue of material fact exists as to whether Plaintiff was exempt under the outside salesperson exemption to the California Labor Code's overtime requirements. Plaintiff occupied a hybrid sales-servicing position and the precise percentage of time Plaintiff spent servicing clients as opposed to selling products to new or existing clients should be determined by a factfinder.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>2. Failure to Provide Meal and Rest Breaks</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p47" level="1">The second cause of action alleges that Defendants failed to compensate Plaintiff for the one hour meal break she was entitled to as a matter of California law. California Labor Code &#167;&#167; 226.7 and 512 require that an employer provide periodic paid meal and rest periods to employees.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p48" level="1">The requirement does not apply to exempt employees. <ital>See</ital> IWC Wage Order 9-2001. Thus, for much the same reasons the Court denied summary judgment as to the first cause of action, the Court finds that genuine issues of material fact exist as to Plaintiff's claim for lost meal and rest breaks.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">Defendants argue that an employer is not obligated to provide such breaks. But that is a red-herring. Plaintiff does not argue that Defendants violated the California statute by failing to force her to take meal breaks, but by subjecting her to a client schedule which precluded her from taking such meal breaks at all. And the fact that Plaintiff took a meal break during her training session is not germane to the availability of meal and rest breaks during the time she was actually employed by VALIC.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>3. Failure to Provide Itemized Wage Statements</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">The third cause of action alleges that Defendants violated California Labor Code &#167; 226(a), which in relevant part requires that an employer issue an itemized wage statement showing gross wages earned, total number of hours worked for hourly wage employees, deductions, and net wages earned. Neither party disputes that Defendants' wage statements did not comply with these requirements.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p51" level="1">Though exempt employees need not receive such wage statements, <ital>see</ital> Cal. Labor Code &#167; 226(a), the Court's prior analysis renders this claim unripe for summary judgment. First, Defendants claim that they acted in good faith that Plaintiff was exempt is unavailing as a matter of law. <ital>See Lopez v. UPS</ital>, No. C 08-05396 SI, 2010 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 26072 (N.D. Cal. March 1, 2010). Second, Plaintiff need not have suffered economic injury in order to bring a claim under the statute. <ital>See Wang v. Chinese Daily News, Inc.</ital>, 435 F. Supp. 2d 1042, 1050-51 (C.D. Cal. 2006).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p52" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court finds that a genuine issue of material fact precludes summary judgment as to the third cause of action.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>4. Section 17200</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p53" level="1">The fourth cause of action alleges that Defendants' violated California Business and Professions code section 17200, <ital>et seq.</ital> The only grounds upon which Defendants move for summary judgment as to this cause of action is that the prior causes of action fail as a matter of law. The Court's analysis as to the first cause of action therefore disposes of Defendants' arguments and summary judgment is DENIED as to the fourth cause of action.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>5. Summary Judgment as to AIG</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p54" level="1">Finally, Defendants move for summary judgment as to AIG on the grounds that AIG did not employ Plaintiff. However, for the reasons identified in Plaintiff's opposition, this is far from clear: the offer letter identified AIG, Plaintiff serviced AIG accounts, Plaintiff received an AIG email address, and Plaintiff was subject to AIG's conditions. And Defendants have offered scant documentary evidence as to the authority that compensated Plaintiff.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. Disposition</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p55" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court DENIES the Motion.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p56" level="0">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p57" level="0">DATED: April 26, 2010</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>