<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><underscore>CIVIL MINUTES &#8212; GENERAL</underscore></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>JAMES F. DODARO, as an individual and on behalf of all others similarly situated</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>STANDARD PACIFIC CORP., et al.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. EDCV 09-1666-VAP (OPx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>EDCV 09-1666-VAP (OPx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">5:09-cv-01666-VAP-DTB</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 11/16/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Marva Dillard, Courtroom Deputy, ATTORNEYS PRESENT FOR PLAINTIFFS: None</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">None Present, Court Reporter, ATTORNEYS PRESENT FOR DEFENDANTS: None</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">PROCEEDINGS: MINUTE ORDER DENYING PLAINTIFF'S MOTION TO CONSOLIDATE (IN CHAMBERS)</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">HONORABLE VIRGINIA A. PHILLIPS, U.S. DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Plaintiff James F. Dodaro's (&#x201C;Plaintiff&#x201D; or &#x201C;Dodaro&#x201D;) &#x201C;Motion to Consolidate All Homebuilder Class Action Cases to Proceed Before Judge Virginia A. Phil[l]ips&#x201D; (&#x201C;Motion&#x201D;) came before the Court for hearing on November 16, 2009. After reviewing and considering all papers filed in support of, and in opposition to, the Motion, the Court DENIES Defendant Plaintiff's Motion, with leave to amend. As indicated at the hearing, however, the Court intends to accept transfer of the Homebuilder Class Action Cases.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On September 3, 2009, Plaintiffs' counsel filed eight putative class action lawsuits against eight homebuilders and their related entities. (Mot. at 2-3.) The eight actions (collectively, the &#x201C;Homebuilder Actions&#x201D;), pending in the Central District, Eastern Division are as follows:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p3" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">&#8226; <underscore>Dodaro v. Standard Pacific Corp., et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1666-VAP (OPx)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">&#8226; <underscore>Stephens, et al. v. Lennar Corp, et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1668-SGL (DTBx)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">&#8226; <underscore>Lamalu et al. v. Richmond American Homes Corp., et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1669-SGL (OPx)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">&#8226; <underscore>Oneto v. The Ryland Group, Inc., et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1670-SGL (DBTx)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">&#8226; <underscore>Maya, et al. v. Centex Corp., et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1671-SGL (OPx)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">&#8226; <underscore>Martinez, et al. v. D.R. Horton, et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1672-VAP (DBTx)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">&#8226; <underscore>Nielson, et al. v. Shea Homes, Inc, et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1673-SGL (DTBx)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" first-line="0" turnover="hanging">&#8226; <underscore>Kelly, et al. v. Beazer Homes USA, Inc., et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1674-SGL (DTBx)</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p11" contd-flag="y">The eight cases involve 26 defendants, and no defendant is named in more than one lawsuit. (Richard McCune Decl. (&#x201C;McCune Decl.&#x201D;) &#182; 4.) The defendants are eight homebuilders and their affiliated entities, such as mortgage affiliates and their parent companies. The eight defendant homebuilders are: (1) Standard Pacific; (2) D.R. Horton; (3) Lennar; (4) Richmond American; (5) Ryland; (6) Centex; (7) Beazer; and (8) Shea.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Each action also names a Plaintiff or Plaintiffs. All Plaintiffs share common counsel &#8212; McCune Wright LLP. Plaintiffs in the Homebuilder Actions allege identical causes of action: (1) fraud; (2) negligent misrepresentation; (3) violation of California's Unfair Business Practices Act, Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167;&#167; 17200, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>; (4) violation of Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167;&#167; 17500, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>; and (5) breach of the implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">The eight complaints also allege that the defendant homebuilders provided loans to &#x201C;unqualified buyers that posed an abnormally high risk of foreclosure to increase both the number of sales and the price of houses in the same neighborhoods that Defendants were selling houses to traditionally qualified and low-foreclosure-risk buyers.&#x201D; (<underscore>See, e.g.</underscore>, Compl. &#182; 14.) Plaintiffs allege that Defendants &#x201C;accomplished this through high pressure sales tactics, and then through their mortgage company, Defendants encouraged and assisted buyers in obtaining mortgages they were unqualified to obtain.&#x201D; (Compl. &#182; 15.) &#x201C;[O]ver time, these unqualified and high-foreclosure-risk buyers began to default on their loans leading to foreclosures and short sales. These foreclosures and short sales of properties were significantly below market value and depressed the value of the houses of the qualified and low-foreclosure-risk buyers.&#x201D; (Compl. &#182; 25.) Plaintiffs are qualified and low-foreclosure-risk homeowners whose property values were negatively affected by foreclosures in their neighborhoods.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">On October 23, 2009, Plaintiff James F. Dodaro, ED09-CV1666-VAP (OPx), filed a &#x201C;Motion to Consolidate All Homebuilder Class Action Cases to Proceed Before Judge Virginia A. Phil[l]ips[,]&#x201D; requesting consolidation of the eight Homebuilder Actions &#x201C;for all pretrial purposes.&#x201D; (Mot. at 2.) On October 26, 2009, Plaintiff Remedios Martinez, ED09-CV1672-VAP (DTBx), filed a nearly identical Motion. In response, Defendants filed the following Motions:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p15" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">1. On November 5, 2009, Standard Pacific Corp., Standard Pacific Homes, Inc., and Standard Pacific Mortgage, Inc. (collectively, &#x201C;Standard Pacific Defendants&#x201D;), defendants in case no. ED09-CV1666-VAP (OPx), filed a &#x201C;Position&#x201D; (&#x201C;Standard Pacific Position&#x201D;), noting that five of the eight homebuilders involved in the Homebuilder Actions opposed Plaintiffs' Motion and &#x201C;expressed their views that consolidation is not warranted at this juncture.&#x201D; (Standard Pacific Position at 2.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">2. On November 2, 2009, Lennar Corporation, Lennar Homes of California, Inc., Universal American Mortgage Co., and Eagle Home Mortgage of California, Inc. (collectively, &#x201C;Lennar Defendants&#x201D;), defendants in case no. ED09-CV1668 SGL (DTBx), filed Opposition (&#x201C;Lennar Opp'n&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">3. On November 2, 2009, Ryland Group, Inc., Ryland Homes of California, Inc., and Ryland Mortgage Company (collectively, &#x201C;Ryland Defendants&#x201D;), defendants in case no. ED09-CV1670 SGL (DTBx), filed Opposition (&#x201C;Ryland Opp'n&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">4. On November 2, 2009, DHI Mortgage Company GP, Inc. (&#x201C;DHI Defendant&#x201D;), defendant in case ED09-CV1672 VAP (DTBx), filed Opposition (&#x201C;DHI Opp'n&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">5. On November 2, 2009, Shea Homes, Inc., J.F. Shea Co., Inc., and Shea Mortgage Inc. (collectively, &#x201C;Shea Defendants&#x201D;), defendants in case no. ED09-CV-1673 SGL (SDFx), filed a &#x201C;Certification and Notice of Interested Parties&#x201D; and &#x201C;<underscore>Amicus</underscore> Opposition to Plaintiff James Dodardo's Motion to Consolidate Homebuilder Class Action Cases&#x201D; (&#x201C;Shea Opp'n&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">6. On November 2, 2009, Beazer Homes USA, Inc., Beazer Homes Holdings Corp., and Beazer Mortgage Corporation (collectively, &#x201C;Beazer Defendants&#x201D;), defendants in case no. ED09-CV 1674 SGL (DTBx), filed Opposition (&#x201C;Beazer Opp'n&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p21" contd-flag="y">None of the Plaintiffs has filed a &#x201C;Notice of Related Cases,&#x201D; as required by L.R. 83-1.3.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> On November 9, 2009, Plaintiffs filed a Reply.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p22">&#8195;Local Rule 83-1.3 provides: &#x201C;At the time a civil action<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> is filed, or as soon as known thereafter, the attorney shall file and serve on all parties who have appeared a Notice of Related Case(s), stating whether any action previously filed or currently pending in the Central District and the action being filed appear:</paratext>
<paratext ID="p23" contd-flag="y" first-line="1" turnover="0">(a) To arise from the same or a closely related transaction, happening or event; or</paratext>
<paratext ID="p24" contd-flag="y" first-line="1" turnover="0">(b) To call for determination of the same or substantially related or similar questions of law and fact; or</paratext>
<paratext ID="p25" contd-flag="y" first-line="1" turnover="0">(c) For other reasons would entail substantial duplication of labor if heard by different judges; or</paratext>
<paratext ID="p26" contd-flag="y" first-line="1" turnover="0">(d) To involve the same patent, trademark or copyright, and one of the factors identified above in a, b or c is present.</paratext>
<paratext ID="p27" contd-flag="y" first-line="1" turnover="0">The Notice of Related Case(s) shall also include a brief factual statement setting forth the basis for the attorney's belief that the action qualifies for related case transfer.</paratext>
<paratext ID="p28" contd-flag="y" first-line="1" turnover="0">The Notice of Related Case also shall be served concurrently with service of the complaint.&#x201D;</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. LEGAL STANDARD</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Rule 42 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure provides:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" first-line="1" turnover="1">If actions before the court involve a common question of law or fact, the court may:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p31" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(1) join for hearing or trial any or all matters at issue in the actions;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(2) consolidate the actions; or</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(3) issue any other orders to avoid unnecessary cost or delay.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p34" contd-flag="y">Fed. R. Civ. P. 42(a). The existence of common issues, while a prerequisite to consolidation, does not compel consolidation. <underscore>Dusky v. Bellasaire Invs.</underscore>, No. SACV07-874 DOC (ANx), 2007 WL 4403985, at *1 (C.D. Cal. Dec. 4, 2007), citing <underscore>Waste Distillation Tech., Inc. v. Pan Am. Res., Inc.</underscore>, 775 F. Supp. 759, 761 (D. Del. 1991); <underscore>Rohm &#38; Haas Co. v. Mobil Oil Corp.</underscore>, 525 F. Supp. 1298, 1309 (D. Del. 1981). &#x201C;The district court has broad discretion under this rule to consolidate cases pending in the same district[,]&#x201D; even when actions are pending before different judges. <underscore>Investors Research Co. v. U.S. Dist. Court for Cent. Dist. of Cal.</underscore>, 877 F.2d 777, 777 (9th Cir. 1989).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">In exercising its broad discretion to consolidate actions, &#x201C;the district court must weigh the saving of time and effort that would be produced by consolidation against any inconvenience, delay, or expense that it would cause.&#x201D; <underscore>Lancer Ins. Co. v. W. Distrib. Co.</underscore>, No. 08-CV-8084-PCT-PGR, 2009 WL 86707, at *1 (D. Ariz. Jan. 13, 2009), citing <underscore>Huene v. U.S.</underscore>, 743 F.2d 703, 704 (9th Cir. 1984). The party moving for consolidation bears the burden of demonstrating that consolidation is appropriate, including showing the benefits outweigh any prejudice caused to the opponent of consolidation. <underscore>Single Chip Sys. Corp. v. Intermec IP Corp.</underscore>, 495 F. Supp. 2d 1052, 1057 (S.D. Cal. 2007); <underscore>Dusky</underscore>, 2007 WL 4403985, at *1.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>III. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Plaintiff requests that the Court consolidate the eight Homebuilder Actions for pretrial matters, arguing they involve identical questions of law and common issues of fact. As the lowest numbered case, Plaintiffs argue consolidation is appropriate in this Court. (Mot. at 4.) Defendants contend that consolidation is improper because the Homebuilder Actions involve distinct underlying facts, and consolidation would delay the proceedings and prejudice Defendants.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Legal Issues</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">Plaintiffs argue that the eight Homebuilder Actions involve identical legal issues because they allege identical causes of action. The eight complaints allege five identical causes of action: (1) fraud; (2) negligent misrepresentation; (3) violation of California's Unfair Business Practices Act, Cal. Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167;&#167; 17200, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>; (4) violation of Cal Bus. &#38; Prof. Code &#167;&#167; 17500, <underscore>et seq.</underscore>; and (5) breach of the implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">While the claims are identical, each defendant employed different contracts in different transactions, which may give rise to the application of different law. Furthermore, Defendants argue that distinct defenses will arise because of the distinct facts underlying the claims. (<underscore>See</underscore> Lennar Opp'n at 6-7.) Thus, while the claims in the eight complaints are identical, the underlying distinct facts may give rise to disparate legal issues. <underscore>See Flintkote Co. v. Allis-Chalmers Corp.</underscore>, 73 F.R.D. 463, 465 (S.D.N.Y. 1977) (&#x201C;the mere fact that two cases assert similar theories of recovery does not constitute a common question of law so as to warrant consolidation.&#x201D;) Thus, this factor weighs against granting consolidation.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Factual Allegations</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">Plaintiffs argue that consolidation is appropriate because the factual allegations in the putative class actions &#x201C;are nearly identical.&#x201D; (Mot. at 4.) Defendants dispute this and point to the following factual distinctions between the eight actions: (1) different Plaintiffs; (2) different Defendants; (3) different transactions involving different contracts; (4) different witnesses; (5) different marketing, sales, lending, and business practices; (6) different properties; (7) different geographical locations; and (8) different business records and files. (Beazer Opp'n at 1-2; DHI Opp'n at 3-4; Standard Pacific Opp'n at 5-6; Lennar Opp'n at 8-9.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">What these actions do have in common is not underlying factual allegations, but the legal theory: that defendant homebuilders &#x201C;had a duty under California law to disclose [facts about unqualified, high-risk home buyers] to plaintiffs and putative class members<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> who were traditionally qualified and put at least 20% down payment on the house.&#x201D; (Mot. at 2.) This novel claim is of such generality that there are a number of potential causes other than the Defendants' alleged conduct. <underscore>See In re Repetitive Stress Injury Litigation</underscore>, 11 F.3d 368, 373 (2d Cir. 1993) (reversing district court consolidation of 44 repetitive stress cases where plaintiffs were employed at different worksites, in different occupations, and experienced different ailments, which &#x201C;may have [had] a cause other than the tortious conduct of an individual defendant much less all the defendants.&#x201D;); <underscore>Flintkote</underscore>, 73 F.R.D. at 465 (denying consolidation where the contracts at issue were similar in some ways, but were dissimilar in a number of important aspects).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">Furthermore, the cases Plaintiffs cite in support consolidation are distinguishable from the facts here. In <underscore>Jacobs v. Castillo</underscore>, 612 F. Supp. 2d 369 (S.D.N.Y. 2009), the court consolidated two medical malpractice cases brought by a mother and son, arising from an injury she suffered. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 373. The court granted consolidation because the two cases involved the same two plaintiffs, the same legal claims, the same time frame, and some of the same defendants. <underscore>Id.</underscore> While <underscore>Jacobs</underscore> involved substantial overlap of parties, claims, and issues, the eight Homebuilder Actions were brought by different plaintiffs, have no common defendants, and are factually distinct.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">In <underscore>Attala Hydratane Gas, Inc. v. Lowry Tims Co.</underscore>, 41 F.R.D. 164 (N.D. Miss. 1966), the court consolidated three antitrust cases involving the same defendant and substantial common issues of law and fact. Here, unlike <underscore>Attala</underscore>, the eight Homebuilder actions involve 26 different defendants and 12 different plaintiffs. While the legal allegations in the complaints are identical, the underlying factual allegations are distinct because each case is based on different conduct involving different parties.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">The facts here similar to <underscore>Jackson v. Ford Consumer Finance Co., Inc.</underscore>, 181 F.R.D. 537 (N.D. Ga. 1998), in which plaintiffs moved to consolidate for pretrial purposes 19 putative class actions against 18 lenders. Each action alleged that individual lenders made payments to mortgage loan brokers in violation of federal law. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 539. Although the plaintiffs alleged identical legal theories of recovery, the court held that because &#x201C;[m]ortgage transactions are structured in a variety of ways,&#x201D; liability would be &#x201C;highly dependent upon the facts of [the particular] financial transaction.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore>, citing <underscore>Culpepper v. Inland Mortgage Corp.</underscore>, 132 F.3d 692, 697 n.5 (11th Cir. 1998). The court denied consolidation because plaintiffs failed to show &#x201C;that the transactions at issue or these lenders' practices are so similar that any economies can be achieved by consolidating these cases for pre-trial procedures.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 539-40. In the absence of such a showing, &#x201C;the fact that liability is dependent upon the facts of each individual transaction counsels against the confusion and duplication of effect that would undoubtedly result from the participation of 18 different lenders in discovery and pre-trial matters regarding transactions as to which all but one or two of those lenders have no relation.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 540.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">As in <underscore>Jackson</underscore>, Plaintiffs here seek to consolidate actions predicated on a legal theory that is &#x201C;highly dependent on the facts of [the particular] financial transaction.&#x201D; <underscore>Jackson</underscore>, 181 F.R.D. at 539. For example, in <underscore>Dodaro v. Standard Pacific Corp, et al.</underscore>, ED09-CV1666 VAP (OPx), Plaintiff James F. Dodaro alleges that the Standard Pacific Defendants failed to adequately disclose that &#x201C;Defendants had sold houses<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> to unqualified and high-foreclosure-risk buyers.&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> Compl. &#182;&#182; 32-35.) Whether Defendants made adequate disclosures depends on, among other things, particular communications made by Defendants in sales materials, purchase agreements, and disclosures. Each case contains similar allegations. Yet, each Defendants' sales materials, purchase agreements and disclosures are different, so it is unlikely that there will be any overlap between the Plaintiffs' fraud and misrepresentation claims. As the Defendants' liability depends upon facts related to each individual transaction, the confusion and duplication that would undoubtedly result from the participation of eight different homebuilders and 26 different defendants in discovery and pretrial matters regarding transactions to which the other homebuilders have no relation counsels against consolidation. <underscore>See Jackson</underscore>, 181 F.R.D. at 540. Thus, Plaintiffs have failed to demonstrate that the transactions at issue are so similar that any economies can be achieved. This factor, therefore, weighs against granting consolidation.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Judicial Efficiency and Prejudice to Defendants</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">Plaintiffs argue that &#x201C;consolidation would promote judicial efficiency and avoid inconsistent adjudications.&#x201D; (Mot. at 4.) Further, Plaintiffs allege that all named plaintiffs support consolidation of the Homebuilder Actions. (Mot. at 5.) Given the early stage of litigation, Plaintiffs reason that Defendants should not be prejudiced by consolidation. (Mot. at 5.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p46" level="1">Defendants counter that consolidation will not advance judicial efficiency, but rather will &#x201C;lead to inefficiencies and exponentially increase the cost of litigation.&#x201D; (DHI Opp'n at 5.) In addition to increased costs, Defendants argue they would be prejudiced by being forced to produce proprietary information to their competitors during discovery. (Shea Opp'n at 5; DHI Opp'n at 5-7; Beazer Opp'n at 2.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p47" level="1">Even when consolidation may enhance judicial efficiency, &#x201C;[c]onsiderations of convenience and economy must yield to a paramount concern for a fair and impartial trial.&#x201D; <underscore>Johnson v. Celotex Corp.</underscore>, 899 F.2d 1281, 1285 (2d Cir. 1990), <underscore>cert. denied</underscore>, 498 U.S. 920 (1990). &#x201C;The systemic urge to aggregate litigation must not be allowed to trump our dedication to individual justice, and we must take care that each individual plaintiff's &#8212; and defendant's &#8212; cause not be lost in the shadow of a towering mass litigation.&#x201D; <underscore>In re Brooklyn Navy Yard Asbestos Litig.</underscore>, 971 F.2d 831, 853 (2d Cir. 1992).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p48" level="1">As noted above, the transactions and contracts are dissimilar in a number of important aspects, which makes it unlikely that consolidation will save time or expense. <underscore>See Flintkote</underscore>, 73 F.R.D. at 465. Further Defendants illustrate several ways in which consolidation would prejudice them. First, Defendants argue they will be prejudiced by being forced to share proprietary information during discovery. &#x201C;[T]he eight homebuilders are well known to be direct competitors of one another in the industry, particularly in the California market. Thus, consolidation of discovery &#8212; ordinarily one of the primary divers of judicial efficiency &#8212; is unlikely to be achieved here.&#x201D; (<underscore>See</underscore> Shea Opp'n at 5; DHI Opp'n at 5-7; Beazer Opp'n at 2 (noting that &#x201C;defendants in the Homebuilder Cases are competitors[,]&#x201D; so &#x201C;consolidation would prejudice each defendant if discovery is consolidated, and all defendants had access to each other's proprietary business information, including marketing strategies and related information.&#x201D;).) <underscore>See Jackson</underscore>, 181 F.R.D. at 537 (denying consolidation because, among other reasons, the defendants were competitors, so consolidation for pretrial purposes raised concerns about possible inappropriate disclosure of defendants' confidential commercial information.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">Additionally, Defendants argue that consolidation will force all Defendants to participate in discovery unrelated to their case, which thereby will increase litigation costs. (DHI Opp'n at 5; Lennar Opp'n at 5-6.) The costs of participating in discovery of eight actions &#8212; rather than in one action &#8212; would increase the cost of litigation significantly for each defendant and likely delay trial. (DHI Opp'n at 5.) If the actions remain separate, however, the parties would participate in discovery related only to the projects constructed by the specific defendant homebuilders in that action.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p50" level="1">Finally, Defendants argue they would be prejudiced &#x201C;in not being able to litigate these claims as they deem in their best interests<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> [The Defendants] should be able to bring motions, take discovery, <underscore>et cetera</underscore>, as they see fit, rather than being restricted by others.&#x201D; (Beazer Opp'n at 2; <underscore>see also</underscore> DHI Opp'n at 6-7, citing <underscore>Habitat Educ. Ctr., Inc. v. Kimbell</underscore>, 250 F.R.D. 390, 395 (E.D. Wis. 2008) (&#x201C;Consolidated briefs and other filings would only complicate this already complex litigation by blurring the distinctions between the projects.&#x201D;).)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p51" level="1">&#x201C;A party may not use aggregation as a method of increasing the costs of its adversaries &#8212; whether plaintiffs or defendants &#8212; by forcing them to participate in discovery or other proceedings that are irrelevant to their case. It may be that such increased costs would make settlement easier to achieve, but that would occur only at the cost of elemental fairness.&#x201D; <underscore>In re Repetitive Stress Injury Litigation</underscore>, 11 F.3d at 373. Here, even if consolidation were more judicially efficient, a proposition of which the Court is not convinced, consolidation would force Defendants to expose their proprietary information to their competitors and to participate in substantial discovery that is irrelevant to their cases. In light of the questionable benefits of consolidation here and the potential prejudice to Defendants, Plaintiffs have not met their burden of demonstrating consolidation is appropriate.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>D. Procedural Deficiencies</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p52" level="1">The Ryland Defendants raise several procedural deficiencies related to these Motions. First, they state that Plaintiffs' counsel failed to timely meet and confer as required by Local Rule 7-3. (Ryland Opp'n at 2-3, 4.) Secondly, they argue that the Court should decline to consolidate the Homebuilder Actions because their action &#x201C;belongs in the Western Division of this Court.&#x201D; (Ryland Opp'n at 5.) As the Court reached its decision to deny the Motions on the merits, it need not reach the procedural issues raised here.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p53" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court DENIES Plaintiffs' Motions to Consolidate, without prejudice. As indicated at the hearing, however, the Court intends to accept transfer of the Homebuilder Actions.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p54" level="1"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED.</bold></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>