<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>FARHAD FAZLI DBA FOUNTAIN VALLEY 76, et al., Plaintiffs,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>CONOCOPHILLIPS COMPANY, Defendant.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. 2:03-cv-04938-FMC-VBKx</docket.line>
<docket.number>2:03-cv-04938-FMC-VBKx</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:03-cv-04938-FMC-VBK</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 09/23/2008</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">ORDER GRANTING DEFENDANT'S MOTION FOR SUMMARY JUDGMENT</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">FLORENCE-MARIE COOPER, JUDGE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">This matter is before the Court on Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment (docket no. 147), filed on August 13, 2008. The Court has considered the moving, opposition and reply documents submitted in connection with the Motion. The Court deems this matter appropriate for decision without oral argument. <ital>See</ital> Fed. R. Civ. P. 78(b); Local Rule 7-15. The hearing set for September 29, 2008, is removed from the Court's calendar. For the reasons and in the manner set forth below, Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment is GRANTED.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. FACTUAL BACKGROUND AND PROCEDURAL HISTORY</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">The facts of this case are familiar to the parties and will be recited only as necessary to elucidate an issue. On November 23, 2004, this Court granted Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment, finding that although the appraised value of the subject gas station was in dispute, Defendant had nonetheless complied with the requirements of the Petroleum Marketing Practices Act (&#x201C;PMPA&#x201D;), because it had given Plaintiff a right of first refusal after it received an offer from a third party to purchase the property. The Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals found that the right of first refusal had not been timely given, and could not, therefore, support a finding of compliance with the PMPA. The Court of Appeals remanded, instructing this Court to &#x201C;determine whether the offer satisfied &#167;2802(b)(3)(D)(iii)(I) (<ital>i.e.</ital>, whether the offer was &#x201C;bona fide&#x201D;).&#x201D;</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. APPLICABLE LEGAL STANDARD</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">Summary judgment is appropriate if there is no genuine issue of material fact and the moving party is entitled to judgment as a matter of law. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c). The moving party bears the initial responsibility of informing the court of the basis of its motion, and identifying those portions of &#x201C;&#x2018;pleadings, depositions, answers to interrogatories, and admissions on file, together with the affidavits, if any,&#x2019; which it believes demonstrate the absence of a genuine issue of material fact.&#x201D; <ital>Celotex Corp. v. Catrett</ital>, 477 U.S. 317, 323, 106 S. Ct. 2548, 91 L. Ed. 2d 265 (1986) (quoting Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(c)). Where the nonmoving party will have the burden of proof at trial, the movant can prevail merely by pointing out that there is an absence of evidence to support the nonmoving party's case. <ital>See id.; see also Nissan Fire &#38; Marine Ins. Co. v. Fritz Cos.</ital>, 210 F.3d 1099, 1106 (9th Cir. 2000) (&#x201C;In order to carry its burden of production, the moving party must either produce evidence negating an essential element of the nonmoving party's claim or defense or show that the nonmoving party does not have enough evidence of an essential element to carry its burden of persuasion at trial.&#x201D;). If the moving party meets its initial burden, the nonmoving party must then set forth, by affidavit or as otherwise provided in Rule 56, &#x201C;specific facts showing that there is a genuine issue for trial.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(e); <ital>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc.</ital>, 477 U.S. 242, 250, 106 S. Ct. 2505, 91 L. Ed. 2d 202 (1986).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">The substantive law governing a claim determines whether a fact is material. <ital>T.W. Elec. Serv. v. Pac. Elec. Contractors Ass'n</ital>, 809 F.2d 626, 630 (9th Cir. 1987); <ital>see also Long v. County of Los Angeles</ital>, 442 F.3d 1178, 1185 (9th Cir. 2006) (&#x201C;Material facts are those which may affect the outcome of the case.&#x201D;) (internal citations omitted). In judging evidence at the summary judgment stage, the Court does not make credibility determinations or weigh conflicting evidence and draws all reasonable inferences in the light most favorable to the nonmoving party. <ital>T.W. Elec. Serv.</ital>, 809 F.2d at 630-31; <ital>see also Brookside Assocs. v. Rifkin</ital>, 49 F.3d 490, 492-93 (9th Cir. 1995). The evidence presented by the parties must be admissible. Fed. R. Civ. P. 56(e). Mere disagreement or the bald assertion that a genuine issue of material fact exists does not preclude the use of summary judgment. <ital>Harper v. Wallingford</ital>, 877 F.2d 728, 731 (9th Cir. 1989).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>III. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Defendant seeks summary judgment on Plaintiff's PMPA claim, unfair business practices claim pursuant to California Business and Profession Code Section 17200 <ital>et seq.</ital>, and claim for declaratory relief.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p6">&#8195;The Court previously granted summary judgment in favor of Defendant on Plaintiff's claims for breach of contract and breach of covenant of good faith and fair dealing. Plaintiff did not appeal those claims.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Petroleum Marketing Practices Act</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">An offer by a franchisor to a franchisee is considered &#x201C;bona fide&#x201D; for purposes of the PMPA if it approaches the fair market value of the property. <ital>Ellis v. Mobil Oil</ital>, 969 F.2d. 784, 787 (9th Cir. 1992). &#x201C;Fair market value is, by necessity, best set by the market itself. An actual price, agreed to by a willing buyer and a willing seller, is the most accurate gauge of the value the market places on a good.&#x201D; <ital>Keener v. Exxon Co., USA</ital>, 32 F.3d 127, 132 (4th Cir. 1994).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Whether an offer to sell a piece of property is bona fide within the meaning of the statute is measured by an objective standard. <ital>Ellis</ital>, 969 F.2d. at 787; <ital>Rhodes</ital>, 143 F.3d at 1372. The offering price &#x201C;should reflect what a willing purchaser would pay for the fee title of the land, the improvements, and the equipment of the terminated franchise.&#x201D; <ital>Ellis</ital>, 969 F.2d. at 788. However, because the test of whether an offer is bona fide measures whether the offer &#x201C;approached&#x201D; fair market value, the test is a flexible one, and a &#x201C;range of prices may have a reasonable claim to being [<ital>i.e.</ital>, approaching] fair market value.&#x201D; <ital>Slatky v. Amoco Oil Co.</ital>, 830 F.2d. 476, 485 (3rd Cir. 1987). As the Tenth Circuit explained about a district court's review on remand:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p9" first-line="2" turnover="1">On remand the district court in <ital>Slatky</ital> received evidence to the effect that appraisers attempt to get within 5% of the anticipated actual selling price; that selling prices can vary from 25% over to 25% under offering price; that properties are often sold at 15% to 20% over the appraised price; that two appraisers attempting to estimate fair market value should reach results within 10% to 15% of each other; and that the expected variation between appraisals could be greater when using the replacement cost approach. <ital>Slatky v. Amoco Oil Co.</ital>, 626 F.Supp. 1223 (M.D.Pa. 1989) (order denying motion for reconsideration of order granting injunctive relief).</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p10" contd-flag="y"><ital>Rhodes v. Amoco Oil Co.</ital>, 143 F.3d 1369, 1374 (10th Cir. 1998).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Here, both sides have presented evidence on the question of the fair market value of the property in question. Plaintiff contends that summary judgment is inappropriate in this case, because the evidence is in dispute, and there is, therefore, a triable issue of fact on the question of value.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p12">&#8195;Plaintiff also argues that the Court, in its earlier order, conceded as much. The Court does not agree. Although the Court acknowledged that the evidence was in conflict, it did not evaluate that evidence nor determine whether the appraisals were too disparate to allow resolution by summary judgment.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">The following evidence has been presented on the issue of the fair market value of the subject property. In 2002, Defendant obtained an appraisal of the property (a gas station being operated by Plaintiff), at $980,000. On April 22, 2003, after having given Plaintiff notice of its intent not to renew Plaintiff's lease, Defendant submitted to Plaintiff a &#x201C;Bona Fide Offer to Sell&#x201D; the property to Plaintiff for $980,000, based on the appraisal it had obtained about a year earlier.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">In May 2003, Plaintiff obtained an appraisal, which valued the property at $745,000.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">In June 2003, Defendant received an offer from a third party, Glenwood Development Company (&#x201C;GDC&#x201D;) to purchase the property for $890,000.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Finally, in May 2004, Plaintiff received an offer from an Abe Kaabipour to purchase the property for $980,000.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Defendant emphasizes the fact that it received an offer to purchase the property for the exact amount of their earlier appraisal. However, the $980,000 purchase offer was made a year after Defendant's offer to sell to Plaintiff for $980,000. Accordingly, the Court looks to the contemporaneous May 2003 appraisal ($745,000) and June 2003 purchase offer ($890,000) to determine whether a genuine issue of material fact exists about the reasonableness of Defendant's $980,000 offering price, <ital>i.e.</ital> whether the $980,000 offering price approached fair market value.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The existence of competing appraisals or offers does not necessarily preclude summary judgment, but the magnitude of the difference between competing valuations may. <ital>Rhodes</ital>, 143 F.3d. at 1372-73 (reversing grant of summary judgment premised on a determination that bona fide offer to sell was made to a franchisee); <ital>but see also Anand v. BP West Coast Products LLC</ital>, 484 F.Supp.2d. 1086 (C.D.Cal. 2007) (granting summary judgment to franchisor where difference or &#x201C;spread&#x201D; between the offering price and the franchisee's appraisal was &#x201C;merely sixteen or nineteen percent&#x201D;). Two cases decided by the Tenth Circuit are illustrative.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">In <ital>Sandlin</ital>, the court reversed judgment for the franchisee after a jury trial, holding that there was no evidence from which the jury could have found that the franchisor's offer was not bona fide. <ital>Sandlin v. Texaco Refining and Marketing Inc.</ital>, 900 F.2d 1479, 1482 (10th Cir. 1990). The franchisor's offer to sell at $216,000 was viewed in the context of appraisals the franchisee had obtained ranging from $200,000 to $233,535; the fact that the $216,000 offer comprised $200,000 for the land and $16,000 for the equipment on the land; and the fact that the franchisor received a purchase offer of $260,000 from another entity after the franchisee refused the $216,000. <ital>Id.</ital> The Tenth Circuit determined that, even in light of the competing valuations, the $216,000 offering price &#x201C;remain[ed] objectively reasonable as a reflection of fair market value[,]&#x201D; which the court explained &#x201C;by definition, is the highest price a willing buyer would pay.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> The court remanded the case with instructions to enter judgment for the franchisor. <ital>Id.</ital> at 1483.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">In contrast, in <ital>Rhodes</ital>, considering &#x201C;the evidence and reasonable inferences therefrom,&#x201D; the Tenth Circuit determined that a genuine issue of material fact existed on the question of whether the franchisor's offer to sell was bona fide. <ital>Rhodes</ital>, 143 F.3d at 1373. The court considered the &#x201C;magnitude of the difference between&#x201D; the appraisal upon which the franchisor's offer to sell was based and the plaintiff's appraisal of $77,500. <ital>Id.</ital> (&#x201C;The lowest appraisal obtained by Amoco from Mr. Hopkins was $132,000. Amoco's lowest appraised value is thus some 70% higher than the Turner appraisal obtained by plaintiff.&#x201D;). The court contrasted the 70% discrepancy with the discrepancy of only 17% in <ital>Sandlin</ital>:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p21" first-line="2" turnover="1">The discrepancy here between Hopkins' $132,000 appraisal and Amoco's offer based on it, and the Turner appraisal of $77,500, is in stark contrast to the facts in <ital>Sandlin</ital>. The highest estimate there was $233,535, and the lowest was $200,000, a difference of about 17%. The appraisals in <ital>Sandlin</ital> must actually be viewed as having less variation than that, however, because the lowest excluded tanks and equipment, while the highest included them. 900 F.2d at 1482 n. 2. While we did not indicate what the permissible differential was in <ital>Sandlin</ital>, it was nowhere close to the 70% variation we are faced with in the instant case. And the $216,000 offer in question in <ital>Sandlin</ital> fell well between the two estimates there.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p22" contd-flag="y"><ital>Rhodes</ital>, 143 F.3d at 1373-74.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Here, in contrast to the situations in <ital>Sandlin</ital> and <ital>Rhodes</ital>, Defendant does not provide a contemporaneous appraisal or represent that the $980,000 offering price was based on an appraisal setting that as the fair market value for the property at the time the sale offer was made. However, in determining whether the offering price of $980,000 represented a bona fide offer, the Court can look to Plaintiff's $745,000 appraisal and the $890,000 purchase offer Defendant received. The differential or &#x201C;spread&#x201D; between Defendant's offering price and these competing valuations of the property, as well as the spread between the two valuations, inform the Court's determination that the offering price represented a bona fide offer.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">The $745,000 appraisal is approximately 24% below Defendant's offering price, and the $890,000 purchase offer is approximately 9% below Defendant's offering price. Conversely, the $980,000 offering price is approximately 31% higher than the $745,000 appraisal and 10% higher than the $890,000 purchase offer. These differentials more closely resemble the expected, permissible 17% differential in <ital>Sandlin</ital> than the 70% differential in <ital>Rhodes</ital>. Additionally, looking at the two valuations in relationship to one another, the $745,000 appraisal and the $890,000 purchase offer are within fifteen to twenty percent of one another.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> The differential between these valuations of the property is not out of line with the type of variation to be expected between such measures of fair market value. <ital>See Rhodes</ital> 143 F.3d at 1374 n.5 (citing <ital>Slatky</ital>'s use of evidence that &#x201C;two appraisers attempting to estimate fair market value should reach results within 10% to 15% of each other&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p25">&#8195;The $745,000 apprisal is 16.29% lower than the $890,000 purchase offer, and the $890,000 purchase offer is 19.46% higher than the $745,000 appraisal.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">The parties here have not proffered evidence to demonstrate that the spread between the offering price and the competing valuations fall within the range of prices that may reasonably be found to represent fair market value. However, the Court finds that the differences between the parties' valuations are not so significant that they present a triable issue of fact. Stated otherwise, the differences between the contemporaneous valuations support a finding that Defendant's offer was bona fide because it fell within the range of prices that may have a reasonable claim to approaching fair market value. Accordingly, the Court GRANTS summary judgment in favor of Defendant on Plaintiff's PMPA claim.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. State Law Claims</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Plaintiff's unfair business practices claim, brought pursuant to California Business and Professions Code &#167;17200 <ital>et seq.</ital>, and declaratory relief claim are derivative of his PMPA claim and, to the extent that the claims relate to the procedural requirement for franchise termination, they are preempted by the PMPA. <ital>See In re Herbert</ital>, 806 F.2d 889, 894 (9th Cir. 1986) (&#x201C;The procedural requirements for franchise termination are set forth in the PMPA. In this area the PMPA preempts all state law.&#x201D;). Additionally, to the extent that Plaintiff's remaining state law claims were premised on his claims of breach of contract and breach of the covenant of good faith and fair dealing, they fail by virtue of the fact that summary judgment was previously granted in Defendant's favor on those claims. Accordingly, the Court GRANTS summary judgment in favor of Defendant on Plaintiff's unfair business practices and declaratory relief claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="0">///</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="0">///</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="0">///</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="0">///</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">For the reasons set forth above, Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment (docket no. 147) is GRANTED. Defendant is ordered to submit a proposed judgment within 10 days of the date of this Order.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="0"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="0">Dated: September 23, 2008.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>