<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><bold>CIVIL MINUTES &#8211; GENERAL</bold></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment><ital>Donnita Hathaway, et al.</ital></title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment><ital>Eulaulah Hathaway, et al.</ital></title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 09-1123-GHK (CTx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-1123-GHK (CTx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-01123-GHK-CT</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 09/29/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">Beatrice Herrera, Deputy Clerk, Attorneys Present for Plaintiffs: None</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">N/A, Court Reporter / Recorder, Attorneys Present for Defendants: None</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">N/A, Tape No.</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Proceedings: (In Chambers) Order re: Defendants' Motion to Dismiss</bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1"><bold>The Honorable GEORGE H. KING, U. S. DISTRICT JUDGE</bold></judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">This matter is before the Court on Defendants Eulaulah, Kenya, and Lalah Hathaway's (&#x201C;Defendants&#x201D;) Motion to Dismiss (&#x201C;Motion&#x201D;) Plaintiffs Donnita Hathaway (&#x201C;Donnita&#x201D;) and Microhits, Inc.'s (together &#x201C;Plaintiffs&#x201D;) Complaint.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> We have considered the papers filed in support of and in opposition to this Motion, as well as the oral argument of counsel at the hearing on August 31, 2009. As the Parties are familiar with the facts of this case, we will repeat them only as necessary. Accordingly, we rule as follows.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p2">&#8195;Universal Music Group (&#x201C;UMG&#x201D;) is also a Defendant in this action, but is not listed as one of the movants on the Motion to Dismiss.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">On February 17, 2009, Plaintiffs filed suit against Defendant, bringing the following claims: (1) a claim for declaratory relief that Donnita is a co-owner of Donny Hathaway's copyright renewal terms, under 28 U.S.C. &#167; 2201 and 17 U.S.C. &#167; 101 <ital>et seq.</ital>; (2) a claim seeking the imposition of a constructive trust for unpaid royalties and an accounting; and (3) a claim for fraud against only Defendant Eulaulah Hathaway. (Compl. at 3-8). The Motion seeks dismissal on the following grounds: (1) the declaratory judgment action to establish co-ownership is time-barred; (2) the constructive trust remedy necessarily fails as it is wholly derivative of the declaratory judgment action; and (3) the fraud claim is both time-barred and pled with insufficient particularity under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 9(b).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. Declaration of Co-Ownership in Renewal Copyright Terms (17 U.S.C. &#167; 2201; 17 U.S.C. &#167; 101 <ital>et seq.</ital>) (Claim One) and Constructive Trust and Accounting (Claim Two)</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Statute of Limitations</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Defendants move to dismiss Donnita's claim for co-ownership in the renewal terms for Donny Hathaway's songs pursuant to the three-year statute of limitations contained in 17 U.S.C. &#167; 507(b) (&#x201C;No civil action shall be maintained under the provisions of this title unless it is commenced within three years after the claim accrued.&#x201D;); <ital>see also Wechsberg v U.S.</ital>, 54 Fed. Cl. 158, 162 n.10 (Fed. Cl. 2002) (&#x201C;Public Law 85-313 established a three-year period of limitations under general copyright law in Title 17 U.S.C. &#167; 115(b). The Copyright Act of 1976 in turn rearranged Title 17 by moving Section 115 to Section 507.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Governing Law</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Under 17 U.S.C. &#167; 304, any work created and registered prior to January 1, 1978 falls within the ambit of the 1909 Copyright Act. According to Eulaulah, Kenya and Lalah Hathaway's List of Copyrights At Issue In Response to Court Order (&#x201C;Copyright List&#x201D;) (Dkt No. 27), every renewal term commencement date listed falls within 2003 or earlier. Under 17 U.S.C. &#167; 304(a)(1)(A), a copyright, the first term of which is subsisting on January 1, 1978, shall endure for 28 years from the date it was originally secured. This means that the latest date on which any of these songs could have been originally copyrighted would have been Dec. 31, 1975 (<ital>i.e.</ital> 28 years prior to the last day of 2003). At oral argument, Plaintiffs' counsel affirmed that only the 1909 Copyright Act is applicable in this case, as they are only seeking co-ownership in the renewal terms of copyrights, the original terms of which commenced prior to the 1976 Act's effective date, January 1, 1978.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p6">&#8195;There are six compositions with original term commencement dates that postdate January 1, 1978 in the Copyright List created by Defendants. Plaintiffs note that they claim an ownership interest in the six songs for which the original term commenced after January 1, 1978, only to the extent that they are derivative of a work copyrighted under the 1909 Copyright Act.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">Therefore, the Parties agree and the record reflects that the 1909 Copyright Act governs the disposition of this case.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Vesting of Renewal Rights</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Under 17 U.S.C. &#167; 304(a)(2)(B)(i), &#x201C;[a]t the expiration of the original term of copyright in a work specified in paragraph (1)(C) of this subsection, the copyright shall endure for a renewed and extended further term of 67 years, which&#8211;(i) if an application to register a claim to such further term has been made to the Copyright Office within 1 year before the expiration of the original term of copyright, and the claim is registered, shall vest, upon the beginning of such further term, in any person who is entitled under paragraph (1)(C) to the renewal and extension of the copyright at the time the application is made[.]&#x201D; Under &#167; 304(a)(1)(C)(ii), &#x201C;the widow, widower, or children of the author, if the author is not living<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> shall be entitled to a renewal and extension of the copyright in such work for a further term of 67 years.&#x201D; If any member of the class of statutory heirs files an application for copyright renewal, each class member's rights in the renewal term vest at that moment. 17 U.S.C. &#167; 304(a)(2)(B)(i). The Parties propose different starting points for the statute of limitations (<ital>see infra</ital> Section I.D), but even the Defendants conceded at oral argument that no claim can accrue under the statute of limitations until rights to the renewal term have vested.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p9">&#8195;Plaintiffs have never asserted to the contrary, and Defendants conceded this point at Oral Argument. (Hr'g Tr., August 31, 2009, at 3:7-4:1).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">The Parties do not dispute and we accordingly conclude that: (1) original copyright terms and renewal terms are distinct property interests with distinct vesting points under the 1909 Copyright Act; and therefore, (2) the statute of limitations for renewal terms bears a separate accrual date from the statute of limitations for original terms.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>D. Accrual Date</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p11" level="1">Defendants propose two alternatives for the date of accrual under 17 U.S.C. &#167; 507(b): (1) the date on which Donnita reached the age of majority and knew or should have known of her co-ownership interest; or (2) the point at which the renewal terms were registered by Eulaulah Hathaway, excluding Donnita's name, which, so they contend, constituted &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; of Donnita's interest.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Defendants first argue Donnita's claims accrued when she reached the age of majority and knew or should have known of her co-ownership claim. (Mot. Dismiss 5-10). For this proposition, Defendants cite two Second Circuit cases. <ital>Stone v. Williams</ital>, 970 F.2d 1043, 1048 (2d Cir. 1992) concluded that the statute of limitations period started running from the date plaintiff was put on notice that she might be Hank Williams, Sr.'s child, but ultimately the court held the claims were not time-barred under a &#x201C;continuing wrong&#x201D; theory. Defendant also discusses <ital>Merchant v. Levy</ital>, 92 F.3d 51, 56 (2d Cir. 1996), which limited <ital>Stone</ital> to its &#x201C;idiosyncratic facts,&#x201D; noting that the distinguishing feature in that case was the &#x201C;uncertainty surround[ing] the relative's status as a member of the author's family.&#x201D; Defendant conceded at oral argument that accrual could not precede the vesting of the renewal rights, which occurred at earliest, the Parties agree, with the filing of the first renewal term applications in 1998. (Hr'g Tr., August 31, 2009, at 3:7-4:1; Copyright List, Dkt No. 27). Rather, Defendants maintain that since Donnita was over the age of majority and knew or should have known of her paternity in 1998, her claims under each copyright renewal term accrued as they were registered by Defendants. However, this &#x201C;inquiry notice&#x201D; test does not govern the accrual of co-ownership claims in the Ninth Circuit. Under <ital>Zuill v. Shanahan</ital>, 80 F.3d 1366, 1369 (9th Cir. 1996), a claim for co-ownership accrues upon the &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; of the plaintiff's interests in the copyright's original or renewal terms: &#x201C;[w]e conclude that claims of co-ownership, as distinct from claims of infringement, accrue when plain and express repudiation of co-ownership is communicated to the claimant, and are barred three years from the time of repudiation.&#x201D; Therefore, we apply the <ital>Zuill</ital> test, not the knowledge or inquiry notice test.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">Following <ital>Zuill</ital>, Defendants argue in the alternative that Donnita's claims with respect to each copyright renewal term accrued upon Defendants' filing of the renewal applications in their names and omitting Donnita's name. (Compl. &#182;16 (&#x201C;In or about 1998, EULAULAH began to register claims to the Renewal Copyrights in her own name and continued to do so as the underlying copyrights came up for renewal. DONNITA's name was never included in the registrations filed by EULAULAH.&#x201D;)). Defendants argue that the mere registration constituted &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; of Donnita's interests in the renewal term, triggering accrual under <ital>Zuill</ital>. Defendants urge us to follow the conclusory proposition contained in <ital>Diamond v. Gillis</ital>, 357 F. Supp. 2d 1003 (E.D. Mich. 2005). In <ital>Diamond</ital>, the Court found &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; had been effected upon the Defendants' registration of two albums with the U.S. Copyright Office &#x201C;in only their names and not Diamond's name.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 1007. Regrettably, this case is devoid of any discussion as to why this satisfies the &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; standard. Moreover, <ital>Diamond</ital> is not binding precedent. After careful consideration of the Parties' arguments and the relevant Ninth Circuit case law, we have concluded that &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; in this Circuit requires more than mere registration with the U.S. Copyright Office.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">First, <ital>Zuill</ital>, 80 F.3d at 1369, expressly stated that the claim would not accrue until &#x201C;plain and express repudiation of co-ownership [was] <ital>communicated</ital> to the claimant<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; (Emphasis added.) Indeed, the Court listed four ways in which the defendants had communicated their &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; to the plaintiffs:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p15" first-line="1" turnover="1">Mr. Shanahan and the corporations he used to market Hooked on Phonics and its predecessors expressly and repeatedly claimed sole ownership of the copyright in 1986 and 1987. They did so by [1] saying so expressly in writing, and [2] by furnishing copies of the Symphonics product in August 1986 with a printed copyright notice. [3] The compensation agreement tendered in January of 1987 claimed sole ownership of the copyright. [4] In the Spring of 1987, Mr. Zuill received a copy of Hooked on Phonics, stating in writing that HMS Publishing Company owned the copyright, and he learned at that time that Mr. Shanahan's company was marketing the product.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p16" contd-flag="y"><ital>Id.</ital> at 1368. Each of the methods listed entails communication with the plaintiff. Only the second example of repudiation cited arguably lacks direct communication to the plaintiff; but nevertheless, the public dissemination of a product with a printed copyright notice better approximates a communication than mere registration of a renewal term at the Copyright Office. Even though Copyright Office records are publicly available, Defendants have not &#x201C;communicated&#x201D; any information to anyone but a government agency. The courts in this Circuit have typically required more. <ital>See Welles v. Turner Entertainment Co.</ital>, 503 F.3d 728, 734 (9th Cir. 2007) (finding plaintiff's claim not time-barred) (&#x201C;The evidence the defendants cite as notice that they were exploiting home video rights in <ital>Citizen Kane</ital> is correspondence between the attorneys for the Estate of Orson Welles and the defendants regarding the inclusion of the <ital>Citizen Kane</ital> screenplay in a &#x2018;home video collector's edition gift set.&#x2019; While this might have informed Beatrice Welles that the defendants were distributing <ital>Citizen Kane</ital> on home video, it is not the plain and express repudiation of copyright ownership that our case law requires<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;); <ital>Silva v. Sunich</ital>, No. 03-9327, 2006 WL 6116645, at *6-8 (C.D. Cal. Sept. 6, 2006) (refusal to pay royalties and failure to give credit for animation series constituted &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D;). Notably, our colleague Judge Dean Pregerson has stated that &#x201C;the registration of a federal copyright by itself does not provide plain and express repudiation, and instead the inquiry is fact-intensive.&#x201D; <ital>Donen v. Paramount Pictures Corp.</ital>, No. CV 08-03383 DDP, 2008 WL 5054340, at *5 (C.D. Cal. Nov. 20, 2008) (citing <ital>Zuill</ital>, 80 F.3d at 1369). Judge Pregerson has characterized <ital>Zuill</ital> as establishing a multi-factor inquiry, in which no one factor is dispositive. <ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Nor are we persuaded that <ital>Aalmuhammed v. Lee</ital>, 202 F.3d 1227 (9th Cir. 2000) advances Defendants' position. In <ital>Aalmuhammed</ital>, the Court found &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; where the authors of the movie <ital>Malcolm X</ital> had listed plaintiff in the credits as an &#x201C;&#x2018;Islamic technical consultant,&#x2019; far below the more prominent names,&#x201D; including the writers. <ital>Id.</ital> at 1231. This case is distinguishable on two grounds. First, the plaintiff in <ital>Aalmuhammed</ital> was affirmatively given another title in the credits, not merely omitted in the credits. Second, the defendants knew that the plaintiff would see the movie he had worked on in some capacity and would be looking for his name in the credits. Knowing this, Director Spike Lee and others who controlled the credits intended them to communicate information to plaintiff, among others. In this case, Donnita was never affirmatively told that she was not a co-owner in the renewal terms, and Defendants had no reasonable expectation that Donnita, as an illegitimate heir, would be checking the U.S. Copyright Office on a regular basis to ascertain whether she had been included in the renewal term registrations. Upon closer investigation, we do not think <ital>Aalmuhammed</ital> ultimately sustains Defendants' position.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">The Copyright Act itself confirms this reading of the case law. 17 U.S.C. &#167; 304(a)(2)(B)(i) vests co-ownership rights in the entire class of statutorily designated heirs upon the registration of the renewal term by any single member of that class. We agree with Plaintiffs that reading this provision to permit repudiation when a class member's name is omitted, would &#x201C;stand [the provision] on its head.&#x201D; (Opp'n 9). This provision creates and protects rights. There is no indication that Congress contemplated this provision would authorize or tolerate stealth cancellation of other heirs' rights.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p19">&#8195;We are confirmed in this belief by Defendants' Submission In Response to Court Request for Information Regarding Renewals (Dkt No. 37) and Defendants' Further Submission In Response to Court Request for Information Regarding Renewals (Dkt No. 39). Defendants' argument that mere registration excluding another party's name may constitute &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; is further undermined by Defendants' submission of sample renewal registration forms and records. Some of these registration forms reveal that Eulaulah Hathaway did not include her own daughters' names. (<ital>See, e.g.</ital>, Dkt No. 39 (including renewal registrations for RE 836-105 and RE 713-293, both of which only list Eulaulah Hathaway's name under &#x201C;Renewal Claimants&#x201D;)). We clearly cannot assign the requested dispositive effect to renewal registrations excluding other potential claimants' names. If this were so, then Kenya and Lalah Hathaway would also be stripped of their rights in the renewal terms, where Eulaulah failed to include their names. That defies logic, the Copyright Act, and Eulaulah Hathaway's own assertions regarding her daughters' status as heirs. (Defs.' Req. Judicial Notice, Ex. F, at 32 (&#x201C;1986 Affidavit of Heirship&#x201D;) (stating that Donny Hathaway had only two daughters, Lalah and Kenya Hathaway)).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">Therefore, in light of the facts we may properly consider on a motion to dismiss, Donnita's co-ownership was not plainly and expressly repudiated when Defendant Eulaulah Hathaway registered the renewal terms without listing Donnita's name. Registration is at best merely one factor for consideration and certainly not dispositive. Here, the Ninth Circuit's test is markedly different from the knowledge or inquiry notice standard in the First, Second, Fourth, Fifth and Seventh Circuits. <ital>Jordan v. Sony BMG Music Entertainment, Inc.</ital>, No. H-06-1673, 2008 WL 5082414, at *14-15 (S.D. Tex. Nov. 25, 2008) (noting Circuit split on issue of co-ownership claim accrual). That a plaintiff should have known of its claim or that its interest might be in jeopardy is irrelevant. Communication of repudiation is the trigger.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">The only other potential candidate for &#x201C;plain and express repudiation&#x201D; is Paragraph 15 of the Complaint, which states: &#x201C;On October 23, 1986, prior to filing Exhibit B, EULAULAH had filed another Affidavit of Heirship stating that DONNITA was not Donny's daughter. EULAULAH never informed DONNITA that she had filed the 1986 Affidavit. DONNITA first became aware of the 1986 Affidavit when LALAH used it as support for her Petition in January, 2007.&#x201D; (Compl. &#182;15). &#x201C;When ruling on a motion to dismiss, we may generally consider only allegations contained in the pleadings, exhibits attached to the complaint, and matters properly subject to judicial notice.&#x201D; <ital>Outdoor Media Group, Inc. v. City of Beaumont</ital>, 506 F.3d 895, 899 (9th Cir. 2007) (internal quotation marks omitted). The &#x201C;incorporation by reference&#x201D; doctrine also &#x201C;permits us to take into account documents &#x2018;whose contents are alleged in a complaint and whose authenticity no party questions, but which are not physically attached to the [plaintiff's] pleading.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Knievel v. ESPN</ital>, 393 F.3d 1068, 1076 (9th Cir. 2005) (citing <ital>In re Silicon Graphics Inc. Sec. Litig.</ital>, 183 F.3d 970, 986 (9th Cir. 1999) (quoting <ital>Branch v. Tunnell</ital>, 14 F.3d 449, 454 (9th Cir.1994))). Here, the Affidavit of Heirship, filed by Eulaulah Hathaway on October 23, 1986, with the Circuit Court of Cook County, Illinois, pursuant to the probate of Donny Hathaway's estate (Docket No. 86P08539) is attached to the Motion to Dismiss, not the Complaint. (Defs.' Req. Judicial Notice, Ex. F, at 32). It states: &#x201C;[t]hat DONNY F. HATHAWAY had only two (2) children who were all living at the time of his death, namely: Eulaulah D. Hathaway, born December 16, 1968. Kenya Hathaway, born January 1, 1971.&#x201D; (<ital>Id.</ital>). We may consider this document as it is &#x201C;incorporated by reference&#x201D; into the Complaint: the Complaint discusses the document's contents, and its authenticity is not disputed. (Compl. &#182;15). However, it does not change the outcome. On a motion to dismiss for failure to state a claim, &#x201C;[a]ll allegations of material fact are taken as true and construed in the light most favorable to the nonmoving party.&#x201D; <ital>Cousins v. Lockyer</ital>, 568 F.3d 1063, 1067 (9th Cir. 2009). Here, we must take as true Donnita's assertion in the Complaint that she did not learn of the 1986 Affidavit disclaiming her heirship until January 2007. (Compl. &#182;15). Therefore, even if that affidavit constitutes &#x201C;plain and express repudiation,&#x201D; the earliest possible accrual date under the &#x201C;plan and express repudiation&#x201D; test would fall in January 2007, and thus the three-year statute of limitations would not yet have run when Donnita filed her Complaint on February 17, 2009.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">Therefore, we cannot say as a matter of law that Donnita's claims for a declaration of co-ownership and the imposition of a constructive trust and an accounting are time-barred. The Motion to Dismiss Claims One and Two is hereby <bold>DENIED</bold>.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. Fraud (Claim Three)</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Donnita's fraud claim has not been pled with the requisite particularity under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 9(b): &#x201C;In alleging fraud or mistake, a party must state with particularity the circumstances constituting fraud or mistake. Malice, intent, knowledge, and other conditions of a person's mind may be alleged generally.&#x201D; <ital>See also Kearns v. Ford Motor Co.</ital>, 567 F.3d 1120, 1126 (9th Cir. 2009) (&#x201C;Rule 9(b) demands that the circumstances constituting the alleged fraud be specific enough to give defendants notice of the particular misconduct<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> so that they can defend against the charge and not just deny that they have done anything wrong. Averments of fraud must be accompanied by the who, what, when, where, and how of the misconduct charged. A party alleging fraud must &#x2018;set forth more than the neutral facts necessary to identify the transaction.&#x2019;&#x201D;) (internal citations and quotation marks omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">The elements of fraud include: &#x201C;(a) misrepresentation (false representation, concealment, or nondisclosure); (b) knowledge of falsity (or &#x2018;scienter&#x2019;); (c) intent to defraud, i.e., to induce reliance; (d) justifiable reliance; and (e) resulting damage.&#x201D; <ital>Kearns</ital>, 567 F.3d at 1126 (citing <ital>Engalla v. Permanente Med. Group, Inc.</ital>, 15 Cal. 4th 951, 974 (1997)). The elements of a claim for fraudulent concealment, stated at a general level, include: &#x201C;(1) the defendant must have concealed or suppressed a material fact, (2) the defendant must have been under a duty to disclose the fact to the plaintiff, (3) the defendant must have intentionally concealed or suppressed the fact with the intent to defraud the plaintiff, (4) the plaintiff must have been unaware of the fact and would not have acted as he did if he had known of the concealed or suppressed fact, and (5) as a result of the concealment or suppression of the fact, the plaintiff must have sustained damage.&#x201D; <ital>Superior Dispatch, Inc. v. Ins. Corp. of New York</ital>, 176 Cal. App. 4th 12, 33 (2009). There is a difference between fraudulent concealment of a material fact by misrepresentation or misleading partial representation and mere non-disclosure in the face of a duty to disclose. <ital>OCM Principal Opportunities Fund v. CIBC World Markets Corp.</ital>, 157 Cal. App. 4th 835, 859 (2007) outlines the &#x201C;four circumstances in which nondisclosure or concealment may constitute actionable fraud.&#x201D; (Quotation marks omitted.) These include:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p25" first-line="1" turnover="1">(1) when the defendant is in a fiduciary relationship with the plaintiff; (2) when the defendant had exclusive knowledge of material facts not known to the plaintiff; (3) when the defendant actively conceals a material fact from the plaintiff; and (4) when the defendant makes partial representations but also suppresses some material facts. Where, as here, there is no fiduciary relationship, the duty to disclose generally presupposes a relationship grounded in some sort of transaction between the parties. Thus, a duty to disclose may arise from the relationship between seller and buyer, employer and prospective employee, doctor and patient, or parties entering into any kind of contractual agreement.<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p26">&#8195;The elements of a fraudulent nondisclosure action not involving a confidential or fiduciary relationship have been stated as follows: &#x201C;(1) Nondisclosure by the defendant of facts materially affecting the value or desirability of the property; (2) Defendant's knowledge of such facts and of their being unknown to or beyond the reach of the plaintiff; (3) Defendant's intention to induce action by the plaintiff; (4) Inducement of the plaintiff to act by reason of the nondisclosure; and (5) Resulting damages.&#x201D; <ital>OCM Principal Opportunities Fund v. CIBC World Markets Corp.</ital>, 157 Cal. App. 4th at 862 n.16 (quoting <ital>Lingsch v. Savage</ital>, 213 Cal. App. 2d 729, 738 (1963)). The <ital>Lingsch</ital> &#x201C;duty to disclose&#x201D; is typically confined to those engaged in a real estate transaction. <ital>See Cooper v. Jevne</ital>, 56 Cal. App. 3d 860, 866 (1976) (citing <ital>Lingsch</ital> for the proposition that &#x201C;where a real estate broker or agent, representing the seller, knows facts materially affecting the value or the desirability of property offered for sale and these facts are known or accessible only to him and his principal, and the broker or agent also knows that these facts are not known to or within the reach of the diligent attention and observation of the buyer, the broker or agent is under a duty to disclose these facts to the buyer.&#x201D;). This &#x201C;duty of a real estate broker or salesperson&#x201D; was later codified at California Civil Code &#167; 2079(a).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<paratext ID="p27" contd-flag="y"><ital>Id.</ital> (citations and quotations marks omitted). Actively concealing a material fact with an intentional misrepresentation of that fact is a basis of liability no different from basic fraud. <ital>See Kearns</ital>, 567 F.3d at 1126. Donnita does not allege any such intentional misrepresentation by Defendant. Beyond such &#x201C;active concealment,&#x201D; for liability to attach for mere non-disclosure, the defendant must have been under some &#x201C;duty to disclose&#x201D; the information, arising from either: (1) a contractual, confidential, or fiduciary relationship, or (2) the making of affirmative representations which are materially qualified or undermined by undisclosed facts. <ital>See also Blickman Turkus, LP v. MF Downtown Sunnyvale, LLC</ital>, 162 Cal. App. 4th 858, 877 (2008) (&#x201C;A duty to disclose can arise from the making of affirmative representations with knowledge of undisclosed facts that materially qualify the facts disclosed, or<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> render [the disclosed facts] likely to mislead<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;) (citations and quotation marks omitted).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Here, Donnita has not alleged any contractual, confidential, or fiduciary relationship between herself and Defendant. All the evidence in the record indicates there was none. Moreover, Donnita does not allege any partial representation, which suppressed some material facts. Plaintiff does not specifically allege that Defendant actively concealed from or misrepresented to Donnita in particular any material fact, for instance, if and when she was questioned by Donnita as to Donnita's rights in her father's estate. Indeed, there is no allegation of any communication or representation whatsoever between Donnita and Defendant. The allegations fail to plead any of the circumstances of the alleged fraud. <ital>See</ital> (Compl. &#182;14 (&#x201C;EULAULAH affirmatively concealed <ital>from the world</ital> that DONNITA was entitled to any part of her father's estate<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;) (emphasis added); &#182;15 (&#x201C;EULAULAH never informed DONNITA that she had filed the 1986 Affidavit.&#x201D;); &#182;18 (&#x201C;EULAULAH, again affirmatively concealing the fact from DONNITA, entered into three (3) separate agreements with BMG<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;); &#182;33 (&#x201C;EULAULAH<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> intentionally concealed from DONNITA the fact that she is entitled to a share of her father's estate, including his copyrights and Renewal Copyrights.&#x201D;); &#182;34 (&#x201C;Among other things, EULAULAH fraudulently denied DONNITA's paternity in probate courts in Illinois both in 1986 and again in 2007. EULAULAH made these and other representations despite the fact that she knew them to be false and despite the fact that she knew keeping the information secret would harm DONNITA while EULAULAH and her daughters would benefit.&#x201D;); &#182;35 (&#x201C;EULAULAH<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> had been concealing material information for many years<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;)). Accordingly, Donnita has failed to specifically plead that Defendant was under any duty to disclose a material fact to Donnita. Therefore, Plaintiff's fraud claim is defective under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 9(b).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Accordingly, Claim Three is hereby <bold>DISMISSED with leave to amend</bold>. As we have dismissed Plaintiff's claim under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 9(b), we need not address Defendant's argument that this claim is time-barred under the applicable statute of limitations. Plaintiffs <bold>SHALL</bold> file a First Amended Complaint (&#x201C;FAC&#x201D;) <bold>within fifteen (15) days</bold> hereof curing any defect in the fraud claim. If Plaintiff fails to do so, the fraud claim will be dismissed with prejudice, and this action will proceed on the remaining claims. In that event, Defendants <bold>SHALL</bold> answer the remaining claims <bold>within ten (10) days</bold> of Plaintiff's failure to file an FAC. If an FAC is timely filed, Defendants <bold>SHALL</bold> respond to the FAC <bold>within twenty (20) days</bold> thereafter.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1"><bold>IT IS SO ORDERED.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1"><underscore>-- : --</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">Initials of Deputy Clerk <underscore>Bea</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>