<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>FREDA TANUVASA, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>FEDERAL DEPOSIT INSURANCE CORPORATION, (&#x201C;FDIC&#x201D;) Successor to Washington Mutual Savings bank (&#x201C;WaMu&#x201D;), JP. MORGAN CHASE BANK, NA (&#x201C;Chase&#x201D;), purchaser of WaMu from FDIC, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 09-02795 DDP (AGRx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-02795 DDP (AGRx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-02795-DDP-AGR</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 01/29/2010</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Order (1) Granting Defendant Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation's Motion to Dismiss; (2) Granting Defendant JP Morgan Chase's Motion to Dismiss</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center">[Motions filed on December 14 and 21, 2009]</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">DEAN D. PREGERSON United States District Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Presently before the Court are Defendant JP Morgan Chase (&#x201C;Chase&#x201D;)'s motion to dismiss Plaintiff's Amended Complaint for failure to state a claim, and Defendant Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation (&#x201C;FDIC&#x201D;)'s motion to dismiss for lack of subject matter jurisdiction. Upon reviewed the parties' moving papers, and considering the arguments advanced therein, the Court GRANTS both motions.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="0">///</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="0">///</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. Background</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Pro se Plaintiff Freda Tanuvasa obtained a $669,755 mortgage loan in connection with the purchase of residential real property located at 13236 Rutgers Avenue in Downey, California (&#x201C;13236 Rutgers Avenue Property&#x201D;). (Am. Compl. &#182; 7.) The loan was secured by a Deed of Trust that was recorded with the Los Angeles County Recorder's Office on December 11, 2006. (<underscore>Id.</underscore>) The Deed of Trust identifies Washington Mutual Bank (&#x201C;WaMu&#x201D;) as the lender, and the California Reconveyance Company as the trustee. Chase acquired WaMu's banking operations from the FDIC on September 25, 2008. (Request for Judicial Notice (&#x201C;RJN&#x201D;), Ex. 4.)<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p5">&#8195;Chase asks the Court to take judicial notice of the Chase-FDIC purchase agreement. The document is available for public review on the FDIC's website, and plaintiff quotes it at length in her complaint. The Court concludes that the purchase agreement is a matter of public record, provided by a government agency for public review, and as such, it is judicially noticeable. <underscore>See NRDC v. Kempthorne</underscore>, 539 F. Supp. 2d 1155, 1166-67 (E.D. Cal. 2008)(taking judicial notice of documents from the website of the United States Bureau of Reclamation).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">In her Amended Complaint, Plaintiff contends that WaMu, the original lender, failed to make material loan disclosures in accordance with the federal Truth in Lending Act (&#x201C;TILA&#x201D;), 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1601 <ital>et seq.</ital> She argues, for example, that WaMu did not inform her of her right to rescind, calculate the annual percentage rate of interest on the loan, or disclose the direct and indirect fees associated with the transaction. She brought the present action seeking damages and declaratory and injunctive relief on May 15, 2009.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">Chase filed a motion to dismiss Plaintiff's initial complaint on June 16, 2009. (Dkt. No. 7.) In an Amended Order, the Court granted the motion as to Plaintiff's claims arising under federal law, but, with respect to her TILA claims, provided her with leave to amend. (Dkt. No. 25.) The Court noted that if Plaintiff failed to amend her complaint such that it stated a <underscore>federal</underscore> claim, it would likely decline to exercise supplemental jurisdiction over any pendent state law claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" level="1">Plaintiff filed an Amended Complaint on December 2, 2009. (Dkt. No. 32.) Chase filed a motion to dismiss the Amended Complaint on December 14, 2009, (Dkt. No. 25), and the FDIC filed a motion to dismiss for lack of subject matter jurisdiction on December 21, 2009, (Dkt. No. 40).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. Legal Standard</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A. <underscore>Motion to Dismiss under Rule 12(b)(6)</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p9" level="1">Pursuant to Federal Rule of Procedure Rule 12(b)(6), a complaint is subject to dismissal when the plaintiff's allegations fail to state a claim upon which relief can be granted.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> When considering a Rule 12(b)(6) motion, courts accept the plaintiff's allegations of material fact as true, and construe the complaint in the light most favorable to the non-moving party. <underscore>Cahill v. Liberty Mut. Ins. Co.</underscore>, 80 F.3d 336, 337-338 (9th Cir. 1996).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">In <underscore>Ashcroft v. Iqbal</underscore>, 129 S. Ct. 1937, 1950 (2009), the Supreme Court explained that a court considering a 12(b)(6) motion should first &#x201C;identify[] pleadings that, because they are no more than conclusions, are not entitled to the assumption of truth.&#x201D; Next, the court should identify the complaint's &#x201C;well-pleaded factual allegations,<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> assume their veracity and then determine whether they plausibly give rise to an entitlement to relief.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p11">&#8195;As a general rule, pro se pleadings are to be liberally construed, and courts must give the claims of pro se litigants fair and meaningful consideration. <underscore>See Haines v. Kerner</underscore>, 404 U.S. 519 (1972). Pro se plaintiffs are not, however, exempt from the requirement of stating a claim upon which relief may be granted.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. Discussion</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. FDIC's Motion to Dismiss</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p12" level="1">Plaintiff concedes that the FDIC is not a proper party in this action, and that all of her claims are directed at Chase. Accordingly, the Court GRANTS the FDIC's motion to dismiss.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Chase's Motion to Dismiss<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p13">&#8195;Chase contends that, pursuant to the terms of the Chase-FDIC purchase agreement, it did not assume liability for borrower-related claims against WaMu. The Court did not reach this argument in its Amended Order because Chase raised the issue for the first time in its reply brief in support of its (first) motion to dismiss. The argument is now properly before the Court, Chase having raised it in its opening brief in support of its motion to dismiss Plaintiff's Amended Complaint. However, because the Court concludes that Plaintiff's TILA claims fail on the merits, the Court need not resolve whether the purchase agreement forecloses borrower claims of this sort against Chase.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">1. TILA Damages</headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="2">In its Amended Order, the Court stated the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p15" first-line="1" turnover="1">[T]he Court can discern from the face of the complaint that TILA's one-year statute of limitations has run. Plaintiff obtained the loan at issue in this case in December 2006. She filed her complaint in this action on May 15, 2009. Therefore, unless equitable tolling applies, TILA's statute of limitations bars her claim for damages.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" first-line="2" turnover="1">Plaintiff does not argue that equitable tolling applies, and the Court finds no basis in her complaint for concluding that it should. The complaint does not indicate when plaintiff discovered the alleged TILA violation, and it does not plead facts suggesting that defendant took steps to prevent her from discovering the alleged nondisclosures. The Court thus grants Chase's motion to dismiss plaintiff's TILA damages claim, but grants plaintiff leave to amend her complaint to include facts relevant to the applicability of equitable tolling.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p17" contd-flag="y">(Am. Order at 5.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">In her Amended Complaint, Plaintiff provides some additional facts in support of her contention that equitable tolling should apply. She alleges, in relevant part, that she did not become aware of her statutory rights under TILA until March 2009, when she &#x201C;started looking to the law for relief&#x201D; after falling behind on her mortgage payments. (Am. Comp. &#182; 23.) She also contends that, but for a lack of knowledge of her statutory rights, she would have brought a TILA damages action before December 2007 (i.e., within TILA's one year statute of limitations for damages claims). (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 21.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Plaintiff's allegations, even liberally construed, are insufficient to establish an entitlement to equitable tolling. &#x201C;[E]quitable tolling may, in the appropriate circumstances, suspend [TILA's one-year] limitations period until the borrower discovers or had reasonable opportunity to discover the fraud or nondisclosures that form the basis of the TILA action.&#x201D; <underscore>King v. California</underscore>, 784 F.2d 910, 915 (9th Cir. 1986). The TILA violations alleged in the Amended Complaint occurred in December 2006. Plaintiff does not allege that any misconduct on WaMu or Chase's part prevented her from discovering the alleged violations, or that those violations were somehow concealed during the applicable limitations period. Ignorance of the law &#8211; the only basis Plaintiff provides &#8211; is not alone sufficient to establish entitlement to equitable tolling. Accordingly, Plaintiff's TILA damages claim is time-barred.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">2. TILA Rescission</headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">In its Amended Order, the Court stated the following:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p21" first-line="1" turnover="1">TILA gives a borrower a right to rescind any credit transaction involving a security interest in the borrower's home if the lender fails to make the required disclosures. 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1635. The right of rescission, however, &#x201C;does not apply to [] residential mortgage transaction[s].&#x201D; Id. &#167; 1635(e)(1). 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1602(w) defines the phrase &#x201C;residential mortgage transaction&#x201D; as &#x201C;a transaction in which a mortgage, deed of trust, purchase money security interest arising under an installment sales contract, or equivalent consensual security interest is created or retained against the consumer's dwelling to finance the acquisition or initial construction of such dwelling.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" first-line="2" turnover="1">Plaintiff does not allege that the loan at issue was used for any reason other than to finance the acquisition of her home. Further, the Court takes judicial notice of a grant deed, dated October 31, 2006, where a Kevin Lee Wilson transferred the 13236 Rutgers Avenue Property to Plaintiff. (RJN, Ex. 2.) Accordingly, the Court concludes the that the mortgage transaction at issue in this case was a residential mortgage transaction within the meaning of 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1602(w), and thus Plaintiff does not have a right to rescind under TILA.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" first-line="2" turnover="1">The Court grants Plaintiff leave to amend her complaint so that she can include facts relating to whether the mortgage transaction at issue in this case was a purchase money mortgage.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p24" contd-flag="y">(Am. Order at 5-6.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">In her Amended Complaint, Plaintiff contends that the loan she obtained from WaMu in 2006 was not a purchase money loan. She alleges that she purchased the 13236 Rutgers Avenue Property in 1998. (Am. Compl. &#182; 14.) In May 2005, she contends, &#x201C;when Plaintiff was faced with losing her home, she had a family friend obtain financing on the promise that Plaintiff will refinance the mortgage as soon as she could.&#x201D; (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#167; 15.) The Amended Complaint states that Plaintiff was able to obtain financing from WaMu in December 2006, enabling her to pay off the previous loan. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 16.) At the time Plaintiff obtained the mortgage loan at issue in this case, she alleges, she had been living in the 13236 Rutgers Avenue Property continuously for eight years and seven months. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> &#182; 17.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">Chase contends that judicially noticeable loan documents contradict, or at least clarify, Plaintiff's account.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Documents not physically attached to a complaint can nonetheless be considered in ruling on a Rule 12(b)(6) motion if the complaint refers to such documents, the documents are central to the plaintiff's claims, and there is no question regarding their authenticity. <underscore>See Branch v. Tunnell</underscore>, 14 F.3d 449, 454 (9th Cir. 1994). Plaintiff's Amended Complaint refers to the loan documents that Chase asks the Court to notice, and Plaintiff does not dispute their authenticity. Further, the documents are central to Plaintiff's claims &#8212; the 2006 mortgage loan is at the heart of the parties' dispute. Accordingly, for the purposes of this Order, the Court takes judicial notice of the Deed of Trust and Grant Deed recorded with the Los Angeles County Recorder's Office in connection with the 13236 Rutgers Avenue Property. (RJN, Exhibits 1-2.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">The recorded loan documents reveal that Plaintiff acquired title to the 13236 Rutgers Avenue Property by way of a Grant Deed from Kevin Lee Wilson. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> Ex. 2.) The Grant Deed was recorded on December 11, 2006, the same date that the Deed of Trust (in connection with the Loan) was recorded. (<underscore>Id.</underscore> Ex. 1.) That Plaintiff may have been a previous owner of the 13236 Rutgers Avenue Property is of no consequence. In 2006, she obtained a loan from WaMu in order to <underscore>acquire</underscore> title to the property from a third party. As such, the transaction was a &#x201C;residential mortgage transaction&#x201D; within the meaning of 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1602(w). TILA does not provide a right to rescind in connection with residential mortgage transactions of this kind. <underscore>See</underscore> 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1635(e)(1). Accordingly, Plaintiff's TILA rescission claim is dismissed with prejudice.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. Conclusion</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Plaintiff's Amended Complaint fails to state a claim upon which relief can be granted. Accordingly, her claims for damages, rescission, and declaratory relief &#8211; all of which are premised on TILA violations &#8211; are dismissed.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="0">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="0">Dated: January 29, 2010</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>