<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<court.message suppress-flag="y"><bold>CIVIL MINUTES &#8211; GENERAL</bold></court.message>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>TRANSPORT INSURANCE COMPANY</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>R.R. STREET &#38; CO., INC., ET AL.; R.R. STREET &#38; CO., ET AL.</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>TRANSPORT INSURANCE COMPANY</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 09-8368 CAS (FMOx)</docket.line>
<docket.line><bold>CV 09-6045 CAS (FMOx)</bold></docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-8368 CAS (FMOx)</docket.number>
<docket.number><bold>CV 09-6045 CAS (FMOx)</bold></docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-06045-CAS-FMO</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 02/08/2010</date.line>
</content.date>
<content.attorney.block>
<content.attorney>
<attorney.line first-line="1">PAUL D. PIERSON, Deputy Clerk, Attorneys Present for Plaintiffs: N/A</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">NOT PRESENT, Court Reporter / Recorder, Attorneys Present for Defendants: N/A</attorney.line>
<attorney.line first-line="1">N/A, Tape No.</attorney.line>
</content.attorney>
</content.attorney.block>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>Proceedings: (In Chambers) PLAINTIFF TRANSPORT'S MOTION TO REMAND</bold> (filed 12/30/09)</headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>DEFENDANT R.R. STREET, ET AL.'S MOTION TO STAY CASE PENDING RESOLUTION OF CV09-6045-CAS OR TO CONSOLIDATE CASE WITH CV09-6045-CAS</bold> (filed 12/30/09)</headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>DEFENDANT TRANSPORT'S MOTION TO DISMISS PLAINTIFFS' COMPLAINT, OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE, TO STAY PROCEEDINGS</bold> (filed 11/12/09)</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">The Honorable CHRISTINA A. SNYDER, U.S. DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. INTRODUCTION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">On August 18, 2009, R.R. Street &#38; Co., Inc. (&#x201C;Street&#x201D;) and National Union Fire Insurance Company (&#x201C;National Union&#x201D;) filed suit against Transport Insurance Company (&#x201C;Transport&#x201D;) in this Court. On September 22, 2009, plaintiffs filed their first amended complaint (&#x201C;FAC&#x201D;), alleging a claim by Street for breach of contract, and claims by National Union for subrogation, equitable contribution, and unjust enrichment.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">On November 10, 2009, Transport filed suit against Street and National Union in the Los Angeles Superior Court, alleging claims for (1) &#x201C;declaratory relief re: breach of contract&#x201D; against Street; (2) &#x201C;declaratory relief re: subrogation&#x201D; against National Union; (3) &#x201C;declaratory relief re: equitable contribution&#x201D; against National Union; and (4) &#x201C;declaratory relief re: unjust enrichment&#x201D; against National Union. On November 16, 2009, Street and National Union removed this action to this Court.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">On November 12, 2009, Transport filed the instant motion to dismiss Street and National Union's FAC, or in the alternative to stay proceedings. On December 30, 2009, Transport filed the instant motion to remand, and Street and National Union filed the instant motion to stay the case pending resolution of related case CV09-6045-CAS filed by Street and National Union on August 18, 2009, or to consolidate the cases. On January 11, 2010, both sides filed their oppositions. Replies were filed on January 19, 2010. After carefully considering the arguments set forth by the parties, the Court finds and concludes as follows.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">From the 1960's to the 1990's, Street distributed the chemical percloroethylene (&#x201C;PerSec&#x201D;), a chlorine-based dry cleaning solvent, for PerSec manufacturer Vulcan Materials Company (&#x201C;Vulcan&#x201D;). Transport's Compl. &#182; 10; Street's FAC &#182;&#182; 6-7. National Union has defended and continues to defend Street in connection with various tort lawsuits brought against Street in California arising out of Street's distribution of PerSec as Street's subrogee. Compl. &#182;&#182; 11-13; FAC &#182;&#182; 7-8. The allegations in the underlying tort suits assert that Street is liable for personal injury or property damage caused by the sale, distribution, use, or handling of PerSec. Compl. &#182; 12; FAC &#182; 9.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">Street is an additional insured under various insurance policies issued to Vulcan by various insurers, including by Transport. Compl. &#182; 16; FAC &#182; 12. Policy No. XGL-731-81-1 (&#x201C;the 1981 Transport Policy&#x201D;), with effective dates of January 1, 1981, to January 1, 1982, was issued by Transport to Vulcan, with Street named as an &#x201C;additional insured.&#x201D; Compl. &#182; 16; FAC &#182; 13. Street and National Union allege that the 1981 Transport Policy is an umbrella policy that affords defense coverage immediately when the alleged property damage or personal injury is &#x201C;not within the terms of the coverage of underlying insurance.&#x201D; FAC &#182; 13. Street and National Union allege that because none of the property damage or personal injury alleged against Street in the underlying tort suits is within the terms of coverage of the underlying insurance, the 1981 Transport Policy requires Transport to pay for Street's defense in each of the tort lawsuits. FAC &#182;&#182; 16-17. National Union claims it is entitled to reimbursement and indemnity from Transport for attorneys' costs expended in its defense of Street. Compl. &#182; 15; FAC &#182;&#182; 16-17. Transport claims that pursuant to the terms of the 1981 Transport Policy, it has no duty to defend Street in the underlying tort suits, and thus that National Union is not entitled to reimbursement and indemnity from Transport for fees and costs expended in its defense of Street. Compl. &#182;&#182; 24-26, 29.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">According to Transport, the procedural history of the state proceedings is as follows: Since January 31, 2005, there has been pending in the Superior Court before Judge Carl J. West an action seeking a declaration of Transport's duty to defend and indemnify Vulcan. Wong Decl. &#182; 2. The relief requested by Transport includes declaratory relief as to the rights and obligations of Transport under the 1981 Transport Policy. Wong Decl. &#182; 3. On August 22, 2006, First State Insurance Company filed a first amended cross-complaint for declaratory relief against various entities including Vulcan, Transport, and National Union regarding indemnity and contribution of these claims. Wong Decl. &#182; 4. On January 24, 2007, all of these cases were consolidated into the Vulcan Consolidated Action before the Superior Court as complex cases. Wong Decl. &#182; 5. On April 11, 2008, Vulcan filed a cross-complaint in the Vulcan Consolidated Action against Street and National Union seeking declaratory relief regarding the rights and obligations under the contractual arrangement between Street and Vulcan. Wong Decl. &#182; 6. During this period, Street and National Union filed answers to the cross-complaint and conducted discovery against Vulcan and Transport, all without objection to the jurisdiction of the Superior Court. Wong Decl. &#182; 6-10. On April 9, 2009, the Superior Court ruled on certain threshold issues pertaining to the 1981 Transport Policy tendered by Transport, and this order is on appeal.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Wong Decl. &#182;&#182; 16-17. On July 2, 2009, the Superior Court granted a stipulated stay for claims against Street and National Union. Wong Decl. &#182; 18. While the stay was in place, the claims against Street and National Union were dismissed by Vulcan on August 20, 2009. Wong Decl. &#182; 19.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p7">&#8195;In its order dated April 9, 2009, the Superior Court made the following findings pertaining to the 1981 Transport Policy:</paratext>
<paratext ID="p8" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">Issue 1: 1) The wording &#x201C;within the terms of coverage of this insurance&#x201D; means that, under the circumstances of this case, a suit must be shown to be actually covered by this excess policy for the provisions to apply. If the defense obligations were &#x201C;payable&#x201D; under the terms of the primary policy, there is no duty to defend under the terms of the [1981] Transport [P]olicy.</paratext>
<paratext ID="p9" contd-flag="y" first-line="1" turnover="1">(Footnote 1 continued)</paratext>
<paratext ID="p10" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">2) Transport's duty to defend does not necessarily extend to any suit making claims that are merely potentially covered.</paratext>
<paratext ID="p11" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">Issue 2: The term &#x201C;underlying insurance&#x201D; refers to <ital>any</ital> underlying primary or SIR insurance for continuous losses, any portion of which occurred during the policy periods during which the [1981] Transport [P]olicy was in effect.</paratext>
<paratext ID="p12" contd-flag="y" first-line="2" turnover="2">Issue 3: Transport is entitled to rely on principles of horizontal exhaustion before Transport has any duty to defend Vulcan under [the 1981 Transport Policy].</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. LEGAL STANDARD</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Federal Declaratory Judgment Act</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p13" level="1">&#x201C;Consistent with the nonobligatory nature of the remedy, a district court is authorized, in the sound exercise of its discretion, to stay or to dismiss an action seeking a declaratory judgment [pursuant to the Federal Declaratory Judgment Act, 28 U.S.C. &#167; 2201(a)]<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> In the declaratory judgment context, the normal principle that federal courts should adjudicate claims within their jurisdiction yields to considerations of practicality and wise judicial administration.&#x201D; <underscore>Wilton v. Seven Falls Co.</underscore>, 515 U.S. 277, 288 (1995); <underscore>see also Huth v. Hartford Ins. Co.</underscore>, 298 F.3d 800, (9th Cir. 2002) (affirming district court's remand of a declaratory judgment action pursuant to <underscore>Wilton</underscore>). In deciding whether or not to exercise its discretion to retain jurisdiction over a declaratory judgment claim, the district court looks (1) to avoid needless determination of state law issues; (2) to discourage litigants from filing declaratory actions as a means of forum-shopping; and (3) to avoid duplicative litigation. <underscore>Huth</underscore>, 298 F.3d at 803 (citing <underscore>Brillhart v. Excess Ins. Co of Am.</underscore>, 316 U.S. 491 (1942)).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. <underscore>Colorado River</underscore> Doctrine</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p14" level="1">In the interest of &#x201C;wise judicial administration,&#x201D; federal courts may stay a case involving a question of federal law where a concurrent state action is pending in which substantially similar claims are raised. <underscore>Colorado River Water Conservation Dist. v. United States</underscore>, 424 U.S. 800, 815 (1976); <underscore>see also Nakash v. Marciano</underscore>, 882 F.2d 1411, 1416 (9th Cir. 1989) (exact parallelism between claims is not required to give rise to <underscore>Colorado River</underscore> abstention: &#x201C;It is enough if the two proceedings are &#x2018;substantially similar.&#x2019;&#x201D;). Federal courts have a &#x201C;virtually unflagging obligation&#x201D; to exercise the jurisdiction conferred upon them: <underscore>Colorado River</underscore> abstention is appropriate, therefore, only under &#x201C;exceptional circumstances.&#x201D; <underscore>Colorado River</underscore>, 424 U.S. at 813.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">In determining whether to stay or dismiss proceedings under <underscore>Colorado River</underscore> and its progeny, a court must consider: (1) whether the state and federal suits are substantially similar; (2) whether staying or dismissing would avoid &#x201C;piecemeal&#x201D; litigation; (3) whether there exists the risk of conflicting results; (4) whether the state proceeding is adequate to protect the parties' rights; (5) whether state or federal law provides the rule of decision on the merits; (6) the order in which the forums obtained jurisdiction; and (7) whether the federal suit was filed in an attempt to forum shop. <underscore>See Colorado River</underscore>, 424 U.S. at 818; <underscore>Moses H. Cone Mem. Hosp. v. Mercury Const. Corp.</underscore>, 460 U.S. 1 (1983); <underscore>Nakash</underscore>, 882 F.2d at 1416. &#x201C;No one factor is necessarily determinative; a carefully considered judgment taking into account both the obligation to exercise jurisdiction and the combination of factors counseling against that exercise is required. Only the clearest of justifications will warrant dismissal.&#x201D; <underscore>Colorado River</underscore>, 424 U.S. at 818-19 (citations omitted).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. <underscore>Rooker-Feldman</underscore> Doctrine</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Pursuant to the <underscore>Rooker-Feldman</underscore> doctrine, a federal court is without jurisdiction to exercise appellate review of state court judgments. <underscore>See Rooker v. Fidelity Trust</underscore>, 263 U.S. 413, 415-16 (1923); <underscore>District of Columbia Court of Appeals v. Feldman</underscore>, 460 U.S. 462, 482-486 (1983). Specifically, the <underscore>Rooker-Feldman</underscore> doctrine prevents &#x201C;a party losing in state court<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> from seeking what in substance would be appellate review of the state judgment in a United States District Court, based on the losing party's claim that the judgment itself violates the loser's federal [constitutional] rights.&#x201D; <underscore>Johnson v. DeGrandy</underscore>, 512 U.S. 997, 1005-06 (1994). The underlying question is whether &#x201C;the district court is in essence being called upon to review the state-court decision.&#x201D; <underscore>Feldman</underscore>, 460 U.S. at 483-484, n.16. However, the <underscore>Rooker-Feldman</underscore> doctrine does not bar a federal suit to set aside a state court judgment obtained through extrinsic fraud. <underscore>See Kougasian v. TMSL, Inc.</underscore>, 359 F.3d 1136 (9th Cir. 2004). In <underscore>Kousgasian</underscore>, a Ninth Circuit panel held that a &#x201C;plaintiff alleging extrinsic fraud on a state court is not alleging a legal error by the state court; rather, he or she is alleging a wrongful act by an adverse party,&#x201D; and is not barred by <underscore>Rooker-Feldman</underscore>. 359 F.3d at 1140-41. &#x201C;Extrinsic fraud is conduct which prevents a party from presenting his claim in court.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 1140.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Transport's Motion to Remand Case CV 09-8368 CAS (FMOx)</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Plaintiff Transport argues that the Court should remand this action for declaratory relief because there is a parallel state action, the Vulcan Consolidated Action, in which the same issues in this declaratory judgment action are being adjudicated. Mot. at 11 (citing <underscore>Wilton v. Seven Falls Co.</underscore>, 515 U.S. 277, 289 (1995); <underscore>Brillhart v. Excess Ins. Co. of Am.</underscore>, 316 U.S. 491, 495 (1942)). First, Transport argues that the common state law issues in these actions support remand because it would provide for the orderly and comprehensive disposition of all state law claims in one consolidated proceeding. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 13, 16 (citing <underscore>Brillhard</underscore>, 316 U.S. at 495; <underscore>Chamberlain v. Allstate Ins. Co.</underscore>, 931 F.2d 1361, 1366-67 (9th Cir. 1991) (&#x201C;[W]hen a party requests declaratory relief in federal court and a suit is pending in state court presenting the same state law issues, there exists a presumption that the entire suit should be heard in state court.&#x201D;)). Indeed, Transport asserts that the 1981 Transport Policy, which is the subject of this lawsuit, is also one of the subjects being litigated in the state court proceedings. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 15. Transport further asserts that Judge West actively encouraged the parties to bring these issues into state court because they were dealing with the same issues there. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 14.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">Second, Transport argues that remand would prevent forum shopping. Mot. at 17. Transport asserts that although they were well aware of the Vulcan Consolidated Action, Street and National Union filed their complaint in Case No. CV09-6045-CAS (FMOx), in an effort to obtain what they perceive to be a more favorable forum. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 17 (citing <underscore>Am. Nat. Fire Ins. Co. v. Hungerford</underscore>, 53 F.3d 1012, 1018 (9th Cir. 1995) (&#x201C;[b]y exercising jurisdiction over a suit that raised the same issues as those in a pending state court action, we would only be encouraging forum shopping in violation of the second <underscore>Brillhart</underscore> principle.&#x201D;)). Transport asserts that Street and National Union's removal of this action is a classic example of forum shopping, as these parties already were parties in the Vulcan Consolidated Action in state court and the Superior Court Judge has already related the cases. <underscore>Id.</underscore> (citing <underscore>Robsac</underscore>, 947 F2d at 1371 (&#x201C;If a declaratory judgment suit is defensive or reactive, that would justify a court's decision not to exercise jurisdiction.&#x201D;)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Third, Transport argues that remand would avoid duplicative litigation, because the Superior Court has already ruled on many of the same issues that this Court will have to consider should it exercise jurisdiction, such as the interpretation of the 1981 Transport Policy regarding when coverage applies, what type of underlying insurance applies to the 1981 Transport Policy, horizontal exhaustion, and other issues relating to Transport's duty to defend. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 19 (citing <underscore>Robsac</underscore>, 947 F.2d at 1373 (&#x201C;The third <underscore>Brillhart</underscore> factor is the policy of avoidance of duplicative litigation. Here it is clear that the policy would be frustrated by permitting the federal action to go forward during the pendency of the state court action<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> All of the issues presented by the declaratory judgment action could be resolved by the state court. Hence, permitting the present action to go forward would waste judicial resources in violation of the third <underscore>Brillhart</underscore> factor.&#x201D;)). Transport further argues that some of those rulings are already being considered by the California Court of Appeal. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 19. Transport asserts that all of the issues in this declaratory judgment action could be resolved in the Vulcan Consolidated Action in state court. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 20.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">Finally, Transport argues that the very nature of the Vulcan Consolidated Action will provide all parties with a chance to adjudicate any claims arising from the 1981 Transport Policy in one proceeding. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 21. Transport further asserts that if remanded, the parties to this action, Transport, Street, and National Union, will become part of the Vulcan Consolidated Action if they are not already parties, because the Superior Court Judge has already related this declaratory judgment action to the Vulcan Consolidated Action. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 22. Transport asserts that National Union is still a party to the Vulcan Consolidated Action because First State Insurance Company's claims against National Union are still pending in the Vulcan Consolidated Action, and both National Union and Street are amenable to service. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 23.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Defendants Street and National Union agree that under <underscore>Wilton/Brillhard</underscore>, the Court has discretion to refuse to exercise jurisdiction in this case. Opp'n at 3. However, defendants argue that the Court should refuse to exercise jurisdiction by staying this action, rather than removing it. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Defendants argue that most of the reactive litigation considered by the reported decisions involves federal declaratory judgment actions intended to preempt state court proceedings, but defendants argue that here a declaratory judgment was filed by plaintiff in state court in hopes of preempting defendants' previously filed federal court proceeding. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 4. Defendants assert that the instant action is therefore reactive litigation because it is a declaratory judgment action brought by an insurance company against its insured, seeking to deny coverage. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 5.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">The Court concludes that it is inappropriate to retain jurisdiction over this action. <underscore>See Wilton</underscore>, 515 U.S. at 283. All of the claims in Case No. CV 09-8368 CAS (FMOx) involve state law issues that have been or can be considered in the ongoing Vulcan Consolidated Action. <underscore>See Huth</underscore>, 298 F.3d at 803 (&#x201C;A district court should avoid needless determination of state law issues.&#x201D;). Furthermore, it appears that defendants Street and National Union were forum shopping when they filed their original action in federal court and then removed this related action to this Court. <underscore>See id.</underscore> Most importantly, the Court finds this litigation in federal court duplicative of that occurring in the Vulcan Consolidated Action. <underscore>See id.</underscore> (holding that a district court &#x201C;should avoid duplicative litigation&#x201D;); <underscore>see also Wilton</underscore>, 515 U.S. at 283 (&#x201C;Where another suit involving the same parties and presenting the opportunity for ventilation of the same state law issues is pending in state court, a district court might be indulging in &#x2018;gratuitous interference&#x2019; if it permitted the federal declaratory relief action to proceed.&#x201D;). Indeed, the Superior Court already interpreted the very same terms of the 1981 Transport Policy that are at issue here to make some threshold legal determinations regarding the policy's provisions in its order dated April 9, 2009. Accordingly, the Court declines jurisdiction under the Federal Declaratory Judgment Act, 28 U.S.C. &#167; 2201(a), and GRANTS plaintiff's motion to remand the action to the Los Angeles Superior Court.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Motion to Stay or to Consolidate Case CV 09-8368 CAS (FMOx)</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">In light of the Court's grant of Transport's motion to remand, it need not reach defendants Street and National Union's motion to stay or to consolidate. As such, it is DENIED as moot.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>C. Motion to Dismiss Case CV 09-6045 CAS (FMOx)</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">Defendant Transport argues that the Court should dismiss or stay Case No. CV 09-8368 CAS (FMOx) pursuant to the <underscore>Colorado River</underscore> doctrine because there is a parallel state court proceeding dealing with identical issues and exceptional circumstances are present. Mot. at 8. First, Transport argues that there has been an absence of substantial progress in the litigation before this Court, while substantial progress has been made in the state court action regarding this issues identified in plaintiffs' complaint. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 10 (citing <underscore>American Int'l Underwriters, Inc. v. Continental Ins. Co.</underscore>, 843 F.2d 1253, 1258 (9th Cir. 1988) (affirming dismissal and noting that &#x201C;[t]he state court judge has decided seven motions and the parties have engaged in substantial discovery. Very little progress has occurred in the federal lawsuit.&#x201D;). Transport asserts that the Superior Court has already ruled on many of the same issues with which this Court will be presented should it exercise jurisdiction. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Transport asserts that R.R. Street and National Union have actively participated in the Vulcan Consolidated Action regarding these issues, and that Judge West has indicated that he would likely relate the complaint filed in this case to the Vulcan Consolidated Action. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 11. Indeed, Transport asserts that plaintiffs have been, and still are, active participants in the Vulcan Consolidated Action, participating in joint conference statements, propounding discovery on Transport, and filing supplemental briefs regarding the 1981 Transport Policy. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 12.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Second, Transport argues that dismissal or a stay would prevent forum shopping, because plaintiffs filed this complaint seeking adjudication of the same state law issues and claims as in the parallel state court actions in an effort to obtain what it perceives to be a more favorable forum. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">Third, Transport argues that dismissal or a stay would prevent piecemeal litigation. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 13 (citing <underscore>American International</underscore>, 843 F.2d at 1258 (finding piecemeal litigation where district court would be deciding matters already being handled in the state court case, requiring duplicative effort and possible inconsistent results)). Transport asserts that there is a danger of inconsistent results regarding certain threshold issues pertaining to the 1981 Transport Policy. <underscore>Id.</underscore> Transport further asserts that if the complaint is not dismissed, Transport will be forced to defend itself on the same issues addressed in the complaint both in federal and state court, and given the complexity of the issues judicial resources would be wasted. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 14 (citing <underscore>In re Countrywide Fin. Corp. Derivative Litigation</underscore>, 542 F. Supp. 2d 1160, 1172 (C.D. Cal. 2008) (&#x201C;[M]ultiple courts proceeding apace on these substantially similar claims is a considerable waste of judicial resources in light of the significant complexity of this litigation.&#x201D;)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Fourth, Transport argues that the state court proceedings are adequate to protect the federal litigants' rights, because all claims in the complaint are based on state law. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 14-15. Transport further argues that because the state court proceedings were deemed &#x201C;complex,&#x201D; meaning that they require &#x201C;exceptional judicial management to avoid placing unnecessary burdens on the court or the litigants and to expedite the case, keep costs reasonable and promote effective decision making by the court, the parties and counsel,&#x201D; dismissal or a stay would further conserve judicial resources. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 15.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Finally, Transport argues that the Superior Court is willing to pursue the issues in plaintiffs' complaint should be considered as support for dismissal of the complaint. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 16. Finally, Transport argues that the other factors of a <underscore>Colorado River</underscore> analysis are either inapplicable or should be granted less weight, because there is no res, and there would not seem to be any inconvenience to the federal forum if the action were to be dismissed. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 17.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">Plaintiffs Street and National Union respond that <underscore>Colorado River</underscore> abstention is not authorized here, because the Vulcan Consolidated Action will not resolve all of the parties' claims against each other and thus the proceedings are not parallel. Opp'n at 9-11 (citing <underscore>Holder v. Holder</underscore>, 305 F.3d 854, 868 (9th Cir. 2002)). Plaintiffs assert that Street and National Union, as Street's subrogee, are no longer parties to the Vulcan Consolidated Action. Opp'n at 11. Moreover, plaintiffs assert that the state court action which relates to the interpretation of the 1981 Transport Policy does not necessarily also encompass the rights of R.R. Street, and those of National Union as R.R. Street's subrogee, under the policy.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 12-13. Furthermore, plaintiffs assert that in the action before this Court, unlike in the state court action, National Union in its individual capacity&#8212;in addition to suing as Street's subrogee&#8212;has sued defendant for equitable contribution towards Street's defense costs, and none of the issues associated with this claim will be raised or resolved in the state court action by Vulcan's reimbursement claim against Transport for defense costs. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 12-13. Plaintiffs further assert that Street's breach of contract claims against Transport for money damages are not synonymous with Vulcan's claims for damages against Transport, because Street's costs of defending the underlying tort litigation have continued for more than two years after Vulcan's ended, and thus the adjudication of Vulcan's rights under the 1981 Transport Policy cannot resolve the different coverage issues between Street and Transport, the amount of damages for which Transport may be liable to Street, National Union's independent claims against Transport for equitable contribution, or the amount of damages for which Transport is liable. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 13.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p30">&#8195;Plaintiffs argue that Transport's argument here depends on various subtle propositions of insurance law, such as that R.R. Street, as an alleged &#x201C;additional insured,&#x201D; cannot have any greater rights under the terms of the 1981 Transport Policy than Vulcan has. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Second, plaintiffs respond that there has been little progress made in resolving the Street-Transport dispute in the Superior Court, because the Superior Court's rulings regarding Vulcan are not necessarily relevant to Street insofar as Street continues to defend itself in an ongoing tort litigation matter while Vulcan settled the same matter in 2007. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 14-15</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">Third, plaintiffs respond that Transport is the party engaged in forum shopping, because plaintiffs had filed an earlier federal action in Illinois. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 15. Furthermore, plaintiffs assert that they have an independent right to file the present action in federal court based on diversity jurisdiction, and that they filed before Transport filed the parallel action in state court. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 15-16. Both arguments ignore the fact that plaintiffs have been litigating these issues in the Superior Court for two years without objection.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">Fourth, plaintiffs agree with Transport that both the state court proceedings and the proceedings in federal court are adequate to protect their rights, and thus that this factor is neutral. <underscore>Id.</underscore> at 17. Finally, plaintiffs respond that no authority supports defendant's proposition that &#x201C;encouragement&#x201D; by a state court should influence whether a federal court surrenders the jurisdiction conferred on it by the Constitution and Congress. <underscore>Id.</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Insofar as Street and National Union's claims in the instant action can be construed as a request that this Court review the Superior Court's decision dated April 9, 2009, including the Superior Court's interpretation of the 1981 Transport Policy, this Court finds that it lacks jurisdiction to do so pursuant to <underscore>Rooker-Feldman. See Feldman</underscore>, 460 U.S. at 483-484, n.16 (holding that the underlying question is whether &#x201C;the district court is in essence being called upon to review the state-court decision.&#x201D;). It appears that plaintiffs in this case are asking this Court to revisit the rulings made by the Superior Court in the Vulcan Consolidated Action, many of which are on appeal to the California Court of Appeal. For example, in its order dated April 9, 2009, the Superior Court found that the term &#x201C;underlying insurance&#x201D; in the 1981 Transport Policy is not limited to the three underlying policies specifically identified in &#x201C;Schedule A&#x201D; of the 1981 Transport Policy, but &#x201C;include[s] <underscore>all</underscore> underlying insurance.&#x201D; The Superior Court further found that &#x201C;all of the underlying coverage would have to be exhausted before Transport's defense obligations are triggered [under the 1981 Transport Policy], pursuant to the horizontal exhaustion rule.&#x201D; However, Street and National Union allege that &#x201C;because Street is not an insured under any of the [underlying] policies listed in &#x2018;Schedule A,&#x201D; the policy &#x201C;requires Transport to pay for Street's defense in each of the Underlying Actions.&#x201D; See FAC &#182;&#182; 16-17. Here, the Court finds that Street and National Union make allegations in the instant action that are directly contradictory to the findings previously made by the Superior Court, and that this Court is barred from considering them pursuant to <underscore>Rooker-Feldman</underscore>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">Furthermore, in applying the <underscore>Colorado River</underscore> doctrine, the Court concludes that this dispute would be better settled along with the proceedings in the Superior Court. First, while the action in federal court is not identical to the Vulcan Consolidated Action, it appears &#x201C;substantially similar,&#x201D; because many of the same documents, facts, and events underlie the two actions. <underscore>See Nakash</underscore>, 882 F.2d at 1416. Moreover, because this Court has remanded the related case <underscore>Transport Ins. Co. v. R.R. Street &#38; Co., Inc.</underscore>, No. CV 09-8368-CAS, <underscore>supra</underscore>, a parallel proceeding to this action is now in the Superior Court and will likely be consolidated with the Vulcan Consolidated Action. <underscore>See Nakash</underscore>, 882 F.2d at 1416. Second, dismissing the action would avoid &#x201C;piecemeal&#x201D; litigation, and there exists here a significant risk of conflicting results. <underscore>See Am. Int'l Underwriters, Inc. v. Continental Ins. Co.</underscore>, 843 F.2d 1253, 1257-58 (9th Cir. 1988) (&#x201C;Piecemeal litigation occurs when different tribunals consider the same issue, thereby duplicating efforts and possibly reaching different results.&#x201D;); <underscore>Colorado River</underscore>, 424 U.S. at 818 (finding that the avoidance of piecemeal litigation is the single most important factor to be considered).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Third, because the dispute solely concerns state law claims, the state proceeding is adequate to protect the parties' rights. <underscore>See Cone</underscore>, 460 U.S. at 23, 26; <underscore>Goldentree Asset Management v. Longaberger Co.</underscore>, 448 F. Supp. 2d 589, 594-95 (S.D. N.Y. 2006) (finding the fact that there are only issues of state law &#x201C;slightly favors abstention&#x201D;). Finally, the Superior Court obtained jurisdiction over the matter first, and at least two years of litigation has been conducted there without significant objection by Street and National Union. <underscore>See Colorado River</underscore>, 424 U.S. at 818; <underscore>Am. Int'l Underwriters, Inc.</underscore>, 843 F.2d at 1258-59. For the foregoing reasons, the Court hereby GRANTS Transport's motion to dismiss.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">In accordance with the foregoing, the Court hereby GRANTS plaintiff Transport's motion to remand Case No. CV 09-8368 CAS (FMOx) to the Los Angeles Superior Court. The Court DENIES as moot defendants Street and National Union's motion to stay or consolidate. The Court subsequently GRANTS defendant Transport's motion to dismiss Case No. CV 09-6045 CAS (FMOx).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="1">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="1">&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;: <underscore>n/a</underscore></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">Initials of Preparer <underscore>PDP</underscore></paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>