<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>CHARLES D. MINOR, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>DOUGLAS SHULMAN, in his official capacity as Commissioner, Internal Revenue Service, and SELVI STANISLAUS, in her official capacity as Executive Officer, California Franchise Tax Board, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>CASE NO. CV 09-01799 MMM (SSx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 09-01799 MMM (SSx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:09-cv-01799-MMM-SS</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 06/01/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center">ORDER GRANTING DEFENDANT'S MOTION TO DISMISS FIRST AMENDED COMPLAINT WITH PREJUDICE; REMANDING CASE TO STATE COURT</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">MARGARET M. MORROW UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1"><ital>Pro se</ital> plaintiff Charles Minor commenced this action in Los Angeles Superior Court on February 4, 2009 (&#x201C;<ital>Minor II</ital>&#x201D;). On March 16, 2009, acting on behalf of its employee, Douglas Shulman, the United States removed the case to federal court.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> Minor filed an amended complaint on April 9, 2009.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> The United States has now moved to dismiss Minor's claims against Shulman.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> Minor filed opposition on April 27.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference> Pursuant to Rule 78 and Local Rule 7-15, the court finds the matter appropriate for decision without oral argument. The hearing scheduled for June 8, 2009 is therefore vacated and taken off calendar.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p2">&#8195;See Notice of Removal, Docket No. 1 (Mar. 16, 2009); see also 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1442 (&#x201C;(a) A civil action<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> commenced in a State court against any of the following may be removed by them to the district court of the United States for the district or division embracing the place wherein it is pending: (1) The United States or any agency thereof or any officer (or any person under that officer) of the United States or any agency thereof, sued in an official or individual capacity for any act under color of such office or on account of any right, title or authority claimed under any Act of Congress for<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> the collection of the revenue&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p3">&#8195;See First Amended Complaint, Docket No. 15 (Apr. 9, 2009).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p4">&#8195;See Defendant's Notice of Motion and Motion to Dismiss First Amended Complaint; Supporting Memorandum of Points and Authorities (&#x201C;Defendant's Mot.&#x201D;), Docket No. 13 (Apr. 14, 2009); see also Government's Reply, Docket No. 19 (May 8, 2009). The State of California has not yet appeared and it is not clear that Minor has served either defendant.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p5">&#8195;See Opposition to Defendant's Motion to Dismiss First Amended Complaint (&#x201C;Minor Opp.&#x201D;), Docket No. 17 (Apr. 27, 2009). Minor also filed an improper surreply, comprised of various quotes and what appeared to be a draft order denying defendant's motion. (See Ruling (Reply) Re Motion to Dismiss, Docket No. 20 (May 26, 2009).) Pursuant to Local Rule 7-10, this filing was stricken.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>I. FACTUAL AND PROCEDURAL BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. <ital>Minor I</ital></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">In August 2006, Minor and his spouse filed a complaint alleging violations of the United States Constitution and federal statutes by the Internal Revenue Service.<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> The Minors alleged that the Internal Revenue Service (&#x201C;IRS&#x201D;), and the California Franchise Tax Board (&#x201C;FTB&#x201D;) had unlawfully attempted to collect taxes, interest and penalties from them.<footnote.reference ID="fr6" refid="f6" style="percent_n">6</footnote.reference> The complaint pleaded twenty eight causes of action alleging that the IRS or the FTB had violated federal law by trying to collect taxes from the Minors.<footnote.reference ID="fr7" refid="f7" style="percent_n">7</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p7">&#8195;See Complaint (&#x201C;<ital>Minor I</ital> Complaint&#x201D;), CV 06-04839 Docket No. 1 (Aug. 3, 2006).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f6"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN6.</label.designator><paratext ID="p8">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 4-5 (&#x201C;The United States and the State of California know that Charles D. Minor and Janet I. Minor have not engaged in any revenue taxable activity, but in order to feed their insatiable appetite for money and power have used purposefully confusing and complicated taxation codes in an attempt to impose their will on Charles and Janet Minor. Through their agent-accomplices (IRS and FTB agents) they have used intimidation, oppression, extortion and fraud to coerce Charles and Janet Minor into paying &#x2018;taxes, interest and penalties&#x2019; that Charles and Janet Minor do not lawfully owe&#x201D;); <ital>id.</ital> at 6 (&#x201C;The first part of this complaint comes under authority of 28 USC &#167; 1346(a)(1): challenging the amounts assessed and collected by the IRS and the FTB that caused Charles D. Minor and Janet I. Minor injury by 1) loss of property through the unlawful taking of property protected by the Constitution of the United States of America, 2) causing severe emotional pain and distress through continual harassment by acts of threats constituting extortion and oppression, and 3) defamation through publishing fraudulent documents in the public record&#x201D;); <ital>id.</ital> at 9 (&#x201C;Charles and Janet Minor, to the best of their knowledge, have never engaged in any revenue taxable activity. Charles and Janet Minor have many times asked the IRS and the FTB to tell them what taxable activity they have engaged in<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> The IRS and the FTB have consistently refused to answer&#x201D; (record citations omitted)); <ital>id.</ital> at 13-14 (&#x201C;Since Charles D. Minor and Janet I. Minor have not engaged in any activity making them liable under United States and California revenue laws and as there are no lawful, procedurally proper assessments concerning Charles and Janet Minor all of the IRS and FTB collection activities concerning Charles D. Minor and Janet I. Minor are fraudulent and unlawful&#x201D;); <ital>id.</ital> at 19 (&#x201C;Charles D. Minor and Janet I. Minor challenge the constitutionality of IRS and FTB collections activities as applied to [them]. Said collection activities violate due process rights protected by the Constitution for the United States of America and its attending Bill of Rights<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f7"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN7.</label.designator><paratext ID="p9">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 23-30. The statutes allegedly violated included 26 U.S.C. &#167;&#167; 6201, 6203, and 7214(a)(1), (2), (7) and 18 U.S.C. &#167;&#167; 1001 and 1341.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p10" level="1">On November 21, 2006, the United States moved to dismiss the Minors' action for lack of subject matter jurisdiction and failure to state a claim upon which relief could be granted. On July 3, 2007, the court granted the motion.<footnote.reference ID="fr8" refid="f8" style="percent_n">8</footnote.reference> It concluded that the doctrine of sovereign immunity barred the Minors' suit against the United States, and that neither Article III, &#167; 2 of the United States Constitution, nor 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1331, upon which the Minors relied, constituted an express waiver of sovereign immunity upon which jurisdiction could be predicated.<footnote.reference ID="fr9" refid="f9" style="percent_n">9</footnote.reference> The court also considered 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1346(a)(1) and 26 U.S.C. &#167; 7433, upon which the Minors alternatively relied. It observed that 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1346(a)(1) waived sovereign immunity for taxpayer suits only if certain preconditions were fulfilled, including plaintiffs' payment of the disputed taxes and the filing of a valid credit claim with the IRS.<footnote.reference ID="fr10" refid="f10" style="percent_n">10</footnote.reference> Because none of these prerequisites had been satisfied, the court concluded that &#167; 1346(a)(1) provided no basis for exercising jurisdiction.<footnote.reference ID="fr11" refid="f11" style="percent_n">11</footnote.reference> As respects 26 U.S.C. &#167; 7433(a), the court noted that it authorized taxpayer suits for damages against the United States only when an IRS employee had acted recklessly, intentionally, or negligently in enforcing the federal tax code; the court observed, however, that the statute required that a plaintiff exhaust administrative remedies before suing, which the Minors had not done.<footnote.reference ID="fr12" refid="f12" style="percent_n">12</footnote.reference> Consequently, the court concluded that it lacked subject matter jurisdiction to hear the Minors' claims against the United States.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f8"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN8.</label.designator><paratext ID="p11">&#8195;See Order Granting Defendant United States' Motion to Dismiss; Denying Plaintiffs' Motion for Summary Judgment; Denying Plaintiffs' Motion to Demand the Court Read All Pleadings; Denying Plaintiffs' Motion to Claim and Exercise Constitutional Rights' Denying Plaintiffs' Demand for Due Process and Brief on Taxation (&#x201C;<ital>Minor I</ital> Dismissal Order&#x201D;), CV 06-04839 Docket No. 52 (July 3, 2007).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f9"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN9.</label.designator><paratext ID="p12">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 4-5.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f10"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN10.</label.designator><paratext ID="p13">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 5.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f11"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN11.</label.designator><paratext ID="p14">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 6.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f12"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN12.</label.designator><paratext ID="p15">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital></paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Turning to the merits of the Minors' claims, the court noted that &#x201C;any funds a taxpayer receives are presumed to be gross income absent proof that an exception listed in the Internal Revenue Code applies.&#x201D; It observed that based on this rule, &#x201C;[c]ourts ha[d] repeatedly deemed frivolous arguments that wages are not taxable.&#x201D;<footnote.reference ID="fr13" refid="f13" style="percent_n">13</footnote.reference> Consequently, the court held that, even if it had jurisdiction, it would dismiss the Minors' causes of action against the United States with prejudice for failure to state a claim on which relief could be granted.<footnote.reference ID="fr14" refid="f14" style="percent_n">14</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f13"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN13.</label.designator><paratext ID="p17">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 6-7 (&#x201C;Although the Minors' complaint and accompanying exhibits total more than 450 pages, they do not show (or even suggest) that the Minors can assert a viable claim against the United States. The Minors allege that they have never engaged in any taxable activity and that defendants' attempts to collect taxes from them are unlawful. They further assert that they are not liable for taxes unless &#x2018;a lawful, procedurally proper assessment is made.&#x2019; These arguments are unavailing<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; (footnotes and citations omitted)).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f14"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN14.</label.designator><paratext ID="p18">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 7 (&#x201C;Even if the court had jurisdiction, moreover, it would dismiss the action with prejudice for failure to state a claim<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> The United States' motion to dismiss is therefore granted&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">Finally, the court addressed various filings by the Minors, including two motions for summary judgment. It concluded that the Minors' claims against the State of California were barred by the Eleventh Amendment, which entitled the FTB and its officials to immunity from suit in federal court.<footnote.reference ID="fr15" refid="f15" style="percent_n">15</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f15"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN15.</label.designator><paratext ID="p20">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 8-9. The court also observed that the State of California had not been properly served and had not appeared. <ital>Id.</ital> at n. 9 (&#x201C;The State of California has not appeared in this action<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> It is not clear to the court that the Minors have served the correct party<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> The record does not show that [the] Minors have completed service on the Franchise Tax Board or its officers&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Having addressed all of the Minors' claims, the court entered judgment against them.<footnote.reference ID="fr16" refid="f16" style="percent_n">16</footnote.reference> The Minors moved for reconsideration,<footnote.reference ID="fr17" refid="f17" style="percent_n">17</footnote.reference> which the court denied.<footnote.reference ID="fr18" refid="f18" style="percent_n">18</footnote.reference> They then filed an appeal in Ninth Circuit.<footnote.reference ID="fr19" refid="f19" style="percent_n">19</footnote.reference> On September 22, 2008, the Ninth Circuit affirmed the court's dismissal for lack of subject matter jurisdiction and failure to state a claim.<footnote.reference ID="fr20" refid="f20" style="percent_n">20</footnote.reference> It also imposed sanctions on the >Minors.<footnote.reference ID="fr21" refid="f21" style="percent_n">21</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f16"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN16.</label.designator><paratext ID="p22">&#8195;See Judgment for Defendants, CV 06-04839 Docket No. 51 (July 3, 2007).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f17"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN17.</label.designator><paratext ID="p23">&#8195;Notice for Reconsideration, CV 06-04839 Docket No. 53 (July 20, 2007).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f18"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN18.</label.designator><paratext ID="p24">&#8195;Order Re Plaintiffs' Notice For Reconsideration, CV 06-04839 Docket No. 56 (Aug. 3, 2007).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f19"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN19.</label.designator><paratext ID="p25">&#8195;Notice of Appeal, CV 06-04839 Docket No. 57 (Aug. 1, 2007).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f20"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN20.</label.designator><paratext ID="p26">&#8195;Defendant's Mot., Exh. 1 (Memorandum Order) at 2-3 (&#x201C;The district court properly dismissed the Minors' action seeking damages for lack of jurisdiction because sovereign immunity bars all suits against the federal government unless it expressly consents to be sued. The IRS and its agents in their official capacities have not waived sovereign immunity, and thus, the Minors' action is barred<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> Finally, because California offers a &#x2018;plain, speedy and efficient remedy&#x2019; in its courts for state tax appeals,<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> the district court properly dismissed the Minors' claims seeking declaratory and injunctive relief against the State<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> The district court also properly dismissed [the] Minors' remaining claims because the defendant state agency is not a &#x2018;person&#x2019; under 42 U.S.C. &#167;&#167; 1983 or 1985<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill>, and it is entitled to Eleventh Amendment immunity&#x201D; (citations omitted)).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f21"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN21.</label.designator><paratext ID="p27">&#8195;<ital>Id.</ital> at 3-4 (&#x201C;Because the arguments raised by the Minors on appeal are wholly without merit, we grant the government's motion to impose sanctions against the Minors for bringing a frivolous appeal<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> We impose sanctions in the amount of $1,000&#x201D; (citations omitted)).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. <ital>Minor II</ital></bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">Charles Minor commenced a new action in Los Angeles Superior Court in February 2009. In his first amended complaint, which names Douglas Shulman of the IRS and Selvi Stanislaus of the FTB as defendants in their official capacities, Minor again alleges unlawful deprivation of property as a result of defendants' tax collection efforts.<footnote.reference ID="fr22" refid="f22" style="percent_n">22</footnote.reference> Attached to the amended complaint are 140 pages of miscellaneous documents, including affidavits signed by Minor denouncing the federal and state systems of taxation; correspondence between Minor and various IRS officials; and notices of overdue federal and state taxes and penalties.<footnote.reference ID="fr23" refid="f23" style="percent_n">23</footnote.reference> On April 27, the United States moved to dismiss Minor's first amended complaint against Shulman under Rule 12(b)(6) of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure. The court issued an order setting a briefing schedule for defendant's motion, and giving Minor instructions for opposing a motion to dismiss.<footnote.reference ID="fr24" refid="f24" style="percent_n">24</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f22"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN22.</label.designator><paratext ID="p29">&#8195;First Amended Complaint at 1-7. The complaint pleads three causes of action: (1) &#x201C;trespass and trespass on the case&#x201D;; (2) &#x201C;trespass on the case &#8211; void judgment&#x201D;; and (3) vicarious liability. (<ital>Id.</ital> at 2-5.)</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f23"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN23.</label.designator><paratext ID="p30">&#8195;The dates on these notices concern taxes not paid from the early 1980s through the mid-2000s.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f24"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN24.</label.designator><paratext ID="p31">&#8195;Order Advancing Briefing Schedule and Providing Notice to <ital>Pro Se</ital> Plaintiff of Standards Governing Motions to Dismiss, Docket No. 16 (Apr. 16, 2009) at 2 (&#x201C;Defendants move to dismiss plaintiff's complaint as barred by the doctrine of res judicata. Res judicata is an affirmative defense<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> <bold>To oppose defendants' 12(b)(6) motion successfully, plaintiff must demonstrate that the allegations in the complaint state a claim upon which relief can be granted, and that this claim is distinct from claims previously litigated</bold>&#x201D; (emphasis original)).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>II. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>A. Legal Standard Governing Motions to Dismiss under Rule 12(b)(6)</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">A Rule 12(b)(6) motion tests the legal sufficiency of the claims asserted in the complaint. Dismissal is proper only where there is either a &#x201C;lack of a cognizable legal theory&#x201D; or &#x201C;the absence of sufficient facts alleged under a cognizable legal theory.&#x201D; <ital>Balistreri v. Pacifica Police Dep't</ital>, 901 F.2d 696, 699 (9th Cir. 1988). The court must accept all factual allegations pleaded in the complaint as true, and construe them and draw all reasonable inferences from them in favor of the nonmoving party. <ital>Cahill v. Liberty Mutual Ins. Co.</ital>, 80 F.3d 336, 337-38 (9th Cir. 1996); <ital>Mier v. Owens</ital>, 57 F.3d 747, 750 (9th Cir. 1995). It need not, however, accept as true unreasonable inferences or legal conclusions cast in the form of factual allegations. See <ital>Bell Atlantic Corp. v. Twombly</ital>, 550 U.S. 544, 127 S. Ct. 1955, 1965 (2007) (&#x201C;While a complaint attacked by a Rule 12(b)(6) motion to dismiss does not need detailed factual allegations, a plaintiff's obligation to provide the &#x2018;grounds&#x2019; of his &#x2018;entitle[ment] to relief&#x2019; requires more than labels and conclusions, and a formulaic recitation of the elements of a cause of action will not do. Factual allegations must be enough to raise a right to relief above the speculative level, on the assumption that all the allegations in the complaint are true (even if doubtful in fact)&#x201D; (citations omitted)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">District courts must construe <ital>pro se</ital> complaints liberally. See, e.g., <ital>Boag v. MacDougall</ital>, 454 U.S. 364, 365 (1982); <ital>Haines v. Kerner</ital>, 404 U.S. 519, 520 (1972); <ital>Resnick v. Hayes</ital>, 213 F.3d 443, 447 (9th Cir. 2000) (indicating that courts must interpret <ital>pro se</ital> pleadings in the light most favorable to the plaintiff). Nevertheless, a <ital>pro se</ital> plaintiff's complaint can be dismissed where it is clear from the allegations that he is not entitled to relief. See <ital>Haines</ital>, 404 U.S. at 520-21 (a <ital>pro se</ital> complaint must establish that plaintiff is entitled to relief); <ital>Pearson v. Brace</ital>, No. CIV S-06-2505 FCD DAD PS, 2007 WL 1574987, *1 (E.D. Cal. May 30, 2007) (considering a <ital>pro se</ital> complaint and noting that &#x201C;the court need not accept as true conclusory allegations, unreasonable inferences, or unwarranted deductions of fact&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">In deciding a Rule 12(b)(6) motion, the court generally looks only to the face of the complaint and documents attached thereto. <ital>Van Buskirk v. Cable News Network, Inc.</ital>, 284 F.3d 977, 980 (9th Cir. 2002); <ital>Hal Roach Studios, Inc. v. Richard Feiner &#38; Co., Inc.</ital>, 896 F.2d 1542, 1555 n.19 (9th Cir.1990). It may also properly consider matters that can be judicially noticed pursuant to Rule 201 of the Federal Rules of Evidence. <ital>Hal Roach Studios, Inc.</ital>, 896 F.2d at1555 n. 19; <ital>Branch v. Tunnell</ital>, 14 F.3d 449, 454 (9th Cir. 1994), cert. denied, 114 S. Ct. 2704 (1994), overruled on other grounds by <ital>Galbraith v. County of Santa Clara</ital>, 307 F.3d 1119 (9th Cir. 2002).<footnote.reference ID="fr25" refid="f25" style="percent_n">25</footnote.reference> Pleadings and orders filed in related federal court actions are a proper subject of judicial notice under Rule 201. See <ital>Molus v. Swan</ital>, CV 05-452 MMA (WMc), 2009 WL 160937, *2 (S.D. Cal. Jan. 22, 2009) (&#x201C;Courts may take judicial notice of their own records<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> Because this Court's prior orders directly relate to the matter before the Court, the Court grants Defendant Swan's request and takes judicial notice [of its prior orders]&#x201D; (citations omitted)); <ital>Estate of Blue v. County of Los Angeles</ital>, 120 F.3d 982, 984 (9th Cir. 1997) (taking judicial notice of pleadings filed in earlier, related cases); <ital>United States ex rel. Robinson Rancheria Citizens Council v. Borneo, Inc.</ital>, 971 F.2d 244, 248 (9th Cir. 1992) (federal courts may &#x201C;take notice of proceedings in other courts, both within and without the federal judicial system, if those proceedings have a direct relation to the matters at issue&#x201D;).<footnote.reference ID="fr26" refid="f26" style="percent_n">26</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f25"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN25.</label.designator><paratext ID="p35">&#8195;Considering matters that can be judicially noticed does not convert a motion to dismiss into a motion for summary judgment. <ital>MGIC Indemnity Corp. v. Weisman</ital>, 803 F.2d 500, 504 (9th Cir. 1986).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f26"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN26.</label.designator><paratext ID="p36">&#8195;Notice can be taken, however, &#x201C;only for the limited purpose of recognizing the &#x2018;judicial act&#x2019; that the order represents on the subject matter of the litigation.&#x201D; <ital>United States v. Jones</ital>, 29 F.3d 1549, 1553 (11th Cir. 1994) (citing <ital>Liberty Mut. Ins. Co. v. Rotches Pork Packers, Inc.</ital>, 969 F.2d 1384, 1388 (2d Cir. 1992)).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging"><bold>B. Res Judicata</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">The United States moves to dismiss Minor's complaint on the basis that it is barred by the doctrine of res judicata.<footnote.reference ID="fr27" refid="f27" style="percent_n">27</footnote.reference> Res judicata is an affirmative defense. See <csc>Fed</csc>.R.<csc>Civ</csc>.<csc>Proc</csc>. 8(c) (&#x201C;In responding to a pleading, a party must affirmatively state any avoidance or affirmative defense, including<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> res judicata&#x201D;). &#x201C;The facts necessary to establish an affirmative defense must generally come from matters outside of the complaint. Thus, with some exceptions, affirmative defenses should be raised in responsive pleadings, not in pre-answer motions brought under Rule 12(b).&#x201D; <ital>Worldcom, Inc. v. Graphnet, Inc.</ital>, 343 F.3d 651, 657 (3d Cir. 2003). The Ninth Circuit has specifically approved use of a Rule 12(b)(6) motion to raise a res judicata defense, however, so long as application of the doctrine does not depend on disputed issues of material fact. See, e.g., <ital>Bayone v. Baca</ital>, 130 Fed. Appx. 869, 872 (9th Cir. May 5, 2005) (Unpub. Disp.) (&#x201C;We have held that the affirmative defense of res judicata may be raised in a motion to dismiss under Rule 12(b)(6),&#x201D; citing <ital>Scott v. Kuhlmann</ital>, 746 F.2d 1377, 1378 (9th Cir. 1984)). The court thus considers whether res judicata bars Minor's action.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f27"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN27.</label.designator><paratext ID="p38">&#8195;Defendant's Mot. at 8.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>1. Claim Preclusion</bold><footnote.reference ID="fr28" refid="f28" style="percent_n">28</footnote.reference></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<footnote ID="f28"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN28.</label.designator><paratext ID="p39">&#8195;The Supreme Court has noted that the terms and concepts associated with preclusion &#x201C;are discussed in varying and, at times, seemingly conflicting terminology, attributable to the evolution of preclusion concepts of the years.&#x201D; <ital>Migra v. Warren City School District Board of Education</ital>, 465 U.S. 75, 77 n. 1 (1984). The Supreme Court has itself &#x201C;on more than one occasion<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> used the term &#x2018;res judicata&#x2019; in a narrow sense, so as to exclude issue preclusion or collateral estoppel<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> When using that formulation, &#x2018;res judicata&#x2019; becomes virtually synonymous with &#x2018;claim preclusion.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> For clarity, the court uses the more specific term &#x201C;claim preclusion&#x201D; wherever possible.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p40" level="1">Claim preclusion &#x201C;applies when the earlier suit: (1) reached a final judgment on the merits; (2) involved the same cause of action or claim; and (3) involved identical parties or privies.&#x201D; <ital>Leon v. IDX Systems Corp.</ital>, 464 F.3d 951, 962 (9th Cir. 2006) (citing <ital>Sidhu v. Flecto Co.</ital>, 279 F.3d 896, 900 (9th Cir. 2002)); see also <ital>Headwaters Inc. v. U.S. Forest Service</ital>, 399 F.3d 1047, 1052 (9th Cir. 2005) (same, quoting <ital>Tahoe-Sierra Preservation Council, Inc. v. Tahoe Regional Planning Agency</ital>, 322 F.3d 1064, 1077 (9th Cir. 2003)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p41" level="1">One of the major functions of claim preclusion &#x201C;is to force a plaintiff to explore all the facts, develop all the theories, and demand all the remedies in the first suit.&#x201D; 18 Wright, Miller &#38; Cooper, <csc>Federal Practice</csc> &#38; <csc>Procedure Juris</csc>. 2d &#167; 4408. &#x201C;Repetitive litigation is not to be allowed simply because the claim bears a new garb.&#x201D; <ital>Thistlewaite v. City of New York</ital>, 362 F.Supp. 88, 93 (S.D.N.Y. 1973). Thus, claim preclusion &#x201C;is a broad doctrine that bars bringing claims that were previously litigated as well as some claims that were never before adjudicated.&#x201D; <ital>Holcombe v. Hosmer</ital>, 477 F.3d 1094, 1097 (9th Cir. 2007) (quoting <ital>Clements v. Airport Authority of Washoe County</ital>, 59 F.3d 321, 327 (9th Cir. 1995)); see also, e.g., <ital>San Remo Hotel, L.P. v. San Francisco City and County</ital>, 364 F.3d 1088, 1094 (9th Cir. 2004) (&#x201C;Claim preclusion precludes relitigation of claims that were raised or should have been raised in earlier litigation,&#x201D; citing <ital>Migra</ital>, 465 U.S. at 77 n. 1 (&#x201C;Claim preclusion refers to the effect of a judgment in foreclosing litigation of a matter that never has been litigated, because of a determination that it should have been advanced in an earlier suit&#x201D;)); <ital>Western Systems, Inc. v. Ulloa</ital>, 958 F.2d 864, 871 (9th Cir. 1992) (&#x201C;Under res judicata, the prior judgment is conclusive &#x2018;not only as to every matter which was offered and received to sustain or defeat the claim or demand, but as to any other admissible matter which might have been offered for that purpose,&#x2019;&#x201D; quoting <ital>Nevada v. United States</ital>, 463 U.S. 110, 130 (1983)); <ital>Costantini v. Trans World Airlines</ital>, 681 F.2d 1199, 1201 (9th Cir. 1982) (&#x201C;[T]he doctrine of res judicata (or claim preclusion) &#x2018;bar(s) all grounds for recovery which could have been asserted, whether they were or not, in a prior suit between the same parties<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> on the same cause of action,&#x2019;&#x201D; quoting <ital>Ross v. IBEW</ital>, 634 F.2d 453, 457 (9th Cir. 1980)).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>2. Whether Minor's Claims Against Shulman Are Precluded</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p42" level="1">As noted, <ital>Minor I</ital> was dismissed with prejudice for failure to state a claim against the United States upon which relief could be granted. A Rule 12(b)(6) dismissal constitutes a &#x201C;final judgment on the merits&#x201D; for claim preclusion purposes. <ital>Federated Dep't Stores, Inc. v. Moitie</ital>, 452 U.S. 394, 399 n. 3 (1981) (&#x201C;The dismissal for failure to state a claim under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 12(b)(6) is a &#x2018;judgment on the merits,&#x2019;&#x201D; citing cases). The first prong of the claim preclusion test is thus satisfied here.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p43" level="1">The second prong is also fulfilled. A suit against a federal official, like Shulman, for acts performed within his official capacity amounts to an action against the sovereign. Courts have held that res judicata &#x201C;bars subsequent litigation against federal officials sued in their official capacity when the United States has won on the same issue in a previous suit.&#x201D; <ital>Thurston v. United States</ital>, 810 F.2d 438, 444 (4th Cir. 1987) (citing <ital>Mathis v. Laird</ital>, 457 F.2d 926 (5th Cir.), cert. denied, 409 U.S. 871 (1972)); see also, e.g., <ital>Headley v. Bacon</ital>, 828 F.2d 1272, 1279 (8th Cir. 1987) (&#x201C;Litigation involving the government is generally binding with respect to governmental officials who are sued in their official capacities in later actions,&#x201D; collecting cases); <ital>Johnson v. District of Columbia</ital>, No. Civ.A. 04-936(RMC), 2005 WL 1903551, *5-6 (D.D.C. July 20, 2005) (&#x201C;Importantly, privity exists for <ital>res judicata</ital> purposes between the government and its officers<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill> Because asserting a claim against a government official in his official capacity is the same as asserting a claim against the government directly, <ital>res judicata</ital> bars Plaintiff's section 1983 claim against Officer Bruce in his official capacity as well&#x201D; (citations omitted)). Although <ital>Minor I</ital> named the United States as defendant, while <ital>Minor II</ital> names Shulman in his official capacity, the privity requirement for claim preclusion is nonetheless satisfied.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p44" level="1">The third and final requirement inquires whether this suit involves the &#x201C;same cause of action&#x201D; as the prior action. Traditionally, four factors are considered in determining whether successive lawsuits involve the same &#x201C;cause of action.&#x201D; <ital>Littlejohn v. United States</ital>, 321 F.3d 915, 920 (9th Cir. 2003). These are: &#x201C;(1) whether rights or interests established in the prior judgment would be destroyed or impaired by the prosecution of the second action; (2) whether substantially the same evidence is presented in the two actions; (3) whether the two actions involve infringement of the same right; and (4) whether the two actions arise out of the same transactional nucleus of facts.&#x201D; <ital>Id.</ital> at 921 (citing <ital>Clark v. Bear Stearns &#38; Co.</ital>, 966 F.2d 1318, 1320 (9th Cir. 1992)). Of these, the last criterion &#x201C;is the most important.&#x201D; <ital>Constantini</ital>, 681 F.2d at 1201 (citing <ital>Harris v. Jacobs</ital>, 621 F.2d 341, 343 (9th Cir. 1980)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p45" level="1">In assessing &#x201C;[w]hat factual grouping constitutes a &#x2018;transaction,&#x2019;&#x201D; courts take a pragmatic approach, &#x201C;giving weight to such considerations as whether the facts are related in time, space, origin, or motivation, whether they form a convenient trial unit, and whether their treatment as a unit conforms to the parties' expectations or business understanding or usage.&#x201D; <csc>Restatement</csc> (<csc>Second</csc>) <csc>Judgments</csc> &#167; 24(b); see also <ital>id.</ital> cmt. a (&#x201C;The present trend is to see [the concept of] claim in factual terms and to make it coterminous with the transaction regardless of the number of substantive theories, or variant forms of relief flowing from those theories, that may be available to the plaintiff; regardless of the number of primary rights that may have been invaded; and regardless of the variations in the evidence needed to support the theories or rights&#x201D;); <ital>Western Systems</ital>, 958 F.2d at 868 (&#x201C;Res judicata bars both claims actually litigated and those that arise from the same transaction and <ital>could have been</ital> litigated in a prior proceeding&#x201D;); <ital>id.</ital> at 871 (&#x201C;Whether two events are part of the same transaction or series depends on whether they are related to the same set of facts and whether they could conveniently be tried together,&#x201D; citing <csc>Restatement</csc> (<csc>Second</csc>) <csc>Judgments</csc> &#167; 24(2)).<footnote.reference ID="fr29" refid="f29" style="percent_n">29</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f29"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN29.</label.designator><paratext ID="p46">&#8195;By contrast, &#x201C;California's res judicata doctrine is based on a primary rights theory. The California Supreme Court [has] explained that the primary rights theory: &#x2018;[P]rovides that a &#x201C;cause of action&#x201D; is comprised of a &#x201C;primary right&#x201D; of the plaintiff, a corresponding &#x201C;primary duty&#x201D; of the defendant, and a wrongful act by the defendant constituting a breach of that duty. The most salient characteristic of a primary right is that it is indivisible: the violation of a single primary right gives rise to but a single cause of action.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Manufactured Home Communities Inc. v. City of San Jose</ital>, 420 F.3d 1022, 1031 (9th Cir. 2005) (quoting <ital>Mycogen Corp. v. Monsanto Co.</ital>, 28 Cal.4th 888,904 (2002) (citations omitted)).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p47" level="1">A careful review of Minor's first amended complaint and its attachments, and a comparison of these documents with the complaint and supporting documentation filed in <ital>Minor I</ital>, demonstrates that this suit satisfies the &#x201C;same cause of action&#x201D; requirement. First and foremost, the action arises out of the same &#x201C;transactional nucleus of facts&#x201D; as <ital>Minor I</ital>. The core of both suits is Minor's theory that the federal government lacks the authority to collect income taxes, and that its efforts to do so over nearly two decades have unlawfully deprived him of certain constitutional, statutory, and common law rights. These facts are related in origin and motivation and would form a convenient trial unit; moreover, it would be reasonable for the federal defendants to expect that the allegations would be litigated in one suit.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p48" level="1">In addition to these factual similarities, the first amended complaint alleges violations that purportedly occurred between the early 1990s and the mid-2000s. The temporal span covered by the present complaint is identical to that at issue in <ital>Minor I</ital>. &#x201C;Matters with a common historic origin ordinarily form a convenient package for joint litigation.&#x201D; 18 Wright, Miller &#38; Cooper, <csc>Federal Practice</csc> &#38; <csc>Procedure Juris</csc>. 2d &#167; 4407.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p49" level="1">Turning to the remaining factors that are relevant in assessing whether the &#x201C;same cause of action&#x201D; requirement is met, Minor clearly alleges infringement of the same rights he asserted in <ital>Minor I</ital>. Although Minor now pleads common law claims, the substance of the rights allegedly violated by the federal defendants' acts and/or omissions is identical. See, e.g., <ital>May v. Circus Circus Enterprises, Inc.</ital>, No. 97-16055, 1997 WL 813996, *1 (9th Cir. Dec. 17, 1997) (Unpub. Disp.) (&#x201C;May cannot defeat the application of res judicata by alleging new statutes or legal theories&#x201D;).<footnote.reference ID="fr30" refid="f30" style="percent_n">30</footnote.reference> Substantially the same evidence would be required to proceed in this action as was necessary in the prior litigation; permitting Minor to relitigate the issues, moreover, would undoubtedly destroy the rights and interests established by the court's judgment in <ital>Minor I</ital>.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f30"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN30.</label.designator><paratext ID="p50">&#8195;See also <ital>Banks v. Int'l Union Electronic, Electrical, Technical, Salaried and Machine Workers</ital>, 390 F.3d 1049, 1052-53 (8th Cir. 2004) (&#x201C;[R]eliance on different substantive law and new legal theories does not preclude the operation of res judicata. Where a plaintiff fashions a new theory of recovery or cites a new body of law that was arguably violated by a defendant's conduct, res judicata will still bar the second claim if it is based on the same nucleus of operative facts as the prior claim,&#x201D; quoting <ital>Lane v. Peterson</ital>, 899 F.2d 737, 744 (8th Cir. 1990) (punctuation omitted)); <ital>Clark v. Haas Group, Inc.</ital>, 953 F.2d 1235, 1238-39 (10th Cir. 1992) (&#x201C;Inasmuch as the doctrine of res judicata precludes parties from relitigating issues that were or could have been raised, parties cannot defeat its application by simply alleging new legal theories&#x201D; (collecting cases)); <ital>Laychock v. Wells Fargo Home Mortgage</ital>, Civil Action No. 07-4478, 2008 WL 2890962, *4 n. 5 (E.D. Pa. July 23, 2008) (&#x201C;Asserting different laws, statutes, or theories of recovery will not by itself preclude application of <ital>res judicata</ital>,&#x201D; citing <ital>United States v. Athlone Industries, Inc.</ital>, 746 F.2d 977, 984 (3d Cir. 1984)); see generally 18 Wright, Miller &#38; Cooper, <csc>Federal Practice</csc> &#38; <csc>Procedure Juris.</csc> 2d &#167; 4411 (&#x201C;A second action may be precluded on the ground that the same claim or cause of action was advanced in the first action even though a different source of law is involved. Claim preclusion may apply to theories advanced under different statutes, under common law and statute, or under the laws of different sovereigns&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p51" level="1">In view of the foregoing, the court concludes that Minor's first amended complaint against Shulman is barred by res judicata and must be dismissed with prejudice.<footnote.reference ID="fr31" refid="f31" style="percent_n">31</footnote.reference> As this dismissal destroys the basis for federal question jurisdiction, the court remands Minor's remaining claims against Stanislaus and the FTB to Los Angeles Superior Court for final determination.<footnote.reference ID="fr32" refid="f32" style="percent_n">32</footnote.reference></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f31"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN31.</label.designator><paratext ID="p52">&#8195;In his opposition, Minor argues that &#x201C;Case number CV06-04839 was dismissed therefore the issues of this case have never been adjudicated. Case no. CV 06-04839 proceeds from an inferior court. This is a court of record and is a superior court. It is the prerogative of the superior court to review the prior case because an inferior court has no presumption of validity. There is no res judicata.&#x201D; (Minor Opp. at 2 (footnotes omitted).) For the reasons discussed, these contentions are unavailing.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<footnote ID="f32"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN32.</label.designator><paratext ID="p53">&#8195;Under 28 U.S.C. &#167; 1367(c), if the district court has dismissed all the claims over which it has original jurisdiction, the court may decline to exercise supplemental jurisdiction over the remaining claims. Here, the dismissal of the federal defendant removes the only basis upon which the court's jurisdiction was predicated. The court therefore declines to exercise jurisdiction over the remaining claims. See <ital>Murphy v. Kodz</ital>, 351 F.2d 163, 167-68 (9th Cir. 1965) (&#x201C;Where the federal head of jurisdiction has vanished from the case, and there has been no substantial commitment of judicial resources to the nonfederal claims it is<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> akin to &#x2018;making the tail wag the dog&#x2019; for the District Court to retain jurisdiction&#x201D;).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>III. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p54" level="1">For the reasons stated, the court grants the United States' motion to dismiss Minor's first amended complaint. Minor's claims against Shulman are dismissed with prejudice. The balance of the action is remanded to state court for further adjudication.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p55" level="0">DATED: June 1, 2009</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>