<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>CENTRAL DISTRICT OF CALIFORNIA</venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>XPAYS, INC., Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>INTERNET COMMERCE GROUP, INC., an Arizona corporation; SK INTERTAINMENT, INC., an Illinois corporation; ADULT PROFIT, a Danish business entity of unknown form; LUCINA S.L., a Spanish business entity of unknown form; WEB TRAFFIC, INC., an Australian corporation; TARASANT, a Singaporean business entity of unknown form; and VEROTEL MERCHANT SERVICES B.V., a Dutch business entity of unknown form, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. CV 06-05688 DDP (FFMx)</docket.line>
<docket.number>CV 06-05688 DDP (FFMx)</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">2:06-cv-05688-DDP-VBK</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 03/04/2009</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER GRANTING IN PART DEFENDANT SK INTERTAINMENT, INC.'S MOTION IN LIMINE NO.1 &#38; GRANTING MOTION IN LIMINE NO.2</bold></headtext></head>
<head><headtext align="center">[Motions in Limine filed on June 16, 2008]</headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">DEAN D. PREGERSON United States District Judge</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">This matter comes before the Court on Defendant SK Intertainment, Inc.'s Motion in Limine #1.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> SK Intertainment (&#x201C;SK&#x201D;) has moved to exclude the report and testimony of Joseph Segal (&#x201C;Segal&#x201D;), designated expert witness of Plaintiff XPays, Inc. (&#x201C;XPays&#x201D;). SK argues that Segal's testimony should be excluded on the following grounds: (1) his report is incomplete in violation of Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(a), and therefore the entirety of his testimony must be excluded; (2) his report and testimony does not meet the requirements of Federal Rule of Evidence 702 because it is not &#x201C;based upon sufficient facts or data&#x201D; or reliable;(3) he is not qualified to testify as to likelihood of or actual confusion or damages, in violation of Federal Rule of Evidence 702; and (4) Segal's testimony regarding the popularity of Paris Hilton is irrelevant. After reviewing the materials submitted by the parties and hearing oral argument, the Court grants in part and denies in part the Motion in Limine.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p2">&#8195;On February 23, 2009, XPays filed a Notice of Non-Opposition to SK's Motion in Limine #2. Accordingly, the Court grants Motion in Limine No. 2.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>I. BACKGROUND</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">This case concerns claims for damages arising out of the use by defendants of portions of Paris Hilton's sex tape, &#x201C;One Night in Paris.&#x201D; XPays argues it is a co-owner of the tape. After acquiring what it argues are exclusive licensing rights, XPays set up a webmaster affiliate program to commercially exploit the video via the internet. Defendant SK runs a website that reviews nude scenes of popular actresses in mainstream film. SK earns revenue through its review site. Defendant ICG is also an internet company that earns revenue through its site(s). XPays alleges that both SK and ICG posted images and clips from the video on their respective websites. The following claims remain in this case: (1) willful copyright infringement by each defendant and (2) violations of the Lanham Act, 15 U.S.C. &#167; 1125(a) by making false or misleading statements regarding the video that caused a likelihood of confusion among the public.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">On September 27, 2007, XPays designated Segal as its expert trial witness on the subjects of internet marketing schemes and the market confusion and other damage caused thereby. On February 29, 2008, XPays served the Expert Report of Joseph Segal. Alterwitz Decl., Ex. A (&#x201C;Segal Report&#x201D;). In that Report, Segal stated that he has been working in the adult internet industry since 1996. Segal Report at 1. Segal has worked as a marketing consultant for the industry and expresses that he has knowledge &#x201C;about determining the cost of a new customer or member acquisition, the value of a membership, and the common marketing methods and practices used to gain new customers that are particular to the adult internet industry.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> In the Introduction to his Report, Segal states that he formed the opinion that &#x201C;the use of images and clips from the Paris Hilton sex video by SK and ICG caused confusion in the marketplace and substantially harmed XPays' rights in the video.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> His Report further opines to some extent on the following points: (1) the popularity of the Paris Hilton sex tape, <underscore>id.</underscore> at 2, (2) how web surfer-consumers get to a particular site and/or are drawn to join that site by marketing, <underscore>id.</underscore> at 2-4 (3) how long a subscriber will continue to subscribe after joining a site for particular content, <underscore>id.</underscore> at 4, and (4) affiliate relationships, <underscore>id.</underscore> at 4-5. SK neither moved for more adequate disclosures nor took Segal's deposition.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">SK moves to exclude Segal's testimony on a number of grounds. First, SK argues that Segal's Report does not meet the disclosure requirements of Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(a)(2), and therefore must be precluded pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 37(c)(1). Second, SK argues that Segal is not qualified to testify with regard to market confusion or damages and that the report is not based on sufficient facts or data to be admissible, in violation of Federal Rule of Evidence 702. Third, SK argues that Segal cannot serve as a damages expert because he does not include damage estimations or calculations. Finally, SK argues that the popularity of Paris Hilton is &#x201C;not relevant and<charfill numchar="3">&#8228;</charfill> not disputed.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>II. LEGAL STANDARDS</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p6" level="1">Two related rules are at issue here: Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(a)(2), which governs disclosure requirements for potential expert testimony, and Federal Rule of Evidence 702, which governs the admissibility of expert testimony at trial.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A. <underscore>Expert Disclosure Requirement, Fed. R. Civ. P. 26(a)(2)(B)</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p7" level="1">The Federal Rules of Civil Procedure provide for significant disclosure of, among other things, potential expert testimony. Pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(a)(2), a party must disclose the identity of any witnesses it may use at trial to present evidence under Federal Rule of Evidence 702. Fed. R. Civ. P. 26(a)(2)(A). Where the witness is retained or specially employed for litigation, as is the case with Segal, the expert must provide a written report. Fed. R. Civ. P. 26(a)(2)(B). That report must contain:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p8" first-line="1" turnover="1">(i) a complete statement of all opinions the witness will express and the basis and reasons for them;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" first-line="1" turnover="1">(ii) the data or other information considered by the witness in forming them;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" first-line="1" turnover="1">(iii) any exhibits that will be used to summarize or support them;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" first-line="1" turnover="1">(iv) the witness's qualifications, including a list of all publications authored in the previous 10 years;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" first-line="1" turnover="1">(v) a list of all other cases in which, during the previous four years, the witness testified as an expert at trial or by deposition; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" first-line="1" turnover="1">(vi) a statement of compensation to be paid for the study and testimony in this case.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p14" contd-flag="y"><underscore>Id.</underscore> These disclosure requirements were meant to curb the practice under the prior rule, where a disclosure was &#x201C;frequently so sketchy and vague that it rarely dispensed with the need to depose the expert and often was even of little help in preparing for a deposition of the witness.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 26, Adv. Comm. Note to 1993 Amdts. The rule requires that experts prepare &#x201C;a detailed and complete written report, stating the testimony the witness is expected to present during direct examination, together with the reasons therefor.&#x201D; <underscore>Id.</underscore> Rule 26(b)(4) allows the deposition of an expert after this report is made. As one district court has put it, a report satisfies Rule 26 if &#x201C;it was sufficiently complete, detailed and in compliance with the Rules so that surprise is eliminated, unnecessary depositions are avoided, and costs are reduced.&#x201D; <underscore>Reed v. Binder</underscore>, 165 F.R.D. 424, 429 (D.N.J. 1996)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p15" level="1">Rule 37(c)(1) provides an &#x201C;incentive&#x201D; for complete disclosure: if a party fails to provide information as required in 26(a), the party will not be allowed to use that information at trial &#x201C;unless the failure was substantially justified or is harmless.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 37(c)(1); Fed. R. Civ. P. 26, Adv. Comm. Note to 1993 Amdts. SK primarily contests only the first of the requirements for a Report, the completeness of the Report's disclosure as to the opinions to be expressed. Fed. R. Civ. P. 26(a)(2)(B)(i).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">B. <underscore>Federal Rule of Evidence 702</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">Under Federal Rule of Evidence 702, trial courts have a gatekeeping function regarding expert testimony. <underscore>Daubert v. Merrell Dow Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</underscore>, 509 U.S. 579, 589 n.7 (1993). Where &#x201C;scientific, technical, or other specialized knowledge will assist the trier of fact&#x201D; in understanding evidentiary or factual issues, an expert witness who is qualified by &#x201C;knowledge, skill, experience, training, or education&#x201D; may &#x201C;testify thereto in the form of an opinion or otherwise.&#x201D; Fed. R. Evid. 702. In addition, Rule 702 requires that:</paratext>
<para><paratext ID="p17" first-line="1" turnover="1">1) the testimony is &#x201C;based upon sufficient facts or data&#x201D;;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" first-line="1" turnover="1">2) the testimony is the &#x201C;product of reliable principles and methods&#x201D;; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" first-line="1" turnover="1">3) the witness has &#x201C;applied the principles and methods reliably to the facts of the case.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p20" contd-flag="y">Fed. R. Evid. 702. District courts must evaluate expert scientific testimony for both relevance and reliability. The proponent of the expert testimony has the burden of establishing that the relevant admissibility requirements are met by a &#x201C;preponderance of the evidence.&#x201D; <underscore>Daubert</underscore>, 509 U.S. at 592 n.10 (citing <underscore>Bourjaily v. United States</underscore>, 483 U.S. 171, 175 (1987)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">In performing its gatekeeping function, a court determines reliability based on a flexible inquiry tied to the facts of the particular case. <underscore>Kumho Tire Co., Ltd. v. Carmichael</underscore>, 526 U.S. 137, 152 (1999). The focus should be &#x201C;solely on principles and methodology, not on the conclusions they generate.&#x201D; <underscore>Daubert</underscore>, 509 U.S. at 595; <underscore>see also</underscore> Fed. R. Evid. 702 Adv. Comm. Note to 2000 Amdt. Although &#x201C;a trial court's gatekeeping function requires more than simply &#x2018;taking the expert's word for it,&#x2019;&#x201D; an expert's experience alone can provide a sufficient foundation for expert testimony, so long as the witness explains &#x201C;how that experience leads to the conclusion reached, why that experience is a sufficient basis for the opinion, and how that experience is reliably applied to the facts.&#x201D; Fed. R. Evid. 702 Adv. Comm. Note to 2000 Amdt. This gatekeeping function, of course, is distinct from a fact-finding role, and leaves ample room for cross-examination to explore the weaknesses in a particular expert opinion, including the experience or knowledge of the expert.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>III. DISCUSSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">SK both attacks the sufficiency of the disclosure and questions whether Segal's potential testimony will satisfy the requirements of Rule 702. In particular, SK attacks (1) Segal's qualifications as an expert, (2) the factual basis for the Report, and (3) the reliability of Segal's testimony.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">With respect to Rule 26, the Court notes that this is not a situation where there was an untimely expert report or no expert report provided at all. Additionally, because Segal has not yet testified in Court, and because XPays has not sought to admit his testimony for specific reasons, it is difficult to establish how Rule 26(a)(2)(B) and Rule 37(c)(1) should limit Segal's testimony. That is, there may be some topics where the testimony could go beyond the disclosure, and would therefore be improper, and some topics where disclosure is adequate. While a disclosure under Rule 26(a)(2)(B) must contain the complete statement for the opinions and the reasons for them, the disclosure need not be so specific that cross-examination would be unhelpful or unnecessary. To the extent the topics have been placed squarely before it, however, the Court considers SK's motion by looking topic-by-topic at Segal's anticipated testimony.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">The Court agrees with SK that Segal's Report is general in many places. However, the Court finds that Segal's Report lays a sufficient foundation to satisfy Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(a)(2)(B) and Federal Rule of Evidence 702 for some topics of testimony. On other potential topics of testimony, however &#8211; including some that are mentioned in his Report &#8211; Segal will be precluded from testifying as an expert. The Court finds that Segal may testify as to marketing techniques of companies, generally why such techniques are used, and different sources of income for these types of sites, including through their relationships with affiliates. The Court finds that Segal may not testify as to the specific amount of damages or losses sustained in this case: he has not opined on this subject and his Report discloses no basis on which he would have been able to make such a determination. To the extent specific further issues arise during, the Court does not preclude SK from raising its challenges at that time. The Court cannot, of course, opine on the relevance or admissibility of specific testimony that has not yet been sought, given, or raised.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="0"><bold>///</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="0"><bold>///</bold></paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">A. <underscore>Marketing</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">The Court finds that Segal may testify about marketing schemes in the adult internet entertainment industry. Segal's Report discusses the advertising approaches used here, and how, based on his experience, customers may respond to these approaches. Additionally, Segal's report discusses other ways that internet companies make money.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">The techniques used in a particular industry reflect specialized knowledge about which expert testimony would assist a jury. Fed. R. Evid. 702. Additionally, the Court finds that Segal's Report adequately discloses the basis for testimony as to marketing schemes in the adult internet entertainment industry. Segal's Report discloses his qualifications in that portion of the industry, discussing his role as a marketing consultant and the time he has spent working in the industry. Segal Report at 1:4-14.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> Segal's opinions on marketing techniques are based on his experience in the industry, and he explains what those experiences have shown. The Court finds that this discussion, and the comparison of those techniques with the documents discussed here as the basis of Segal's opinion, meets the threshold for reliability required in Rule 702. Although the Court recognizes that Segal's opinions do not provide significant detail, SK may use cross-examination to critique these opinions &#8211; and may object to those portions of his testimony that go beyond the basis provided in his declaration. Segal may testify about marketing techniques used by internet companies. Additionally, Segal may testify as to sources of revenue at which those marketing approaches are aimed, including those structured through affiliate programs.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p29">&#8195;For the purposes of Rule 26, it is relevant, though certainly not dispositive, that SK has not challenged the adequacy of Segal's disclosure until now. <underscore>Cf. Harvey v. District of Columbia</underscore>, 949 F. Supp. 874, 877 (D.D.C. 1996)</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p30" level="1">Segal may not testify, however, as to the costs of a new customer or member acquisition. Although Segal's Report indicates that he has knowledge on the subject, the Report contains no opinions as to costs. Because Rule 26(a)(2)(B) requires that a report provide &#x201C;a <ital>complete statement</ital> of the opinions a witness will present,&#x201D; testimony of opinions outside of that Report would be inappropriate. Fed. R. Civ. P. 26(a)(2)(B) (emphasis added).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">B. <underscore>Confusion in the Marketplace</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p31" level="1">Segal's Report states that &#x201C;it is [his] opinion that the use of images and clips from the Paris Hilton sex video by [the defendants] caused confusion in the marketplace and substantially harmed XPays' rights in the Video.&#x201D; Segal Report at 1:25-28.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p32" level="1">While Segal may testify to the marketing techniques used by advertisers to draw customers in the adult internet industry, Segal's Report does not contain sufficient analysis or disclosure of his opinion for him to testify as to consumer confusion in this case. Although the Introduction to Segal's Report states that he has concluded that the advertisements &#x201C;caused confusion in the marketplace,&#x201D; nothing in the Report indicates analysis getting to that conclusion. While the Report opines on how a consumer might act, it does so by discussing the harm that might come from such actions, as opposed to the basis for confusion or data or evidence indicating there was in fact confusion. <underscore>See</underscore> Segal Report at 3:17-4:3. Put differently, although Segal repeatedly refers to &#x201C;confusion&#x201D; and &#x201C;harm,&#x201D; the discussion actually only goes to harm as opposed to actual confusion. Additionally, Segal repeatedly refers to what consumers and affiliates <ital>might</ital> have done. The only citation to actual events in this case indicating that the advertisements &#x201C;caused confusion&#x201D; is the citation to an increase in SK's sales during July 2004. While the Court considers it appropriate for Segal to opine on the potential reactions of consumers based on his experience in marketing (indeed, the likely reactions of customers may be crucial to such techniques), there is nothing in the Report to satisfy the Court that his opinion that the clips &#x201C;caused&#x201D; confusion was based on sufficient facts to make that opinion reliable. Accordingly, Federal Rule of Evidence 702 precludes Segal from testifying to this specific conclusion.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="center">C. <underscore>Damages</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p33" level="1">Additionally, the Court finds that Segal may only testify to damages in limited ways. The exact ways in which XPays intends to use Segal to opine on damages are not clear to the Court. Focusing specifically on the fact that Segal's Report does not include damages calculations, SK seeks to prevent XPays from opining on damages altogether.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p34" level="1">Segal may not testify as to the specific amount of damages in this case or perform damages calculations. Though his Report states that he has concluded that use of images and clips from the video &#x201C;substantially harmed XPays' rights in the Video,&#x201D; Segal's Report does not discuss any specific costs of membership to Mrskin.com or CelebrityHardcore.com. Nor does he discuss other specific damages numbers that would be relevant to this case. Segal neither suggests that he is qualified to perform a damages calculation &#8211; particularly in a way that would be helpful to a jury &#8211; nor suggests that he has attempted to make such a calculation. The only point at which Segal mentions specific dollar amounts is through an example of membership fees. <underscore>See</underscore> Segal Report at 4:8-10. It is unclear to the Court whether this example has a basis in the record of this case. The Court does not consider this brief reference sufficient to give notice that specific damages are a subject in Segal's opinion, to establish that he is qualified to quantify damages in an expert witness capacity, or to establish that he is qualified to opine on the particular profit structure of different adult internet industry sites. Thus, on the grounds of both Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 26(a)(2)(B) and Federal Rule of Evidence 702, Segal may not testify on the specific amount of damages in this case.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p35" level="1">Segal may, however, testify generally as to the sources of revenue for an adult internet site, even though those sources of revenue may have some impact on the jury's damages. Segal's experience in and knowledge of the industry give the discussion in his Report sufficient reliability to satisfy Rule 702. Likewise, the Report appears to provide a sufficient disclosure on these issues and therefore satisfies rule 26(a)(2)(B). Again, SK is free to cross-examine Segal in order to undermine his credibility or the merit of his opinions on these issues and SK is likewise free to raise Rule 26 issues again should Segal testify on the basis of information or to opinions that are not disclosed in the Report.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">D. <underscore>Popularity of Paris Hilton and the Video</underscore></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p36" level="1">Additionally, SK protests to any testimony by Segal on Paris Hilton's popularity. The Court will not preclude Segal from mentioning the fact that Hilton is popular; this fact may be relevant to other parts of his testimony, and he discusses it in connection with that in his report. It does not appear to the Court that Segal's Report discloses a basis for the apparent opinion that Hilton's video is the most popular in years. Segal Report at 6:5-6. Although Segal may testify from his own recollection on this issue, he may not testify as an expert to that fact, as the basis for that opinion is either unclear or absent. <underscore>Cf. Atmel Corp. v. Information Storage Devices, Inc.</underscore>, 189 F.R.D. 410, 415-16 (N.D. Cal. 1999).</paratext></para>
</section.body>
<head><headtext align="left" first-line="0" turnover="hanging"><bold>IV. CONCLUSION</bold></headtext></head>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p37" level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court will allow Segal to testify as to marketing approaches and reasons why those marketing approaches might be successful based on this particular industry, affiliate relationships, and potential sources of revenue for a site linked to those issues. For instance, Segal may testify about how long a subscriber will tend to subscribe to a site and how these sites tend to make money. SK is free to cross-examine Segal as to the extent and nature of his experience on these subjects. As Segal's Report discloses no basis for him to opine on the actual damages in this case, he may not testify to that subject. Additionally, to the extent Segal's testimony actually goes beyond the scope of the Report at trial in a way not addressed here, SK is free to object to that testimony at that point.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p38" level="0">IT IS SO ORDERED.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p39" level="0">Dated: March 4, 2009</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>