<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.thomsonreuters.com/legal/judicialdocs http://prod.content.judicial.int.westgroup.com/ContentService/resources/judicialartifact/schema/judicial.artifact.xsd">
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name><bold>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</bold></venue.name>
<venue.name><bold>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF OKLAHOMA</bold></venue.name>
</content.venue>
<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>MGT CONSTRUCTION MANAGEMENT, INC., a Virginia corporation, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>EAST END VILLAGE, LLC, an Oklahoma limited liability company, Defendant.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>
<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>Case No. 15-cv-336-GKF-TLW</docket.line>
<docket.number>15-cv-336-GKF-TLW</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">4:15-cv-00336-GKF-TLW</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>
<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 08/31/2015</date.line>
</content.date>
<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold><underscore>ORDER</underscore></bold></headtext></head>
<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1"><csc>Gregory Y.K. Frizzell, Chief Judge</csc> UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</judge.line>
</content.judge>
<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext ID="p1" level="1">Before the court is the motion to dismiss of defendant East End Village, LLC (&#x201C;East End&#x201D;). [Dkt. #12]. Plaintiff MGT Construction Management, Inc. (&#x201C;MGT&#x201D;) asserts claims for breach of contract, unjust enrichment, foreclosure of mechanic's liens, and tortious interference. MGT's claims arise from an alleged contract through which East End employed MGT as its general contractor on a development project in downtown Tulsa.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p2" level="1">There are two other lawsuits involving East End, MGT, and several of MGT's subcontractors that were filed in Tulsa County District Court before this lawsuit commenced. In the first, MGT's subcontractors, as MGT has here, filed for foreclosure on mechanic's liens on the development properties. In the second, East End sued MGT for breach of contract, breach of fiduciary duty, false representation, quiet title, and slander of title. East End's quiet title claim is also brought against MGT's subcontractors. The parties expect the two state court actions to be consolidated. For ease of reference, the court will refer to the to-be-consolidated actions collectively as the &#x201C;state court action.&#x201D;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p3" level="1">East End asks this court to abstain from exercising jurisdiction over MGT's claims under the Supreme Court's decision in <ital>Princess Lida of Thurn and Taxis v. Thompson</ital>, 305 U.S. 456 (1939), which guides a federal court's abstention analysis when two lawsuits in different courts require the exercise of jurisdiction over the same <ital>res</ital> in two <ital>in rem</ital> proceedings.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p4" level="1">Under <ital>Princess Lida</ital>, when &#x201C;the same parties are involved in litigation that is <ital>in rem</ital> or <ital>quasi in rem</ital>, the court where the last suit was filed must yield jurisdiction.&#x201D; <ital>Cassity v. Pitts</ital>, 995 F.2d 1009, 1012 (10th Cir. 1993) (citing <ital>Princess Lida</ital>, 305 U.S. at 466). East End argues MGT's claim for foreclosure of liens is an <ital>in rem</ital> action, and thus, subject to the <ital>Princess Lida</ital> doctrine. In addition, East End argues MGT's other claims are <ital>quasi in rem</ital> because their outcome potentially impacts the property that is the subject of MGT's foreclosure claim. Thus East End argues <ital>Princess Lida</ital> requires this court to decline to exercise subject matter jurisdiction over all of MGT's claims and dismiss the case under Rule 12(b)(1).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p5" level="1">In response, MGT admits the foreclosure claim is <ital>in rem</ital>. However, MGT argues <ital>Princess Lida</ital> is not an isolated test, but rather one of several factors to be considered in the larger abstention analysis outlined in <ital>Colorado River Water Conservation Dist. v. United States</ital>, 424 U.S. 800 (1976). The <ital>Colorado River</ital> factors guide a court in determining whether to abstain from exercising jurisdiction &#x201C;to avoid duplicative litigation&#x201D; when a parallel state court action is already underway. <ital>See</ital> 17A Fed. Prac. &#38; Proc. &#167; 4247. MGT argues the <ital>Colorado River</ital> factors, considered as a whole, support this court's retention of jurisdiction over its claims. Those factors are:<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference></paratext>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p6">&#8195;The Supreme Court recognized four additional factors in <ital>Moses H. Cone Mem'l Hosp. v. Mercury Constr. Corp.</ital>, 460 U.S. 1 (1983). Those factors, included here as factors 5-8, are now part of the <ital>Colorado River</ital> analysis as conducted in the Tenth Circuit. <ital>See Fox v. Maulding</ital>, 16 F.3d 1079, 1082 (10th Cir. 1994).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext ID="p7" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(1) Whether either court has assumed jurisdiction over property;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p8" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(2) The inconvenience of the federal forum;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p9" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(3) The desirability of avoiding piecemeal litigation;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p10" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(4) The order in which the courts obtained jurisdiction;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p11" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(5) The vexatious or reactive nature of either the federal or the state action;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p12" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(6) Whether federal law provides the rule of decision;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p13" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(7) The adequacy of the state court action to protect the federal plaintiff's rights; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p14" first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(8) Whether the party opposing abstention has engaged in impermissible forum shopping.</paratext></para>
<paratext ID="p15" contd-flag="y"><ital>Fox v. Maulding</ital>, 16 F.3d 1079, 1082 (10th Cir. 1994). Relevant here, the first factor presents the same question for the court as <ital>Princess Lida</ital>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p16" level="1">The court is unaware of any specific guidance from the Tenth Circuit as to whether <ital>Princess Lida</ital> should be considered a separate rule or, alternatively, as simply the first of the <ital>Colorado River</ital> factors. Some circuits take the latter approach. <ital>See e.g., Alpert v. Riley</ital>, 2011 WL 801978, **10-11 (S.D.Tex. Feb. 10, 2011) (&#x201C;The Fifth Circuit treats the <ital>Princess Lida</ital> principle as one of the factors considered under <ital>Colorado River</ital>.&#x201D;). Some of those circuits nevertheless treat <ital>Princess Lida</ital> as a <ital>dispositive</ital> factor. <ital>Derma Pen, LLC v. 4EverYoung Ltd.</ital>, 2015 WL 791595, *7 (D. Utah Feb. 25, 2015) (unreported) (citing <ital>F.D.I.C. v Four Star Holding Co.</ital>, 178 F.3d 97, 102 (2d Cir. 1999) &#38; <ital>Washington St. Corp. v. Lusardi</ital>, 976 F.2d 587, 589 (9th Cir. 1992) (Second and Ninth Circuits treat first <ital>Colorado River</ital> prong as dispositive)); <ital>see also Scherbenske v. Wachovia Mortg.</ital>, FSB, 626 F.Supp.2d 1052, 1057 (E.D.Cal. 2009) (same regarding Ninth Circuit).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p17" level="1">Courts in the Tenth Circuit have applied <ital>Princess Lida</ital> without reference to <ital>Colorado River</ital> or its other factors, suggesting <ital>Princess Lida</ital> operates as an independent rule or at least as a dispositive factor for <ital>in rem</ital> or <ital>quasi in rem</ital> cases. <ital>See, e.g., Cassity v. Pitts</ital>, 995 F.2d 1009, 1012 (10th Cir. 1993); <ital>Wilcoxson v. Sec. Bank &#38; Tr. Co. of Lawton</ital>, 516 F.Supp. 3, 4 (W.D. Okla. 1980). Given that the parties agree the foreclosure claims are <ital>in rem</ital>, both here and in the state court action, <ital>Princess Lida</ital> prevents this court from exercising jurisdiction over MGT's foreclosure claim. Accordingly, that claim must be dismissed.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p18" level="1">MGT's other claims are contractual or quasi-contractual in nature. East End argues these claims are <ital>quasi in rem</ital>, and thus subject to the <ital>Princess Lida</ital> rule, because their outcome potentially impacts the property that is the subject of MGT's foreclosure claim. In support, East End cites several cases in which claims involving the disposition of the assets of a trust were considered <ital>quasi in rem</ital> for <ital>Princess Lida</ital> purposes because the claims potentially impacted the <ital>res, i.e.</ital>, the trust. None of those cases involved claims for damages unrelated to a trust. MGT's breach of contract and quasi-contract claims seek money damages and could be resolved without this court exercising <ital>in rem</ital> jurisdiction over the properties that are already within the jurisdiction of the state court. Thus, <ital>Princess Lida</ital> does not require the dismissal of MGT's other claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p19" level="1">However, East End also invokes <ital>Colorado River</ital>, which, as noted above, provides several factors to guide the court in deciding whether to abstain from exercising jurisdiction to avoid duplicative litigation. Unlike the <ital>Princess Lida</ital> rule, <ital>Colorado River</ital> is not limited to <ital>in rem</ital> claims. Thus, if the <ital>Colorado River</ital> factors support abstention, the court may stay or dismiss this case.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p20" level="1">Before reaching the factors, the court must determine a threshold issue&#8212;whether the federal and state proceedings are &#x201C;parallel,&#x201D; meaning that &#x201C;substantially the same parties&#x201D; are litigating &#x201C;substantially the same issues.&#x201D; <ital>Fox</ital>, 16 F.3d at 1081. As noted above, in the state court action, East End brings breach of contract, breach of fiduciary duty, false representation, quiet title, and slander of title claims against MGT based on the work done, or not done, on the development project. The same parties are litigating the consequences of the difficulties surrounding the same development project under the same contract between MGT and East End. The court concludes these are &#x201C;substantially the same issues&#x201D; as those presented in this case, and thus, the cases are parallel.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p21" level="1">Having determined the cases are parallel, the court must next use the eight <ital>Colorado River</ital> factors listed above to determine &#x201C;whether deference to [the] state court proceedings is appropriate under the particular circumstances.&#x201D; <ital>Fox</ital>, 16 F.3d at 1082. In doing so, &#x201C;[n]o single factor is dispositive; &#x2018;[t]he weight to be given to any one factor may vary greatly from case to case, depending on the particular setting of the case.&#x2019;&#x201D; <ital>Fox</ital>, 16 F.3d at 1082 (citing <ital>Cone</ital>, 460 U.S. at 16).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p22" level="1">As noted above, the first factor, jurisdiction over property, is not relevant to MGT's contract and quasi-contract claims. Of the remaining factors, some are neutral or do not discourage an exercise of jurisdiction. The federal forum is equally convenient as the state forum; the two courthouses are one block apart. Neither lawsuit appears to be &#x201C;vexatious or reactive.&#x201D; Vexatious or reactive lawsuits in this setting are &#x201C;contrived&#x201D; claims, merely &#x201C;defensive tactical maneuvers.&#x201D; <ital>Cone</ital>, 103 U.S. at 17, n. 20. Both lawsuits appear to be genuine assertions of claims based on difficulties related to the development project. MGT's claims in this case arise under state law, and thus federal law does not provide the rule of decision. The state court is an adequate forum for the assertion of MGT's claims, which can be brought there as counter-claims and/or defenses. The court is unconvinced that MGT will face bias in state court because it is an out-of-state entity. As East End notes, Oklahomans staff each court and would serve as jurors in either setting.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p23" level="1">Other factors weigh in favor of abstention. Allowing MGT's contract and quasi-contract claims to proceed in this suit would result in piecemeal litigation and could lead to inconsistent rulings as to the parties' conduct and the implications of that conduct under the contract between them. The risks associated with piecemeal litigation are particularly acute in this case, where both lawsuits and all claims hinge on the interpretation and application of the same contract to the parties' behavior. Given that these claims can all be resolved by the state court and cannot all be heard in this court, this factor weighs heavily in favor of abstention. <ital>See 1st Nat'l Credit Corp. v. Von Hake</ital>, 511 F.Supp. 634, 644 (D.Utah 1981) (dismissing federal action to avoid piecemeal litigation).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p24" level="1">As discussed in more detail below, the state court action predates this action by three days. Although the lawsuits began close in time and thus the order in which the courts obtained jurisdiction does not weigh heavily, it nevertheless weighs in favor of abstention.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p25" level="1">Finally, the court examines whether MGT, the party opposing abstention, has engaged in impermissible forum shopping. On June 12, 2015, MGT and East End agreed to waive the provision of their contract requiring mediation prior to litigation. East End filed its state court action against MGT later that day. MGT, having lost the &#x201C;race to the courthouse,&#x201D; filed this federal action against East End three days later. East End may well have chosen the state court forum for its lawsuit against MGT in part because the state court is the only place it could sue both MGT and MGT's subcontractors. The subcontractors, unlike MGT, are Oklahoma entities whose presence in this lawsuit would defeat diversity jurisdiction. MGT clearly sees &#x201C;a tactical advantage from the application of federal court rules,&#x201D; as it could have presented its claims in the state court action. That kind of forum shopping &#x201C;weighs in favor of&#x201D; abstention. <ital>Travelers Indem. Co. v. Madonna</ital>, 914 F.2d 1364, 1371 (9th Cir. 1990) (cited in <ital>Fox</ital>, 16 F.3d at 1082).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p26" level="1">Weighing all of these factors together, and giving particular weight to the factors most relevant to the circumstances here&#8212;especially the avoidance of piecemeal litigation&#8212;the court concludes abstention is appropriate under <ital>Colorado River</ital> for MGT's contractual and quasi-contractual claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p27" level="1">Having so concluded, the court may either stay these proceedings or grant dismissal. Either path &#x201C;necessarily contemplates that the federal court will have nothing further to do in resolving any substantive part of the case<charfill numchar="4">&#8228;</charfill>&#x201D; <ital>Cone</ital>, 103 U.S. at 28; <ital>see also</ital> 17A Fed. Prac. &#38; Proc. &#167; 4247. Because MGT's claims may be asserted in the state court action, this court concludes the best course is to dismiss this action, recognizing the federal courts &#x201C;remain open to a dismissed plaintiff who later demonstrate[s] the inadequacy of the state forum.&#x201D; <ital>Cone</ital>, 103 U.S. at 28.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p28" level="1">WHEREFORE, the defendant's Motion to Dismiss [Dkt. #12] is granted.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext ID="p29" level="1">ENTERED this 31st day of August, 2015.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>