===== NDGA_532192_L.1.03-cv-00121-181-KCLTO.request.xml =====
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load>
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF GEORGIA</venue.name>
<venue.name>ATLANTA DIVISION</venue.name>
</content.venue>

<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>UNDERWRITERS INSURANCE COMPANY, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>ATLANTA GAS LIGHT COMPANY, and GENERAL PIPELINE COMPANY, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>

<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>CIVIL ACTION FILE NO. 1:03-CV-0121-JEC</docket.line>
<docket.number>1:03-CV-0121-JEC</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">1:03-cv-00121-JEC</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>

<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 10/14/2008</date.line>
</content.date>

<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold><u>ORDER &#x0026; OPINION</u></bold></headtext></head>

<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">JULIE E. CARNES UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>

<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>


<para><paratext level="1">This case is presently before the Court on plaintiff's Request for Defendant to Supplement Discovery Responses [151], defendant's Motion for Protective Order [159], plaintiff's Motion to Compel [165], defendant's Motion to Supplement Filing Regarding Motion for Protective Order [167], and defendant's Motion to Enforce Consent Order [170], Plaintiff's Request for Defendant to Supplement Discovery Responses [151] and defendant's Motion to Supplement Filing [167] are <bold>GRANTED as unopposed.</bold> As to the remaining motions, for the following reasons, the Court concludes that defendant's Motion for Protective Order [159] should be <bold>DENIED,</bold> plaintiff's Motion to Compel [165] should be <bold>GRANTED,</bold> and defendant's Motion to Enforce Stipulation [17 0] should be <bold>GRANTED.</bold></paratext></para>
<head-c><u><bold>BACKGROUND</bold></u></head-c>
<para><paratext level="1">This dispute arises out of a tort claim filed by Tina Henry against defendants Atlanta Gas Light Company (&#x201C;AGLC&#x201D;) and General Pipeline Company (&#x201C;GP&#x201D;) for a house fire that led to the death of two residents of a home in which AGLC and GP had been doing work. (Order [126] at 1.) Ms. Henry filed suit against AGLC and GP, alleging that both had acted negligently. <italic>{Id.)</italic> Plaintiff Underwriters Insurance Company (&#x201C;Underwriters&#x201D;) provided insurance that covered GP&#x2019; s work on the Henry home.    <italic>{Id.)	</italic>AGLC was purportedly covered as  an &#x201C;additional insured&#x201D; on GP's policy.  <italic>{Id..)</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Underwriters filed this action seeking a ruling that it was not obliged, under the terms of the GP policy, to indemnify, cover or defend AGLC in the Henry litigation. <italic>{Id.</italic> at 2.) AGLC brought a counterclaim against Underwriters seeking full reimbursement, as well as attorney's fees and damages, for Underwriters&#x2019; allegedly, bad faith refusal to pay the entire amount of a settlement that was ultimately assessed against AGLC. (Order [126] at 2.) The Court granted summary judgment to AGLC on its coverage claim, finding that AGLC qualified as an &#x201C;additional insured&#x201D; under the GP policy. <italic>{Id:</italic> at 3.) Following the Court's summary judgment order, the only claim left to be decided was AGLC's bad faith claim against Underwriters. <italic>{Id.)</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">On May 4, 2005, Underwriters moved for summary judgment on the bad faith claim. (PL's Mot. for Summ. J. [86].) AGLC indicated that it needed additional discovery before it could respond to the motion. (Def.&#x2019;s Resp. to PL's Mot. for Summ. J. [90].) Following an unsuccessful attempt at mediation, the Court reopened discovery. (Order [107].) Pursuant to the Court's direction, the parties submitted a Joint Scheduling Order that provided timetables for both parties to conduct discovery &#x201C;relevant to AGLC's remaining [bad faith] claims.&#x201D;  (Consent Scheduling Order [108].)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">The parties&#x2019; subsequent efforts to conduct discovery on the bad faith claims have been contentious and frequently unproductive. Indeed, the discovery period opened with a motion to compel and a request for the Court to conduct an <italic>in camera</italic> review of the documents on Underwriters&#x2019; privilege log to determine whether those documents should be produced.   (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. to Compel [109].)  The motion to compel was swiftly followed by a motion for a protective order pertaining to various interrogatories and requests for production. (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. for Protective Order [115].) The Court issued a final ruling on AGLC's motion to compel on February 19, 2008, triggering a two-month discovery period that should have expired on April. .19, 2008. (Order [144].) However, the parties have been unable to meet the April 19 deadline because they have now become embroiled in yet another discove'ry dispute, which is the subject of the motions that are currently before the Court.  (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. for Protective Order [159] and PL's Mot. to Compel [165].)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">The latest round of motions involves a dispute over Underwriters&#x2019; request for a Rule 30(b)(6) deposition of AGLC. <italic>(Id.)</italic> Underwriters has served a Rule 30(b)(6) notice covering the following topics: (1) the factual basis for AGLC's bad faith claims; (2) the amount and reasonableness of AGLC's claim for attorney's fees; (3) AGLC's responses to Underwriters&#x2019; interrogatories and requests for production concerning AGLC's remaining claims; and (4) AGLC's files relating to gas service, repairs and maintenance at the Henry home, and information concerning a service call to the Henry home made by AGLC in January 1999 as a result of a gas leak.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> (PL's Mot. to Compel [165] at Ex. B.) AGLC has refused to comply with the notice. <italic>{Id.</italic> at 1.) Underwriters has thus filed a motion to compel AGLC's compliance.  <italic>(Id. )</italic></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195; Underwriters initially served the Rule 30(b)(6) notice shortly after the Court reopened discovery on AGLC's bad faith claim at the end of 2005. (PL's Mot. to Compel [165] at Ex. B.) Underwriters re-noticed the deposition during the two-month discovery period following AGLC's motion to compel in February, 2008.  <italic>(Id.)</italic></paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext level="1">AGLC objects to certain topics listed in the Rule 30(b)(6) notice: specifically topics related to the underlying Henry litigation. (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. for Protective Order [159].) AGLC contends that discovery concerning the Henry claim is irrelevant because the Court has already granted summary judgment on the coverage issue. <italic>{Id.</italic> at 11-13.) AGLC also suggests that discovery concerning the Henry claim is unduly burdensome and cumulative, because Underwriters has access to the discovery that was conducted in the Henry litigation. <italic>{Id.</italic> at 13-16.) AGLC has thus filed a motion for a protective order as to those topics in the Rule 30(b) (6) notice that relate to the underlying Henry claim.  <italic>{Id.  </italic> at 13.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">AGLC also objects to Underwriters&#x2019; proposed timing of the Rule 30(b)(6) deposition. (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. to Enforce Consent Order [170].) After reviewing the Rule 30(b)(6) notice, AGLC informed Underwriters of its belief that the first four topics listed in the notice could be more efficiently addressed by an expert witness, as opposed to a corporate representative. <italic>{Id.</italic> at 4.) Thereafter, AGLC sought an agreement to delay the deposition until after Underwriters had conducted expert, discovery. <italic>{Id.)</italic> In a Consent Order that was entered on April 21, 2008, Underwriters agreed that it would only ! seek a Rule 30(b) (6) deposition in the event that it needed additional information <italic>after</italic> completing expert discovery. (Stipulation and Consent Order [155].) Underwriters has reviewed the reports of AGLC's expert witnesses, but it has yet to depose those witnesses. (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. to Enforce Consent Order [170] at 2-3.) AGLC has thus filed a motion to postpone the Rule 30(b) (6) deposition until after Underwriters has deposed AGLC's expert witnesses. <italic>(Id.)</italic></paratext></para>
<head-c><u><bold>DISCUSSION</bold></u></head-c>
<head-0><bold>I. <u>Underwriters<italic>&#x2019;  </italic> Motion to Compel and AGLC's Motion for Protective Order</u></bold></head-0>
<head-1><bold>A.   All of the Topics Listed in Underwriters&#x2019; Rule 30(b) (6) Notice are Relevant.</bold></head-1>
<para><paratext level="1">The Federal Rules contemplate liberal and permissive discovery of relevant information. <italic>See</italic> <sc>Fed.</sc> R. <sc>Civ.</sc> P. 26(b). Pursuant to Rule 26(b), &#x201C;[pjarties may obtain discovery regarding any nonprivileged matter that is relevant to any party's claim or defense.&#x201D; <italic>Id.</italic> In the discovery context, the term &#x201C;relevant&#x201D; has been construed broadly to encompass &#x201C;any matter that bears on, or that reasonably could lead to other matter that could bear on, any issue that is or may be in the case.&#x201D; <italic>Oppenheimer Fund, Inc. v. Sanders,</italic> 437 U.S. 340, 351 (1978). See also <italic>Adkins v. Christie,</italic> 488 F.3d 1324, 1331 (11th Cir. 2007}(noting that district courts are &#x201C;bound to adhere &#x201C;to the liberal spirit&#x2019;&#x201D; of Rule 26) (quoting <italic>Burns v. Thiokol Chem. Corp.,</italic> 483 F.2d 300, 305 (5th Cir. 1973)). Evidence does not have to be admissible at trial to be relevant under Rule 26. <sc>Fed.</sc> R. <sc>Civ.</sc> P. 26(b). It simply has to be &#x201C;reasonably calculated to lead to the discovery of admissible evidence.&#x201D; <italic>Id.</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">AGLC contends that the following items in Underwriters&#x2019; Rule 30{b)(6) notice are not relevant to its bad faith claims:</paratext>

<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">5.	Any service call made by AGLC in January 1999 to the home located at 1043 Hillcrest Drive, Atlanta, as a result of a call from Tina Henry regarding a gas leak.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">6.	AGLC's responses to Underwriters&#x2019; Interrogatories to AGLC regarding its remaining claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">7.	AGLC's responses to Underwriters&#x2019; Requests for Production to AGLC regarding its remaining claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">8.	AGLC's files relating to gas service, repairs, and maintenance at the Henry home.</paratext></para>
<paratext contd-flag="y">(Def.&#x2019;s Mot. for Protective Order [159] at 9.}  The basis of AGLC's relevance objection to Items 6 and .7 is unclear.   Both items specifically request information relating to AGLC's bad faith claims.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Items 5 and 8 are less directly related to the bad faith claims, but are nevertheless- relevant under Rule 26.  Under Georgia law, bad faith  is  defined  as  a  &#x201C;&#x2018;&#x2018;frivolous  and  unfounded  denial  of liability.&#x2019;&#x201D; <italic>Russell  v.   Dairyland Ins.   Co.,  </italic> 580 F. Supp. 726, 730- 731 {N.D. Ga. 1984)  (Evans, J.)(quoting <italic>State   Farm  Mut.   Auto.    Ins.</italic> <italic>Co.   v.   Harper, </italic> 125 Ga. App. 696, 188 S.E. 2d 813 (1972) ).<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference> An insurer is not liable for bad faith when it has &#x201C;reasonable grounds to contest [a] claim.&#x201D; <italic>Roland v.   Georgia  Farm Bureau Mut.   Ins.   Co., </italic> 265 Ga. 776, 777, 462 S.E. 2d 623, 625 (1995;.  Reasonable grounds exist where there is a &#x201C;doubtful question of law&#x201D; or a &#x201C;disputed question of fact.&#x201D;  Fed., Jus. <italic>Co.  </italic> v. <italic>Nat&#x2019;1   Dist rib.   Co.,    Inc.,  </italic> 203 Ga. App. 763, 769, 417 S.E. 2d 671, 676 (1992).  The facts surrounding the underlying Henry claim clearly bear on the question of whether Underwriters had reasonable grounds to deny the claim and contest coverage.  Items 5 and 8 are thus relevant to AGLC s bad faith claim. See <italic>Oppenheimer  Fund,  </italic> 437 U.S. at 351.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195; Bad faith can also be shown by an insurer's conduct while handling a claim. <italic>See Georgia Farm Bureau Mut. Ins. Co. v. Jackson,</italic> 240 Ga. App. 127, 130, 522 S.E. 2d 716, 719-20 (1999) (finding bad faith where the insurer did not take its position that there was a &#x201C;doubtful question&#x201D; of law until 14 months after the initial claim was made).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<head-1><bold>B.   The Requested Discovery Is Not Unreasonably Cumulative or Burdensome</bold>.</head-1>
<para><paratext level="1">AGLC contends, in the alternative, that Underwriters&#x2019; requests for deposition testimony on the above topics is &#x201C;unduly burdensome.&#x201D; (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. for Protective Order [159] at 13.)  In support of this argument, AGLC notes that Underwriters is in possession of the entire file from the underlying Henry litigation, including the deposition testimony of various corporate representatives.  <italic>{Id.  </italic> at 14.)  AGLC suggests that the testimony Underwriters now requests is cumulative I   &#x2018; of the testimony provided in the previous lawsuit.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference> <italic>(Id.)</italic> The Court does not agree.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195; Rule 26(b)(2) requires the Court to limit discovery that is &#x201C;unreasonably cumulative or duplicative.&#x201D; <sc>Fed.</sc> R. Civ. P. 26(b)(2), Rule 26(c) permits the Court to enter a protective order to limit discovery that causes &#x201C;annoyance, embarrassment, oppression, or undue burden or expense.&#x201D;  <sc>Fed.</sc> R. <sc>Civ.</sc> P. 26(c).</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext level="1">Underwriters was not a party to, and thus did not have an opportunity to conduct discovery in, the underlying Henry litigation. In defending its interests in this case, Underwaters should not be forced to rely, on the discovery efforts of third parties in a previous case.   Moreover, Underwriters&#x2019; deposition requests are unquestionably reasonable and hardly extraordinary.  Underwriters simply seeks to depose a corporate party concerning the basis of the &#x0024;1 million dollar bad faith claim that it has asserted against Underwriters.   See Provide <italic>Commerce,    Inc.    v.    Preferred   Commerce, inc.,   </italic> 2008 WL 360588 *2-3 (S.D. Fla. 2008) (discussing a corporate party's duty to prepare and produce a corporate representative to respond to a Rule 30(b)(6)notice).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">In short, the Court finds that all of the topics on Underwriters&#x2019; Rule 30(b)(6) notice are relevant and permissible under the Federal Rules. There is no basis for prohibiting the requested discovery as unduly burdensome, or on any other grounds. Accordingly, AGLC's motion for protective order [159] is <bold>DENIED</bold> and Underwriters&#x2019; motion to compel [165] is <bold>GRANTED.</bold></paratext></para>
<head-0><bold>II. <u>AGLC's Motion to Enforce the April 21, 2008 Consent Order</u></bold></head-0>
<para><paratext level="1">The only remaining question concerns the timing of Underwriters&#x2019; requested deposition.  After reviewing Underwriters&#x2019; Rule 30(b)(6) notice, AGLC informed Underwriters of its belief that several of the topics in the notice could be addressed more efficiently by an expert witness, as opposed to a. corporate representative.  (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. to Enforce Consent Order [170] at 4. )  In an attempt to avoid another round of discovery motions, AGLC proposed that Underwriters withdraw the Rule 30(b) (6} notice until after Underwriters had conducted expert discovery. <italic>{Id.}     </italic> In exchange for Underwriters&#x2019; agreement to withdraw the notice for the time being, AGLC agreed to:  (1) provide interrogatory answers covering topics 1-4 of the notice; and (2) provide its expert reports and make its experts available for deposition in compliance with the existing scheduling order.  <italic>(Id.)</italic> Underwriters reserved its right to continue with the Rule 30(b) (6) deposition if, after completing expert discovery, it still believed that it needed additional information. <italic>(Id.  </italic> at 5.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">The parties memorialized their agreement in a Consent Order on April 21, 2008. (Stipulation and Consent Order [155].) The Consent Order provides that:</paratext>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">a.	AGL[C] will provide interrogatory answers to the subjects covered in Items 1-4 [of the Rule 30(b)(6) notice]. Subject to the approval of this Stipulation and Consent Order, AGL[C] has agreed to provide interrogatory answers by April 25, 2008.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">b.	AGL[C] will name experts on the subjects in Items 1-4 and will provide expert reports on or before the current established deadline of May 12, 2008, and will make its experts available for deposition, as contemplated by the Court's current scheduling orders. .</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">c.	Items 1-4 of [Underwriters'] Rule 30(b)(6). Notice are withdrawn for the time being. <bold>In the event [Underwriters] believes that it needs more information than is provided in the interrogatory answers and the expert testimony, it may file a new Rule 30(b) (6) Notice on the same topics after the completion of discovery. </bold> AGL[C] agrees not to object to the new notice on grounds that it is untimely, but may raise any other objections. The Court hereby permits such re-nqtice of the issues addressed in items 1-4 after the current discovery deadline. If necessary, the Court will resolve any objections AGL[C] may have to the propriety of any further Rule 30{b) (6) Notice. If the discovery produces new information, the Parties reserve the right to seek further discovery regarding the new information and the Court's guidance regarding the scope of such discovery.</paratext></para>
<paratext contd-flag="y"><italic>(Id.)	</italic>The  Consent  Order  clearly establishes  a  sequence  for completing discovery:  (1)  First, AGLC will provide interrogatory answers addressing the first four topics listed in Underwriters&#x2019; Rule 30 (b) (6} notice; (2) Next, AGLC will disclose its experts on those topics and make those experts available for deposition; (3} Then, Underwriters  will  depose AGLC's  experts;  and  (4}  Finally,  if Underwriters believes it needs more information than is provided in the interrogatories and expert testimony, it can re-notice the Rule 30(b)(6) deposition <italic>after  the  completion   of discovery.       (Id.)</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">AGLC has provided the interrogatory answers and expert reports that are required under the Consent Order.  (Def.&#x2019;s Mot. to Enforce Consent Order [17 0] at 2.)   Although AGLC has made its experts available for deposition, Underwriters has yet to depose those experts, as required to trigger AGLC's obligation to submit to a Rule 30(b) (-6) deposition under the plain terms of the Consent Order. <italic>(Id.</italic> at 2-3.)  Accordingly, the Court <bold>GRANTS</bold> AGLC's motion to enforce the parties&#x2019; consent order [170] .   In the revised discovery deadlines that are set out below, the Court will require Underwriters to complete its discovery of AGLC's expert witnesses prior to conducting the Rule 30(b) (6) deposition that it requests.</paratext></para>
<head-0><bold>III. <u>Timelines for Completing Discovery</u></bold></head-0>
<para><paratext level="1">Based on the Court's review of the latest filings, there are several items of discovery that remain to be completed in this case. The  remaining discovery should be completed according to the following schedule:</paratext>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(1} Underwriters should depose AGLC's expert witnesses by <bold>Friday, October 31, 2008.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(2)	If requested by Underwriters, AGLC should submit to a Rule 30{b) (6) deposition by <bold>Friday, November 7, 2008.</bold> All of the&#x2019; items listed in Underwriters&#x2019; Rule 30(b) (6) notice are proper topics of questioning in the deposition.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(3)	Underwriters should disclose its experts and provide expert reports to AGLC by <bold>Friday, November 14, 2008.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(4)	AGLC should depose Underwriters&#x2019; experts by <bold>Friday, November 21, 2008.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(5)	AGLC should identify any rebuttal experts, if any, and provide expert reports, by <bold>Friday, November 28, 2008.</bold></paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(6)	Underwriters should depose AGLC's rebuttal experts by <bold>Monday, December 8, 2008,</bold> thereby ending discovery on the remaining claims in this case.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="hanging">(7)	Motions for summary judgment are due by <bold>Monday, December 22, 2008.</bold> Response and reply deadlines are to be governed by Local Rule 7.1(B) and (C).</paratext></para></para>
<para><paratext level="1">The parties  are directed to cooperate  in completing the remaining discovery.  The parties shall work together in a serious attempt to resolve any further disputes without the Court's intervention. Any additional motions to compel or motions for protective order will result in an assessment of fees to the losing party, and quite likely additional sanctions, pursuant to Rule 37 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure. Plaintiff's request for sanctions against defendant remains under advisement.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Finally, the Court will <u><bold>not</bold></u> grant any extensions to the above deadlines. Motions for summary judgment must be filed by the deadline set out above; any corresponding responses and replies shall be filed by the deadlines set out by local rule.</paratext></para>
<head-c><u><bold>CONCLUSION</bold></u></head-c>
<para><paratext level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court <bold>GRANTS as unopposed</bold> plaintiff's Request for Defendant to Supplement Discovery Responses [151] and defendant's Motion to Supplement Filing [167]. The Court <bold>DENIES</bold> defendant's Motion for Protective Order [159], <bold>GRANTS</bold> plaintiff's Motion to Compel [165], and <bold>GRANTS</bold> defendant's Motion to Enforce Consent Order [170].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">SO ORDERED, this <u>14</u> day of October, 2008.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>
