===== NDGA_532193_L.1.03-cv-00121-218-KCLTO.request.xml =====
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load>
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF GEORGIA</venue.name>
<venue.name>ATLANTA DIVISION</venue.name>
</content.venue>

<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>UNDERWRITERS INSURANCE COMPANY, Plaintiff,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>ATLANTA GAS LIGHT COMPANY, and GENERAL PIPELINE COMPANY, Defendants.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>

<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>CIVIL ACTION FILE NO. 1:03-CV-0121-JEC</docket.line>
<docket.number>1:03-CV-0121-JEC</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">1:03-cv-00121-JEC</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>

<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 03/18/2009</date.line>
</content.date>

<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><u><bold>ORDER  &#x0026;  OPINION</bold></u></headtext></head>

<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">JULIE E. CARNES CHIEF UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>

<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>
<para><paratext level="1">This case is presently before the Court on defendant Atlanta Gas Light Company's Motion for Summary Judgment [187], plaintiff Underwriters&#x2019; Motion for Summary Judgment [194], and defendant Atlanta Gas Light Company's Motion for Oral Argument [217]. The Court has reviewed the record and the arguments of the parties and, for the reasons set out below, concludes that defendant Atlanta Gas Light Company's Motion for Summary Judgment [187] should&#x2019; be <bold>DENIED,</bold> plaintiff's Motion for Summary Judgment [194] should be <bold>GRANTED,</bold> and defendant Atlanta Gas Light Company's Motion for Oral Argument [217] should be <bold>DENIED.</bold></paratext></para>
<head-c><u><bold>BACKGROUND</bold></u></head-c>
<para><paratext level="1">This dispute arises out of a tort claim filed by Tina Henry against defendants Atlanta Gas Light Company {&#x201C;AGLC&#x201D;) and General Pipeline Company (&#x201C;GP&#x201D;) following a house fire that led to the death of two residents of a home in which AGLC and GP had been doing work. (Order [126] at 1.) Ms. Henry filed suit against AGLC and.GP, alleging  that  both  had  acted negligently.    <italic>(Id.)	</italic>Plaintiff Underwriters Insurance Company (&#x201C;Underwriters&#x201D;) provided insurance that covered GP's work on the Henry home.    <italic>{Id.)	</italic>AGLC was purportedly covered as an &#x201C;additional insured&#x201D; on GP's policy. <italic>[Id.)</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Underwriters filed this action seeking a ruling that it was not obliged, under the terms of the GP policy, to indemnify, cover or defend AGLC in the Henry litigation. <italic>(Id.</italic> at 2.) AGLC brought a counterclaim against Underwriters seeking full reimbursement, as well as attorneys&#x2019; fees and damages, for Underwriters&#x2019; allegedly bad faith refusal to pay the entire amount of a settlement that was ultimately assessed against AGLC. (Order [126] at 2.) The Court granted summary judgment to AGLC on its coverage claim, finding that AGLC qualified as an &#x201C;additional insured&#x201D; under the GP policy. <italic>(Id.</italic> at 3.) Following the Court's summary judgment order, the only claim left to be decided was AGLC's bad faith claim against Underwriters. <italic><bold>(Id.)</bold></italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">On May 4, 2005, Underwriters moved for summary judgment on the bad faith claim. (PL's Mot. for Summ. J. [86].) AGLC indicated that it needed additional discovery before it could respond to the motion. (Def.&#x2019;s Resp. to PL's Mot. for Summ. J. [90].) Following an unsuccessful attempt at mediation, the Court reopened discovery. (Order [107].) The parties subsequently engaged in a protracted and contentious discovery period focused solely on the bad faith claim. (See Order [181].) In its most recent order resolving various discovery disputes, the Court set a deadline of December, 2008 for the parties to complete discovery and file summary judgment motions.. <italic><bold>(Id.)</bold></italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Pursuant to the Court's order, the parties filed cross motions for summary judgment on AGLC's bad faith claims on December 22, 2008.<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> (Def. AGLC's Mot. for Summ. J. [187] and PL's Mot. for Summ. J. [194].)  Those motions are presently before the Court.</paratext></para>]
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195; AGLC also filed a motion for oral argument on the summary judgment motions. (Def. AGLC's Mot. for Oral Argument [217].) The i parties have extensively briefed the summary judgment motions, and the evidence necessary to rule on those motions is in the written record. Accordingly, AGLC's motion for oral argument [217] is <bold>DENIED.</bold></paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<head-c><u><bold>DISCUSSION</bold></u></head-c>
<head-0><bold>I.   Summary Judgment Standard</bold></head-0>
<para><paratext level="1">Summary judgment is appropriate when the &#x201C;pleadings, the discovery and disclosure materials on file, and any affidavits, show that there is no genuine issue as to any material fact and that the movant is entitled to a judgment as a matter of law.&#x201D;&#x201C; <sc>Fed.</sc> R. Civ. P. 56(c). A fact's materiality is determined by the. controlling substantive law. <italic>Anderson v. Liberty Lobby, Inc., All</italic> U.S. 242, 248 (1986). An issue is genuine when the evidence is such that a reasonable jury could return a verdict for the nonmovant.. <italic>Id.</italic> at 249-50.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Summary judgment is not properly viewed as a device that the trial court may, in its discretion, implement in lieu of a.trial on the merits. Instead, Rule 56 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure mandates the entry of summary judgment against a party who fails to make a showing sufficient to establish the existence of every element -essential to that party's case on which that party will bear the burden of proof at trial. <italic>Celotex   Corp.    v.    Catrett,    All  </italic> U.S. 317, 322 (1986}.  In such a situation, there can be no genuine issue as to any material fact, as a complete failure of proof concerning an essential element of the non-moving party's case necessarily renders all other facts immaterial.  <italic>Id.  </italic> at 322-23 (quoting <sc>Fed.</sc> R. <sc>Civ.</sc> P. 56(c) ) .</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">The movant bears the initial responsibility of asserting the basis for his motion.   <italic>Id.   </italic> at 323.   However, the movant is not required to negate his opponent's claim.  The movant may discharge his burden by- merely &#x201C;&#x2018;showing&#x2019;--that is,  pointing out. to the district court&#x2014;that there is an absence of evidence to support the non-moving party's case.&#x201D; <italic>Id.</italic> at 325. After the movant has carried his burden, the non-moving party is then required to &#x201C;go beyond the pleadings&#x201D; and present competent evidence designating &#x201C;specific facts showing that there is a genuine issue for trial.&#x201D; <italic>Id.  </italic> at 32 4.  While j the court is to view, all evidence and factual inferences in a light most favorable to the non-moving party, <italic>Samples   v.   City of Atlanta,</italic> 846 F.2d .1328, 1330 (11th Cir. 1988), &#x201C;the mere existence of <italic>some</italic> alleged factual dispute between the parties will not defeat an otherwise properly supported motion for  summary judgment;  the requirement is that.there be no <italic>genuine  </italic> issue of <italic>material  </italic> fact.&#x201D; <italic>Anderson,   All  </italic> U.S. at 247-48 (1986).</paratext></para>
<head-0><bold>II.  AGLC's Claims Under O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 33-4-6</bold></head-0>
<para><paratext level="1">O.C.G.A.  &#x00A7;  33-4-6  subjects  an  insurer  to  penalties  and attorneys&#x2019; fees if it refuses to pay a covered claim in &#x201C;bad faith.&#x201D; O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 33-4-6.<footnote.reference ID="fr2" refid="f2" style="percent_n">2</footnote.reference>  In this context, &#x201C;bad faith&#x201D; means a &#x201C;frivolous or unfounded&#x201D; denial of a claim. <italic>Reserve Life Ins. Co. v. Ayers,</italic> 217 Ga. 206, 212 (1961) . <italic>See also Roland v. Georgia Farm Bureau Mut. Ins. Co.,</italic> 265 Ga. 776, 777 (1995)(overturning an award of penalties under &#x00A7; 33-4-6 where the insurer's refusal to pay &#x201C;was neither frivolous nor unfounded&#x201D;). Although &#x201C;reasonable and probable:cause&#x201D; to deny a claim &#x201C;may fall short of a complete defense to coverage, &#x2018;it Vindicate [s] the good faith of the [insurer] as effectually as would a complete defense to the action.&#x2019;&#x201D; <italic>Executive Risk Indem., Inc. v. AFC Enter., Inc.,</italic> 510 F. Supp. 2d.1308, 1334 (N.D. Ga. 2007) (Pannell, J.) (quoting <italic>Worsham v. Provident Co., Inc.,</italic> 249 F. Supp. 2d 1325, 1341 (N.D. Ga. 2002)). Thus, an insurer is entitled to summary judgment on a claim under &#x00A7; 33-4&#x2014;6 if it had &#x201C;any reasonable ground for [denying] the claim.&#x201D; <italic>Commercial Union Ins. Co. v. F.R.P. Co.,</italic> . 172 Ga. App. 244, 249 (1984).</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f2"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN2.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195;  Section 33-4-6 provides, in relevant part:</paratext>
<paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">In the event of a loss which is covered by a policy of insurance and the refusal of the insurer to pay the same within 60 days after a demand has been made by the holder &#x25A0; of the policy and a. finding has been made that such refusal was in bad faith, the insurer shall be liable to pay such holder, in addition to the loss, not more than 50 percent of the liability of the insurer for the loss or &#x0024; 5,000.00, whichever is greater, and all reasonable attorney's fees for the prosecution of the action against the insurer.</paratext>
<paratext contd-flag="y">O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 33-4-6.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext level="1">Applying the above standard, the record evidence clearly precludes AGLC's claim under &#x00A7; 33-4-6. The policy provision at issue provided coverage to an &#x201C;additional insured&#x201D; for &#x201C;liability arising out of [GP's] ongoing operations performed for [the additional insured].&#x201D; (Order [82] at 26.) Underwriters narrowly, although reasonably, interpreted the &#x201C;ongoing operations&#x201D; language to mean that a claim must relate to work that &#x201C;is actually in profgress] . &#x201C; <italic>{Id.</italic> at 28.) &#x2018; Underwriters also narrowly, but again reasonably, interpreted the &#x201C;arising out of&#x201D; language to require a causal connection between GP's actions and the loss.  <italic>(Id.  </italic> at 43.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">In its preliminary investigation, Underwriters obtained information indicating that a GP employee had turned on the gas and relit the furnace in the Henry home in connection with a pipe renewal project that GP was performing for AGLC prior to the Henry fire. <italic>(Id.</italic> at 11.) Based on this information, Underwriters concluded that the loss connected with the Henry fire potentially &#x201C;arose out of&#x201D; the &#x201C;ongoing operations&#x201D; that GP was performing for AGLC, triggering coverage of AGLC as an &#x201C;additional insured&#x201D; under the policy. (Order [82] at 11.) Consequently, Underwriters agreed to defend AGLC in the Henry litigation.  <italic>(Id.  </italic> at .13.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">As discovery developed in the Henry litigation, AGLC's status as an additional insured became more questionable. <italic>(Id.</italic> at 14.) Ms. Henry testified in her deposition that no one from GP had entered her residence at any time, and that she believed it was an AGLC employee who had relit the furnace prior to the fire. <italic>(Id.)</italic> Her testimony was corroborated by the deposition testimony of William Parrish, GP's foreman on the pipe replacement job. <italic>(Id.</italic> at 18.) In addition,. AGLC employee Joe Guidry testified that he, had inspected the Henrys&#x2019; furnace about a year prior to the fire and found it to be unsafe, but that he only verbally warned the Henrys of its condition and did not &#x201C;red tag&#x201D; it.<footnote.reference ID="fr3" refid="f3" style="percent_n">3</footnote.reference>  (Order [82] at 14.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f3"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN3.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195; A &#x201C;red tag&#x201D; is a danger card that AGLC servicemen are trained to put on gas appliances that they deem unsafe to relight. (Order [82] at 15.)</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext level="1">Based on the above testimony. Underwriters determined that the loss connected with the Henry fire may have arisen out of the sole negligence of AGLC, as opposed to any &#x201C;ongoing operations&#x201D; performed by GP. <italic>{Id.</italic> at 15, 26.) Underwriters therefore formally reserved its right to deny coverage to AGLC for the loss. <italic>{Id.)</italic> However, it continued to pay AGLCs defense costs until the parties completed a mediation in January, 2003 that resulted in a global settlement of the Henry claim.  <italic>(Id.)</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Underwriters subsequently filed this declaratory action to resolve the coverage issue. (Compl. [1].) Following discovery, the Court granted AGLC's motion for summary judgment on coverage. (Order . [82] at 51.) In its summary judgment order, the Court rejected Underwriters&#x2019; interpretation of the policy terms &#x201C;ongoing operations&#x201D; and &#x201C;arising out of.&#x201D; <italic>{Id.</italic> at 26-50.) However, as is apparent from the Court's 51-page discussion, the interpretation of those terms, and the coverage issues in general, presented novel and complex questions of Georgia law.  <italic>{Id.)	</italic>.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">The policy did not clearly define the term &#x201C;ongoing operations&#x201D; nor the term &#x201C;arising out of.&#x201D;  <italic>{Id.   </italic> at 36, 48.)  Neither did the case law clarify the meaning of either term. <italic>{Id.</italic> at . 46.) Particularly with respect to the &#x201C;arising out of&#x201D; language, the Court noted in its order that: &#x201C;There is no directly applicable Georgia caselaw concerning the issue before this Court.&#x201D; (Order [82] at 4 6.) The Court indicated that both parties had suggested plausible interpretations. <italic>{Id.</italic> at 37, 48.) Ultimately, the Court's holding in favor of AGLC was in large part based on the fact that the terms &#x201C;arising out of&#x201D; and &#x201C;ongoing operations&#x201D; were both ambiguous, and that &#x201C;ambiguities in an insurance contract must be strictly construed against the insurer as the drafter of the document.&#x201D; <italic>{Id.}</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Given the uncertainty about the meaning of the relevant terms, it simply cannot be said that plaintiff's coverage position was &#x201C;frivolous or unfounded.&#x201D; <italic>See Roland,</italic> 265 Ga. at 777 (holding that the trial court erred in awarding bad faith penalties where the insurer's refusal to pay was &#x201C;based on a doubtful question of law&#x201D;) and Fireman's <italic>Fund Ins. Co. v. Dean,</italic> 212 Ga. App. 262, 266 (1994)(<sup>w,</sup>our courts have consistently held that no bad faith exists where there is a doubtful question of law involved&#x2019;&#x201D;)(quoting <italic>Schoen v. Atlanta Cas. Co.,</italic> 200 Ga. App. 109, 111 (1991)). The Court thus rejects AGLC's argument that Underwriters&#x2019; coverage position &#x201C;lacked a reasonable foundation.&#x201D; (AGLCs Br. in Supp. of Mot. for Summ. J. [187] at 16.)  &#x2022;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">The Court likewise rejects AGLC's suggestion that Underwriters&#x2019; conduct during the Henry litigation, or during this litigation, establishes &#x201C;bad faith.&#x201D; <italic>(Id.</italic> at 18-23.) Under &#x00A7; 33-4-6, the &#x201C;reasonableness of [an insurer's] coverage decision must be judged based on the facts appearing to [the insurer] at the time of its decision.&#x201D; <italic>Executive Risk,</italic> 510 F. Supp. 2d at 1334. <italic>See also Royal Ins. Co. v. Cohen,</italic> 105 Ga. App. 746, 747 (1962) (&#x201C;Where it appears from the evidence that the [insurer's] refusal to pay was justified on the basis of the facts appearing to the [insurer] at the time of the refusal, bad faith is not shown.&#x201D;}. Thus, Underwriters&#x2019; conduct during the course of the present litigation does not support an award of damages under &#x00A7; 33-4-6. <italic>Executive  Risk,  </italic> 510 F. Supp. 2d at 1334 (&#x201C;any bad faith . . . which occurred after the filing of the suit is not a basis for bad faith under O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 33-4-6&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">In any case, none of Underwriters&#x2019; alleged conduct is indicative of the sort of &#x201C;bad faith&#x201D; contemplated by &#x00A7; 33-4-6. As examples of &#x201C;bad faith&#x201D; during the Henry litigation, AGLC cites Underwriters&#x2019; : (1) failure to immediately provide a copy of the insurance policy.to AGLC; and (2) formulation of an &#x201C;action plan&#x201D; to divest AGLC of coverage during the Henry litigation. (AGLCs Br. in Supp. of Summ. J. [187] at 19.) Contrary to AGLC's argument, both of these actions were harmless.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">As an initial matter, Ms. Henry did not file suit against AGLC and GP until April 25, 2001.  (Order [82] at 9.)  It is undisputed that Underwriters provided a copy of the policy to AGLC in May, 2001, shortly after Ms. Henry filed suit. (AGLC s Resp. to .&#x25A0;&#x25A0;PL's Undisputed Facts [199] at 31 10.) Underwriters&#x2019; failure to furnish a copy of the policy before Ms. Henry even filed the lawsuit giving rise to AGLC's potential liability does not indicate bad faith. In any case, AGLC had ample time to examine the policy before Underwriters formally reserved its rights to deny coverage in May, 2002.  (See Order [82] at 15.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">As to the alleged &#x201C;action plan&#x201D; to divest AGLC of coverage, the &#x201C;plan&#x201D; is outlined in a note that was apparently, part of Underwriters&#x2019; claim file. (AGLC'sMot. for Summ. J. [187] at Ex. 0.) The note directs some unnamed party to &#x201C;complete discovery&#x201D; in the Henry case and &#x201C;make a motion for summary judgment on behalf of GP.&#x201D; <italic>(Id.)</italic> It then indicates, rather cryptically, that Underwriters &#x201C;may decline coverage&#x201D; to AGLC based on the results of discovery and the motion for summary judgment. <italic>(Id.)</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">There is nothing sinister about the fairly routine &#x201C;plan&#x201D; to file a motion for summary judgment on behalf of an insured in a liability case. Neither is there anything improper about the general observation that the results of the summary judgment motion &#x2018;could result in a loss of coverage to AGLC under Underwriters&#x2019; interpretation of the &#x201C;additional insured&#x201D; provision. In any event, the &#x201C;action plan&#x201D; was never implemented, as Underwriters did not file a motion for summary judgment on behalf of GP.   (PI.&#x2019;s Opp'n to AGLC's Mot. for Summ. J. [201] at 16.)</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">Underwriters&#x2019; alleged &#x201C;bad faith&#x201D; conduct in this litigation is similarly innocuous.  That conduct includes: (1) deciding to file this declaratory judgment action one day prior to the mediation of the underlying Henry claim and (2) &#x201C;concealing&#x201D; the initial statement from GP foreman William Parrish suggesting that Parrish had entered the Henry home and lit the furnace prior.to the fire.<footnote.reference ID="fr4" refid="f4" style="percent_n">4</footnote.reference>  (AGLC's Br. in Supp. of Mot. for Summ. J. [187] at 19-20.)</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f4"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN4.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195; AGLC also suggests that Underwriters&#x2019; failure, to date, to indemnify AGLC for the Henry loss pursuant to the Court's summary judgment order is evidence of bad faith. (AGLC's Br. in. Supp. of Mot. for Summ. J. [187] at 19-20.) Underwriters&#x2019; failure, to. indemnify AGLC will likely subject Underwriters to a hefty interest obligation. <italic>See</italic> O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 7-4-15 (providing for statutory interest on liquidated demands) and <italic>Buchanan v. Bowman,</italic> 820 F. 2d 359, 362 (11<sup>th</sup> &#x00C7;ir. 1987) (&#x201C;a sum is liquidated when it is fixed and certain&#x201D;) . However, the delay in payment is largely a result of continuing litigation on AGLC's bad faith claims and countless discovery disputes, for which both parties bear some responsibility. It does not constitute bad faith.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext level="1">In support of the first contention, AGLC argues that the timing of the declaratory judgment action was designed to give Underwriters &#x201C;leverage&#x201D; in the mediation.  <italic>(Id.)     </italic> However, it is undisputed that Underwriters continued to provide a defense to AGLC through the conclusion of the mediation, incurring over &#x0024;160,000 in attorneys&#x2019; fees and &#x0024;200,000 in settlement expenses on behalf of AGLC.  (Order [82] at 23-34.)   It is thus unclear what sort of &#x201C;leverage&#x201D; AGLC believes that Underwriters was trying to obtain by filing this declaratory action. Moreover, AGLC has not cited any evidence to suggest that the declaratory judgment action negatively impacted the mediation in any way.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">As to the Parrish statement, the Court has already determined that Underwriters legitimately withheld this document pursuant to the work product . doctrine. (Order [144] at 10-11.) The Parrish statement was part of Underwriters&#x2019; claim file, which was prepared in anticipation of litigation and protected by the work product doctrine. (Id.) Thus, Underwriters was not required to'produce the Parrish statement, or any other document in its claim file,, until AGLC met its burden to show either a &#x201C;substantial need&#x201D; for the document or an exception to the work product doctrine. <italic>{Id.</italic> at 22.) The fact that AGLC was ultimately able to meet this burden does not mean that Underwriters acted in bad faith by asserting the doctrine in the first place.  <italic>[Id.)</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">In reality, the only conduct of which AGLC can complain is Underwriters&#x2019; decision to file this declaratory judgment action. That decision caused AGLC to incur attorney's fees and expenses that would have been unnecessary had Underwriters conceded coverage. Although the Court understands AGLC's frustration, Underwriters cannot be penalized under &#x00A7;  33-4-6  for pursuing its &#x201C;legally justified&#x201D; coverage position in this case.<footnote.reference ID="fr5" refid="f5" style="percent_n">5</footnote.reference> <italic>First Fin. Ins. Co.</italic> v. <italic>Rainey,</italic> 261 Ga. 52 (1991)(holding that an insurer could not be liable for penalties under &#x00A7; 33-4-6 where the Court of Appeals had divided six to three on the coverage issue). <italic>See also Nat&#x2019;1 Life Ins. Co. v. Alembik-Eisner,</italic> 582 F. Supp. 2d 1362, 1370 (N.D. Ga. 2008)(Forrester, J.) (&#x201C;the insurer is entitled to judgment as a matter of law if . .&#x2019;. &#x2018; . the question of liability is close&#x201D;). Accordingly, Underwriters&#x2019; motion for summary judgment on AGLC's bad faith claim under O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 33-4-6 is <bold>GRANTED</bold> and AGLC's motion for summary judgment on that claim is <bold>DENIED.</bold></paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f5"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN5.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195; The Court also notes that the majority of the fees and expenses are likely related to the litigation surrounding AGLC's bad faith counterclaims.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<head-0><bold>III. AGLC's Claims Under O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 13-6-11</bold></head-0>
<para><paratext level="1">AGLC's claim for attorney's fees and expenses of litigation under O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 13-6-11 also fails as a matter of law. Georgia courts have repeatedly held that &#x201C;O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 33-4-6 is the exclusive remedy for bad faith denial of [insurance] benefits.&#x201D; <italic>United Se.rv. Auto Ass'n v. Carroll,</italic> 226 Ga. App 144, 148 (1997) (reversing the trial court's award of litigation expenses under &#x00A7; 13-6-11). <italic>See also Howell v. S. Heritage Ins. Co.,</italic> 214 Ga. App. 53 6, 53 7 (1994) (&#x201C;The penalties contained in O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 33-4-6 are &#x25A0;&#x25A0; the exclusive remedies  for an insurer's bad faith refusal to pay insurance proceeds.&#x201D;).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">In addition, as discussed above, there is no evidence that Underwriters &#x25A0;&#x201D;has acted in bad faith.&#x201D;   <italic>See  </italic> O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 13-6-11. Neither has Underwriters been &#x201C;stubbornly litigious&#x201D; or caused AGLC . any &#x201C;unnecessary trouble and expense&#x201D; beyond that which ordinarily attends  any  litigation.    <italic>Id.	</italic>Accordingly,  the  Court  <bold>GRANTS</bold> Underwriters&#x2019; motion for summary judgment and <bold>DENIES</bold> AGLC's motion for summary judgment on AGLC's claim for attorney's fees and litigation expenses under O.C.G.A. &#x00A7; 13-6-11.</paratext></para>
<head-c><u><bold>CONCLUSION</bold></u></head-c>
<para><paratext level="1">For the foregoing reasons, the Court <bold>DENIES</bold> defendant Atlanta Gas  Light  Company's  Motion  for  Summary  Uudgment  [187],  <bold>GRANTS</bold> plaintiff's Motion for Summary Judgment [194], and <bold>DENIES</bold> defendant . Atlanta Gas Light Company's Motion for Oral Argument [217].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">SO ORDERED, this  <u>18</u> day of March, 2009.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>
