===== NDGA_532153_L.1.07-cv-01065-34-KCLTO.request.xml =====
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<n-load>
<n-document>
<n-docbody>
<judicial.artifact>
<content.venue>
<venue.name>IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</venue.name>
<venue.name>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF GEORGIA</venue.name>
<venue.name>ATLANTA DIVISION</venue.name>
</content.venue>

<content.long.title level="primary">
<individual.title>
<title.segment>UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, Petitioner,</title.segment>
<title.segment.connector type="vs">v.</title.segment.connector>
<title.segment>MARTIN M. CHANDLER, Respondent.</title.segment>
</individual.title>
</content.long.title>

<content.docket.number>
<docket.line>CIVIL ACTION NO. 1:07-CV-1065-RLV-LTW</docket.line>
<docket.number>1:07-CV-1065-RLV-LTW</docket.number>
<docket.line suppress-flag="y">1:07-cv-01065-RLV</docket.line>
</content.docket.number>

<content.date xml:lang="en">
<date.line type="filed">Filed 04/03/2008</date.line>
</content.date>

<decision>
<decision.body>
<opinion category="lead">
<head><headtext align="center"><bold>ORDER GRANTING MOTION BY PETITIONER UNITED STATES OF AMERICA TO ADJUDICATE RESPONDENT MARTIN M. CHANDLER IN CIVIL CONTEMPT AND DIRECTING ARREST <u>OF RESPONDENT MARTIN M. CHANDLER</u></bold></headtext></head>

<content.judge role="majority" xml:lang="en">
<judge.line first-line="1">ROBERT L. VINING JR. SENIOR UNITED STATES DISTRICT JUDGE</judge.line>
</content.judge>

<opinion.body>
<section>
<section.body>

<para><paratext level="1">By Order dated March 6, 2008, and filed March 11, 2008, the Court directed respondent Martin M.  Chandler  (&#x201C;respondent&#x201D;), proceeding without assistance of counsel, to appear before the Court at a hearing scheduled to commence at 10:30 a.m., on March 27, 2008, in Courtroom 353 of the U.S. Courthouse in Rome, Georgia. [Doc. 28] .<footnote.reference ID="fr1" refid="f1" style="percent_n">1</footnote.reference> At such hearing, respondent was to show cause why the motion by petitioner United States of America to adjudicate respondent in civil contempt of the previous Order of this Court dated January 10, 2008, should not be granted.</paratext></para>
<footnote ID="f1"><footnote.body><para><label.designator>FN1.</label.designator><paratext ID="p">&#8195;    References shall be to the docket numbers assigned by the Clerk of the Court to documents filed in this case.</paratext></para></footnote.body></footnote>
<para><paratext level="1">With respondent having failed to appear at the show cause hearing set for March 27, 2008, of which respondent received notice, and good cause having been shown, the Court enters the following Findings of Fact and Conclusions of Law in support of granting petitioner's motion to adjudicate respondent in civil contempt of the Order of the Court dated January 10, 2008, and ordering respondent to be taken into custody until such time as respondent purges himself of his civil contempt of that Order.</paratext></para>
<head-c><u><bold>FINDINGS OF FACT</bold></u></head-c>
<para><paratext level="1">1.	On December 22, 2006, petitioner United States of America, on behalf of the Internal Revenue Service (&#x201C;1RS&#x201D;), pursuant to the provisions of 26 U.S.C. &#x00A7;&#x00A7;7402(b) and 7604(a), filed in the U.S. District Court for the Northern District of Georgia a Petition to Enforce an 1RS Summons. [Doc. 1]. That 1RS Summons was issued to respondent, on September 21, 2006, and served upon respondent by certified mail, on September 22, 2 006, by Melissa Milligan, a duly commissioned Special Agent (&#x201C;SA&#x201D;) employed in the Criminal Investigation Division of the Phoenix, Arizona, Field Office of the 1RS. [Doc. 1].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">2.	That 1RS Summons directed Martin M. Chandler to appear before 1RS SA Milligan, on October 17, 2006, at 1:00 p.m., in Tempe, Arizona, to testify and produce the books, records, and other documents described in the Summons. [Doc. 1].  The Petition to Enforce was filed after respondent failed to comply with that IRS Summons. [Doc. 1] .</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">3.	By Order entered on February 8, 2007, respondent was directed to appear before U.S. Magistrate Judge Linda T. Walker and show cause why respondent should not be compelled to comply with that 1RS Summons that was issued to and served upon him. [Doc. 3]. That Order scheduled such show cause hearing in this case before Magistrate Judge Walker, at the United States Courthouse in Atlanta, Georgia, for April 12, 2007. [Doc. 3]. At the request of respondent, the hearing at which respondent was to show cause why he had not complied with the 1RS Summons was continued to May 8, 2007. [Doc. 8].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">4.	By Response to Order to Show Cause filed on March 6, 2 007, respondent Chandler requested: 1) release of investigations into his personal tax liability; 2) release of a liens by the 1RS upon respondent's property; and 3) an award of &#x0024;2 0,000,000 in damages. [Doc. 5]. On May 3, 2007, petitioner United States filed and served upon respondent its Motion and supporting Memorandum of Law to dismiss plaintiff's claims for injunctive and monetary relief that were set forth in respondent's Response to Order to Show Cause filed on March 6, 2007. [Doc. 9].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">5.	On May 8, 2 007, a hearing was held before Magistrate Judge Walker at the United States Courthouse in Atlanta, Georgia. Among those present at that hearing were respondent, SA Milligan, and Daniel A. Caldwell, counsel for petitioner. At that hearing respondent was afforded the opportunity to show cause why he had failed to comply with the 1RS Summons that had been issued to and served upon him.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">6.	By Report and Recommendation entered November 14, 2007, Magistrate Judge Walker recommended: that the Petition to Enforce 1RS Summons be granted; that respondent's counterclaims for injunctive and monetary relief be dismissed; and that respondent be ordered to pay petitioner's costs and reasonable attorney's fees incurred in enforcing the Summons. [Doc. 13]. Objections to the Report and Recommendation were filed on behalf of respondent with this Court on January 4, 2008. [Doc. 16].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">7.	By Order dated January 10, 2 08, and entered January 11, 2008, this Court adopted the Report and Recommendation of Magistrate Judge Walker that the Petition to Enforce 1RS Summons be granted as the opinion and Order of this Court. [Doc. 17]. By that Order the Court directed petitioner to submit supporting materials to document costs and reasonable attorney's fees incurred in enforcement of the 1RS Summons. Id. Judgment was entered in favor of petitioner on January 10, 2008. [Doc. 18]. As of March 27, 2008, respondent had filed no appeal of the Order and Judgment entered in this case on January 10, 2 008.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">8.	On January 24,  2008, petitioner's costs were taxed against respondent, in the amount of &#x0024;560.44, and made part of the Judgment. [Doc. 2 0].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">9.	By letter to respondent dated January 16, 2008, 1RS Special Agent Milligan directed respondent to produce to her, on or before January 23, 2008, all documents sought through the 1RS Summons previously issued to respondent. [Doc. 22 - Exh. A] . Thereafter, by letter dated January 24, 2008, from counsel for petitioner, respondent was requested to produce all documents sought through the 1RS Summons to Special Agent Milligan immediately. [Doc. 22 - Exh. B] . Furthermore, respondent was requested to tender payment to the Government, in the amount of &#x0024;560.44, in satisfaction of costs awarded in this case. <italic>Id.</italic> Respondent was notified through that letter that a motion for civil contempt would be brought against him if he did not provide to Special Agent Milligan, on or before January 31, 2008, all documents sought through the 1RS Summons previously issued to respondent. <italic>Id.</italic></paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">10.	By letter to counsel for petitioner dated January 30, 2008, respondent stated that:</paratext>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">U.S. District Judge Robert L. Vining Jr.&#x2019;s adoption of the Report and Recommendation of Magistrate Judge Walker is void ab initio due to the mistakes of fact and law regarding subject matter jurisdiction FRCP 12(h)(3).</paratext></para>
<paratext contd-flag="y">[Doc. 22 - Exh. C at p. 6].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">11.	On February 11, 2008, petitioner filed a motion to adjudicate respondent in civil contempt of this Court for having failed to comply with the 1RS Summons issued to respondent with which respondent was directed to comply by Order of this Court dated January 10, 2 0 08 and entered on January 11, 2 008. [Doc. 22].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">12.	By Order dated March 6, 2008, and entered March 11, 2008, the Court directed respondent to appear before the Court in Courtroom 353 of the U.S. Courthouse in Rome, Georgia, on March 27, 2008, at 10:30 a.m., and show cause why respondent should not be held in civil contempt of the Court for his failure to obey the Order of the Court dated January 10, 2008. [Doc. 28].  The Court directed the Clerk of the Court to serve a copy of that Order upon respondent by mailing a true copy thereof to the following mailing address provided to the Court by respondent :</paratext>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">Martin M. Chandler</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">c/o Dogwood Financial Services LLC</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">Post Office Box 23</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">Grayson GA 30017</paratext></para>
<paratext contd-flag="y">[Doc. 2 8 at p. 3].</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">13.	On March 26, 2 008, a &#x201C;Commercial Affidavit&#x201D; with the Court that was co-signed by respondent and an individual identified as Arch Bishop John Brown III was entered on the docket. [Doc. 29]. Included in that &#x201C;Commercial Affidavit&#x201D; was a copy of the Order directing respondent to appear before the Court on March 27, 2 008, and show cause why he should not be held in civil contempt. <italic>Id.</italic> at pp. 32-34. In that &#x201C;Commercial Affidavit&#x201D; it was stated that &#x201C;Senior U.S. District Judge Vining's Orders are without standing.&#x201D; <italic>Id.</italic> at p. 4. In that Commercial Affidavit it was further stated that &#x201C;U.S. District Court Judge Vining's Order is actionable under 18 U.S.C. &#x00A7;3571 for each violation[.]&#x201D; <italic>Id.  </italic> at p. 24.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">14.	On March 26, 2008, a document signed by respondent and dated March 25, 2008, was entered on the docket. [Doc. 31]. That document stated:</paratext>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">Dear Gentlemen:</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">In 1976 in Public Law 94-381 the jurisdiction of all United States District Courts were changed to Administrative Courts under the Executive Branch of the federal government and have no authority to hear or consider the law. US District Courts are courts of consent. I, Martin M. Chandler, DO NOT CONSENT.</paratext></para>
<paratext contd-flag="y">[Doc. 31 at p. 1].  That document further stated &#x201C;Daniel Caldwell III is appearing Pro Se because of USCS &#x00A7;&#x00A7; 71 and 72.&#x201D; <italic>Id.</italic> Attached to that document was a copy of the weekly calendar of the Court, in which the hearing at which respondent was to show cause why he should not be held in civil contempt was listed as being scheduled. <italic>Id.  </italic> at p. 2.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">15.	A hearing on petitioner's civil contempt motion was held before the Court on March 27, 2008, at the United States Courthouse in Rome, Georgia.  Present at that hearing were 1RS SA Milligan and counsel for petitioner.  Respondent failed to appear before the Court on March 27, 2 0 08, at the time and location scheduled for the hearing.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">16.  The Court finds that there is no realistic possibility that any lesser sanction other than incarceration may coerce the compliance of respondent Martin M. Chandler with the 1RS Summons and the Order of the Court, dated January 10, 2008, by which respondent Chandler has been ordered to comply with that 1RS Summons.  This finding is based upon facts including:</paratext>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">The failure of respondent to comply in whole or in part with the 1RS Summons since that Summons was issued to respondent in September 2006;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">The election of respondent not to appeal the Order and Judgment entered against respondent, on January 10, 2008, that directed respondent to comply with the Summons;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">The failure of respondent to comply with the Summons after the Order of the Court dated January 10, 2008, imposed upon respondent the costs of having to pay costs and attorney's fees incurred by petitioner in enforcement of the 1RS Summons ,-</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">The statements of respondent in submissions to the Court that the Orders of this Court are &#x201C;without standing&#x201D; and that respondent does not &#x201C;consent&#x201D; to the authority of this Court; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">The failure of respondent to appear before the Court on March 27, 2 008, and show cause why he should not be held in civil contempt after respondent's submissions to the Court clearly establish respondent received the Order of the Court dated March 6, 2 008, that directed respondent to appear before the Court on March 27, 2008.</paratext></para></para>
<head-c><u><bold>CONCLUSIONS OF LAW</bold></u></head-c>
<para><paratext level="1">1.	Courts &#x201C;have inherent power to enforce compliance with their lawful orders through civil contempt.&#x201D; <italic>Citronelle-Mobile Gathering, Inc. v. Watkins,</italic> 943 F.2d 1297, 1301 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir. 1991) (citing <italic>Shillitani v. United States,</italic> 384 U.S. 364, 370, 86 S.Ct. 1531, 1535 (1966) .</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">2.	To achieve compliance with those orders, courts can impose both coercive and compensatory sanctions. <italic>Citronelle-Mobile,</italic> 943 F.2d at 1304. Those options include: a coercive daily fine; a compensatory fine; imposition of attorney's fees and expenses incurred by a movant seeking compliance with a court's order; and coercive incarceration. <italic>Id.</italic> &#x201C;Although the district court has the authority to impose sanctions designed to ensure compliance, the sanctions cannot be any greater than necessary to ensure such compliance.&#x201D; <italic>Ci tronelle -Mobile,</italic> 943 F.2d at 13 04 <italic>{citing Mercer v.   Mitchell,  </italic> 908 F.2d 763, 768 n.9 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir.1990)).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">3.	Due process requires that the Court inform the alleged contemner of the contemptuous conduct, and provide a hearing in which the alleged contemnor may explain why the court should not make a contempt finding. <italic>Mercer,  </italic> 908 F.2d at 767.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">4.	A finding of civil contempt is supported if such contempt is clear and convincing, as demonstrated by: (1) the violated order being valid and lawful; (2) the order being clear, definite, and unambiguous; and (3) the violator of that order having the ability to comply with the order. <italic>McGregor v. Chierico,</italic> 2 06 F.3d 1378, 13 83 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir. 2000). This clear and convincing evidence standard is more exacting than the preponderance of the evidence standard but, unlike criminal contempt, does not require proof beyond a reasonable doubt. <italic>In Re Jove Engineering, Inc. v. I.R.S.,</italic> 92 F.3d 1539, 1545 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir. 1996) .</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">5.	Once a movant establishes clearly and convincingly that a court order has been violated, the burden of production shifts to a respondent to produce evidence to explain why compliance with such order has not occurred. United <italic>States</italic> v. <italic>Rylander,</italic> 460 U.S. 752, 755, 103 S. Ct. 1548, 1552 (1983); <italic>Commodity Futures Trading Comm'n. v. Wellington Precious Metals, Inc.,</italic> 950 F.2d 1525, 1529 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir. 19 90) ; <italic>Citronelle-Mobile,</italic> 943 F.2d at 1301; <italic>United States v. Hayes,</italic> 722 F.2d 723, 725 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir.1984) . In meeting such burden of production, a respondent is barred, under the principle of <italic>res judicata,</italic> from raising in the contempt proceeding any issue that was or could have been raised at the 1RS Summons enforcement hearing. <italic>Rylander,  </italic> 460 U.S. at 756-57, 98 S.Ct. at 1552.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">6.	Under the provisions of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure :</paratext>
<para><paratext first-line="1" turnover="1">Service of process is not required to notify a party of a decree or injunction, or of an order that the party show cause why that party should not be held in contempt of such an order. With respect to a party who has once been served with a summons, the service of the decree or injunction itself or of an order to show cause can be made pursuant to Rule 5 [of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure].</paratext></para>
<paratext contd-flag="y">Fed. R. Civ. P. 4.1 (Advisory Committee Notes, 1993 Adoption). Respondent Chandler was properly served with the Order of the Court dated March 6, 2 008, to show cause and appear before the Court on March 27, 2008, by a true copy of that Order to Show Cause being mailed to respondent at his mailing address provided to the Court. Respondent has confirmed he received notice of that Order to show cause and appear before the Court on March 27, 2008, by including a copy of that Order dated March 6, 2 008, in a submission by respondent to the Court entered on March 26, 2 008.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">7.	The Order of the Court dated January 10, 2008, that directed respondent to comply with the 1RS Summons is lawful, clear and unambiguous. Respondent has failed to produce any evidence why he has not been able to comply with that lawful Order. Instead, respondent's submissions to the Court have repeatedly challenged the authority of the Court to issue that Order. Respondent Chandler is in civil contempt of the Order of the Court dated January 10, 2008, that ordered him to comply with the 1RS Summons.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">8.	For the reasons set forth in Finding of Fact Number 16, <italic>supra,</italic> it is the conclusion of the Court that lesser coercive sanctions such as imposition of a daily coercive fine will not result in respondent Chandler complying with the Order of this Court dated January 10, 2008. The Court has the discretionary authority to incarcerate respondent until such later time as the Court may determine that such &#x201C;civil contempt sanctions lose their coercive effect ... become punitive and violate the contemnor's due process rights.&#x201D; <italic>In Re Lawrence,</italic> 279 F.3d 1294, 1300 (11<sup>th</sup> Cir. 2002). Therefore, the Court concludes that respondent should be incarcerated as a proper exercise of the Court's civil contempt authority. That incarceration is not imposed for the purpose of punishment but for the purpose of coercing the compliance of respondent with the Order of the Court dated January 10, 2 008, in order that respondent may purge himself of civil contempt.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">9. &#x201C;An order of civil commitment of a person held to be in contempt of a decree or injunction issued to enforce the laws of the United States may be served and enforced in any district.&#x201D; Fed. R. Civ. P. 4.1(b) . Because respondent is in civil contempt of Orders directing him to comply with provisions of the Internal Revenue Code, any Order by the Court directing the civil commitment of respondent until he purges himself of that civil contempt may be enforced in any United States judicial district. <italic>See S.E.C. v. Resource Development, L.L.C.,</italic> 86 Fed.Appx. 14 {5<sup>th</sup> Cir. Dec. 23, 2003)(contempt orders issued in connection with defendants&#x2019; violations of federal securities laws may be properly served and enforced in any judicial district).</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">10. Following service and enforcement of an Order directing respondent's commitment for his civil contempt of the Court, respondent shall not be entitled to arraignment or bond. See <italic>Schmidt v. Joslin,</italic> 2006 WL 1499773 at *2 (N.D. Tex. Nov. 30, 2 006). Respondent can secure his release from custody by purging himself of civil contempt through: complying with the Order of the Court dated January 10, 2008; and providing to 1RS SA Milligan all documentary and testimonial information sought through the 1RS Summons previously issued to respondent.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1"><bold>WHEREFORE,</bold> for the reasons set forth in these Findings of Fact and Conclusions of Law,</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1"><bold>IT HEREBY IS ORDERED</bold> that petitioner's motion to adjudicate respondent in civil contempt of the Order of the Court dated January 10, 2008, is granted;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1"><bold>IT FURTHER IS ORDERED</bold> that a warrant shall be issued for the arrest and detention of respondent Martin M. Chandler by the United States Marshals Service or any authorized United States Officer;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1"><bold>IT FURTHER IS ORDERED</bold> that a copy of this Order shall be personally served upon respondent Martin M. Chandler by the United States Marshals Service or any authorized United States Officer;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1"><bold>IT F&#x00DC;RTHER IS ORDERED</bold> that respondent Martin M. Chandler be taken into custody by the United States Marshals Service or any authorized United States Officer;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1"><bold>IT FURTHER IS ORDERED</bold> that respondent Martin M. Chandler: shall thereafter appear before the nearest United States Magistrate Judge to state whether respondent has purged himself of civil contempt by complying with the Order of the Court dated January 10, 2008; and, if respondent has not purged himself of civil contempt, thereafter be taken to an available detainment facility located nearest to the United States District Court in Atlanta, Georgia;</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1"><bold>IT FURTHER IS ORDERED</bold> that respondent Martin M. Chandler shall thereafter be detained until such time as respondent purges himself of civil contempt by complying with the 1RS Summons issued to respondent, on September 21, 2006, and Order of the Court, dated January 10, 2008, through providing to 1RS SA Milligan all documents and testimony sought through that 1RS Summons; and</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">IT F&#x00DC;RTHER IS ORDERED petitioner shall submit to the Court, within twenty (20} day of entry of this Order, supporting materials to document travel and lodging costs incurred by SA Milligan to attend the hearing before the Court on March 27, 2008, which shall be taxed to respondent Martin M. Chandler.</paratext></para>
<para><paratext level="1">SO ORDERED this <u>3<sup>rd</sup></u> day of <u>APRIL</u>, 2008.</paratext></para>
</section.body>
</section>
</opinion.body>
</opinion>
</decision.body>
</decision>
</judicial.artifact>
</n-docbody>
</n-document>
</n-load>
